<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9054">Nativity 13</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9041"> Hymns on Nativity -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܝܠܕܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XIII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XIII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 13</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>In the days of the King whom they called by the name of Semha,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> our Lord sprang up
               among the Hebrews: and Semha and Denha<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> ruled, and came, King upon earth, and Son
               in Heaven; blessed be His rule!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>In the days of the king who enrolled men in the book of the dead, our Redeemer came
               down and enrolled men in the book of the living. He enrolled, and they also: on high
               He enrolled us, on earth they enrolled Him. Glory to His Name!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>In the days of the king whose name was Semha, the type and the Reality met together,
               the king and the King, Semha and Denha. His Cross upon His shoulders, was the sign of
               His Kingdom. Blessed be He Who bare it.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Thirty years He went in poverty upon the earth! The sounds of praise in all their
               measures let us twine, my brethren, to the years of the Lord, as thirty crowns to the
               thirty years. Blessed be His Birth!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>In the first year, that is chieftain over the treasures and Dispenser of abundant
               blessings, let the Cherubim who bare up the Son in glory,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> praise Him with us! He
               left His glory, and toiled and found the sheep that was lost. To Him be
               thanksgiving!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>In the second year, let the Seraphim praise Him yet more with us. They that had
               proclaimed the Son Holy,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> by and by saw Him when He was reviled among the
               gainsayers; He bore the contempt and taught praise. To Him be Glory!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>In the third year, let Michael and his followers, that ministered to the Son in the
               highest, praise Him with us. They saw Him on the earth when He was ministering,
               washing feet, cleansing souls. Blessed be His lowliness!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>In the fourth year, let the whole earth praise Him with us. It is but small for the
               Son, and it marvelled because it saw that it entertained Him in its bed that is so
               very mean. He filled the bed, and filled the Heaven. To Him be Majesty!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>In the fifth year, the Sun shone unto the earth. With its breath let it praise our
               Sun Who brought His breadth down low, and humbled His mightiness, that the subtle eye
               of the unseen soul might be able to look upon Him. Blessed be His brightness!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>In the sixth year again, let the whole air praise Him with us, in whose wide space
               it is that all things are made glorious, which saw its mighty Lord that had become a
               little Child in a little bosom. Blessed be His dignity!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>In the seventh year, the clouds and winds rejoiced with us and sprinkled the dews
               over the flowers, for they saw the Son who enslaved His brightness and received
               disgrace and foul spitting. Blessed be His Redemption!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>In the year also that is eighth, let the fields give praise, that suckle their
               fruits from His fountains. They worshipped because they saw the Son in arms and the
               pure One sucking pure milk. Blessed be His good pleasure!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>In the ninth year, let the earth glorify the might of her Creator, Who laid seed in
               her in the beginning that she might bring forth all her produce; for it saw Mary, a
               thirsty land, who yielded the fruit of a Child that was a wonder, yea, a marvel.
               [Then] it praised Him more exceedingly, for that He was a great Sea of all good
               things. To Him be exaltation!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>In the tenth year, let the mount Sinai glorify Him, it which trembled before its
               Lord. It saw that they took up stones against its Lord; He received stones, Who
               should build His Church upon a Stone.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> Blessed be His building!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>In the eleventh year, let the great sea praise the fists of the Son that measured
               it,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> and it was astonished and saw that He came down, was baptized in a small
               water, and cleansed the creatures. Blessed be His noble act!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>In the twelfth year, let the holy Temple praise Him, that saw the Child when He sat
               amongst the old men: the priests were silent when the Lamb of the Feast bleated in
               His feast. Blessed be His propitiation!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>In the thirteenth year, let the crowns praise with us the King who conquered, that
               died and was crowned with a crown of thorns, and bound upon Adam a great crown at His
               right hand. Blessed be His Apostleship!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>In the fourteenth year, let the passover in Egypt praise the Passover that came and
               passed over all, and instead of Pharaoh sunk Legion,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> instead of horses choked the
               devil. Blessed be His vengeance!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>In the fifteenth year, let the lamb of the gluttons praise Him: since our Lord was
               so far from slaughtering it as Moses did, that He even redeemed mankind with His own
               Blood. He that feeds all, died for all. Blessed be His Father!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>In the sixteenth year, let the wheat praise by its type that Husbandman,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> Who
               sowed His Body in the barren earth, since it covers all, spreads itself out and
               yields new Bread. Blessed be the Pure One!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>In the seventeenth year, let the Vine praise the Lord that garnished it. He planted
               a vineyard, souls were as vineplants. He gave peace to the vineyard, but destroyed
               the vineyard that brought forth wild grapes. Blessed be its Uprooter!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>In the eighteenth year, let the Vine which the wild boar out of the wood had eaten,
               praise the True Vine which trimmed Himself, and kept His fruit, and brought the
               fruits to the Lord of the Vineyard.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/> Blessed be His Vintage!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>In the nineteenth year, let our leaven praise the true leaven which worked itself in
               among those that were in error, and drove them all together, and made them one mind
               by one Doctrine. Blessed be thy doctrine!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>In the twentieth year, let salt praise Thy living Body, wherewith are salted the
               bodies and the souls of all the faithful, and faith is the salt of men wherewith they
               are preserved.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/> Blessed be Thy preserving!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>In the twenty-first year, let the waters of the desert praise Thee. They are sweet
               to them afar off, they are bitter to them<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> that are near, who did not minister to
               Him. The [chosen] people and the nations were bitter in the desert, and He destroyed
               them. They were sweetened by the Cross which redeemed them. Blessed be Thy
               pleasantness!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>In the twenty-second year, let arms and the sword praise Thee: they sufficed not to
               kill our adversary. It was Thou that killed him, even Thou who didst fix the ear on,
               which Simon’s sword cut off. Blessed be Thy healing!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>In the twenty-third year, let the ass praise Him, that gave its foal for Him to ride
               on, that loosed the bonds, that opened the mouth of the dumb, that opened also the
               mouth of the wild asses<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12"/> when the race of Hagar gave a shout of praise.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/>
               Blessed be the praise of Thee!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <ab>In the twenty-fourth year, let the Treasury praise the Son. The treasures marvelled
               at the Lord of treasures, when in the house of the poor He was increasing, Who made
               Himself poor that He might enrich all.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/> Blessed be Thy rule!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="29">
            <ab>In the twenty-fifth year, let Isaac praise the Son, for by His goodness he was
               rescued upon the Mount from the knife, and in his stead there was the victim, the
               type of the Lamb for the slaughter.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15"/> The mortal escaped, and He that quickens all
               died.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16"/> Blessed be His offering!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="30">
            <ab>In the twenty-sixth year, let Moses praise Him with us, for that he was afraid and
               fled from his murderers. Let him praise the Lord that bore the spear and that
               received the nails in His hands, in His feet. He entered into hell and spoiled
               it,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17"/> and came forth. Blessed be Thy Resurrection!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="31">
            <ab>In the year which is the twenty-seventh, let the eloquent speakers praise the Son,
               for they found no cloke to save our cause. He was silent in the judgment-hall, and He
               carried our cause. Honour be to Him!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="32">
            <ab>And in this year let all judges praise Him, who, as being just men, killed the
               ungodly; let them praise the Son who died for the wicked, as being good. Though Son
               of the Just One, He gave them all manner of good things in abundance. Blessed be His
               bowels of mercy!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="33">
            <ab>In the eight and twentieth year, let all mighty men of valour praise the Son,
               because they delivered not from him who took us captive. He only is to be praised,
               who being slain showed us life.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18"/> Blessed be His delivery!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="34">
            <ab>In the twenty-ninth year, let Job praise Him with us, who bore sufferings for
               himself, and our Lord bore for us the spitting and the spear, and the crown of
               thorns, and scourges, contempt and reproach, yea mocking. Blessed be His mercy!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="35">
            <ab>In the year that is thirteenth, let the dead praise Him with us, because they are
               quickened, and the living, because they have turned to repentance,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19"/> because height
               and depth were set at one by Him. Blessed be He and His Father! </ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">I.e., August.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">I.e., Dayspring.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">Ps. xcix. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">Is. vi. 2; Mat. xxvi. 53; 1 Tim. iii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">Cephas—Petros—stone.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">Is. xl. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">Mark v. 9; Luke viii. 30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8">John xii. 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9">John xviii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10">Mark ix. 49.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11">Exod. xv. 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12">Gen. xvi. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13">Acts ii. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14">2 Cor. viii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15">Heb. xi. 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16">Is. liii.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17">Is. xlix. 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18">Rev. v. 9.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
