<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9056">Nativity 15</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9041"> Hymns on Nativity -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܝܠܕܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XV"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XV
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 15</head>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He above all in His Birth! (bis).</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Celebrate, O nations, this feast, first fruits of all feasts;—recount the sufferings
               that were, and the wounds and pains,—that we may know what plagues, He healed, the
               Son Who was sent.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who sufficed to heal our pains!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Celebrate, O saved nations, Him Who saves all in His Birth.—Even my feeble tongue,
               has become a harp through His mercy.—The excellency of the Firstborn, in His Festival
               let us sing.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who has made us meet for His Feast!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>How then can any one, admire a physician,—until he hear and learn, what were the
               pains he healed?—And when our plagues are proclaimed, then is our Healer
               magnified.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who is exalted in our pains!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Created things were worshipped: because the worshipper was foolish,—he used to
               worship all things; but One they worshipped not.—He came down therefore in mercy and
               broke, the yoke that enslaved all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who loosed our pains!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>The mercies of the Highest were revealed; He came down and set free His creature.—In
               this blessed month, wherein are made releases of slaves,—the Lord underwent bondage,
               to call the bond to freedom.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who brought freedom!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>The Lord of the months chose Him, two months for His doings.—His Conception was in
               Nisan, and His Birth in Conun.—In Nisan He sanctified them that were conceived; and
               them that were born He set free in Conun.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who makes glad His months!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>The Sun revealed in silence, his worshippers to his Lord:—it was grievous to him, a
               servant, to be worshipped instead of his Lord.—Lo! creation is glad, that the Creator
               is worshipped.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is the Child that is worshipped.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>The months wore three crowns, and crowned Him in His triumphs.—Blessed is the Sun
               for His Birth, and for His Resurrection desired,—and for His Ascension blessed; the
               months have borne Him crowns.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has triumphed in His months!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>Unveil and make glad thy face, O Creature, in our feast.—Let the Church sing with
               voice; Heaven and earth in silence!—Sing and praise the Child, who has brought
               release for all!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has annulled the bonds!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>When fools did reverence to the Sun, in reverence to him they disgraced him.—But now
               when all know he is a servant, in his course his Lord is worshipped;—all servants
               rejoice, that as servants they are reckoned.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who ordered their natures!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>We have done perverse things, who have become servants of servants.—Lo! our freedom
               compelled him, a servant, to become lord to us:—the Sun, the servant for all, we have
               made Lord for all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who to Himself has turned us!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>And the Moon too which was worshipped, has been set free by His Birth.—For ’tis
               strange that by her light, which enlightens the eyes,—by it the eyes were darkened,
               that they gazed on her as a God.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be the beam that has enlightened us!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Fire commended Thy Birth, which drew away worship from it.—The magi used to worship
               it: they who have worshipped before Thee.—They left it and worshipped its Lord; they
               exchanged fire for the Fire.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who has bathed us in His light!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>In place of the senseless fire that eats up its own body of itself,—the magi adored
               the Fire Who gave His Body to be eaten.—The live coal drew near and sanctified, the
               lips that were unclean.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who has mixed His Fire in us!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>Delusion blinded men, to worship created things:—fellow servants were worshipped,
               and the God of all was wronged.—He Who is to be worshipped came down to His birth,
               and gathered to himself worship.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who by all is worshipped!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>The All-knowing saw, that men worship things that were made:—He put on a body that
               was made, that in our custom He might take us captive,—and by a body that was made,
               drew us to the Creator.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who drew us with guile!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>The Evil One knew how to harm us; and by lights he blinded us,—by possessions he
               hurt us, through gold he made us poor,—by the graver’s graven images, he made us a
               heart of stone.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who came and softened it!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>They graved and set up stones, whereon men should stumble.—They set them not on the
               highway, for the blind to stumble on:—they called them Gods, that on them with open
               eyes men might stumble.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who exposed the idols which they feared!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>Sin had spread its wings, and covered all things,—that none could discern, of
               himself or from above, the truth.—Truth came down into the womb, came forth and
               rolled away error.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who dispelled Sin by His Birth!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>For Mercy endured not, to see the way hindered.—When He came down for conception, He
               opened the way and made it easy:—when He came forth in birth, He trod it and marked
               its miles.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is the peace of Thy Way!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>He chose the Prophets; they cleared the way for the people:—He sent the Apostles;
               they smoothed paths for the nations.—The snares of the Evil One were shamed, when
               feeble men cleared them away.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who made our paths plain!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>The graven images blinded, their gravers in secret:—they graved eyes on stone, and
               darkened the eyes of the soul.—Praise to Thy Birth that opened, the sight that was
               blinded.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has restored sight!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>Let women praise Her, the pure Mary,—that as in Eve their mother,—great was their
               reproach,—lo! in Mary their sister,—greatly magnified was their honour.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who sprang from women!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>Let the nations praise Thy Birth, that they have gained eyes to see,—how their wine
               has made them reel; and they have seen their own humiliation?—They come to know
               themselves, and worship Him who has rescued them.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who has taught repentance!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>Its worship mankind—had spread everywhere:—Him Who is to be worshipped it sought
               not, that worship should be paid Him.—But He endured not—worshippers that err.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who came down and is worshipped!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>The gold of the idols worshipped Thee, that Thou didst treat it as alms; which
               availed not apart, for the uses of life.—It hasted to Thy purse, as it had hasted to
               the manger.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Whom Creation has loved!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>The frankincense worshipped Thy Birth, which had served demons.—It sorrowed then in
               its vapour: it exulted when it saw its Lord.—Instead of being the incense of
               delusion, it was an oblation before God!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is Thy Birth which is worshipped!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <ab>The myrrh worshipped Thee for itself, and for its kindred ointments.—The hands that
               bore its ointment, had anointed abominable graven images.—To Thee the perfume was
               sweet, from the anointing wherewith Mary anointed Thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is Thy savour which is sweet to us!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="29">
            <ab>The gold that had been worshipped worshipped thee, when the magi offered it.—That
               which had been worshipped in molten images, gave worship to Thee.—With its
               worshippers it worshipped Thee, it confessed that Thou art He that is to be
               worshipped.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who claimed worship for Himself!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="30">
            <ab>The Evil One fled and his hosts, he that used to exult in the world.—In the high
               places they sacrificed heifers to him, in the gardens they slew bulls for him.—He
               swallowed up all creation, he filled his belly with prey.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who came and made him disgorge!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="31">
            <ab>Of him the Lord said, that he had fallen from Heaven.—The Abhorred One had exalted
               himself; from his uplifting he has fallen. The foot of Mary has trod him down, who
               bruised Eve with his heel.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who by His Birth laid him low!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="32">
            <ab>Chaldeans went about, in all places and led astray:—the preachers of delusion, were
               shamed through the world,—they were shamed and overcome,—by the preachers of
               truth.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be the Babe Whom they preached!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="33">
            <ab>Sin had spread out, her nets for the draught.—Praise be to Thy Birth that captured,
               the nets of delusion.—The soul took flight on high, which had been taken in the
               deep.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who prepared for us wings!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="34">
            <ab>His Will was able, even by force to rescue us.—But since it was not force that made
               us guilty, it was not by force He purged us.—The Evil One by enticement enslaved us:
               Thy Birth enticed to give us life.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who planned and gave us life!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="35">
            <ab>The creatures complained that they were worshipped; in silence they sought
               release.—The All-Releaser heard, and because He endured it not He came down,—put on
               the form of a servant in the womb, came forth, set free Creation.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who made his Creation his gain!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="36">
            <ab>Mercy was kindled on high, at the voice of Creation that cried out:—Gabriel was
               sent; he came and gave tidings of Thy Conception.—When Thou camest to the Birth,
               Watchers gave tidings of thy coming forth.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be by Thy Worship above all!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="37">
            <ab>For greater is the joy of the Birth than the Conception.—Yea it was one angel, that
               brought us tidings of Thy Conception:—but in the joy of Thy Birth, a multitude of
               Watchers brought tidings.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be Thy tidings in Thy day!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="38">
            <ab>Glory to Thee I too in Thy day, will offer, O Thou that art worshipped!—Take of the
               fruit that is mine; and give me mercy which is Thine!—For if the evil that is in me
               gives gifts, how much more shalt Thou give Who art good!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is Thy wealth in Thy servant!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="39">
            <ab>The two things Thou soughtest, in Thy Birth have been done for us.—Our visible body
               Thou hast put on; Thy invisible might we have put on:—our body has become Thy
               clothing; Thy Spirit has become our robe.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has been adorned and has adorned us!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="40">
            <ab>Height and depth were amazed, that Thy Birth subdued the rebels.—For that we gave
               Thee hostages, Thou gavest us the Paraclete:—when the hostages went up from us, the
               Captain of the host came down to us.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who took away and sent down!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="41">
            <ab>Come ye mouths of all and pour forth, and be in the likeness of waters, and wells of
               voices! May the Holy Spirit come,—and sing glory through us all, to the Father Who
               has redeemed us through His Son!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He above all in His Birth!</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
