<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9043">Nativity 2</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9041"> Hymns on Nativity -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܝܠܕܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_II"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_II
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 2</head>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Blessed be that Child, Who gladdened Bethlehem to-day! Blessed be the Babe Who made
               manhood young again to-day! Blessed be the Fruit, Who lowered Himself to our famished
               state! Blessed be the Good One, Who suddenly enriched our necessitousness and
               supplied our needs! Blessed He Whose tender mercies made Him condescend to visit our
               infirmities!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Praise to the Fountain that was sent<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> for our propitiation. Praise be to Him Who
               made void the Sabbath by fulfilling it! Praise too to Him Who rebuked the leprosy and
               it remained not, Whom the fever saw and fled! Praise to the Merciful, Who bore our
               toil! Glory to Thy coming, which quickened the sons of men!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Glory to Him, Who came to us by His first-born! Glory to the Silence,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> that spake
               by His Voice. Glory to the One on high, Who was seen by His Day-spring! Glory to the
               Spiritual, Who was pleased to have a Body, that in it His virtue might be felt, and
               He might by that Body show mercy on His household’s bodies!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Glory to that Hidden One, Whose Son was made manifest! Glory to that Living One,
               Whose Son was made to die! Glory to that Great One, Whose Son descended and was
               small! Glory to the Power Who did straiten His greatness by a form, His unseen nature
               by a shape! With eye and mind we have beheld Him, yea with both of them.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Glory to that Hidden One, Who even with the mind cannot be felt at all by them that
               pry into Him; but by His graciousness was felt by the hand of man! The Nature that
               could not be touched, by His hands was bound and tied, by His feet was pierced and
               lifted up. Himself of His own will He embodied for them that took Him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Blessed be He Whom free will crucified, because He let it: blessed be He Whom the
               wood also did bear, because He allowed it. Blessed be He Whom the grave bound, that
               had [thereby] a limit set it. Blessed be He Whose own will brought Him to the Womb
               and Birth, to arms and to increase [in stature]. Blessed He whose changes purchased
               life for human nature.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Blessed He Who sealed our soul, and adorned it and espoused it to Himself. Blessed
               He Who made our Body a tabernacle for His unseen Nature. Blessed He Who by our tongue
               interpreted His secret things. Let us praise that Voice whose glory is hymned with
               our lute, and His virtue with our harp. The Gentiles have assembled and have come to
               hear His strains.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Glory to the Son of the Good One, Whom the sons of the evil one rejected! Glory to
               the Son of the Just One, Whom the sons of wickedness crucified! Glory to Him Who
               loosed us, and was bound for us all! Glory to Him Who gave the pledge, and redeemed
               it too! Glory to the Beautiful, Who conformed us to His image! Glory to that Fair
               One, Who looked not to our foulnesses!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Glory to Him Who sowed His Light in the darkness,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> and was reproached in His
               hidden state, and covered His secret things. He also stripped and took off from us
               the clothing of our filthiness.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> Glory be to Him on high, Who mixed His salt<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> in
               our minds, His leaven in our souls. His Body became Bread, to quicken our
               deadness.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Praise to the Rich, Who paid for us all, that which He borrowed not;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> and wrote
               [His bill], and also became our debtor! By His yoke He brake from us the chains of
               him that led us captive. Glory to the Judge Who was judged, and made His Twelve to
               sit in judgment on the tribes, and by ignorant men condemned the scribes of that
               nation!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Glory to Him Who could never be measured by us! Our heart is too small for Him, yea
               our mind is too feeble. He makes foolish our littleness by the riches of His Wisdom.
               Glory to Him, Who lowered Himself, and asked;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> that He might hear and learn that
               which He knew; that He might by His questions reveal the treasure of His helpful
               graces!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Let us adore Him Who enlightened with His doctrine our mind, and in our hearing
               sought a pathway for His words. Praise we Him Who grafted into our tree His fruit.
               Thanks to Him Who sent His Heir, that by Him He might draw us to Himself, yea make us
               heirs with Him! Thanks to that Good One, the cause of all goods!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Blessed He Who did not chide, because that He was good! Blessed He Who did not
               spurn, because that He was just also! Blessed He Who was silent, and rebuked; that He
               might quicken us with both! Severe His silence and reproachful. Mild His severity
               even When He was accusing; for He rebuked the traitor, and kissed the thief.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Glory to the hidden Husbandman of our intellects! His seed fell on to our ground,
               and made our mind rich. His increase came an hundredfold into the treasury of our
               souls! Let us adore Him Who sat down and took rest; and walked in the way, so that
               the Way was in the way, and the Door also for them that go in,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/> by which they go in
               to the kingdom.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Blessed the Shepherd Who became a Lamb for our reconcilement! Blessed the Branch Who
               became the Cup of our Redemption! Blessed also be the Cluster, Fount of medicine of
               life! Blessed also be the Tiller, Who became Wheat, that He might be sown; and a
               Sheaf,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/> that He might be cut! [Blessed be] the Architect Who became a Tower for
               our place of safety!<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> Blessed He Who so tempered the feelings of our mind,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12"/>
               that we with our harp should sing that which the winged creatures’ mouth knows not
               with its strains to sing! Glory to Him, Who beheld how we had pleased to be like to
               brutes in our rage and our greediness; and came down and was one of us, that we might
               become heavenly!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Glory be to Him, Who never felt the need of our praising Him; yet felt the need as
               being kind to us, and thirsted<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> as loving us, and asks us to give to Him, and
               longs to give to us. His fruit was mingled with us men, that in Him we might come
               nigh to Him, Who condescended to us. By the Fruit of His stem He grafted us into His
               Tree.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Let us praise Him, Who prevailed and quickened us by His stripes! Praise we Him, Who
               took away the curse by His thorns! Praise we Him Who put death to death by His dying!
               Praise we Him, Who held His peace and justified us! Praise we Him, Who rebuked death
               that had overcome us! Blessed He, Whose helpful graces cleansed out the left
               side!<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Praise we Him Who watched and put to sleep him that led us captive. Praise we Him
               Who went to sleep, and chased our deep sleep away. Glory be to God Who cured weak
               manhood! Glory be to Him Who was baptized, and drowned our iniquity in the deep, and
               choked him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15"/> that choked us! Let us glorify with all our mouths the Lord of all
               creatures!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Blessed be the Physician Who came down and amputated without pain, and healed wounds
               with a medicine that was not harsh. His Son became a Medicine, that showed sinners
               mercy. Blessed be He Who dwelt in the womb, and wrought therein a perfect Temple,
               that He might dwell in it, a Throne that He might be in it, a Garment that He might
               be arrayed in it, and a Weapon that He might conquer in it.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Blessed be He Whom our mouth cannot adequately praise, because His Gift is too great
               for skill of orators [to tell]; neither can the faculties adequately praise His
               goodness. For praise Him as we may, it is too little.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>And since it is useless to be silent and to constrain ourselves, may our feebleness
               excuse such praise as we can sing.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>How gracious He, Who demands not more than our strength can give! How would Thy
               servant be condemned in capital and interest, did he not give such as he could, and
               did he refuse that which He owed! Ocean of glory Who needest not to have Thy glory
               sung, take in Thy goodness this drop of praise; since by Thy Gift Thou hast supplied
               my tongue a sense for glorifying Thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">There is perhaps an allusion here to the pool of Siloam, which comes
               from the root employed in the original.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">This name is given by St. E. to the Father, to suggest to the mind
               that there was a period when the Father had not begun to work by His Word.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">St. E. seems to mean, that whereas the alterations man undergoes in
               his body tend ultimately to decay the same when undergone by our Lord tended to
               life.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">Ps. xcvii. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">Zech. iii. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">Mark ix. 49.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">Ps. lxix. 4. Comp. Luke xvi. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8">Luke ii. 46.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9">John x. 9, xiv. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10">Alluding to the wave-offering, Levit. xxiii. 11, which was ordinarily
               interpreted of Christ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11">Ps. lxi. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12">Prov. xviii. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13">Mat. xxv. 40.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14">Allusion is here made perhaps to Eccles. x. 2, <quote>a wise man’s heart is
               at his right hand, but a fool’s heart is at his left.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n15">Luke viii. 33.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
