<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9052">Nativity 11</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9041"> Hymns on Nativity -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܝܠܕܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XI"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XI
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 11</head>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>(The Virgin Mother to Her Child.)</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>I shall not be jealous, my Son, that Thou art with me, and also with all men. Be
               Thou God to him that confesses Thee, and be thou Lord to him that serves Thee, and be
               Brother to him that loves Thee, that Thou mayest gain all!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>When Thou didst dwell in me, Thou didst also dwell out of me, and when I brought
               Thee forth openly, Thy hidden might was not removed from me. Thou art within me, and
               Thou art without me, O Thou that makest Thy Mother amazed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>For [when] I see that outward form of Thine before mine eyes, the hidden Form is
               shadowed forth <hi rend="doubleQuotes">in my mind,</hi> O holy One. In Thy visible form I see Adam, and in Thy
               hidden form I see Thy Father, who is joined with Thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Hast Thou then shown me alone Thy Beauty in two Forms? Let Bread shadow forth Thee,
               and also the mind; dwell also in Bread and in the eaters thereof. In secret, and
               openly too, may Thy Church see Thee, as well as Thy Mother.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>He that hates Thy Bread is like unto him that hates Thy Body. He that is far off
               that desires Thy Bread, and he that is near that loves Thy Image, are alike. In the
               Bread and in the Body, the first and also the last have seen Thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Yet Thy visible Bread is far more precious than Thy Body; for Thy Body even
               unbelievers have seen, but they have not seen Thy living Bread. They that were far
               off rejoiced! their portion utterly scorns that of those that are near.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Lo! Thy Image is shadowed forth in the blood of the grapes<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> on the Bread; and it
               is shadowed forth on the heart with the finger of love, with the colors of faith.
               Blessed be He that by the Image of His Truth caused the graven images to pass
               away.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Thou art not [so] the Son of Man that I should sing unto Thee a common lullaby; for
               Thy Conception is new, and Thy Birth marvellous. Without the Spirit who shall sing to
               Thee? A new muttering of prophecy is hot within me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>How shall I call Thee a stranger to us, Who art from us? Should I call Thee Son?
               Should I call Thee Brother?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> Husband should I call Thee? Lord should I call Thee, O
               Child that didst give Thy Mother a second birth from the waters?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>For I am Thy sister, of the house of David the father of us Both. Again, I am Thy
               Mother because of Thy Conception, and Thy Bride am I because of Thy sanctification,
               Thy handmaid and Thy daughter, from the Blood and Water wherewith Thou hast purchased
               me and baptised me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The Son of the Most High came and dwelt in me, and I became His Mother; and as by a
               second birth I brought Him forth so did He bring me forth by the second birth,
               because He put His Mother’s garments on, she clothed her body with His glory.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab><persName>Tamar</persName>, who was of the house of <persName>David</persName>, <persName>Amnon</persName> put to shame; and virginity fell and
               perished from them both. My pearl is not lost: in Thy treasury it is stored, because
               Thou hast put it on.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The scent of her brother-in-law slunk from <persName>Tamar</persName>, whose perfume she had stolen. As
               for <persName>Joseph</persName>’s Bride, not even his breath exhaled from her garments, since she
               conceived Cinnamon.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> A wall of fire was Thy Conception unto me, O holy Son.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The little flower was faint, because the smell of the Lily<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> of Glory was great.
               The Treasure-house of spices stood in no need of flower or its smells! Flesh stood
               aloof because it perceived in the womb a Conception from the Spirit.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The woman ministers before the man, because he is her head. <persName>Joseph</persName> rose to minister
               before his Lord, Who was in <persName>Mary</persName>. The priest ministered before Thy ark by reason of
               Thy holiness.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab><persName>Moses</persName> carried the tables of stone which the Lord wrote, and <persName>Joseph</persName> bare about the
               pure Tablet in whom the Son of the Creator was dwelling. The tables had ceased,
               because the world was filled with Thy doctrine.</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">The Roman Editor points out that this alludes to a rite in the Syrian
               Liturgy, in which the officiating Priest is instructed to dip one portion of the
               consecrated bread into the cup and sprinkle the rest with it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">Mat. xii. 50.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">Cant. iv. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">Cant. ii. 1.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
