<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9051">Nativity 10</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9041"> Hymns on Nativity -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܝܠܕܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_X"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_X
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 10</head>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>In Thee will I begin to speak, Thou Head that didst begin all created things.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> I,
               even I will open my mouth, but it is Thou that fillest my mouth.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> I am the earth to
               Thee, and Thou art the husbandman. Sow Thy voice in me,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> Thou that sowedst Thyself
               in the womb of thy Mother.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>“All the chaste daughters of the Hebrews,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> and the virgins’ daughters of the chief
               men, are astonished at me! For Thee doth the daughter of the poor meet with envy, for
               Thee, the daughter of the weak with jealousy. Who hath given Thee to me?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab><quote>O Son of the Rich One, Who abhorred the bosom of the rich women, who led Thee to
               the poor? for Joseph was needy and I also in want, yet Thy merchants have come, and
               brought gold, to the house of the poor.</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>She saw the Magi: her songs increased at their offerings; “Lo! Thy worshippers have
               surrounded me, yea thy offerings have encircled me. Blessed be the Babe who made His
               Mother a harp for His words:</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>“And as the harp waiteth for its master, my mouth waiteth for Thee. May the tongue
               of Thy Mother bring what pleases Thee; and since I have learnt a new Conception by
               Thee, let my mouth learn in Thee, O new born Son, a new song of praise.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>“And if hindrances are no hindrances to Thee, since difficulties are easy to Thee,
               as a womb without marriage conceived Thee, and a belly without seed brought Thee
               forth, it is easy for a little mouth to multiply Thy great glory.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>“Lo! I am oppressed and despised, and yet cheerful: mine ears are filled with
               reproof and scorn; and it is a small thing to me to bear, for ten thousand troubles
               can a single comfort of Thine chase away.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab><quote>And since I am not despised by Thee, O Son, my countenance is bright; and I am
               slandered for having conceived, and yet have brought forth the Truth who justifies
               me. For if Tamar was justified by Judah, how much more shall I be justified by
               Thee!</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>David Thy father sung in a psalm of Thee before Thou hadst come, that to Thee should
               be given the gold of Sheba.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> This psalm that he sung of Thee, lo! it, whilst Thou
               art yet a child, in reality heaps before thee myrrh and gold.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>And the hundred and fifty Psalms that he wrote, in Thee were seasoned, because all
               the sayings of prophecy stood in need of Thy sweetness, for without Thy salt all
               manner of wisdom were tasteless.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/></ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">Rev. iii. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">Ps. lxxxi. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">Heb. vi. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">The Virgin Mother here speaks.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">Ps. lxxii. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">Job vi. 6.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
