<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9046">Nativity 5</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9041"> Hymns on Nativity -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܝܠܕܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_V"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_V
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 5</head>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>At the birth of the Son, there was a great shouting in Bethlehem; for the Angels
               came down, and gave praise there. Their voices were a great thunder: at that voice of
               praise the silent ones came, and gave praise to the Son.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Blessed be that Babe in whom Eve and Adam were restored to youth! The shepherds also
               came laden with the best gifts of their flock: sweet milk, clean flesh, befitting
               praise! They put a difference, and gave Joseph the flesh, Mary the milk, and the Son
               the praise! They brought and presented a suckling lamb to the Paschal Lamb, a
               first-born to the First-born, a sacrifice to the Sacrifice, a lamb of time to the
               Lamb of Truth. Fair sight [to see] the lamb offered to The Lamb!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The lamb bleated as it was offered before the First-born. It praised the Lamb, that
               had come to set free the flocks and the oxen from sacrifices:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> yea that Paschal
               Lamb, Who handed down and brought in the Passover of the Son.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The shepherds came near and worshipped Him with their staves. They saluted Him with
               peace, prophesying the while, <quote>Peace, O Prince of the Shepherds.</quote> The rod of Moses<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/>
               praised Thy Rod, O Shepherd of all; for Thee Moses praises, although his lambs have
               become wolves, and his flocks as it were dragons, and his sheep fanged beasts. In the
               fearful wilderness his flocks became furious, and attacked him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Thee then the Shepherds praise, because Thou hast reconciled the wolves and the
               lambs within the fold; O Babe, that art older than Noah and younger than Noah, that
               reconciled all within the ark amid the billows!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>David Thy father for a lamb’s sake slaughtered a lion. Thou, O Son of David, hast
               killed the unseen wolf that murdered Adam, the simple lamb who fed and bleated in
               Paradise.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>At that voice of praise, brides were moved to hallow themselves, and virgins to be
               chaste, and even young girls became grave: they advanced and came in multitudes, and
               worshipped the Son.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Aged women of the city of David came to the daughter of David; they gave thanks and
               said, <quote>Blessed be our country, whose streets are lightened with the rays of Jesse!
               Today is the throne of David established by Thee, O Son of David.</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The old men cried, <quote>Blessed be that Son Who restored Adam to youth, Who was vexed to
               see that he was old and worn out, and that the serpent who had killed him, had
               changed his skin and had gotten himself away. Blessed be the Babe in Whom Adam and
               Eve were restored to youth.</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The chaste women said, O Blessed Fruit, bless the fruit of our wombs; to Thee may
               they be given as first-born. They waxed fervent and prophesied concerning their
               children, who, when they were killed for Him, were cut off, as it were
               first-fruits.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The barren also fondled Him, and carried Him; they rejoiced and said, Blessed Fruit
               born without marriage, bless the wombs of us that are married; have mercy on our
               barrenness, Thou wonderful Child of Virginity!</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">Ps. l. 9; Is. lxvi. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">Exod. iv. 4, etc.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
