<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9049">Nativity 8</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9041"> Hymns on Nativity -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܝܠܕܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_VIII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_VIII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 8</head>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>That Thy Resurrection might be believed among the gainsayers, they sealed Thee up
               within the sepulchre, and set guards; for it was for Thee that they sealed the
               sepulchre and set guards, O Son of the Living One!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>When they had buried Thee, if they had neglected Thee and left Thee, and gone, there
               would have been room to lie [and say] that they did steal, O Quickener of all! When
               they craftily sealed Thy sepulchre, they made Thy Glory greater.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>A type of Thee therefore was Daniel, and also Lazarus; one in the den, which the
               Gentiles sealed up, and one in the sepulchre, that the People opened. Lo! their signs
               and their seals reproved them.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Their mouth had been open, if they had left Thy sepulchre open. But they went away
               because they had shut Thy sepulchre and sealed it, and closed up their own mouths.
               Yea they closed it, and when they had senselessly covered Thy sepulchre, all the
               slanderers covered their own heads.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>But in Thy Resurrection Thou persuadest them concerning Thy Birth; since the womb
               was sealed, and the sepulchre closed up; being alike pure in the womb, and living in
               the sepulchre.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> The womb and the sepulchre being sealed were witnesses unto
               Thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The belly and hell cried aloud of Thy Birth and Thy Resurrection: The belly
               conceived Thee, which was sealed; hell brought Thee forth which was closed up. Not
               after nature did either the belly conceive Thee, or hell give Thee up!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Sealed was the sepulchre whereto they had entrusted Thee, that it might keep the
               dead [safe], Virgin was the womb which no man knew. Virgin womb and sealed sepulchre,
               like trumpets, proclaimed Him in the ears of a deaf people.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The sealed belly and the closed rock were amongst the accusers. For they slandered
               the Conception as being of the seed of man, and the Resurrection as being of the
               robbery of man; the seal and the signet convicted them, and pleaded that Thou wert of
               Heaven.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The people stood between Thy Birth and Thy Resurrection. They slandered Thy Birth,
               Thy Death condemned them: they set aside Thy Resurrection, Thy Birth refuted them;
               they were two wrestlers that stopped the mouth that slandered.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>For Elijah they went and searched the mountains:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> as they sought him on earth,
               they the more confirmed that he was taken up. Their searching bare witness that he
               was taken up, in that it found him not.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>If then prophets that had had forewarning of Elijah’s ascension, doubted as it were
               of his going up, how much more would impure men speak slander of the Son? By their
               own guards He convinced them that He was risen again.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>To Thy Mother, Lord, no man knew what name to give. Should he call her Virgin, her
               Child stood [there]; and married no man knew her to be! If then none comprehended Thy
               Mother, who shall suffice for Thee?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>For she was, alone, Thy Mother; along with all, Thy Sister. She was Thy mother, she
               was Thy Sister. She along with chaste women<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> was Thy betrothed. With everything
               didst Thou adorn Her, Thou ornament of Thy Mother.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>For she was Thy Bride by nature ere Thou hadst come; she conceived Thee not by
               nature after Thou wast come, O Holy One, and was a Virgin when she had brought Thee
               forth holily.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Mary gained in Thee, O Lord, the honours of all married women. She conceived [Thee]
               within her without marriage. There was milk in her breasts, not after the way of
               nature. Thou madest the thirsty land suddenly a fountain of milk.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>If she carried Thee, Thy mighty look made her burden light; if she gave Thee to eat,
               it was because Thou wert hungry; if she gave Thee to drink [it was], because Thou
               wert thirsty; willingly if she embraced Thee, Thou, the coal of mercies, didst keep
               her bosom safe.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>A wonder is Thy Mother. The Lord entered her, and became a servant: the Word entered
               her, and became silent within her; thunder entered her, and His voice was still: the
               Shepherd of all entered her; He became a Lamb in her, and came forth bleating.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The Belly of Thy Mother changed the order of things, O Thou that orderest all! The
               rich went in, He came out poor: the High One went in, He came out lowly. Brightness
               went into her and clothed Himself, and came forth a despised form.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The Mighty went in, and clad Himself with fear from the Belly. He that giveth food
               to all went in, and gat hunger. He that giveth all to drink went in, and gat thirst.
               Naked and bare came forth from her the Clother of all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The daughters of the Hebrews that cried in the Lamentations of Jeremiah, instead of
               lamentations of their Scriptures, used lulling-songs from their own books: a hidden
               Power within their words was prophesying.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Eve lifted up her eyes from Sheol and rejoiced in that day, because the Son of her
               daughter as a medicine of life came down to raise up the mother of His mother.
               Blessed Babe, that bruised the head of the Serpent that smote her!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>She saw the type of Thee from the youth of Isaac the fair. For Thee Sarah, as seeing
               that types of thee rested on his childhood, called him, saying, O child of my vows,
               in whom is hidden the Lord of vows.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Samson the Nazarite shadowed forth a type of Thy working. He tore the lion, the
               image of death, whom Thou didst destroy, and caused to go forth from his bitterness
               the sweetness of life for men.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Hannah also embraced Samuel; for Thy righteousness was hidden in him who hewed in
               pieces Agag as [a type] of the wicked one. He wept over Saul, because Thy goodness
               also was shadowed forth in him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> How meek art Thou! How mighty art Thou, O
               Child!<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> Thy judgment is mighty, Thy love is sweet! Who can stand against Thee? Thy
               Father is in Heaven, Thy Mother is on earth; who shall declare Thee?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> If a man
               should seek after Thy Nature, it is hidden in Heaven in the mighty Bosom of the
               Godhead; and if a man seek after Thy visible Body, it is laid down before their eyes
               in the lowly bosom of Mary.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The mind wanders between Thy generations, O Thou Rich One! Thick folds are upon Thy
               Godhead. Who can sound Thy depths, Thou great Sea that made itself little?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>We come to see Thee as God, and, lo! Thou art a man: we come to see Thee as man, and
               there shineth forth the Light of Thy Godhead!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Who would believe that Thou art the Heir of David’s Throne? A manger hast Thou
               inherited out of [all] his beds, a cave has come down to Thee out of all his palaces.
               Instead of his chariots a common ass’s colt, perchance, comes down to Thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>How fearless art Thou, O Babe, that dost let all have thee [to carry]: upon every
               one that meets with Thee dost Thou smile: to every one that sees Thee, art Thou
               glad-some! Thy love is as one that hungers after men.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Thou makest no distinction between Thy fathers and strangers, nor Thy Mother and
               maidservants, nor her that suckled Thee and the unclean. Was it Thy forwardness or
               Thy love, O Thou that lovest all?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>What moves Thee that Thou didst let all that saw Thee have Thee, both rich and poor?
               Thou helpedst them that called Thee not. Whence came it that Thou hungeredst so for
               men?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>How great was Thy love, that if one rebuked Thee, Thou wast not wroth! if a man
               threatened Thee, Thou wast not terrified! if one hissed at Thee, Thou didst not feel
               vexed! Thou art above the laws of the avengers of injuries.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Moses was meek, and [yet] his zeal was harsh, for he struggled and slew. Elisha
               also, who restored a child to life, tore a multitude of children in pieces by bears.
               Who art Thou, O Child, whose love is greater than that of the Prophets?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>The son of Hagar who was wild, kicked at Isaac.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> He bore it and was silent, and
               his mother was jealous. Art Thou the mystery of him, or is not he the type of Thee?
               art thou like Isaac, or is it not he that is like Thee?</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">Ps. lxxxviii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">2 Kings ii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">Ps. xlv. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">1 Sam. ii. 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">Luke ii. 52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">Is. liii. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">Gen. xvi. 12, and xxi. 9.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
