<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9059">Nativity 18</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9041"> Hymns on Nativity -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܝܠܕܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XVIII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XVIII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 18</head>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Praise be to Him Who sent Him! (bis)</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, O Church, for lo! in thee is the sound,—of the great feast the
               festival of the King!—Sion is deserted, her gates are sore athirst,—and forsaken of
               festivals.—Blessed thy gates that are open yet not filled,—and thy halls that are
               enlarged yet suffice not!—In the midst of thee lo! is the sound, of the nations that
               cry out, and have put to silence the People.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, O Church, that in thy festivals,—the Watchers rejoice amid thy
               festivity!—for one night the Watchers gave praise,—on the earth which withheld and
               refused praise.—Blessed thy voices that have been sown and reaped,—and in Heaven
               stored up in garners!—Thy mouth is a censer, and thy voices as perfumes, breathing
               vapour in thy festivals.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, O Church, that all oblations,—are brought unto thee in this
               feast.—The Magi once among traitors, offered them to the Truth.—Blessed thy abode
               that He bowed Himself and dwelt therein, Son of the King Who is worshipped with
               gifts!—Gold from the West, and spices from the East,—are offered in Thy
               Festivals.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, O Church, that there is not with thee,—a tyrant King slayer of
               babes! for he killed in Bethlehem the little ones at random,—that he might put to
               death the Child that gives life to all.—Blessed thy children that are envied and
               worshipped,—by Kings, for those are promised for Thy worship,—the crowns of the
               East:—he who trod down thy dear ones, shall be trodden down by thy beloved.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, O Church, for lo! over thee,—Isaiah too exults in his
               prophecy,—”Lo a Virgin shall conceive and bear,—a Son” Whose name is great mystery!—O
               interpretation revealed in the Church!—two names that were joined and became
               one;—”Emmanuel,”—God be with thee ever, Who joined thee with His members!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, O Church, in Micah who cried out,—<quote>A Shepherd shall come forth
               from Ephrata</quote>:—for He came to Bethlehem to take—from thence the rod of Jesse and to
               rule the nations.—Blessed thy lambs that are sealed with His seal,—and thy sheep that
               are kept by His sword!—Thou art, O Church,—the abiding Bethlehem,—for in thee is the
               Bread of Life!<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, O Church, for lo! in thee rejoices,—Daniel also the man
               beloved,—who foretold that the glorious Messiah shall be killed,—and the city of
               holiness be laid desolate at His killing!—Woe to the People that was rejected and is
               not converted—Blessed the nations that were called and turned not away!—The bidden
               guests refused,—and others in their stead enjoyed their banquet.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, O Church, for on thy, lute, lo! King David sings psalms in thee!
               In the Spirit he sings of Him <quote>Thou art My Son and I—this day have begotten Thee</quote> in
               the glories of holiness.—Blessed thy ears that have been purged to hear!—On His day
               watch thou as His Body and call on Him;—be taught by Sion,—which saddened His Feast;
               make Him glad Who has gladdened thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, O Church, that all festivals—have taken flight from Sion and
               sheltered with thee!—In the midst of thee the wearied Prophets have found rest,—from
               the labour and the reproachthey bore in Judah.—Blessed the books unrolled in thy
               temples,—and the festivals celebrated in thy shrines!—Sion is forsaken,—and lo! today
               the nations shout in thy festivals.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, O Church, in ten blessings,—which our Lord has given as a mystery
               complete:—for on ten all the numbers hang, therefore art thou perfect by ten
               blessings.—Blessed thy crowns that are twined—with all blessings mixed in every
               crown!—O blessed one,—with every blessing crowned, on me too send thy blessing!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, Ephrata, mother of Kings, that from thee sprang the Lord of
               diadems!—Micah gave thee tidings that He is from everlasting, and the span of His
               times is not comprehended.—Blessed thine eyes which first of all discerned Him!—thee
               He deemed worthy to see Him when He appeared,—Chief of benediction,—and Beginning of
               gladness, thou didst receive first of all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, Bethlehem, that the towns envy thee,—and the fortified cities!—As
               they envy thee, so the women envy Mary,—and the virgins daughters of princes.—Blessed
               the maiden in whom He deigned to abide,—and the city wherein He deigned to sojourn;—a
               poor maiden,—and a small city, He chose Him to humble Himself.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Blessed art thou, Bethlehem, that in thee was the beginning,—for Him the Son Who
               from everlasting is in the Father!—It is hard to comprehend, that before Time He
               is,—Who in thee made Himself subject to Time.—Blessed thine ears, for in thee first
               was heard the cry—of the Lamb of God who exulted in thee!—Narrow though thy
               manger,—He spread Himself on all sides, and was worshipped of every creature.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Blessed art thou too, Mary, that thy name—is great and exalted because of thy
               child!—Thou canst tell then how and how long—and where He dwelt in thee, the great
               One in small room.—Blessed thy mouth that praised and enquired not,—and thy tongue
               that glorified and questioned not!—For His Mother was uncertain concerning Him,—even
               while she carried Him in the womb; who then shall suffice to comprehend Him?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>O Woman, thou whom no man knew,—how can we behold the Son thou hast borne?—For no
               eyes suffice to stand—before the transfigurations of the glory, that is on Him.—For
               tongues of fire abide in Him—Who sent tongues by His Ascension.—Be every tongue
               warned,—that our questioning is as stubble, and as fire our scrutiny.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>Blessed is he the priest who in the sanctuary,—offers to the Father the Son of the
               Father,—the fruit that is plucked from our tree, though it be wholly of the Divine
               Majesty!—Blessed the hands that are hallowed and offer Him!—and the lips that are
               spent in kissing Him!—The Spirit in the Temple—longed for His embrace; and at His
               Crucifixion rent the veil and went forth.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>The Archangel gave thee greeting,—as the earnest of holiness—Earth became to him new
               Heavens,—when the Watcher came down and sang glory on it.—The sons of the Highest
               encompassed thy habitation—because of the Son of the King that dwelt in thee.—Thy
               abode below,—to the Heaven above was made like by the host of Watchers.</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">Bethlehem = House of Bread.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
