<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9057">Nativity 16</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9041"> Hymns on Nativity -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܝܠܕܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XVI"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XVI
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 16</head>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Glory to all of Thee from all of us! (bis.)</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Who then that is mortal man, can declare concerning the All-Life giver,—Who quitted
               the height of His Majesty, and abased Himself to humility?—Thou Who exaltest all in
               Thy Birth, exalt my weak mind,—to declare of Thy Birth; not that I should search out
               Thy Majesty,—but that I should proclaim Thy grace.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who conceals and reveals in His discourses!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>It is a great marvel that the Son, dwelt wholly in a body;—abode therein wholly and
               it sufficed for Him; dwelt therein though not bounded thereby.—His Will was wholly
               therein; His bounds reached wholly to His Father.—Who is sufficient to tell, how
               though He dwelt wholly in a body.—He likewise dwelt wholly in all?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who though without bounds was bounded!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Thy Majesty is concealed from us; Thy Grace is revealed before us.—I will be silent,
               O Lord of Thy Majesty; and I will tell of Thy grace.—Thy grace clove to Thee, and
               bowed Thee down to our vileness:—Thy grace made Thee a babe; Thy grace made Thee
               man:—it straitened, it enlarged, Thy Majesty.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be the might that became little and became great!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Glory to Him Who became lowly, though lofty He was by His nature!—He became in His
               love the firstborn of <persName>Mary</persName>, Firstborn though He be of Godhead.—He became in name the
               offspring of <persName>Joseph</persName>, offspring though He be of the Most High.—He became by His own
               Will man, God though He be by His Nature.—Glorified be Thy Will and Thy Nature!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be Thy Glory which put on our image!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Yea, O Lord, Thy Birth, has become mother of all creatures; for it travailed anew
               and gave birth, to mankind which gave birth to Thee. Thou wast born of it bodily; it
               was born of Thee spiritually.—All that Thou camest for to birth, was that man might
               be born in Thy likeness.—Thy Birth became the author of birth to all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who became a youth and to all gave youth!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>When man’s hope had broken down, hope was increased by Thy Birth.—Good tidings of
               hope they bore, the Heavenly Ones to men.—<persName>Satan</persName> who cut off our hope, his own hope by
               his own hands had cut off.—when he saw that hope was increased: Thy Birth became to
               the hopeless,—a fountain teaming with hope.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who bore the tidings of hope!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>The day of Thy Birth is like Thee, for it is desired and loved as Thou.—We who saw
               not Thy Birth, and its flame as in its own time,—in this Thy day we see Thee, even as
               Thou wast a babe;—beloved by all men, lo! in Thee the Churches rejoice;—Thy day
               adorns and is adorned.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be Thy day which was ordained for us!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Thy day has given us a gift, to which the Father has none other like;—It was not
               Seraphim He sent us, nor yet did Cherubim come down among us;—there came not Watchers
               or Ministers, but the Firstborn to Whom they minister.—Who can suffice to give
               thanks, that the Majesty which is beyond measure—is laid in the lowly manger!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who gave us what He had won!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>That generation Thy Birth made glad, and our generation Thy day makes glad: twofold
               was the happiness of that generation, for they saw Thy Birth and also Thy day:—less
               is the happiness of them that come after, for the day of Thy Birth they see only.—Yet
               because they that then were, doubted, greater is the happiness of them that come
               after,—who though they have not seen Thee have believed in Thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be Thy happiness that is added to us!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>The Magi exalted from afar; the Scribes murmured near at hand;—the prophet showed
               his message, and <persName>Herod</persName> his wrath;—the scribes showed their doctrine, the Magi showed
               their offerings. It is a marvel that to Him, the Babe, they of His own house hasted
               with their swords, and they that were strangers with their offerings.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be Thy Birth which has stirred up all!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>The bosom of <persName>Mary</persName> amazes me, that it sufficed for Thee, Lord, and embraced Thee.—All
               creation were too small, to conceal Thy Majesty;—Heaven and earth too narrow, to be
               in the likeness of wings,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> to cover Thy Godhead.—Too small for Thee was the bosom
               of earth; great enough for Thee was the bosom of <persName>Mary</persName>.—He dwelt in the bosom and
               healed in her bosom.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>He was wrapped meanly in swaddling clothes, and offerings were offered Him.—He put
               on garments in youth, and from them there came forth helps: He put on the waters of
               baptism, and from them there shone forth beams:—He put on linen cloths in death, and
               in them were shown forth triumphs; with His humiliations, His exaltations.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who joined His Glory to His Passion!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>All these are the changes of raiment, which Mercy put off and put on,—when He strove
               to put on <persName>Adam</persName>, the glory which he had put off.—He was wrapped in swaddling-clothes
               as <persName>Adam</persName> with leaves; and clad in garments instead of skins.—He was baptized for
               <persName>Adam</persName>’s sin, and buried for <persName>Adam</persName>’s death:—He rose and raised <persName>Adam</persName> into Glory.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who came down and clothed him and went up!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Though Thy Birth had sufficed, for <persName>Adam</persName>’s sons as for <persName>Adam</persName>;—O Mighty One Who didst
               become a babe, in Thy Birth anew hast Thou begotten me!—O pure One Who wast baptized,
               let Thy Washing wash away our filth—O Living One who wast buried, may we gain life in
               Thy death!—I will praise all of Thee in Him that fills all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Glory to all of Thee from all of us!</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">The word used for <quote>bosom</quote> in this stanza, also means <quote>wing.</quote></note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
