<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9058">Nativity 17</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/9041"> Hymns on Nativity -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܝܠܕܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XVII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_on_the_Nativity/Hymn_XVII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 17</head>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Praise to Thee from every mouth on this Day of Thy Birth!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Infants were slain because of Thy Birth, Thou Giver of life to all—But because He
               Who was slain was a King, our Lord the Lord of Kingdoms,—the tyrant in subtlety, gave
               for Him slain hostages,—clad in the mysteries of His slaying: the ranks of heaven
               received,—the hostages that they of earth offered.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be the King who magnified Him!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>All the Kings of the house of <persName>David</persName>, transmitted and hauled on each to each,—the
               throne and crown of the Son of <persName>David</persName>, as guardian of a deposit.—In one they reached
               their bound and limit, when He came, the Lord of all things,—and took away from them
               all things, and cut off the transmission of all things.…</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who is clad in that which is His!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>The doves moaned in <placeName>Bethlehem</placeName>, that the serpent destroyed their offspring.—The eagle
               betook himself to <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, to go down and receive the promises.—<placeName>Egypt</placeName> rejoiced in Him
               that there came, abundance for payment of debts,—which had failed the sons of <persName>Joseph</persName>.
               Among the sons of <persName>Joseph</persName> He laboured and paid—the debts of the sons of <persName>Joseph</persName>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who called Him out of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>The Scribes read daily, that the Star arises out of <persName>Jacob</persName>.—For the People were the
               Voice and the reading, for the nations the rising of the Star and the
               interpretation:—for them were the Books and for us the facts; for them boughs and for
               us fruits.—The Scribes read in things written; the Magi saw in things done, the
               outshining of that which was read.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who added to us their books!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Who is able to tell, of the withdrawal and the appearings,—of the shining star that
               went, before the bearers of the offerings?—It appeared and proclaimed the crown; it
               was hid and concealed His Body.—It was for the Son in twofold wise, herald and
               guardian;—it guarded His Body, it proclaimed His Crown.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who has given wisdom to them that proclaim Him!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>The tyrant gazed on the Magi, as they asked <quote>Where is the son of the King?</quote>—While
               his heart was gloomy, he sought for himself a cheerful countenance.—With the sheep he
               sent wolves, that should kill the Lamb of God.—The Lamb went down to <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, that
               thence He might judge them,—whence He had saved them.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who yet again subdued them.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>The Magi declared to the tyrant, <quote>When thy servants joined us,—the bright star
               withdrew itself, yea the paths hid themselves.</quote>—The blessed ones knew not, that the
               king had sent bitter foes,—murderers as if worshippers, to destroy the sweet
               fruit,—whereof the bitter eat and are made sweet.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: To Thee be glory, Medicine of life!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>When there the Magi received, commandment to go and seek Him.—it is written of them
               that they saw, that bright star and rejoiced.—Thus it is known that it had been
               withdrawn; therefore rejoiced they at its aspect.—It was hid and hindered the
               murderers, it arose and called the worshippers;—it overthrew a part and it called a
               part.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has triumphed in both parts!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>The abhorred one who slew the children, how did he overlook the Child?—Justice
               hindered him that he thought, the Magi would return to him.—While he stayed waiting
               to seize, the Worshipped and His worshippers,—everything escaped his hands, the
               offerings and the worshippers took flight,—from the tyrant to the Son of the
               King.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Glory to Him who knows all counsels!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>The blameless Magi as they slept, meditated on their beds:—sleep became a mirror,
               and a dream rose on it as light.—The murderer they saw and trembled, as his guile and
               his sword flashed forth.—He taught the men guile, he sharpened the sword to
               sharpness:—the Watcher taught the sleepers.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He who gives prudence to the simple!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>The simple who believe have known, two Comings of Christ:—but the foolish scribes
               have not even perceived one Coming.—Yet the nations have life in the first, and shall
               rise again there in the second.—The People whose mind is blinded, the first Coming
               has dispersed;—the second shall blot out their memory.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be the King Who is come and is to come!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>When the Saviour arose as the blind, the Sun showed forth his beams,—and they were
               clothed in darkness: the Brightness sent forth his light,—and He brought the sons of
               the stars, to make manifest the sons of darkness.—For lo! among you is the star, but
               on your eyes the veil.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: To Thee be glory, newborn Sun!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Prophets declared concerning His Birth, but they made not plain the time thereof.—He
               sent the Magi, and they came and showed of its time.—Yet the Magi who made known the
               time, made not plain who the Child should be.—A star of splendid light, in its course
               showed who the Child was,—how splendid was His lineage.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who by them all was pointed out!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>They scorned the trumpet of <persName>Isaiah</persName>, which sounded forth His pure Conception,—they
               silenced the lute of the Psalms, which sang of His Priesthood;—the harp of the Spirit
               they hushed, which sang again of His Kingdom;—under deep silence they closed up, the
               great Birth that joined the cry—of them above with them below.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who appeared in the midst of silence!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>His voice was the secret key that opened the mouths of the Magi.—Whereas preachers
               were silent in <placeName>Judah</placeName>, they made their voice sound through creation;—and the Gospel
               which those had scorned, these who came from far took and departed.—The scorners
               began to hear their own orders from strangers, who cried out the name of the Son of
               <persName>David</persName>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who by our voice has put them to silence!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>Whereas the People scorned offerings, and brought them not to Him the Son of the
               King,—He sent His herald to the nations, and caused them to come with their
               offerings:—yet not all of them caused He to come, for it could not suffice for
               them,—the narrow bosom of <placeName>Bethlehem</placeName>; but the bosom of Holy Church,—enlarged itself
               and contained her children.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has made the barren fruitful!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>The slayers of <placeName>Bethlehem</placeName> mowed down the tender flowers that among them—should perish
               the tender seedling, wherein was hidden the Bread of life.—But the ear of corn that
               has life had escaped, that it should come to the sheaves in harvest:—the grape that
               escaped when young, gave itself to the treading,—that its wine might give life to
               souls.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Glory to Thee, Treasury of life!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>The murderers went into a paradise, full of tender fruits:—they shook off the
               flowers from the bough, blossoms and buds they destroyed,—unblemished oblations he
               offered, the persecutor unwittingly.—To him woe, but to them blessing! <placeName>Bethlehem</placeName> was
               first to give, virgin fruits to the Holy One.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who receives the first fruits!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>The Scribes were silenced in envy, the Pharisees in jealousy.—Men of stone cried out
               and gave praise, who had a heart of stone.—They applauded in presence of the Stone,
               the rejected that has become the Head.—Stones were made flesh by that Stone, and
               obtained mouths to speak; stones cried out through that Stone.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be Thy Birth that has caused stones to cry out!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>The Star that is written in Scripture, the nations beheld from afar,—that the People
               might be shamed which is near; O People instructed and puffed up! which by the
               nations hast been in turn instructed, how and where they saw,—that vision whereof
               <persName>Balaam</persName> spake; a stranger he who spread abroad concerning it,—strangers they who saw
               it.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who has provoked to jealousy them of His own house!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>Let my supplication draw nigh to Thy Door, yea my poverty to Thy Treasury!—Give to
               me my Lord without measure, as God unto man!—And though Thou increase gifts as Son of
               the Blessed, and though Thou add to them as Son of the King;—though I be thankless as
               are all creatures of dust, as <persName>Adam</persName> so is the son of <persName>Adam</persName>,—and as the Blessed so too
               is the Son of the Blessed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <ab>Response: Praise be to Thee Who art like unto Thy Father!</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
