<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Evagrius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_18"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_18
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 18: The Triumph of Evagrius</head>
         <p>And we also saw Evagrius, who was a man of great ability and learning, and who, through
            the experience of the matters which had passed over him, had acquired the discernment of
            good thoughts; and he had on several occasions gone down to the city of Alexandria and
            shut the mouths of the heathen philosophers. Now he commanded the brethren who were with
            us not to drink their fill of water, because devils were always to be found in the
            places where there were fountains of water, even according to the word of our Lord, Who
            said, <quote>When the evil spirit hath gone forth from a man, it departeth and wandereth about
            in the places wherein there is no water seeking rest, which it findeth not</quote> (St. Matthew
            12, 43). And he spake unto us many things concerning the labours of ascetic excellence,
            and he confirmed our souls in the faith. Now many of the monks neither ate bread nor
            fruit (God forbid!), but bitter herbs and vegetables soaked in vinegar; and some of them
            never slept at all during the night, but, either sitting up or standing, they continued
            to pray until the morning.</p>
         <p>Here endeth the Triumph of Evagrius</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
