<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Triumph of another Ammon</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_23"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_23
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 23: The Triumph of another Ammon who was in Nitria</head>
         <p>And we also saw there a certain Abbâ whose name also was Ammon, and he possessed [a
            number of] small houses which were exceedingly beautiful, and a courtyard, and a well of
            water, and other things for use; and a certain brother, who wished earnestly to obtain
            mercy, came to him, and said unto the blessed man, <quote>Build me a little house wherein I
            may dwell.</quote> Then the holy man, like one who was going forth [to do] this, ordered him
            not to depart from these chambers until he could find one which would be convenient for
            him; and he left to him everything he had, together with the chambers, and went and shut
            himself up in a house which was far away from that place. And if the brethren who came
            to him seeking to have mercy shown to them were many, he would assemble the whole
            brotherhood, and [tell] one to draw water, and another to bring bricks, and a house for
            them would be completed in a day. Then the brethren would invite those who were ready to
            inhabit the chambers to refresh themselves in the church, and whilst they were resting
            there he would fill his cloak, and baskets also, with bread and with other things which
            they would want to make use of, and would carry them to the new house, and it was not
            known to any man that he was the source (or head) of the gifts of each one of them. And
            at eventide the brethren who were ready to take up their abode in these [new] chambers
            would come there, and would find ready before them whatsoever they required.</p>
         <p>Here endeth the Triumph of the other Ammon</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
