<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Eulogius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_13"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_13
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 13: The Triumphs of the Blessed <persName>Eulogius</persName></head>
         <p>we saw also another mighty elder whose name was <persName>Eulogius</persName>, who entreated God to give him
            at the time when he was about to offer up the Offering such knowledge that he might be
            able to know the mind of each and every one of the monks who drew nigh to [partake of]
            the Holy Things; and on several occasions this man saw monks prepared to draw nigh to
            the Holy and Glorious Mysteries, and restrained them, saying, <quote>How is it that ye dare to
            draw nigh to the Holy Mysteries [seeing that] ye have evil minds?</quote> <pb n="362"/>And to another of
            them also he said, <quote>This night thou hast pondered in thy mind about filthy fornication.</quote>
            And to another he said, <quote>Thou hast thought in thy mind that whether a man be righteous
            or wicked there is nothing to hinder thee from drawing nigh to the goodness of God.</quote> And
            to another he said, <quote>Thou hast had doubt in thy mind whether the Holy Things are able to
            sanctify those who draw nigh to them; therefore keep thou away for a little from the
            Holy Mysteries, and repent with all thy soul, so that thou mayest obtain remission of
            [thy] sins, and thou mayest be held worthy of association with <persName>Christ</persName>. For if ye do not
            cleanse your thoughts before ye draw nigh [to them] ye will be unable to [obtain
            forgiveness].</quote></p>
         <p>Here endeth the Triumph of <persName>Eulogius</persName></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
