<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Abba Theon</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_7"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_7
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 7: The Triumphs of Abba <persName>Theon</persName></head>
         <p>And we also saw another blessed man, who lived at some distance from the city, at a
            place which faced the open desert, and his name was <persName>Theon</persName>; he was a holy man who had
            shut himself up in a small house by himself, and he had kept silence for thirty years,
            and because he had performed many mighty deeds he was held to be a prophet among <pb n="338"/>the
            people. For every day a multitude of sick folk went forth to him, and he would stretch
            out his hand through the window and lay it upon them, and would send them away healed.
            Now the countenance of the blessed man appeared to be like that of an angel, and his
            eyes sparkled, and he was filled with all the grace of God. A short time ago certain
            thieves came by night against the blessed man from a great distance, thinking that they
            would find a large quantity of gold with him, and they were prepared to kill him, but
            when he had said a prayer they found themselves fast bound with ropes before the door,
            [and they had to stay there] until the morning. And when the crowds of people came to
            him in the morning, they had it in their minds to commit the thieves to the flames, but
            the blessed man felt himself urged to speak a word unto the men, and he said, <quote>Let these
            thieves depart in peace, for if ye do not let them, the gracious gift of healing which I
            possess will depart from me.</quote> Then the multitudes hearkened unto his words, for they did
            not dare to treat them lightly, and straightway the thieves went and took up their abode
            with the brethren [and] monks, and changed their former manner of life, because they
            truly repented of that which they had done in the past.</p>
         <p>Now this man, through the gift which God had bestowed upon him, knew three languages,
            and he was able to read Greek, Latin, and Egyptian, a fact concerning the blessed man
            which we have learned from many folk; and when he knew that we were strangers he wrote
            down [the fact] in a book, and thanked God on our behalf. His food consisted of garden
            herbs, and they said that he used to go forth from his cell by night and mingle with the
            wild animals of the desert, and he gave them to drink of the water which he found. The
            footmarks which appeared by the side of his abode were those of buffaloes, and goats,
            and gazelle, in the sight of which he took great pleasure.</p>
         <p>Here end the Triumphs of Abba <persName>Theon</persName></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
