<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Triumph of Ammon the First</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_22"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_22
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 22: The Triumph of <persName>Ammon the First</persName></head>
         <p>There was in the early times in <placeName>Nitria</placeName> a certain man whose name was <persName>Ammon</persName>, whose soul
            the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> saw being taken up to heaven, and this man became the chief of the
            monks who were in <placeName>Nitria</placeName>. He belonged to a noble family, and because his parents were
            exceedingly rich, they urged him to marry a wife, although he was unwilling to do so;
            and having persisted in urging him [he did so], but in the wedding chamber he persuaded
            the maiden who became his bride to keep [her] virginity, and he promised to do the same.
            Now after a few days he departed to the country of <placeName>Nitria</placeName>, and the maiden herself called
            all the members of her household to virginity, and turned her house into a nunnery.</p>
         <p>Now the blessed <persName>Ammon</persName> was living by himself in the country of <placeName>Nitria</placeName>, and they brought
            unto him a certain young man who had been seized with madness and he was bound with
            chains; a mad dog had bitten him, and the madness of the animal had entered into him,
            and his body was torn by the severe pain which was in it. And when the blessed man saw
            that the relatives of the young man were making supplication unto him, he said unto
            them, <quote>What are ye bringing to me, O men? Ye are seeking from me what is greater than my
            power, and besides it lieth in your own hands to help and to heal the young man. Get ye
            gone, and restore [the value of] the widow’s bull which ye slew secretly, and your son
            shall be given back to you healed.</quote> Then they, as people who had been rebuked, fulfilled
            his commandment, with gladness, and he prayed straightway, and their son was healed.</p>
         <p>And on one occasion certain people came to visit the blessed <persName>Ammon</persName>, and he, having
            learned their mind, said unto them, <quote>Bring hither to me a large potter’s vessel, so that
            there may be an abundance of water for the people who come here.</quote> Now, although they
            promised him that they would do so, one of them, as soon as he had gone to his village,
            took counsel and said unto his companion, <quote>I am not going to carry the potter’s vessel
            on my camel and kill it</quote>; and when the other man heard this, he saddled his asses, and
            carried the vessel to the holy man with great labour. And the blessed man <persName>Ammon</persName> said
            unto the man before he could speak, saying, <quote>What [is this]? Behold, thy friend’s camel
            died whilst <pb n="377"/>thou wast coming here</quote>; and when the man returned he found that the camel
            had been killed by wolves. And many [other] miracles were worked by this man.</p>
         <p>Here endeth the Triumph of <persName>Ammon</persName></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
