<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Apology</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_1"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_1
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The Histories of <persName>the Monks who lived in the Desert of <placeName>Egypt</placeName></persName>, which were compiled by
            Saint <persName>Hieronymus</persName></head>
         <head>And moreover, in the might of and with confidence in <persName>Christ</persName>, we begin to write the
            Histories of the solitary Monks who lived in the Desert of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, which were composed by
            the blessed <persName>Hieronymus</persName> [Died A.D. 420]</head>
         <head>Chapter 1: The Apology, and the reason for [writing] the Book, [which are addressed]
            to those who required [them] from him</head>
         <p>Blessed be God Who desireth the welfare of all the children of men, Who wisheth that
            they may live and come to the knowledge of the truth, Who hath led us also into <placeName>Egypt</placeName>,
            and hath shewed us the great and marvellous things which are worthy to be remembered at
            all times, and to be written down in a book, Who hath given us the Cause of our
            salvation and of every one who wisheth to be helped further, and Who hath given unto us
            a demonstration of the good life and the doctrine which is able to rouse up the soul to
            the excellent rule of the ascetic life. Now therefore, I am not worthy to begin this
            history, for inferior men are not capable of approaching the histories of great men,
            since they are unable to narrate them as they really are, and still less are they able
            to set them down in writing in a book, and they ought not to be so bold as to attempt to
            explain matters which are difficult in mean and halting words; and it must appear to be
            great presumption which will bring danger in its train, for incapable men to undertake
            such things, and to be so bold as to write in a book sublime histories. But inasmuch as
            I have been requested, earnestly and frequently, on several occasions, by the
            brotherhood of blessed men who had their habitation in the Mount of Olives, to write an
            account of the lives and deeds of the blessed men, and of the solitary dwellers who were
            in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, according to what I myself have seen of their abundant love, and their patient
            endurance, and their vexatious toil for God’s sake, I have then put my trust in their
            prayers, and have been so bold as to narrate the following history, and to set it down
            in writing, so that I myself may gain a fair and abundant reward, and so that those who
            hearken unto the same may be benefited [thereby], and may emulate such beautiful deeds,
            and may depart from the world in a state of perfection, and may enjoy peace and rest
            through <pb n="317"/>the excellent long-suffering of their toil. For in very truth I have observed
            and seen the treasure of <persName>Christ</persName> which is hidden under human garments, and I have not
            buried it for the advantage of many, but have brought it forward that it may be for the
            good of every one. And I am sure that for me to give this benefit to the blessed
            brethren will be noble merchandise for me, for they will pray for the redemption of my
            soul.</p>
         <p>At the beginning of this book then I make [mention] first of all of the coming of our
            Redeemer <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, by Whose doctrine the blessed and holy brethren who are in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>
            are led, for I have seen many fathers there who were living the lives of angels, and
            were fashioning their lives into the similitude of that of the Redeemer. And I have also
            seen others, who were young men, and who were like unto the Prophets; and they did work
            which was divine and marvellous, and they were men who were indeed servants of <persName>Christ</persName>,
            and they had no care of this earth and nothing belonging to time vexed their minds.
            Verily these men, although they appeared to be living upon earth, had their habitation
            in heaven; for some of them were not even conscious that it was the world [wherein they
            lived], and did not even know that there were wickednesses committed in the world. And
            verily [it was with them] even as it is written in the Psalm, <quote>Great is the peace of
            those who love Thy Law</quote> (Psalm 119:165); and again it is written, <quote>I will be to them a
            Father, and they shall be unto Me sons and daughters, saith the Lord</quote> (2 Corinthians
            6:18), the Stay of all creation.</p>
         <p>And, moreover, many of them when they heard of what was spoken in the world [found it]
            to be strange unto them, and all the good things and all the cares of this world were
            forgotten by them; for a man saw them sown in the desert, and they were, like true sons,
            expecting their father <persName>Christ</persName>, and like husbandmen of the truth and honourable servants
            they waited for <persName>Christ</persName> their companion. They had care neither for houses, nor meats, nor
            raiment, for the coming of <persName>Christ</persName> their hope was the one thing for which their thoughts
            waited. Therefore, whensoever any of them lacked the things which were necessary, they
            sought neither city, nor village, nor brother, nor friend, nor parents, nor children,
            nor servants that the things which they lacked might be supplied by them, but their
            desire and their faith were sufficient for them, [and they only needed] to spread out
            their hand in supplication, and to offer up the confession of their lips to God, and
            immediately their prayers were ended everything [they needed] was found before them. Why
            is it necessary to speak at length concerning their faith in <persName>Christ</persName>, which was able to
            remove mountains? And, more<pb n="318"/>over, many of them restrained fountains and streams of
            running water, and walked upon the floods of the river Nile, and destroyed serpents, and
            worked cures, and wonders, and mighty deeds, even like unto those of the holy Prophets,
            and <placeName>the blessed Apostles</placeName>, by the might of their Lord. And it is a well-known and evident
            thing to every inhabitant of that country that the world standeth through their prayers,
            and that through them the life of the children of men is held to be precious by God.</p>
         <p>And I have also seen [in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>] a numerous nation of monks who could neither be defined
            nor counted, and among them were men of every sort and condition, and they lived both in
            the desert and in the villages, and no earthly king hath ever been able to gather
            together so great a number of men into his service; for there is neither village nor
            city in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> or in the Thebaïd which is not surrounded by monasteries as by walls, and
            many multitudes of people rest upon their prayers as they do upon God. Some of the monks
            live quite close [to the towns and villages] in caves and on the waste land, and many of
            them afar off, and they all in every place make manifest their labour in a marvellous
            manner as if they were envious of each other. The object of the zeal of those who [live]
            afar off is that none of their fellows shall surpass them in the labours of the fear of
            God, and the greatest anxiety of those who [live] near is to vanquish by their life and
            deeds those who lived at a distance and are famous, even though the things of evil (or
            wickednesses) vex them from every place. Therefore, as one who hath obtained great
            benefit from them, and as one who hath examined carefully the labours of the life and
            deeds, whereby I have also obtained benefit, I now approach this history with the view
            of making the successful monks [more] zealous by the memorials which I hand on [to
            them], and for the edification and profit of those who are beginning to emulate
            strenuously their rules of life. First of all then, by the grace of God, I will write at
            the beginning of this history the narratives of the lives and deeds of the great and
            holy fathers, by whose hands our Lord hath wrought at this present time the same kind of
            things as he wrought by the hands of His Prophets and <placeName>Apostles</placeName>; for it is our Lord
            Himself, Who then, as now, worked, as He still worketh, everything in every man.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
