<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Triumph of Serapion</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_29"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_29
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 29: The Triumph of <persName>Serapion</persName></head>
         <p>And we also saw in the regions of <placeName>Arsinoïtes</placeName> a certain elder whose name was <persName>Serapion</persName>; he
            was the father of all the monasteries, and the head of numerous brotherhoods, which
            contained about ten thousand men, and he took the greatest care in providing for the
            wants of all the brethren. And in the season of harvest he would make those who worked
            for hire from year to year bring and gather together to him twelve ardebs of wheat, that
            is to say, forty bushels, that it might serve for his ministrations to those in want,
            and might be distributed by his hands, so that in that district no destitute man might
            be found, and he sent to the needy in <persName>Alexandria the Great</persName> their gifts. Now the fathers
            of whom we have already spoken did not at any time neglect to visit the whole of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>,
            but as a result of the toil of the brethren they used to fill boats with food and
            apparel, and send them year after year to the poor who were in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, because the
            poor and needy who lived round about them were too few [to exhaust their benevolence].
            And we saw in the region of <placeName>Babylon</placeName> and <placeName>Memphis</placeName> many great fathers, and many, yea
            innumerable, monks who were adorned with works which were glorious before God.</p>
         <p>Here endeth the Triumph of <persName>Serapion</persName></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
