<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Isidore</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_14"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_14
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 14: The Triumph of Isidore</head>
         <p>And we also saw in Thebaïs the monastery of the blessed Isidore, which was a strong
            building with a high brick wall, and in it dwelt thousands of monks; in it also were a
            well, and a garden, and whatsoever was required for the food of its inhabitants. None of
            the monks ever went forth from the monastery, for they had as a doorkeeper a certain
            elder who would neither permit any man to depart, nor to come in, except him who had
            determined in his mind to remain there until the day of his death, and never to leave.
            And this doorkeeper had a small house by the side of the gate wherein he received such
            strangers as came [by night], and in the morning he would give them a blessing (i.e., a
            gift) and dismiss them in peace. Now there were two of the elders who used to go outside
            the building, and they did so to sell the work of the brethren, and to bring in such
            things as were required by them. And the elder who was always at the door was in the
            habit of saying that all the monks who dwelt within the building were so holy that all
            of them could work miracles, and that it was impossible for any one of them to fall into
            sickness before the day of his departure from the world, and that whensoever the end of
            any of them was coming he knew it beforehand, and told all the the brethren about it,
            and then he lay down and died.</p>
         <p>Here end the Triumphs of Isidore</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
