<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Triumphs of the Monks who were in Nitria</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
               target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_21"
               >
               https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_21
            </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
               target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
               Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 21: The Triumphs of the Monks who were in Nitria</head>
         <p>And we came also to the district of Nitria, where we saw many great disciples who had
            departed from the world, and some were natives of the country, and some were strangers
            (i.e., foreigners), who were more excellent in glory than the others, and they were
            emulating each other in the beautiful deeds of strenuousness, and were striving to
            outstrip each other in their noble and glorious lives and works. Now some of them
            possessed divine vision, and others works of ascetic excellence. And as we were coming
            from the desert some of their number saw us when we were afar off, and they met us on
            the way, and some of them brought water, and others washed our feet, and others washed
            our garments, and others entreated us to eat, and others called us to the doctrine of
            glory, and others to the vision of divine knowledge, and each one of them wished to help
            us so far as it lay in his power to do so. And however much a man might speak about
            their glorious life, it would be impossible for him to describe it as it really is. For
            they dwell in a waste place, and their dwellings are remote, and the men live apart from
            each other so that one man may not be known to his fellow, and that he may neither be
            seen readily nor his voice heard, and they live in the strictest silence, and each one
            of them is secluded within his cell, and only on Saturday and Sunday do they assemble in
            the church, and so meet each other. On several occasions many of them have been found
            dying in their chambers without ever having seen each other except when assembled for
            service in the church; for some of them only assembled once every three or four months,
            and thus they were remote from each other. Now these monks have much affection both for
            each other and for the rest of the brethren, for each one of them would be exceedingly
            anxious to give up his chamber to any man who wished to seek for grace.</p>
         <p>Here end the Triumphs of the Monks who were in Nitria</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
