<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Abba Hor</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_3"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_3
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 3: The Triumphs of the holy Man Abba <placeName>Hor</placeName></head>
         <p>And we saw also another wonderful man whose name was Abbâ <placeName>Hôr</placeName>, now he was the Abbâ of
            one thousand monks, and he had an angelic form and was about ninety years of age; his
            beard flowed down over his breast, and it was white and beautiful, and his countenance
            was so glorious that those that saw him were reproved by the sight thereof only. And
            this blessed man had for a very long time lived a life of the utmost austerity at a
            remote place in the desert, but subsequently he took certain monasteries in the desert
            which was near <placeName>Shainâ</placeName>, and gathered together a brotherhood, and he planted so many wild
            trees at that spot that they formed a dense wood in the wilderness. For the fathers who
            lived with him there said that before this man came there from the desert there was not
            even a shrub in the place; now he planted these trees in order to fill a want, and to
            prevent the brethren who were gathered together to him from being troubled by searching
            for wood. And in his prayer to God he took the same pains and strove that all the needs
            of the brethren might be supplied, so that they would only have to be anxious about
            their redemption, and that nothing which they used might be wanting for them, [so that
            they might have no excuse for negligence]. When formerly the blessed man lived in the
            desert of <placeName>Dalgâw</placeName> he used to eat roots and herbs, and to drink water when he was able,
            and he passed the whole time of his life in prayer and praise; but when he arrived at
            complete old age, an angel appeared unto him in a dream, in the desert, and said, <quote>Thou
            shall become a great race, and shalt be set in authority over a numerous people, and
            those who shall be saved through thee shall be ten myriads [in <pb n="334"/>“number], and thou shalt
            be a governor in the new world, and above every one else in the world thou shalt have
            life. And,</quote> said the angel unto him, <quote>fear not, for thou shalt never be in want of food,
            whensoever thou criest unto thy God, until the day of thy departure from this
            world.</quote></p>
         <p>And having heard these things the blessed Abbâ <placeName>Hôr</placeName> journeyed on his way diligently and
            came to the desert which is nigh unto <placeName>Shainâ</placeName>, and first of all he lived there by himself
            in a little tabernacle (or booth), which he made, and he fed upon garden herbs soaked in
            vinegar, and on several occasions he ate only once a week. And because originally he had
            no knowledge of letters, when he rose up to go forth from the desert into <placeName>Shainâ</placeName>, the
            knowledge of the Holy Books was given unto him by Divine Grace so fully that he was able
            to repeat all the Scriptures by heart; and when he had come [to <placeName>Shainâ</placeName>] and a book was
            given unto him by the brethren to read, he read it forthwith as if he were a man who had
            been always acquainted with books. And there was added unto him also the gracious gift
            of being able to cast out devils, and many of them came to him by the constraint [of
            this gift], against their wills, and would shriek out through his acts. And he wrought
            so many other cures so often that from all sides there were gathered together unto him
            brethren who lived in monasteries, one thousand in number.</p>
         <p>And when the man of God saw us, he rejoiced in us, and saluted us, and straightway he
            offered up a prayer; and he washed our feet with his own hands, and began to teach us,
            for he was exceedingly well acquainted with the Scriptures, even as a man who had
            received the gift from God, and he expounded to us many chapters of the Scriptures, and
            delivered to us the orthodox faith; moreover, he urged us to prayer, and to partake of
            the Mysteries. For it was the habit of all the great monks not to give food to their
            bodies until they had offered spiritual sustenance to their souls, that is to say, the
            participation in the Body and Blood of <persName>Christ</persName>. And having partaken of the Mysteries we
            gave thanks unto God, and he urged us [to come] to the table of food, and he called to
            our recollection the ascetic lives of noble men, and said, <quote>I know a certain man in this
            desert who for three years past hath not eaten anything which is of this earth, but an
            angel cometh to him once in three days, and bringeth him heavenly food and placeth it in
            his mouth, and this sufficeth him instead of meat and drink. And I know that there came
            to this man in a lying vision devils who were in the forms of horses and chariots of
            fire and numerous horsemen, as if they had come from a king, and they said unto him,
            <quote>Thou <pb n="335"/>“‘hast become perfect in everything, O man, but now, bow down and worship me, and
            I will take thee up [to heaven] like <persName>Elijah</persName>.</quote> Then the monk said in his mind, <quote>I worship
            the King and Redeemer every day, and if this creature were [a king] he would not ask me
            to worship him now.</quote> And when he had said unto him that which was in his mind, <quote>I have a
            King, and I worship Him always, and thou art not a king,</quote> immediately the <persName>Devil</persName> removed
            himself and was no more found.</quote> Now Abbâ <placeName>Hôr</placeName> told us these things because he wished to
            conceal his own rules and manner of life, and to tell us stories about those of other
            monks, but the fathers who were always with him told us that it was Abbâ <placeName>Hôr</placeName> himself who
            had seen these things.</p>
         <p>Now this man was more glorious in his life than very many of the fathers. And because of
            the multitude of the monks who came to him he used to call the brethren who were with
            him, to come to make houses for the new comers each day; some of the brethren spread the
            mud, and others brought the bricks, and others cut down the wood, and when their
            building was finished, he would supply the needs of those who came. On one occasion a
            lying brother who had hidden his clothes came to him, but the blessed man rebuked him
            before every man, and brought his clothes into the light, so that as a result of this
            [exposure] no man might in future dare to tell a lie in his presence. Now the beauty of
            his life and deeds made him so glorious that he was able to gather together very many
            monks to him, and one saw the congregation of the monks with him in the church like a
            band of righteous men who were splendid in their garb, and they glorified God with
            praises continually.</p>
         <p>Here end the Triumphs of Abba <placeName>Hor</placeName></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
