<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Hor, Isaiah, Paul, and Nopi</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_17"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_17
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 17: The Triumphs of Abba Hor, and Isaiah, and Paul, and Nopi, the
            Confessors</head>
         <p>On a certain occasion it happened that Abbâ Hôr and Isaiah, and Paul met each other by
            chance by the side of a great river, and all three of them were chaste and perfect
            ascetics, who were going to visit a certain great confessor whose name was Nôpî, who
            lived at a place which was three stages distant, and they said to each other, <quote>Let each
            of us shew the other his triumphs, and in what way, and to what extent he is, on account
            of his deeds, honoured by God.</quote> And Abbâ Hôr said unto them, <quote>I beg God for this
            gift—that we may journey to the place in that country by the might of the Holy Spirit,
            without any labour [on our part]</quote>; and immediately he had prayed, a boat was found to be
            ready, and a wind favourable for its journey was blowing, and they sailed up against the
            stream, and in a short time found themselves at that place.</p>
         <p>And when they had gone up from the river, Isaiah said unto them, <quote>O my beloved, would it
            not be a greater [display of the power of] God if that man whom we are going to see were
            to come to us and meet us, and were to describe to each of us his life and works?</quote> And
            Paul said unto them, <quote>God hath revealed unto me that after three days He will take him,
            and that the man whom we are going to see will depart from this world into life.</quote> Now
            when they had journeyed onwards a short distance from that place, the man himself met
            them, and saluted them; and Paul said unto him, <quote>Brother, explain to us thy manner of
            life and works, for the day after to-morrow thou wilt go to God.</quote> And Abbâ Nôpî said
            unto them, <quote>Blessed be God, Who hath also revealed these things unto me, and hath shewn
            me concerning your coming and concerning your life and works.</quote> And when he had described
            the upright dealings of each one of them, and how they lived, and how they laboured, he
            afterwards began to speak and to describe his own life and works, and he spake
            thus:—</p>
         <p><quote>Since the day wherein I confessed the Name of our Lord Jesus Christ, our Redeemer and
            God, no falsehood whatsoever hath gone forth from my mouth on earth, and I have never
            taken any earthly thing, for an angel hath fed me each day with heavenly food. In my
            heart I have never had any “other desire than that which is of God; and God hath not
            hidden from me anything which is honourable and glorious; and I have never been deprived
            of or lacked the light of mine eyes. I have never gone to sleep in the daytime, and
            during the night season I have never rested from making supplication to God, and the
            angel of God hath accompanied me always and hath shewn me the might of the world which
            is to come, and His light hath never gone out in my mind. Every request which I made
            unto God I have received straightway. At all times I have seen myriads of angels
            standing before God. I have seen the companies of the saints. I have seen the
            congregations of the martyrs. I have seen the triumphs of the monks who mourn. I have
            seen the works of the solitary brethren, and the congregations of the righteous. I have
            seen all created things glorifying God. I have seen Satan delivered over to the burning
            fire. I have also seen his angels suffering torments, and the righteous enjoying the
            happiness which hath no cessation.</quote> And, having told us these things, and many others
            which were like unto them, on the third day he delivered up his soul; and straightway
            the angels and the armies of the martyrs received it, and took it up into heaven, and we
            saw them singing praises and heard them.</p>
         <p>Here end the Triumphs of Abba Hor, and Isaiah, and Paul, and Nopi, the Confessors</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
