<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Apollo, and of John the Desert
               Dweller</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_11"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_11
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 11: The Triumphs of <persName>another Apollo</persName>, and of John, the dweller in the
            Desert</head>
         <p>And we also saw another holy man in the region of <quote>Or <placeName>(or Akûr, i.e., Acre)</placeName>, whose name
            was also <persName>Apollo</persName>, who was a righteous man; his handicraft was originally that of a
            blacksmith, but he had been converted to the way of truth, and he laboured afterwards in
            the service of the brethren, and supplied their needs. And on one occasion <persName>Satan</persName> came
            unto him in the form of a woman, who appeared to be anxious to work in the service of
            the brethren, and the blessed man happened at the time to be working at his trade, and
            he took up the red-hot iron and thrust it into the woman</quote>s face, and burned it so
            severely that she shrieked out, and the brethren who were in the chambers heard her
            cries. And from that time forward the blessed man was able to hold red-hot iron in his
            hands without being hurt. And this man also received us, and gave us refreshment, and he
            related unto us the histories of the men who had lived with him in that country, and of
            those who still lived there, and said:—</p>
         <p>There is in this desert one of our brethren whose name is <persName>John</persName>, who is now exceedingly
            old, and whose works of ascetic excellence are superior to those of all the other monks
            in the country. No man can find him at once, because he wandereth about from place to
            place in the desert. During the early period [of his life] he stood for three whole
            years praying, and he never sat down or went to sleep, but he was in the habit of
            snatching a little sleep as he stood. A certain priest used to bring him the Offering
            (i.e., sacramental bread) from Sunday to Sunday, and besides that he ate nothing. And
            one day the devil stood up in the form of a priest, and was exceedingly anxious to bring
            him a woman, but as soon as the blessed <persName>John</persName> had recognized him, he said unto him, <quote>Out
            upon thee, O thou <pb n="356"/>“who art full of guile, thou father of all falsehood, thou enemy of
            all righteousness! Wilt thou never cease to lead astray the souls of Christians? And
            dost thou dare to trample underfoot even the Holy Mysteries?</quote> Then the <persName>Devil</persName> said unto
            him, <quote>A very little more, and I should have been master over thee in thy fall, for thus
            have I led many a man astray, and I have driven him out of his mind and made him mad,
            but when many holy men made supplication to God on his behalf in their prayers, he came
            back to his senses.</quote> And having said these things unto him the <persName>Devil</persName> departed from him.
            Now the legs of the blessed man burst open because of standing over much upon them, and
            a discharge of water and pus ran from them; but the angel [of the Lord] drew nigh unto
            him and said, <quote>The Lord shall be thy meat and the Holy Spirit thy drink, and thou mayest
            be certain that this spiritual food shall suffice for thee.</quote> And having healed his
            wounds he made him to pass from that place. Then the blessed man went about in the
            desert and fed himself upon roots, and he used to come Sunday by Sunday to his place and
            partake of the Holy [Offering].</p>
         <p>Now a certain man who was paralysed wished to go to him and be healed, and immediately
            his legs touched the back of the ass which he was going to ride, through his faith only
            they were healed, before the holy man had offered up even a prayer on his behalf. On one
            occasion the holy man <persName>John</persName> begged the priest who ministered unto him to bring him a few
            palm leaves, as it were for pleasure, and he brought them to him, and the blessed man
            plaited them together; and the priest took some of the plaits and made a girth of them
            for his ass. Now there was a certain paralytic who wished to go to the blessed man and
            be healed, and he entreated the priest to carry him to him; and the priest took him and
            set him upon the ass, and immediately his legs touched the back of the ass which he was
            going to ride and the girth which the blessed man <persName>John</persName> had plaited, through his faith
            only they were healed, before the holy man had offered up even a prayer on his behalf.
            (Such is the story as told in another manuscript.) On another occasion he sent a gift
            (or blessing) to those who were ill, and immediately they had tasted it they were healed
            of their sicknesses.</p>
         <p>And on another occasion it was revealed to him that some of the brethren of his
            monasteries were not upright in their lives and works; and he wrote an epistle to them
            all, and accused the elders of being negligent, and the brethren of running after
            adulation, and it was known that this really was so. And he wrote also to the fathers
            who were neglectful, and who held lightly the salvation of the brethren who were with
            them, and he told the others to amend their lives, and to make their <pb n="357"/>deeds better, and
            he revealed [to them] also how that a reward (or penalty) was laid up for both groups of
            them. And he called the others to perfection in the spiritual life and its works, and he
            reminded them that they must neglect the things which are visible, and follow after
            those which are invisible. <quote>For it is time that we shewed forth the manner of our life
            and the works thereof, and it is meet that we should not pass the whole period of our
            lives [as] children and youths, but we must draw nigh unto the perfection of knowledge,
            and take up our stand upon the majesty of [its] glory.</quote> These and many other things did
            our father, the holy man <persName>Apollo</persName>, relate to us concerning the blessed <persName>John</persName>, and we
            marvelled at the greatness thereof. Now we have not written them all down, not because
            they were not true, but because of the want of faith of various men; but we ourselves
            believe them to be true, and we are fully persuaded that they are so, because those who
            related unto us the wonderful things of his life and deeds had certainly seen them with
            their own eyes, and these men were both numerous and great.</p>
         <p>Here end the Triumphs of Abba <persName>John</persName> and of <persName>Apollo</persName> who dwelt in the Desert</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
