<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Abba Abban</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_5"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_5
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 5: The Triumphs of Abba Abban [Benus]</head>
         <p>And we saw another blessed man whose virtues were more abundant than those of all
            [other] men, and whose name was Abbân [Benus]; the brethren who were with him related
            that he had never sworn, or told a lie, or been angry with any man, or rebuked any man
            even by a word. He had passed his whole life in silent contemplation and in humility,
            and in his manner of life he was as one of the angels, and he clothed himself in the
            deepest humility. And when we had entreated him earnestly to address to us a word of
            exhortation, it was only with the greatest difficulty that he could be persuaded to say
            unto us a few words. On one occasion, when the labourers in the fields which were near
            the river begged him [to drive away] a certain hippopotamus which was doing them harm by
            his [great] strength, the blessed Abbâ Abbân [Benus] commanded the animal in a gentle
            voice, saying, <quote>I adjure thee to depart in the name of Jesus Christ</quote>; and the
            hippopotamus, as if driven away by an angel, never more appeared in that district.</p>
         <p>Here end the Triumphs of Abba Abban [Benus]</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
