<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Monks of Oxyrrhynchus</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_6"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_6
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 6: The History of the Lives and Acts of <persName>the Brethren who were in the City of
            <placeName>Oxyrhyncus</placeName></persName></head>
         <p>And we came also to <placeName>Oxyrhyncus</placeName>, a great city in <placeName>Thebaïs</placeName>, but we are not able to relate
            all the wonderful things which [we saw] therein; for the city is so full of the
            habitations of the brethren that the walls thereof are wellnigh thrust out with them, so
            many are the brethren! And there are so many other monasteries round about the walls, on
            the outside, that one would think that they were another city, and the sanctuaries of
            the city, and the temples which are therein, and all the spaces about them, are filled
            with the monks. And besides these there were thirteen churches in which the people
            assembled, for the city was exceedingly large. There was a place set apart for the monks
            to pray in each of the <pb n="337"/>monasteries, and one might think that the monks were not very
            much fewer in numbers than the ordinary inhabitants of the city, for they were so
            numerous that they even filled the [buildings at] the entrances to the city, and some of
            the monks lived in the towers by the side of the gates thereof. Now the people said that
            the monks who lived inside were five thousand in number, and that five thousand brethren
            lived round about it, and there was not an hour, either of the day or the night, wherein
            they were not performing the service of God. But there were also heretics in the city,
            and they were not of the heathen who dwelt therein. And all the inhabitants of the city
            were believers, and they would hearken to the Scriptures so readily that the Bishop was
            able to proclaim peace to the people even in the streets; and the officers and the
            princes of the city, who were lavish in their gifts to the congregations, used to place
            watchers at the gates and entrances thereof that if they saw any needy person or any
            stranger they might bring him to them, in order that they might supply his need from
            their gifts. And what shall we say concerning the fear of God which was in these men to
            such a degree that, when they saw us, who were strangers, passing through the streets,
            they drew nigh, like angels, unto us [and helped us]? And how can a man describe
            adequately the multitude of monks and the innumerable virgins who used to live there?
            Now we would make known that which we have learned from the holy Bishop who was there,
            namely, that he had under his authority ten thousand monks and twenty thousand virgins.
            I am wholly unable to express how great is the love of strangers and the affection which
            exist among these men and women, for our cloaks and the other portions of our apparel
            were wellnigh torn to rags by the force which each one of them, in the ardour of his
            love, displayed in dragging us to his home. And we saw there multitudes of fathers and
            of great monks who possessed gifts of divers kinds, for some had the gift of speaking,
            and some of doing works, and some of doing mighty deeds, and some of working signs.</p>
         <p>Here endeth the History of the Monks in the City of <placeName>Oxyrhyncus</placeName></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
