<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Abba Elijah</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_8"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_8
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 8: The Triumphs of Abba Elijah</head>
         <p>And we also saw another priest in the desert of Antinoë, the metropolis of the Thebaïd,
            whose name was Elijah; he was about one hundred and ten years old, and the monks used to
            say that the spirit of Elijah the Prophet rested upon him. Now this blessed man Elijah
            was famous in the desert, for he had lived therein for seventy years, and it is wholly
            impossible to find a word which would adequately describe the sterility and desolation
            of that desert, and of the mountain in which he lived. He never went down to Shainâ, but
            there was a narrow path along which a man could walk with the greatest difficulty and
            make his way to him [guided] by the rough stones which were placed on both sides of the
            way; and his dwelling was under a rock in the cave. Now his appearance was terrible, for
            by reason of old age which had laid its hold upon him he trembled greatly; nevertheless
            he worked signs daily, and he never ceased to heal the sick. And the fathers told us
            concerning him that there was no man among them who could remember the time when he went
            up [to live] in the mountain. In his old age he used to eat three ounces of bread every
            evening, and three olives, but in his early manhood he partook of food only once a week,
            and subsisted thereon.</p>
         <p>Here end the Triumphs of Abba Elijah</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
