<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Abba Pithyrion</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_19"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_19
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 19: The Triumph of Abba <persName>Pithyrion</persName></head>
         <p>And we also saw in <persName>Thebaïs</persName> a certain high mountain which lay by the river, and it was an
            exceedingly terrible mountain with high barren peaks, and in the caves thereof there
            dwelt many monks; and these men had as Abbâ one <persName>Pithyrion</persName>, who was a disciple of the
            holy man <persName>Anthony</persName>. He was the third who had received that place from <persName>Anthony</persName>, and he used
            to perform many mighty deeds, and to carry on the persecution of devils openly; and
            since he was the man who had received the place of <persName>Anthony</persName>, the blessed and great man,
            and of Ammonius his disciple, he received also, and rightly so, the inheritance of his
            labours. Now <persName>Pithyrion</persName> spake many other things, and he discoursed with power, especially
            on the faculty of discerning spirits, saying, <quote>There are certain devils which cling to
            the passions, and on several occasions they turn our good desires into evil; therefore,
            O my sons, those of you who wish to drive away devils must first of all bring into
            subjection your lusts, for a man must vanquish not only every lust, but he must drive
            away the devil thereof. It is right that ye should overcome your lusts little by little,
            so that in the same way ye may drive away the devils which appertain thereto. There is a
            devil which belongeth to a wasteful and dissolute life, and he who is able to conquer
            the desire therefor is also able to drive away that devil.</quote> And this man used to eat
            twice a week, that is to say on Sunday, and on Thursday, and his food consisted of a
            little flour and some water which he baked into a thin cake; and he was unable to eat
            anything else, because his nature was thus.</p>
         <p>Here endeth the Triumph of <persName>Pithyrion</persName></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
