<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Copres and Petarpemotis</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_16"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_16
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 16: The Triumphs of Abba Copres and of the Blessed Petarpemotis</head>
         <p>And again we saw another holy man whose name was Copres, and he dwelt in the desert, and
            was the archimandrite of fifty men; he used to perform many mighty deeds, for he could
            cure many sicknesses and diseases of various kinds, and he cast out devils, and drove
            away evil spirits, and did other wonderful works, some of which we saw with our own
            eyes. Now when he saw us, he saluted us, and prayed over us, and washed our feet, and he
            began to ask us questions about the world and the affairs thereof, but we entreated him
            to relate to us the story of his life and works first of all, and how it came to pass
            that God gave him such gifts, and by what kind of works he had become worthy of the
            same. And the blessed man, in whose mind there existed not the smallest degree of pride,
            began to tell us about his own life and works, and also about those of the great, and
            wonderful, and perfect fathers, the examples of whose lives and works he strove both to
            imitate and to emulate; and he answered and said unto us:—O my sons, my manner of life
            and my mourning are not to be compared with those of the early fathers.</p>
         <p>For there was here before me a certain man, whose name was Petarpemôtîs, who was first
            and chief of all the monks who dwelt in this place; it was he who first made manifest
            (i.e., wore) this garb, and it was he who invented it. Now formerly he had been a thief,
            and a plunderer of the tombs of the heathen, and he had a great reputation for
            committing wickednesses of every kind connected with robbery and theft, and the
            following matter was the cause of [his finding] life. He once went to rob the religious
            house of a certain blessed woman who dwelt therein chastely, and without knowing it he
            found himself upon the roof of her house; and being unable to go into her house and
            plunder it, because the roofs of the house were as flat as the ground and they had no
            rain water pipes [leading thereto], for there is no rain in Thebaïs, and there was no
            place on the roof whereby he could enter the house, or by which he could leave it again,
            and he was neither able to descend nor to escape from it, he [was obliged to] stay there
            until the morning, and he wondered meanwhile in his mind what he should do until the
            daylight came. And whilst he was there he sank into a light sleep, and he saw in the
            form of a man an angel who said unto him, <quote>Devote thou not such close attention, and
            diligence, and watching to thy life of thievery. If thou wishest to change thy
            wickedness into a life of good deeds thou must serve with the service of angels before
            Christ the King, and thou shalt receive from Him this power and authority.</quote> And
            immediately he had heard [these things] he received [them] from him with gladness, and
            he who had appeared unto him in the form of an angel shewed him a company of monks, and
            commanded that he should have dominion over them.</p>
         <p>And when he woke up from his slumber, he saw the nun standing before him, and saying
            unto him, <quote>O man, what doest thou here? And what is thy report? Whence comest thou? Who
            art thou?</quote> He saith unto her, <quote>I know not, but I beseech thee to shew me the church.</quote>
            And when she had shewn him the church, he went and fell down before the feet of the
            elders, and he entreated them that he might become a Christian, so that he might find an
            occasion for repentance. Now when the elders knew who he was, they marvelled at him, and
            they began to admonish him that henceforth he must not be a slayer of men; and he begged
            them that he might [be allowed] to learn the Psalms, and when he had learned three
            verses of the first Psalm, he said, <quote>These are sufficient for me to learn.</quote> And he
            tarried with the elders for three days, and straightway he went forth from them, and
            departed into the desert. And when he had lived [there] for five weeks without bread, a
            man came to him carrying bread and water, and he entreated him to eat thereof and to
            refresh himself. Now Petarpemôtîs lived there for three years in prayer and tears, and
            he fed himself upon the roots which were in the desert, and wandered about eating them;
            and after three years he returned to the church, and repeated before the fathers the
            belief and all the doctrine of the Church, and although he had never learned letters, he
            could repeat the Scriptures by heart. Then the elders marvelled at him and wondered how
            a man of his kind could have attained such a degree of learning and asceticism, and they
            gave him further light in respect of speech and learning, and when they had bestowed
            baptism upon him, they entreated him to remain with them. And he tarried with them for
            seven days more, and he went forth and departed to the desert, where he lived for a
            further period of seven years; and this blessed man was held to be worthy of a constant
            [gift of] bread, which was found every Sunday in his pillow-cloth. When he had prayed
            and given thanks, he would partake thereof, and then he would fast again until the
            following Sunday without in any way suffering.</p>
         <p>And he came back again from that wilderness with works of spiritual excellence, and he
            departed from the desert, and made manifest his rule of abstinence and self-denial, and
            he incited many to follow after him. Now there drew nigh unto him a certain young man
            who entreated him that he might become his disciple, and having received him
            Petarpemôtîs dressed him in the way that he himself was dressed, that is to say, he wore
            a shirt with short sleeves, and an outer garment, and he placed a cowl upon his head,
            and tied a napkin about his loins, and he showed him the way and the rules of a life of
            mourning, and he trained him [in the life and deeds of the monks], and he placed a cape
            on his shoulders.</p>
         <p>Now the custom of the blessed man was as follows: When a Christian died he remained with
            him the whole night long in vigil and prayer, and he would reverently dress him and bury
            him. And when that disciple saw him dressing the Christians who died in this way, he
            said unto him, <quote>Wilt thou also dress me in this manner when I die, O master?</quote> And he
            said unto him, <quote>I will dress thee in this fashion, and I will wrap thee in a shroud
            until thou shalt say unto me, <quote>I have enough.</quote> </quote> Now after no great length of time that
            disciple died, and the words of his master were indeed fulfilled, for Petarpemôtîs
            dressed him reverently in the fear of God, as was right, and he said in a loud voice
            before all those who were standing [there], <quote>Have I dressed thee well, O my son, or dost
            thou still lack anything?</quote> And the dead man sent forth a voice, and they all heard it,
            saying, <quote>Thou hast dressed me, O my father, thou hast fulfilled thy promise, and hast
            completed thine undertaking</quote>; and wonder laid hold upon all those who were standing
            there, and they glorified God. Then the blessed man departed into the desert according
            to his custom, and he went that he might occupy himself in his daily round of devotion,
            even as a man who fleeth from vainglory.</p>
         <p>And after these things he went forth from the desert and departed to work for the
            brethren who were his disciples, and who were sick; now one of these was nigh unto
            death, and this God had revealed unto him, and the day wherein he would pass away was
            nigh, and the village was far away. And because he did not wish to enter therein by
            night (for he suspected evil), and because he would fulfil the word of our Lord, which
            said, <quote>Walk in the light whilst ye have the light, and he who walketh in the light shall
            not be tripped up</quote> (St. John 12, 35), when he saw that the day was declining, he
            answered and said unto [the sun], <quote>Tarry thou on the path of thy course, and wait for me
            a short time until I can come to the village</quote>; and the sun stood still for a while, and
            went not down, and remained in his place, and he neither set nor went to rest until
            Petarpemôtîs had entered the village. Now this appearance was known unto all those who
            dwelt in the village, and they all ran, and stood still, and gazed for a long time at
            the sun, which set not. And when they saw Petarpemôtîs coming from the desert, they
            asked him, <quote>What is the meaning of the sign of this sun which goeth not down?</quote> Then he
            said unto them, <quote>Do ye not remember the word of our Lord which said, <quote>If ye have in you
            faith like unto a grain of mustard-seed, ye shall work miracles which shall be greater
            and more excellent than these</quote>?</quote> (St. Matthew 17, 20.) Now when they heard these things
            great fear laid hold upon them, and they knew immediately that it was he who had held
            back the sun, and large numbers of them remained with him and became his disciples.</p>
         <p>And he went into the house of one of his disciples who had been sick, and found that he
            was dead, and he drew nigh to the bier whereon the dead man was lying, and he prayed,
            and kissed him, and said unto him, <quote>Dost thou desire to depart to God now, O my son, or
            wouldst thou remain alive in the body?</quote> And the dead man sat up, and made answer unto
            him, saying, <quote>It is better for me to leave the body that I may be with Christ, for I
            have no desire to live in the body</quote>; and the blessed man said unto him, <quote>Then die in
            peace, my son, and make entreaty before God on my behalf that thou mayest go unto Him.</quote>
            And immediately the blessed man had said these words the man died on his bier. Then fear
            fell upon all those who were standing there, and they said, <quote>Verily this is a man of
            God</quote>; and when the blessed man had dressed him carefully (or well), he kept vigil the
            whole night [by him] and prayed and sang Psalms, and [then] he buried him in a proper
            manner.</p>
         <p>And Petarpemôtîs went and visited another brother who was sick, and he saw that he was
            dying with difficulty, and that he was troubled in his mind; now his mind was rebuking
            him, and his conscience was pricking him because of his wickednesses. And the blessed
            man said unto him, <quote>How canst thou go to God seeing that thou art prepared to carry with
            thee the accusation of neglect of thy works, that is to say, lax intentions in respect
            of thy manner of life?</quote> Then that brother begged and entreated him to pray to God on his
            behalf, that there might be given unto him a little longer period of life so that he
            might amend his ways and deeds. And he answered and said unto him, <quote>Now that thy life
            hath come to an end thou askest for time for repentance! What hast thou been doing all
            thy life long? Wast thou not able to heal thy blemishes? Yet thou hast added others to
            thy negligence!</quote> But the man made supplication the more to him, and begged and entreated
            him to pray that he might rise up [again from his bed of sickness]. And Petarpemôtîs
            said unto him, <quote>If thou wilt not add sins to thy sins, but wilt seek with all thy soul
            to repent, I will entreat God on thy behalf, for He is good and merciful, and ask Him to
            grant thee time and life that thou mayest pay back all that thou owest.</quote> And when he had
            prayed he said unto him, <quote>God hath granted thee to live in the body for three years
            longer, but only through earnest supplication (?)</quote>; then he took him by the hand and
            raised him up from his sickness straightway, and he led him away with him and carried
            him off to the desert, where he lived with him for three years.</p>
         <p>And when the three years were ended, he brought him back to his village, and set him
            before God, not as an ordinary man merely, but as a messenger who had been chosen by
            God, and they all marvelled at his works. And when the brethren were gathered together
            to him, Petarpemôtîs set that brother in the midst, and he narrated unto them the
            doctrine of life the whole night long; and suddenly he sank into a slumber, wherein he
            departed from this life to our Lord. Then the blessed man dressed him for burial, and he
            accompanied him to the grave with prayers.</p>
         <p>Now they used to say that very many wonderful works were wrought by him, and they
            testified that on several occasions he walked upon the waters. And besides this he was
            once found in an upper chamber with the brethren, although the doors had been shut, for
            he had come in to them in the air by the power of angels. And they also said that he
            obtained from God everything which he asked for, and that he had the power to go
            whithersoever he pleased and whensoever he pleased, without trouble. And the blessed
            Petarpemôtîs once related to the brethren a story of how, on one occasion when he had
            gone out from the desert, he saw in his dream as if he had been taken up into heaven,
            and he saw there the good things that were prepared for the monks, and that the mouth of
            man could not describe, and that could not be uttered thereby. And he also said, <quote>I saw
            Paradise with the eyes of this body, and I saw there the many multitudes of the saints,
            and I tasted the fruits of Paradise.</quote> And he produced a proof of his assertion, that he
            might shew that the things which had been said by him were true, for he gave his
            disciples to eat [of the fruit of] a great, and marvellous, and extraordinarily large
            fig-tree, which possessed an odour that was different from any other smell in the
            world.</p>
         <p>And whilst this holy man Copres was relating unto us all these things concerning
            Petarpemôtîs, he said, <quote>I have seen in my youth [portions] of that fig-tree in the hands
            of his disciples, and I kissed them, and wonder at the odour thereof laid hold upon me;
            and the tree remained with his disciples for many years as a manifestation [of the truth
            of his words] unto many. For it was great beyond measure, and it had such wonderful
            properties that any sick person who inhaled its odour was straightway healed of his
            sickness.</quote></p>
         <p>Now they say that at the beginning of his going into the desert, when he had not tasted
            food of any kind whatsoever for five weeks he found a man in the parched desert carrying
            bread and water, who begged of him to eat, and when he had done so he removed himself
            from him. And on another occasion the Evil One shewed him some fine gold which [in
            quantity] surpassed the treasures of Pharaoh, king of Egypt, and he answered and said
            unto him that showed him the gold, <quote>May thou and thy money go to hell.</quote> These and
            suchlike great things were, according to what they said, performed by Abbâ Petarpemôtîs,
            and they spake many other things before us the which [if written] the world could not
            contain. And, according to what these men said, Petarpemôtîs spake unto us, saying, <quote>If
            we who are little people perform things which are little, like unto ourselves, that is
            to say, if we heal the halt and the blind, which selfsame things the physicians do by
            means of their art, in what consisteth the greatness?</quote> Now whilst Copres, the elder, was
            relating these things unto us, one of us slumbered and fell into a sleep, and this man
            did not believe the things which he had heard the blessed man say. And having fallen
            asleep, he saw a marvellous book, and the book was laid upon the knees of this elder,
            and it was written wholly in gold, and above it there stood an old man who said unto him
            in a very threatening manner, <quote>Didst thou not hear well what was being said that thou
            didst fall asleep?</quote> Then immediately the man awoke from his sleep, and told us in the
            Greek tongue what he had seen.</p>
         <p>Now whilst our brother was relating this dream to us, a certain villager was found to be
            standing there before him bearing upon his shoulders a bucket of sand, and he was
            waiting there to hear the end of his story; and we begged him to tell us why he was
            carrying the sand, and why he stood there, and what he wanted. Then Abbâ Copres answered
            and said unto us, <quote>My sons, it is not seemly for us to boast, but it is fitting that we
            should declare before you the triumphs of the fathers, so that we may not be unduly
            exalted in our minds, and so lose our reward. Nevertheless, because of the earnestness,
            and for the sake of the welfare of you who have come unto us from a distance, we will
            not deprive you of benefit, and we will relate before your brotherhood whatsoever God
            hath wrought by our hands. At one time the land which is about us produced nothing, and
            it was with the greatest difficulty that the villagers who owned it were able to gather
            from it as much again as they sowed, for the worms were produced in the ears, and they
            destroyed all their harvest. Now some of those husbandmen had been converted by us, and
            they begged us to pray for their harvest, and we said unto them, <quote>If ye have faith in
            God even this desert sand shall bring forth crops for you</quote>. Then, without any doubt
            whatsoever, they filled their bosoms with the sand which is trodden under our feet, and
            they entreated us to bless it, and when we had prayed that it might be unto them even
            according to their faith, they went and mixed it with the wheat and sowed it in their
            fields, and immediately their land produced for them abundant crops, and they were
            larger than the crops obtained from the other lands in Egypt. Thus it became the custom
            for them [to bring sand] each year, and to trouble us [to bless it].</quote></p>
         <p>And he also related unto us a certain wonderful thing which the Lord had wrought for us
            when large numbers of the brethren were gathered together, and he said, <quote>On one occasion
            I went down to the city, and I found there a certain Manichean who was leading the
            multitudes into error, and because I was unable to rebuke and convince him openly I
            turned towards the multitudes, and said unto them, <quote>Kindle ye a large fire, and let the
            two of us go into it when it is burning brightly, and he who remaineth in the fire
            without being burnt shall be the man who possesseth the true faith.</quote> And when this had
            been done, and the crowd had lit a fire with ready zeal, I urged the Manichean to go
            with me “into it, but he said, <quote>Let each of us go in by himself, and, moreover, it is
            meet that thou shouldst be the first to go in because thou didst give the command to
            have it made.</quote> Then, having made upon myself the sign of the Cross in the Name of Jesus
            Christ, I went into the fire, and was unharmed thereby, for the flame parted asunder on
            this side and on that, and it vexed me in no wise. And when I had remained in the fire
            for half an hour, and the multitudes had seen the wonderful thing, they cried out, and
            gave thanks to God, and compelled the Manichean to go into the fire, and when, because
            of his fear, he was unwilling to go into it, the crowd took him, and pushed him into the
            fire, and he was wholly consumed. As for me they took me, and escorted me to the church,
            and ascribed praise to God as they went.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>And on another occasion when I was passing by a certain heathen temple, the heathen
            were offering up sacrifices to their idols; and I said unto them, <quote>Why do ye who are
            rational beings offer up sacrifices to things which are dumb? Are ye of your own will
            dumb that ye sacrifice to dumb things?</quote> And they admitted that what I said was good, and
            they came after me, and believed in Christ.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>And, moreover, we had a garden in a certain neighbouring place which was [intended] for
            the pleasure of the brethren who came unto us from afar off, and a certain poor man used
            to work therein. And one of the heathen went into the garden and stole some vegetables
            and departed; but he was not able to cook them, for although he kept the fire burning
            under the saucepan for three hours, they remained in the same state as when they were
            taken from the garden, and even the water would not boil! And when the man came to his
            senses he took the vegetables and brought them to us, and he begged that he might be
            forgiven the offence, and become a Christian; and he actually became one. Now on that
            very day certain brethren came unto us from a distance, and it is probable that those
            vegetables were brought on their account, so that they might enjoy them; and when we had
            tasted them, we gave thanks unto our Lord, for we had a twofold joy, first, because of
            the redemption of the soul of the man who had stolen them, and secondly, because the
            brethren who had come to us enjoyed them.</quote></p>
         <p>These and many other wonderful things did our holy father Copres relate to us, and when
            he had made us rest, he took us into his garden and shewed us the palms and other fruit
            trees which Koprîs [sic] had planted with his own hands for the encouragement of those
            husbandmen who believed in Christ, and to whom he had said that this desert was able to
            bring forth fruit for those who believed in God; <quote>And,</quote> said he, when <quote>I saw that they
            had sown sand, and that their crops were abundant, I also planted this garden for the
            enjoyment of the brethren, and it has come to its present state [of perfection].</quote></p>
         <p>Here end the Triumphs of Copres and Petarpemotis</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
