<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Abba Ammon</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_4"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_4
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 4: The Triumphs Of Abba <persName>Ammon</persName></head>
         <p>Now we saw in Thebaïs another man whose name was <persName>Ammon</persName>, who was the Abbâ of three (or
            thirty) thousand monks; and they called these monks also <quote>men of <placeName>Tabenna</placeName>.</quote> And they
            lived lives of the greatest austerity, and they used to put their head cloths over their
            faces, and they covered themselves when they ate, and they turned their looks towards
            the ground, so that one might not see the other; and they kept strict silence, so that
            they might think that they were in the desert, and they did these things in order that
            each might hide his works of ascetic excellence from his fellows. When they sat at table
            it was a mere matter of form, and they did so in such a way as to deceive each other,
            and to make each other say, <quote>Behold, they are eating.</quote> Some of them only carried their
            hands to their mouths once or twice and took a <pb n="336"/>piece of bread, or an olive, or a portion
            of something else of all the food which was set before them, and it was unto them
            sufficient for a meal; and others ate in silence a piece of bread only, and endured
            [hunger] without touching any of the other dishes of food which were placed before them;
            and others only reached out their hands to the dishes of cooked food three times and
            ate. Now their souls were weaned from everything. And since we marvelled at all their
            glorious deeds we obtained benefit from them all.</p>
         <p>Here end the Triumphs of Abba <persName>Ammon</persName></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
