<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Triumphs of the Blessed Fathers</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_20"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_20
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 20: The Triumphs of the Blessed Fathers</head>
         <p>And we also saw many other fathers and monks in several places throughout Egypt who used
            to work mighty deeds and miracles, but they were so many in number that we cannot
            mention them all, and we therefore only narrate a few things out of many. For what shall
            we say of the upper part of the Thebaïd, namely that [which is near] Syene, wherein live
            many wonderful men, and countless monks, who lead lives which are wholly beyond the
            nature of ordinary men? For at the present time they raise the dead, and, like Peter,
            they walk upon the water, and, to this very day, everything which our Redeemer performed
            by His saints is performed by these holy men. Now because of the great danger which we
            should run of thieves and barbarians falling upon us, we did not dare to go up the Nile
            any further to the south than Lycus, and therefore could not see the holy men who were
            there. Now we were not able to know even the fathers of whom we have spoken above
            without toil and tribulation, and it was only with the greatest difficulty that we were
            able to narrate their histories, for in order to do this we had to suffer much, and we
            were within a very little of having to endure many tribulations; but at length we were
            worthy to see these men. For on seven occasions we were delivered, and on the eighth
            evil came not nigh unto us, because, at all times, God protected us.</p>
         <p>On the first occasion we nearly perished of hunger and thirst whilst we were wandering
            about in the desert [without food] for five days and five nights. On the second occasion
            we fell among savage, rugged mountains until our feet were pierced by the stones, and we
            suffered very great pain, and very nearly had to yield up our souls. On the third
            occasion we sank in the mud several times up to our backs, and there was none to help
            [us], and we cried out the words of the blessed David, <quote>Save me, O God, for the waters
            have come even unto my soul, I have sunk into a dark abyss, wherein is no place on which
            to stand. Save me from the mire that I sink not</quote> (Psalm 69, 1, 2). On the fourth
            occasion a flood of many waters burst upon us at the period of the inundation of the
            Nile, and we walked about in the water, and we sank down very nearly to the nostrils [of
            the animal which we rode], and we cried out and said, <quote>Drown us not, O Lord, in a
            whirlpool of waters, and let not the abyss swallow us up, and let not the pit close its
            mouth over us</quote> (Psalm 69, 14, 15). On the fifth occasion we fell in with some river
            thieves whilst we were walking along on the river banks to go into the city of
            Dekaplîôs, and they pursued us and sought to capture us, until very little breath was
            left in our nostrils, for they chased us for a distance of ten miles. On the sixth
            occasion we were sailing on the Nile when the boat capsized and sank under us. On the
            seventh occasion we were arriving at Lake Mareotis, and we were cast up on a small
            desert island, where the papyrus plant groweth, and we passed there three whole days and
            nights under the open sky in severe cold and with the rain falling upon us; now the
            season was the days of the Epiphany.</p>
         <p>The story of the eighth occasion may be superfluous, but it is helpful. For when we were
            going to Nitria we passed a great deep place in one of the fields, which was full of
            water, and after the waters had run off the fields several crocodiles remained therein;
            now three very large crocodiles were stretched out on the edge of the pool, and we drew
            nigh to them that we might see them, because we thought they were dead. But they ran
            after us very fast, and we cried out with a loud voice, saying, <quote>In the name of Jesus
            Christ, spare our souls,</quote> whereupon the crocodiles, as if they had been driven away from
            us by angels, cast themselves into the water. And we made our way to Nitria with all
            possible haste, and as we went we meditated upon the words of the righteous man Job, who
            said, <quote>Seven times He shall deliver thee from tribulation, and on the eighth evil shall
            not draw nigh unto thee</quote> (Job 5:19). Therefore we gave thanks unto our Lord, who had
            redeemed us out of all tribulations, and had made manifest unto us great and marvellous
            revelations by the hands of his believing saints and monks.</p>
         <p>Here end the Triumphs of the Blessed Fathers</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
