<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Triumph of Philemon</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_27"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_27
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 27: The Triumph of Philemon</head>
         <p>And we also saw there a certain elder who was exceedingly holy and humble, and he was
            constantly seeing revelations, and his name was Philemon; and when this man was offering
            unto God the service [due] to him, he saw an angel standing at the right hand of the
            altar. He used to write and set down in a book the names of those brethren who drew nigh
            to the Gift of Grace, and he took care that the names of those who did not come to the
            congregation were erased, and such men, after three days, died. On several occasions the
            devils beat this man, and they brought so many sicknesses upon him that he was unable to
            stand by the altar, and could not even offer up the Offering; but an angel came and took
            him by the hand, and straightway he received strength, and the angel made him to stand
            up healed before the altar. And the brethren saw the scars made by his beatings, and
            marvelled.</p>
         <p>Here endeth the Triumph of Philemon</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
