<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Dioscurus</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_15"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_15
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 15: The Triumph of <persName>Dioscurus</persName></head>
         <p>And we saw also another holy man in <placeName>Thebaïs</placeName>, whose name was <persName>Dioscurus</persName>, and he was the
            Abbâ of one hundred monks. And when the monks were about to draw nigh to the gracious
            gift of the Mysteries, he would say to them, <quote>Peradventure there is a man among you who
            dareth to draw nigh to the Holy Things, in whose mind the lust for women hath risen up
            during the night. The nocturnal <pb n="363"/>“pollution which is not of the thoughts, is a customary
            though involuntary emission, and it is not the result of desire, for it is a natural
            result, and is derived from the actual substance of the body; therefore we are not
            guilty of sin. On the other hand, the filthy vision proceedeth from the mind, and the
            evil desire is the cause of the same.</quote> And <persName>Dioscurus</persName> used to say, <quote>It is right that a
            monk should be superior to the law of nature, and that the smallest impurity whatsoever
            should not be in his body; but he should humble himself in such wise that owing to much
            fasting the physical matter of the body may not be able to increase. And it is not right
            for a monk to approach lusts, for if he doth, in what respect are we superior to the men
            of this world whom we see in several cases curbing their lusts, either for the sake of
            the health of the body, or for other befitting causes? How much more, then, is it
            fitting for a monk to take care concerning the health of his mind, and of his soul, and
            of his spirit?</quote></p>
         <p>Here endeth the Triumph of <persName>Dioscurus</persName></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
