<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Triumph of Apollo the Less</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_30"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_history_of_the_Monks/Chapter_30
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 30: The Triumphs of <persName>Apollo</persName> the Less, the Reader and Martyr</head>
         <p>And we saw also the granaries of <persName>Joseph</persName> (i.e., the <placeName>Pyramids of Gizah</placeName>) wherein he
            collected grain in the time of famine. And there was there, in <placeName>Thebes</placeName>, a certain monk
            whose name was <persName>Apollo</persName>, and he made manifest many mighty deeds, and led a life of great
            works; he was held to be worthy of the office of deacon, and his works of spiritual
            excellence were as glorious and renowned as [those of] the famous monks of old. During
            the period of the persecution he made many martyrs by putting courage into the hearts of
            the confessors of <persName>Christ</persName>, but at length he himself was seized and put under ward in the
            prison-house, and the wickedest men among the heathen used to come to him and heap words
            of hatred and blasphemy upon him. Now one of those who behaved thus was a certain
            singer, who was a famous man, and was beloved by all the people; and this man drew nigh
            and reviled the blessed <persName>Apollo</persName>, and called him a wicked man, and a liar, and a hater of
            all mankind, and said that he was guilty <pb n="380"/>of death before all the people. Then to him the
            blessed man <persName>Apollo</persName> made answer, and he said unto him, <quote>O man, may God have mercy upon
            thee, and may the sin which hath been uttered by thee not be accounted unto thee as
            anything.</quote></p>
         <p>Now when the man who was a singer, whose name was <persName>Philemon</persName>, had heard these things, he
            repented at the words of the blessed man, because he had gone into the place where he
            was, and caused him pain, and he went down immediately, and stood up before the throne
            of the judge, and in the presence of all the people said unto him, <quote>O judge, thou art
            acting wickedly in tormenting the servants of God without a cause, for the Christians
            neither say nor do wicked things, on the contrary, they even bless their enemies.</quote> Now
            when the judge heard the things which <persName>Philemon</persName> was saying, he thought at first that he
            had gone mad through his pride, and that having gone mad he had spoken; but as soon as
            the judge perceived that he persisted in his words, he answered and said unto him, <quote>Thou
            art mad, O man, and hast suddenly become a fool.</quote> And <persName>Philemon</persName> made answer to him and
            said, <quote>I have not gone mad, O thou wicked judge, but I am a Christian, and I fear the
            God of heaven.</quote> And the judge and all the people wished to persuade him [to be quiet] by
            means of flattering speeches, but, when they saw that he would not yield to them, they
            applied to him all kinds of wicked tortures. And after these things they seized the
            blessed and holy <persName>Apollo</persName>, and brought him [there], and they laid many stripes upon him,
            and they scourged him as men scourge those who are wicked and who lead the people into
            error.</p>
         <p>Then the blessed <persName>Apollo</persName> spake unto the judge, saying, <quote>I pray God that thou also, O
            judge, and all those who are here present with thee may follow after my error</quote>; and when
            the judge perceived that he had spoken such words unto him, he commanded that both
            <persName>Apollo</persName> and <persName>Philemon</persName> should be delivered over to be burnt by fire in the presence of all
            the multitude. And when they were in the blazing fire before the judge the blessed
            <persName>Apollo</persName> cried out with a loud voice unto God, so that all the assembly and even the judge
            himself might hear, saying, <quote>O Lord, give not to be broken the souls which confess Thee,
            but make us to see Thy deliverance boldly.</quote> Then straightway a brilliant cloud, which
            was laden with dew, appeared, and it enveloped these men and quenched the flames of
            fire; and the crowds and the judge marvelled and cried out, saying, <quote>One is the God of
            the Christians.</quote></p>
         <p>And certain wicked men made known the things which had taken place to the governor of
            <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and he chose out from among his bodyguard some savage and merciless men, <pb n="381"/>and
            sent them for all those who were with the judge, and for <persName>Philemon</persName>, and the blessed
            <persName>Apollo</persName>, and other confessors came with them. And as they were going along the road, the
            gracious gift of the Spirit lighted upon <persName>Apollo</persName>, and he began to teach the soldiers, and
            as he spake they hearkened unto him, and they repented at his words, and believed in
            <persName>Christ</persName>, and they all stood up with the prisoners before the throne. And as soon as the
            governor perceived and knew that they could not be changed from the faith of <persName>Christ</persName>, he
            commanded that they should be cast into the depth of the sea; and since they were
            drowned of their own will for <persName>Christ</persName>’s sake, this became unto them a sign of baptism.
            Now the sea refused to keep them, and it brought them together near the shore, and on
            the spot where they had lain a temple was built in their honour, and in it great
            miracles were wrought; and such grace was found with the blessed man, and he was so
            greatly honoured that he was heard by <persName>Christ</persName> in respect of the things for which he
            prayed and made supplication. And we ourselves saw the martyrium wherein he and those
            who had testified with him were laid, and we prayed and worshipped God, and also touched
            their dead bodies, for they were not as yet buried because of the inundation of the
            Nile, but lay embalmed upon their biers in <placeName>Thebaïs</placeName>, and for this reason we made ready to
            insert here the history of the man.</p>
         <p>Here end the Triumph of <persName>Apollo</persName>, the Monk and Martyr, and the other Histories of the Holy
            Men which were written by Hieronymus the Monk.</p>
         <p>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghost, now, and always, and for
            and ever.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
