<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en">The Book of the Dove by <persName>Barhebraeus</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR cleaning and initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus">Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <title>Bar Hebraeus's Book of the Dove Together with some chapters from his Ethikon</title>,
               translated by A. J. Wensinck, Leyden: E. J. Brill, 1919.
            </p>
            <p>Published in 1919, this translation is in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="3"/>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>Introduction In the same way as we find, o my<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3-1"/>
               brother, in bodily medicine books describing the behaviour of patients not attended
               by a physician, it is becoming, in psychic medicine, to give instructions concerning
               the behaviour of those patients who are without or far from a leader;<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n3-2"/> especially in this our age, in which the Syriac
               world is bereft of an <pb type="external" n="522"/>Initiated, who has personally
               experienced the straitness of the way leading to the kingdom and the narrowness of
               the gate giving entrance to it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3-3"/> It is,
               therefore, our aim to give this sort of clear and simple instruction.</p>
            <p>Into four chapters this book is divided, which is small in extent but great in power.
               The first [contains] instruction concerning the bodily labour accomplished in the
               monastery. The second [describes] the quality of psychic labour performed in the
               cell. The third explains the spiritual rest which the consoling Dove imparts to the
               Perfect, elevating them to royal rank and introducing them into the divine cloud<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n3-4"/> where the Lord is said to abide. The fourth is
               a tale of the author's gradual progress in teachings and some sentences communicated
               to him in revelations.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3-5"/></p>
            <p>These four kinds [of states] are represented by the four periods <pb n="4"/> of
                  <persName>Noah</persName>'s life: the first, that of the works of his
               righteousness which made him pleasant unto God. The second, that of his entering the
               ark, which saved him from the destruction of the deluge. The third, that of his
               leaving the ark, when the dove had announced to him that the waters had disappeared
               from the surface of the earth. The fourth, that of the revelations he received and
               the covenant established with him; the planting of the vineyard, his drinking wine
               and his getting drunk.</p>
            <p>However— <persName>Noah</persName>'s dove was irrational and mortal; but <pb
                  type="external" n="523"/>this dove is rational and immortal. She even gives reason
               to the rational<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4-1"/> and life to the living. She
               flies without leaving her nest above, the church of the firstborn<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n4-2"/> in heaven. She reaches all quarters without
               stirring from her place. All images are represented in her without her possessing
               colour herself. She abides in the East, yet the West is full of her. Her food is
               fire, and who is crowned by her with wings will breathe forth flames from his mouth.
               All those who are burning from love and sick from affection reveal their secrets to
               her and she slakes their thirst. Her speech touches every ear, but few hear her
               voice. She calls every man by his name, but one of a thousand answers her. Her cooing
               is much sweeter than the sound of the organ. As the poet describes her: She's very
               pure and full of shame, No mouth can put on her a blame.</p>
            <p>She bears no sign of things material Being spiritual, incorporeal.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="5"/>
         <div type="chapter" n="1">
            <head>Chapter the First</head>
            <head>On the Bodily Service in the Monastery</head>
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>Section the First</head>
               <head>On Man's Alienation from the World<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5-1"
                  /></head>
               <p>Man becomes alien to the world and its desires by two causes. One is essential and
                     veracious,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5-2"/> occurring very seldom. It is
                  a divine impulse moving in the mind of man,<pb type="external" n="524"/> awaking
                  him from his sleepiness to meditate night and day on the torture threatened
                  against the sinners in the world to come and on the enjoyment promised to the
                  righteous in the kingdom of God. This cause is only found among a few people, at
                  long intervals and in some countries only.</p>
               <p>The other cause is fortuitous and secondary. It is love of vain glory, which makes
                  man long after becoming famous, to such a degree, that he submits to the hard
                  labours of asceticism in order to acquire glory; thus rich people have tried to
                  acquire it by suffering great hardship. This cause is found among many people, at
                  all times and everywhere. Though it be simple,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n5-3"/> it is not wholly to be rejected. For often the <pb n="6"/>
                  seed is cast on the earth unintentionally, yet brings forth many fruits. Whereas
                  many a seed is treated carefully by the husbandman, yet proves to be
                     unproductive.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6-1"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>Section the Second</head>
               <head>On Repentance<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6-2"/></head>
               <p>As soon as an intelligent man understands the noxiousness of sin, he repents of
                  the trespasses committed by him. Those to which he is accustomed, he throws from
                  him and he determines not to trespass again,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6-3"
                  /> consoling himself with [the thought], that repentance whenever it is offered
                  [to God], is accepted;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6-4"/> as in the case of
                  the inhabitants of <placeName>Ninive</placeName>, and in that of
                     <persName>Simon</persName>, the head of the Apostles. <pb type="external"
                     n="525"/>Sins<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6-5"/> spring either from reason,
                  as haughtiness, vain glory, envy and sycophancy; or from choler, as anger, hot
                  temper or rancour; or from desire, as covetousness, wantonness and lasciviousness.
                  Extremely great is the sin of those who know, small though it may be.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n6-6"/></p>
               <p>A repentant who trespasses has to implore God's forgiveness with mournful sighs,
                  confessing his sins, as also those did who were baptized by
                     <persName>John</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6-7"/> And to the
                  Apostles came those who believed, and told their faults; and <persName>Peter the
                     Apostle</persName> says: Confess your faults one to the other.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n6-8"/> And <persName>John the Apostle</persName>
                  <pb n="7"/> says: If we confess our sins, He is faithful and just to forgive us
                  our sins.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7-1"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>Section the Third</head>
               <head>On Renunciation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7-2"/></head>
               <p>When true repentance has been established in a man's soul and he sees that worldly
                  possessions exceeding necessary want are sought for the sake of sinful passion, he
                  rejects them and it pleases him to renounce them.</p>
               <p>There are three ranks of renouncers: the lowest, the middle and the highest
                     one.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7-3"/></p>
               <p>The lowest [consists] of those who leave luxury from fear of future torments.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n7-4"/> The middle one of those who hate temporary
                  enjoyment in view of that of Paradise. The highest of those who, because they seek
                  the Good one alone, turn away their faces from all beside Him. This aim is praised
                  by the<pb type="external" n="526"/> Initiated. The objects of renunciation<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n7-5"/> are money, dress, food, dwelling-place and
                  furniture. Money, in so far as the renouncer does not possess it at all.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n7-6"/> Dress, in so far as he is clad in a mean
                  garment of wool or hair, covering the body down to the knees, girding his loins
                  with a belt. If he likes it, he adds a mantle, a coil and shoes.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n7-7"/> Food, in so far as he prepares for a year, a
                  month or a day, bread of wheat, barley or millet, which he moistens with grease,
                  oil or salt water.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7-7"/> His dwelling-place is in
                  a small cell, a cave or a hut. Or he will <pb n="8"/> have no fixed place at all,
                  as also <persName>our Lord</persName> had none; but in any corner which presents
                  itself, he will sit down and sleep.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8-1"/>
                  Furniture, in so far as he uses utensils of clay, wood or gourd.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n8-2"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
               <head>Section the Fourth</head>
               <head>On Humbleness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8-3"/></head>
               <p>As many people practise renunciation involuntarily, the sign of essential
                  renunciation is obedience.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8-4"/> But humbleness
                  has also other signs; for instance that one sits down in the assembly beneath him
                  who is lower in rank;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8-5"/> that, at the time <pb
                     type="external" n="527"/>of prayer, he stands behind without bearing it
                  difficultly; that he gladly will have intercourse with the poor and the needy and
                  will go with them when they invite him;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8-6"/>
                  that he puts on despisable garments without shame.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n8-7"/></p>
               <p><persName>Mar Isaac</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8-8"/> says:
                  Humbleness, without labour, indemnifies many sins.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n8-9"/>
                  <persName>Johannes the Prior</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8-10"/>
                  says: If haughtiness, without other evils, has made <persName>Satan</persName>
                  fall from heaven, humbleness, without other virtues, carries up to heaven.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n8-11"/> When man is <pb n="9"/>sick from
                  haughtiness, he is healed by knowledge of <choice><sic>his self</sic><corr>himself</corr></choice>:<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-1"/> having been created in his beginning from a
                  sordid drop, [in] his end [he] becomes the foetid food of worms. One of the
                  Initiated has said: How should he exalt himself, who two times has come forth from
                  an urethra?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-2"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
               <head>Section the Fifth</head>
               <head>On Patience<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-3"/></head>
               <p>As humbleness is joined to obedience, so obedience is necessarily joined to
                  patience in trouble. Trouble<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-4"/> is either of a
                  temporal or of an eternal nature. So is rest. Because temporal trouble is the
                  cause of eternal rest, and temporal rest that of eternal trouble, the Initiated,
                  who possess the mind of <persName>Christ</persName>, patiently bear temporal
                  trouble for the sake of eternal rest.</p>
               <p>The troubles<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-5"/> which it is becoming to bear
                  patiently are: strife against the passions of gluttony and carnal desire,<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-6"/> voluntary labours of asceticism, involuntary
                  temptations which,<pb type="external" n="528"/> by divine permission, serve to try
                  the solitary—as annoying and impeding accidents, coming across evil and ungodly
                  men, falling from rocks, disdain and contempt which superiors and fellow brethren
                  lay on the shoulders of the novices serving in the monastery, even if they have
                  committed no fault, <pb n="10"/>so that they fall into annoying maladies:
                  aversion, bodily weariness, mental confusion, despondency, darkness of
                  deliberations, deprivation of human help. All [these evils] are healed by the word
                  of the Lord: He that shall endure unto the end, the same shall be saved;<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-1"/> and by the sayings of the holy Fathers on
                  the excellency of patience.</p>
               <p>In short: he who does not burn from love of God, resembles the tile of limestome
                  which is used as a foundation-stone on the bank of a river and endures not for one
                  hour. If, however, it is baked, it endures like a rock.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
               <head>Section the Sixth</head>
               <head>On the Love of the Brethren<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-2"/></head>
               <p>Love of the brethren is the sign of essential patience, appearing not in offence,
                  but in gladness of mind and goodness of will. A true friend is he who is loved on
                  account of his self, because his friend delights in his intercourse. The cause of
                  this delight, in truth, is not in outward nor in inward beauty, but in the hidden
                  consanguinity of two persons.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-3"/> For many
                  love those who are of a simple disposition and narrow-minded. But man loves also
                  him, who aids him towards some corporeal aim, or conducts him towards some psychic
                  profit <pb type="external" n="529"/>as a teacher of true<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n10-4"/> contemplation and profitable practice.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n10-5"/> Loved<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-6"/> is he who has a
                  mind, not a fool; who is chaste, neither greedy nor covetous; whose intercourse is
                  agreeable, not being irascible. Some friends<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-7"
                  /> reckon their friend as their <pb n="11"/>relative and give him what is abundant
                  to themselves. Others estimate him like themselves. Others seek their friend's
                  profit more than their own. And others expose themselves to temptations on behalf
                  of their friend.</p>
               <p>A friend has the duty to aid his friend, not after a demand pressing or not
                  pressing, but before being asked he shall give. He shall destroy his enemies and
                  forgive his faults without recollecting his stains. He shall not conceal his good
                     qualities,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-1"/> nor be burdensome to
                     him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-1"/> He shall not listen to the tales
                  of his neighbour. He shall not ogle him through a crevice, nor spy upon him
                  through fissures. If any provide not for his own faithful kindred, he is worse
                  than the infidels, as <persName>Paul</persName> the blessed says.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-2"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
               <head>Section the Seventh</head>
               <head>On the Offences of the Tongue<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-3"/></head>
               <p>After these things it is necessary for us to speak of the offences of this strait
                  way, because he who is not acquainted with their noxiousness, is not on his guard
                  against them. They are the following.</p>
               <p>Vain speech<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-4"/> is that which, being spoken,
                  is not meritorious, nor being restrained, is sinful. Usually its cause is
                  idleness. It is healed by solitude and by accustoming the tongue to silence.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-5"/> Some put a smooth stone into their mouth,
                  thereby shutting off their babbling.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-6"/></p>
               <pb type="external" n="530"/>
               <pb n="12"/>
               <p>Chattering<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-1"/> is abundance of speech. Its
                  cause is natural aptitude for outbursts of the tongue and exercise in telling the
                  tales of the Ancients. It is healed in the same way as the preceding [fault].</p>
               <p>Speech which is indirectly sinful<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-2"/> consists
                  of tales concerning the glory, the prevalence and the opulency of wicked people.
                  For when the simple hear these [tales], their heart falls into sickness and their
                  faith diminishes. They are healed by: The end of the wicked shall be
                     destruction,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-3"/> in this world and in the
                  world to come.</p>
               <p>Quarrelling consists of setting upright the will, and disobedience. Its cause is
                  haughtiness, which induces man to extol his self, and hatred which brings him to
                  reject his fellow. It is healed by breaking these two impure passions.</p>
               <p>Litigation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-4"/> is fighting with words, set up
                  by the oppressor or the oppressed. The former is healed by: Do violence to no
                     man;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-5"/> the latter by: If any man will sue
                  thee at the law and take away thy coat, let him have thy cloak also.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-6"/></p>
               <p>Scorn. It has two causes. The first, that a man seeks to oppress the object of his
                  scorn. The second consisting in a bad habit fixing its dominion in a man, on
                  account of his intercourse with fools. It is healed by: Whosoever shall say to his
                  brother, Raca, shall be in danger of the council: but whosoever shall say, Thou
                  fool, shall be in danger of hell fire.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-7"/> He
                  who is treated scornfully, shall ascribe it to his own fault and not impute it to
                  him who treats him scornfully; <pb type="external" n="531"/>so he evitates to hate
                  him.</p>
               <p>Curse and malediction.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-8"/> The former is
                  declaring a <pb n="13"/>thing alien to God. The latter, a man's praying for the
                  evil of <choice><sic>an other</sic><corr>another</corr></choice> one. The Initiated, hearing: Bless and maledict
                     not,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-1"/> will neither curse nor
                  maledict.</p>
               <p>Singing is composed of words which excite lascivious emotions; the passion of
                  fornication is hidden in it. Therefore it is reprehensible. He who is sick by
                  singing is healed by its opposite: the reciting of Psalms.</p>
               <p>Jest<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-2"/> is a word which excites laughter<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-3"/> deadly for the heart and defiling honesty.
                  Its cause is frankness of speech, which by the Initiated is called the scorching
                  wind damaging the vegetation during harvest. It is healed by: Woe unto you that
                  laugh now! for ye shall mourn and weep.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-4"
                  /></p>
               <p>Ridicule is showing a man's stains mockingly, in the way of disdain and disregard.
                  It is healed by: Take heed that ye despise not one of these little ones.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-5"/></p>
               <p>Detraction<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-6"/> and taunt is showing stains in
                  the way of hatred and rancour,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-7"/> they are
                  healed by: Blessed is he who sitteth not in the seat of the scornful.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-8"/></p>
               <p>Falsehood<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-9"/> is affirming what is not, as if
                  it were; and that which is, as if it were not. It is healed by: Thou shalt destroy
                  those who speak falsehood.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-10"/> Know, that it
                  is not sinful if it be the cause of psychic profit;<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n13-1"/> as it was not in<pb type="external" n="532"/> the case of
                     <persName>Rahab</persName> when she hid the spies and said: they are not with
                  me. Therefore one of the Fathers<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-11"/> has
                  said: It is possible to make use of it, but cautiously.</p>
               <pb n="14"/>
               <p>Backbiting<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-1"/> is mentioning the trespasses of
                  others unto others, the calumniated not being present. Its cause is usually this
                  that the backbiter, by detecting the faults of others, means to be estimated
                  blameless. Backbiting happens also in the way of amazement or compassion, when one
                  says: I wonder at the mind of so and so, how has he fallen into adultery. And: I
                  am sorry for so and so, that he has been entangled in theft. This sickness is
                  healed by enumerating the virtues of him that trespasses; afterwards the backbiter
                  will not calumniate again if he be intelligent.</p>
               <p>Sycophancy<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-2"/> is mentioning evil unto him
                  concerning whom it has been said or done. Its cause is the tendency to denigrate
                  him who has said the evil, or to flatter him concerning whom it has been said. If
                  the latter be honest, he will not believe the sycophant, but despise and reprimand
                  him and not go far with him into these things; then the sycophant will go away
                  ashamed.</p>
               <p>Double dealing.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-3"/> The wretch who practises
                  it will praise either of two litigants to his face and detract him behind his
                  back. It is healed by: The Lord shall destroy double dealing.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-4"/></p>
               <p>Flattery.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-5"/> The flatterer falls into four
                  evils. Into <pb type="external" n="533"/>falsehood when he calls bitter sweet.
                  Into hypocrisy when he often flatters. Into error when he says what he does not
                  know exactly. Into guiltiness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-6"/> when he
                  gladdens the unjust.</p>
               <p>He who is flattered falls into two damages: into boasting and into haughtiness.
                  Either of them is healed by silence.</p>
               <p>Rudeness of speech.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-7"/> If for instance one
                  says: But for so and so, the wolf would have eaten me. Whereas he <pb n="15"
                  />should have said: But for the Lord, who sent to my help so and so, the wolf
                  would have eaten me.</p>
               <p>Vain investigation. If for instance one investigates that which to know does not
                  profit, and which not to know does not harm; for instance: to investigate after
                  the name of <persName>Melchisedek</persName>'s father.</p>
               <p>From all these things<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-1"/> the novice is
                  purified in the furnace of the monastery, as silver is purified from refuse.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-2"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
               <head>Section the Eighth</head>
               <head>On the Novice's turning backwards<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-3"
                  /></head>
               <p>When the novice fulfills the duties of the monastery according to his power and
                  proves steadfast in those [duties of] behaviour, which suit to the state of his
                  position and he knows that the time of his entering the ark of the cell draws
                  near, hard deliberations of fear will rise in his heart and he will begin to say
                  to himself: I am not able to bear constant reclusion; this is too great a thing
                  for me; it suits me not to disparage it. Having entered, I shall perhaps not be
                  able to bear it patiently and, leaving it, become an object of laughter for the
                  demons and a spectacle for the angels and man. So it will be better for me to be
                  in the world and, if it be necessary for me to practise righteousness, to practise
                  it there. Or<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-4"/> have not the ancient just,
                     <persName>Abraham</persName>, <persName>Isaac</persName> and<pb type="external"
                     n="534"/>
                  <persName>Jacob</persName>, possessed wives and sons and daughters and various
                  possessions, and yet pleased God better than all solitaries<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n15-5"/>? <pb n="16"/> Just so <persName>Moses</persName>, the head of
                  the prophets, who spoke with God face to face; and <persName>David</persName>, the
                  king and prophet, who has been surnamed the heart of God. The head of the
                  apostles, <persName>Peter</persName>, had a mother in law, yet was entrusted with
                  the keys of heaven. And also others were at the head of shops, as
                     <persName>Priscilla</persName> and <persName>Aquila</persName>, yet were
                  just.</p>
               <p><persName>Aba Macarius</persName> was sent towards two married women in the town
                  in order to learn from them righteousness. On marriage there is a divine command,
                  as: Be fruitful and multiply, and replenish the earth and subdue it;<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-1"/> but concerning virginity there is none at
                  all. As the blessed <persName>Paul</persName> says: Concerning virginity I have no
                  commandment of God: yet I give my judgment.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-2"
                  /></p>
               <p>When the novice often meditates upon such thoughts, or better: When he is
                  overwhelmed by carnal desire, he is preparing to return to the world and on the
                  way of falling from spiritual behaviour into dwelling with matter, if the eyes of
                  his mind are not opened by a physician,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-3"/>
                  who is an Initiated.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
               <head>Section the Ninth</head>
               <head>On directing the Novice in his Course<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-4"
                  /></head>
               <p>When the master and leader of the novice has secretly become aware of the latter's
                  halting between two opinions,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-5"/>
                  <pb type="external" n="535"/>he says to him mournfully: Woe unto me, my son, woe!
                  because I see that you intend to choose the evil part of
                  <persName>Lot</persName>'s wife, who turned backwards and became a pillar of salt.
                  Have you not heard [the word of] the Lord who says: No man, having put his hand to
                  the plough, and looking back, is fit <!-- in the Syriac Bible. --><pb n="17"/> for
                  the kingdom of God.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17-1"/> Verily you are to be
                  wondered at, comparing yourself with the holy fathers, with the prophets and the
                  apostles! Is a fly able to do what a lion does? Or can a thorn reach the measure
                  of a cedar? No, my son, err not. But know, that lawful marriage is to be preferred
                  to false, double-hearted virginity, which intends to serve God and the world; but
                  not to true virginity, which is not divided between <persName>Christ</persName>
                  and an earthly king, nor subject to a double-hearted law, but has devoted its love
                  to God alone.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17-2"/> It is of a beautiful life,
                  it carries its head upright, it is lightfooted, enlightened, exalted above matter,
                  far from the flesh. It has been said rightly:<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n17-3"/> A married layman's hands are bound, his feet are tied
                  together. An unmarried layman's hands are only impeded. But the true solitary,
                  though being on the earth, is elevated unto heaven on his spiritual wings.
                  Usually, when a layman is not able to fulfill the wants of his wife and children
                  he is likely to fall into robbery and theft. For who is able<pb type="external"
                     n="536"/> to bear the bad character of a woman or to fulfill all her needs?
                  Verily such a man will by this vexation be brought to seek the end of his
                  life.</p>
               <p>The ways by which sin enters [people who are in] the world are many: envy,
                  rancour, hatred, desire, love of finery, love of money, covetousness, avarice,
                  criticism of God's unintelligible judgments, as: Why are the wicked, my enemies,
                  opulent, whereas the good, my friends, are starving? And many other things, which
                  the Elect may evitate.</p>
               <p>By such [admonitions] the novice is edificated and he will return unto his place,
                  if care takes his hand.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="18"/>
            <div type="section" n="10">
               <head>Section the Tenth</head>
               <head>On the Tokens of [good] Direction</head>
               <p>Of the steadfastness of the novice there are certain tokens. They are the
                  following: a quiet gait, a demure voice, a sweet speech, a chaste appearance,
                  modest looks, concealed gladness, mean habits, inconsiderable food, perfect love,
                  the reciting of psalms with understanding, love of strangers, purity of
                  deliberations. For every brother, who is steadfast in these things, will bear his
                  struggle gladly and pray that his enemy may repent. He will listen to words of
                  wisdom and not wonder greatly at the narrative of a thing which he has never seen,
                  nor at a tale which he has never heard. He will not ask him whom he meets: Whereto
                  or for which reason do you go? His lips will not tell laughable stories.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n18-1"/> He will not love finery <pb type="external"
                     n="537"/>like a woman. He will not cast looks here and there on his body and
                  his habits, nor twist his fingers, nor play with the hairs of his beard, nor with
                  his tandstick, save only secretly. Being hungry he will not yawn; nor, awake, will
                  he gape; nor form spittle, as it occurs to him. He will not gesticulate during
                  conversation. At meals he will take a low place, not a high one. He will not have
                  intercourse with magistrates.</p>
               <p>By these inclinations<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18-2"/> the steadfast novice
                  is to be recognized; in order to acquire them he serves in the monastery.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <pb n="19"/>
         <div type="chapter" n="2">
            <head>Chapter the Second</head>
            <head>On the Psychic Service which is Accomplished in the Cell</head>
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>Section the First</head>
               <head>On the Duties of the Cell</head>
               <p>The habitation of the cell has to take place with distinction, not in the way of a
                  groove, as is the case with many persons who become recluses without having fixed
                  an aim, towards which the labour of their behaviour shall be directed.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n19-1"/> This aim consists in expecting from the
                  Lord the gift of the illumination<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19-2"/> of the
                  mind and the aptitude to behold the spiritual things in their nature and to have
                  communion with them; together with many other things which are effectuated unto
                  [the recluse].</p>
               <p>When he has fulfilled this, the duties of the cell are given him. They are:
                  solitude, true asceticism, which is accomplished by prayer, invocation, reciting
                  and meditation; definite ritual prayers at fixed times; vigils; weeping; fasting;
                  manual labour; abiding abroad; guarding the heart against evil passions, which<pb
                     type="external" n="538"/> are:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19-3"/>
                  dejectedness, wantonness, lasciviousness, anger, rancour, <pb n="20"/>envy,
                  desires, covetousness, vain glory, [assuming] a false appearance, haughtiness,
                  boast, reprehension.</p>
               <p>When the heart is purified from such evil passions, it has necessarily to be
                  adorned with good qualities, as patients,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-1"/>
                  besides evitating things which cause harm, have also to make use of remedies. They
                  are: love of teachings, faith, thanksgiving, hope, fear of God, poverty,
                  confidence, purity of deliberations, remembrance of death.</p>
               <p>This is the behaviour of the pure in heart, which shall see God.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-2"/></p>
               <p>We shall describe each of these [qualities] peculiarly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>Section the Second</head>
               <head>On Solitude<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-3"/></head>
               <p>Solitude, in the intellectual eyes of the Initiated, is [of] so great [a value],
                  that, even if being bare and devoid of all other excellency, they have praised it
                  higher than intercourse accompanied by virtuous [practice]. For the blessed
                     <persName>Palladius</persName> says: I asked <persName>Aba Sarmata</persName>
                  saying to him: What shall I do? I do not practise the works of monks, but I am
                  eating and sleeping; and my deliberations are disturbed. He answered me: Stay in
                  your cell and do what you are able to do, without being troubled; then I trust,
                  that you will be praised like <persName>Antonius</persName>.</p>
               <p>Many are the profits of solitude. The first, which is much more elevated and
                  exalted than all the others, is spiritual <pb type="external" n="539"/>enjoyment,
                  which you will acquire by the true knowledge of the divine nature.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-4"/> Further, liberation from worldly care which
                     <pb n="21"/>impedes spiritual service, from the backbiting of the fellow
                  brethren, from the reprehension of the unrighteous, from seeking to please, for
                  those who are pleasant unto men, will be confounded, because God rejects them;
                  from seeing and hearing ugly things which easily adhere to [human] nature, but
                  leave it only with difficulty. For man is more swift in retaining of small evil
                  much, than of great excellence little. On account of the violence of wicked
                  mankind, as it has been said, it is impossible to tame<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n21-1"/> the beasts of the field, nor do the gazelles on the mountains
                  stretch themselves before the shearer. If the beasts of <choice><sic>pray</sic><corr>prey</corr></choice> come near,
                  man will strip them of their hides near the walls. If the eagle inhabits the town,
                  smoke will blind its eyes.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-2"/> [Lastly
                  solitude] liberates the fellow brethren from the recluse's obtrusion.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-3"/></p>
               <p>Intercourse, however, has also profits:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-4"/>
                  teachings, supporting the weak, exercise and training; bearing the obtrusion of
                  narrow-minded and angry people; prudence springing from experience.</p>
               <p>Therefore, when the novice has acquired these things in the monastery, in which he
                  is put to the test as gold in the furnace,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-5"/>
                  he has to choose solitude and reclusion in the cell.</p>
               <p>It is, however, the duty of the recluse to cut off intercourse with other people
                  by a strong constraint and to get accustomed to the constant quiet of the
                  cell.</p>
               <p>During the whole year he shall not meet with anyone excepted when partaking of the
                  sacraments on Sundays. And, without necessity, nobody shall visit him. For many
                  have commenced with hard labours and ended with a reprehensible<pb type="external"
                     n="540"/> life, on account of their constant intercourse with lay people, <pb
                     n="22"/>the sight of rich women and their instruction, promising the knowledge
                  of the future<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-1"/> and the examination of
                  hidden things. Finally their cells <choice><sic>beame</sic><corr>became</corr></choice> the meeting-places of the
                  inhabitants of towns and villages, and so they fell from an enlightened life into
                  the behaviour of blindness.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-2"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>Section the Third</head>
               <head>On fourfold Asceticism: Prayer, Invocation, Recitation, Meditation<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-3"/></head>
               <p>Prayer. Forgiving the faults of him who has sinned against him, turning eastward,
                  elevating his hands, and looking to the earth as if being ashamed before his Lord,
                  the solitary shall begin his prayer by saying several times: O God, be merciful to
                  me, a sinner.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-4"/> My Lord, have mercy upon me.
                  My Lord, endow me with those things which Thou knowest to be profitable to me.
                  Then God will give him that of which he has no idea to ask.</p>
               <p>Invocation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-5"/> of God consists in repeating
                  ten sentences<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-6"/> from the glorifications of
                  the blessed children,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-7"/> six of those
                  beginning with Blessed be thou, and four beginning with Bless ye. The smallest
                  number of repetitions is three; the middle, seven; the complete, forty, according
                  to time and wise.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-8"/></p>
               <pb n="23"/>
               <p>As to the reciting of the New Testament, though the soul may not perceive the
                  delight it gives, in the beginning, yet it traces in the mind spiritual
                  meditations instead of carnal phantasies, and so, gradually, the mind
                  <choice><sic>aquires</sic><corr>acquires</corr></choice> purity.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23-1"/> It<pb
                     type="external" n="541"/> is becoming to recite every day seven chapters: from
                  the Gospels, one from every one of them, one from the Acts, one from the catholic
                  epistles, one from the epistles of the blessed <persName>Paul</persName>. At the
                  end of every chapter the reciter has to kneel three times before the cross, which
                  is the symbol of <persName>our Lord</persName>. The book has to be laid on a
                  chair. He who is not a reciter, shall meditate upon the works of God.</p>
               <p>Meditation is of three kinds. The first, that one meditates his sins, for if man
                  does not demolish his soul, it cannot be built. The second, that man meditates
                  upon the justness of God's judgments and the torments destined for the wicked. So
                  the fear of God will become strong in his heart. The third, that one meditates
                  upon the effusions of God's mercy and the goods promised to the good; then
                  thanksgivings will be multiplied in his mouth and his thoughts will be made to
                  abide in the spiritual world and he will have spiritual intercourse with the
                  Angels of light and the souls of the just.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
               <head>Section the Fourth</head>
               <head>On ritual Prayer and the Division of Times<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n23-2"/></head>
               <p>If <persName>Moses</persName>, the Great, could not draw near the thorn-bush
                  before having put off his shoes from his feet, [in order to meet] Him who is
                  outside all sensual apperception, how could it be possible for the mind to speak
                  in prayer, if it had not been concentrated from divagation? Though in the
                  beginning the mind is not easily concentrated, yet, after steady exercise and
                  after receiving the sweetness of prayer it is easily conducted <pb type="external"
                     n="542"/><pb n="24"/>towards the treasury of the heart,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n24-1"/> abiding with God in ecstasy.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n24-2"/></p>
               <p>Pure prayer<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-3"/> is inconsistent with a
                  multitude of words, for when ye pray, use not vain repetitions as the heathen do,
                  for they think that they shall be heard for their much speaking.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-4"/> Obligatory prayer is this: to stand, the
                  face turned eastward, the hands folded, to concentrate the mind and to say three
                  times the prayer of Holy art thou, o God. Every time he who prays shall prostrate
                  himself and make the sign of the cross on his face. Then he shall say three times:
                  Our Lord, have mercy upon me. Every time he shall kneel down. Then he shall say:
                  Glory to thee, our Lord, glory to thee, our Lord, glory to thee, our hope for
                  ever. Then, standing upright he shall proceed with Our Father which art in heaven.
                  Then prayer is finished.</p>
               <p>The fixed ritual prayers are seven. The first, morning prayer, at sunrise. After
                  it the solitary shall recite four chapters from the Gospels. Until the completion
                  of the third hour he shall be occupied with prayer<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n24-5"/> and meditation. Then he shall pray the second ritual prayer,
                  that of the third hour, and until the completion of the sixth hour he shall
                  <choice><sic>fatigate</sic><corr>fatigue</corr></choice> himself with manual work; if he has not such work, he shall be
                  occupied with meditation. Then he shall pray the third ritual prayer, that of
                  noon, and sleep a little, because this short sleep is helpful for vigils<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-5"/> and because it frustrates the strife of the
                  demon of weariness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-6"/> (who at this time of
                  the day forces the <pb n="25"/>solitary to look perpetually into the sunrays) as
                  the solitary assumes an immovable or nearly immovable attitude.</p>
               <p>Then again he shall do manual work until the completion<pb type="external" n="543"
                  /> of nine hours. Then he shall pray the fourth ritual prayer, that of the ninth
                  hour, and recite the other three chapters and until sunset be occupied with
                     prayer.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-1"/> Thereupon he shall pray the
                  fifth ritual prayer, evening prayer, and until the completion of two hours of the
                  night be occupied with prayer<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-1"/> and
                  meditation. Thereupon he shall pray the sixth ritual prayer, that of compline.
                  Having slept until midnight he shall pray the seventh ritual prayer. If he is
                  overwhelmed by sleep, he shall indulge in it by stealth,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n25-2"/> sitting,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-3"/> until the
                  completion of the tenth hour of the night. Then he shall sleep no more, but repeat
                  invocations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
               <head>Section the Fifth</head>
               <head>On the Reciting of Psalms and Vigils<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-4"
                  /></head>
               <p>Before every one of the four ritual prayers of the day and that of the evening,
                  the solitary shall regularly recite two of the fifteen parts of the Psalter;
                  before compline one; before nightprayer four.</p>
               <p>Vigils are to be lengthened and shortened according to the state of the
                     solitary.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-5"/> For many watch during a third
                  part of the night, two hours in its beginning and two in its end; during two
                  thirds they lie down to sleep. Others watch during <pb n="26"/>half the night and
                  lie down to sleep during the other half. The perfect, as <persName>Aba
                     Arsenius</persName>, in the evening preceding Sunday turn their back to the sun
                  and stand till it rises before them. <pb type="external" n="544"/>Helpful<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n26-1"/> towards vigils are spare food and small
                  labour and a short sleep at noon. Therefore the body shall be burdened with
                  labours only with measure for we are ordered to destroy passions, not life.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n26-2"/> So, whosoever has got an indigestion by
                  labours, shall give rest to the body and its powers, then return to his labours.
                  Some perform forty kneelings after the prayer of compline; others forty more after
                  morning prayer.</p>
               <p>The reciting of Psalms has to take place with weeping. The cause of weeping is the
                  contrition of the heart and the burning of the soul with love of God. A certain
                  solitary dreamt that he was reciting Psalms before <persName>David</persName> the
                  son of <persName>Isai</persName>, who said to him: I wonder at you; how have you
                  learnt to recite Psalms without having learnt to weep? Weeping cannot be without
                  distinction. Therefore it has been said: it is very necessary to shorten the
                  recitation of Psalms somewhat, that the soul may stick to distinction, remaining
                  lucid. On account of this some solitaries absolve the Psalter one time every week;
                  others every month. The weak, however, do not shorten their reciting of Psalms for
                  the sake of increased distinction, but by the influence of the demon of
                  dejectedness, who makes strife against them. For the like it is sufficient to
                  recite only the short Psalm O, Praise the Lord, all ye nations; praise him, all ye
                     people.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n26-3"/> For the Lord of the vineyard
                  regards only the readiness of the <pb type="external" n="545"/>will, not the
                  quantity of the work and he pays the hire to the labourers of the eleventh hour as
                  well as to the first ones <pb n="27"/>who have borne the burden and the heat of
                  the day. Some solitaries who do not belong to the exquisite, reckon the offering
                  of the eucharist in solitude as belonging to the labours. But they do not take
                  into consideration that sayings from the anaphora as: As often as you are
                  assembled in my name, and: To thee thy servants bow their heads, and many other
                  sayings are only applicable to the community.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
               <head>Section the Sixth</head>
               <head>On Fasting<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-1"/></head>
               <p>If a multitude of stinking viands, by the vapours they cause, obscure the eyes of
                  the soul without giving it the opportunity to see any spiritual thing—by
                  refraining from them the mirror of the mind<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-2"
                  /> becomes enlightened and it acquires the aptitude to reflect spiritual
                     images.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-3"/></p>
               <p>In fasting there are three ranks: the common, the peculiar and the more
                     peculiar.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-4"/></p>
               <p>The common one is this: absolutely not to eat nor to drink during the day, as is
                  the custom of the Easterns. Or: only not to eat animals or what is related to
                  them, during the day, as is the custom of the Westerns. They take vegetables and
                  herbs, the former in the evening, the latter by day also.</p>
               <p>This first, common way of fasting has several ritual precepts: the faster, from
                  morning-time onwards, shall have the intention to fast; for many do not eat
                  accidentally, yet they are not reckoned as fasters. He shall beware from any food
                  or <pb n="28"/><pb type="external" n="546"/>drink passing through his throat. He
                  shall not use his spittle,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-1"/> except in case
                  of sickness.</p>
               <p>Peculiar fasting<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-2"/> is that of the
                  solitaries, fasting in which not only the stomach but also the senses refrain from
                  culpable inclinations. It has also ritual precepts: shutting the eyes from
                  unchaste looking; binding the tongue against all sinful speech; occluding the ear
                  against listening to impure words.</p>
               <p>More peculiar fasting is that of the Perfect; fasting in which not only the
                  stomach and the senses but also the soul refrains from impure deliberations. It
                  has one ritual precept: to eradicate all worldly meditations from the depth of the
                  heart. The elevation unto this rank, though difficult, becomes easy by training.
                  As it has been said: Nature is easy and giving an opportunity to all sorts of
                  change. It has the power of receptivity according to the measure in which you
                  force it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-3"/></p>
               <p>The Apostolic constitutions command: If any member of the clergy be found to fast
                  on Sunday or Sabbath, excepted on the Sabbath preceding Passover, he shall be
                     dismissed.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-4"/> In the same way the Fathers
                  who were assembled at <placeName>Gangra</placeName> have said: If anyone on
                  account of pretended asceticism shall fast on Sunday, he shall be anathemised.
                  Therefore the solitary shall break his fasting on Sunday and Sabbath at the third
                  hour, albeit by a crumb; further he shall take food in the evening hours in order
                  to comply with the commandment, not because food is meritorious.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="external" n="547"/>
            <div type="section" n="7">
               <head>Section the Seventh</head>
               <head>On manual Work<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-5"/></head>
               <p>That manual work is excellent is affirmed by the Initiated.</p>
               <pb n="29"/>
               <p>When <persName>Aba Antonius</persName> was stricken with dejectedness there
                  appeared unto him an angel who sat and spun threads; then the angel rose from his
                  work and prayed; again he sat down and worked, and again rose and prayed. Then he
                  said: do the same, <persName>Antonius</persName>, and be saved. <persName>Aba
                     Atir</persName> said to <persName>Aba Anbistion</persName>: make small your
                  stomach and increase your manual work. <choice><sic>An other</sic><corr>Another</corr></choice> has said: accept no
                  favour from anyone; but let your hands be sufficient for your sustenance.</p>
               <p>To those who say: it is not becoming to work<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29-1"
                  /> because <persName>our Lord</persName> has commanded us to become as the fowls
                  of the air, which sow not, nor do they reap, and because he praised
                     <persName>Mary</persName> who did not work, above <persName>Martha</persName>
                  who was anxious about work—we give the answer: these commandments are apt for the
                  Perfect, who have acquired spiritual work. And the solitary who has not yet
                  acquired this, would not be able to bear [the abode] in the cell on account of the
                  passions and desires idleness awakes in him. And though <persName>Paul</persName>,
                  the blessed, would have been entitled to be sustained by the people, because he
                  was their head, yet he would not even eat the bread of the Thessalonicians
                  gratuitously, but day and night he toiled at saddlery, lest he should become
                  burdensome to any of them. And the other apostles were fishermen. Some brethren of
                  the desert used to reap with the husbandmen; others braided baskets and mats.</p>
               <p>It is however the duty of the solitary not to praise that which he sells and not
                  to conceal but to show its stains. He<pb type="external" n="548"/> shall not ask
                  an immodest price and he shall sell to the needy and indigent.</p>
               <p>To the members of the clergy it is allowed not to work; for those who work in the
                  sanctuary are sustained by the sanctuary. And they which wait at the altar are
                  partakers with the altar.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29-2"/> And though it be
                  allowed to the Fathers to supply <pb n="30"/>their wants at the cost of their
                  flocks, yet is it more profitable for them to work without accepting anything from
                  anyone. Here the author confesses his guilt, saying: I teach but I do not learn; I
                  write but I have neglected; I preach but I do not practise; I admonish but I have
                  sinned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
               <head>Section the Eighth</head>
               <head>On Abiding abroad<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-1"/></head>
               <p>Abiding abroad is divided into two kinds: the bodily and the spiritual one.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-2"/></p>
               <p>The bodily one is bodily departure from paternal home to a foreign place. The
                  spiritual is intellectual departure from the corruptible world towards the kingdom
                  of heaven in which the angels dwell. Bodily abiding abroad which does not take
                  place on account of psychic need and the desire to acquire spiritual profit, is to
                  be rejected.</p>
               <p>Psychic need consists of four kinds: the first, persecution on account of one's
                     confession;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-3"/> the second, offence on the
                  part of the brethren, when he who is the stumbling block is not able to justify
                     himself<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-4"/> before them; the third,
                  immoderate praise being spent on the solitary in the place where he has <pb
                     type="external" n="549"/>become renowned,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-5"
                  /> as <persName>Aba Euagrius</persName> says: If your cell becomes a trodden soil,
                  flee from it; the fourth, the strife of fornication in the place where the brother
                     dwells.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-6"/></p>
               <p>Spiritual profit [to be gained by abiding abroad] is of three <pb n="31"/>kinds:
                  the first, necessary teachings;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-1"/> the
                  second, seeing excellent men; the third, the beneficial influence of holy
                     places.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-2"/> These are the meritorious
                  motives of abiding abroad. If it has other motives—pleasure, fleeing from the
                  trouble of reclusion or from need, or the solitary being disdained in his place—it
                  is to be blamed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-3"/> and its cause is the demon
                  which makes man wander about.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-4"/> For this
                  demon instigates the mind of the solitary to wander from place to place. At first
                  he soothes him by making his intercourse with others bear a harmless character;
                  afterwards he causes him to fall into the hands of the demon of fornication, or of
                  anger, or of distress and despondency.</p>
               <p>It is the duty of him who goes to visit one of the Fathers, to occupy himself with
                  the invocation of God on his way,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-5"/> and not
                  to neglect any of the ritual prayers. At any village or town he reaches, he has
                  first to present himself at the church.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-6"/> He
                  shall not remain longer than three days in the same village or town.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-7"/> And when he has reached the cell of the
                     Father<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-8"/> [he wishes to visit], he shall
                  not knock at his door, but sit down till he will perceive and call him. Then he
                  shall draw near humbly and greet him becomingly, without speaking before he is
                  asked. In accordance with the question he shall give his answer, quietly, without
                  adding anything.</p>
               <pb n="32"/>
               <p>When he asks for a commandment, he shall request modestly. <pb type="external"
                     n="550"/>He shall not stay with him longer than one day. Being asked after the
                  state of his place, he shall tell the stories of its just and excellent men. He
                  shall not mention its many gardens and trees nor the opulence of its fruits and
                  products, lest he be blamed for love of pleasure and gluttony.</p>
               <p>The Initiated reckon the third kind of profit to be secondary [importance],
                  saying: the divine power inhabiting the bones of saints reaches all places. When
                  to a certain Master his disciple said: I wish to go to Jerusalem, he said to him:
                  You err greatly; for every man strives to ascend unto Jerusalem on high, and you
                  unto Jerusalem beneath? For the hour cometh, when ye shall neither in this
                  mountain, nor yet at Jerusalem, worship the Father. For God is spirit; and they
                  that worship him must worship him in spirit and in truth.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n32-1"/> Stay therefore in your cell and strive to see in yourself Him
                  who is near to all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
               <head>Section the Ninth</head>
               <head>On evil Passions</head>
               <p>Now it is becoming to speak of the impure passions attacking the solitary in the
                  cell from which he has necessarily to be purified. They are, as we have said
                  above: Dejectedness.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n32-2"/> At times when the
                  solitary is not able to perform the usual service, the demons compel him to
                  perform it, and, though his body is weary, to rise and to recite Psalms. At these
                  times the solitary who vexes himself with labours, resembles a man who draws water
                  and empties it into a leaky bucket. Therefore it is profitable for him to give <pb
                     type="external" n="551"/>his body some rest and to interchange his bodily
                  labours with spiritual ones. For many have performed great labours, but because
                  they have not laboured with distinction they have not attained the way of God.</p>
               <pb n="33"/>
               <p>Wantonness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-1"/> is healed by hunger<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-2"/> by which the mind is purified and spiritual
                  enjoyments are attained and by which the spirit is made humble, the desires are
                  quenched and the weariness of sleep lightened.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n33-3"/> Lessening the quantity of food has to take place
                     progressively:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-4"/> he who is accustomed to
                  take one crust of bread daily, shall diminish this quantity with one sixtieth of a
                  crust every day; so after a month he will have reached half a crust without being
                  damaged. Some solitaries take one pound of bread every day; others two thirds,
                  others half a pound. The majority take food only once a day; some every second
                  evening; others from Sunday to Sunday.The Naziraeans abstain from eggs, milk,
                  grease, cheese and fish. They are subject to two passions: desire of delicious
                  food, which urges the Naziraean to break his vows of abstention; and vain glory
                  advising him to extol his virtues. If he is vanquished by these two [passions], he
                  falls into eating secretly that which he does not eat publicly. They are both
                  healed by his breaking the vow of abstention without fulfilling his want
                  wholly.</p>
               <p>Lasciviousness.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-5"/> The demon of fornication
                  causes the solitary to see disdainful phantasma's, to utter impudent words and to
                  listen to the answers, and to imagine that these things really happen to him. He
                  explores carnal desire and excites<pb type="external" n="552"/> it and seduces the
                  solitary to relax and give way to impudence full of impurity. This passion is
                  healed by constant starving and abstinence from intercourse with women and boys,
                  and from looking at them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-6"/> For
                     <persName>Aba Amon</persName> says: when I came into the desert, I was a boy.
                  And <persName>Aba Paphnutius</persName> the simple <pb n="34"/>turned me away
                  saying: I do not permit the face of a boy resembling that of a woman to inhabit
                  Skete. And the holy <persName>Basilius</persName> says: if a man says he cannot be
                  damaged by the intercourse with women, he is either not a man or he is not aware
                  of his passion, like one who is drunk, yet pretends to be master of his senses.
                  Excepted are the Perfect who, in the same way as they are not affected by
                  passionate deliberation when seeing the magnificent luminaries in the sky or the
                  glorious flowers on the earth, so they are not scorched in their hearts by
                  exciting inclinations when seeing a desirable face and elegant beauty.</p>
               <p>He<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-1"/> who is healed from this passion, at
                  first will be tormented by natural inclination and impulse <choice><sic>whithout</sic><corr>without</corr></choice>
                  phantastic representations of copulation. In the middle stage he will perceive
                  natural inclination <choice><sic>whithout</sic><corr>without</corr></choice> phantasies and impulse. When he is being
                  completely healed even natural inclination will cease, because passionate
                  deliberation has ceased.</p>
               <p>Anger.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-2"/> When a man's enemy<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-3"/> is weaker than himself, the fire of his
                  anger will be kindled, his heart blood will become hot and his face red. When he
                  is stronger than himself his blood will flow back to the depth of his heart, <pb
                     type="external" n="553"/>his colour will become pale and his choler will be
                  changed into fear.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-4"/> The causes<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-5"/> which strengthen anger are spiritual
                  haughtiness, quarrelsomeness and covetousness. It is healed by:<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-6"/> Learn from me, for I am <choice><sic>week</sic><corr>meek</corr></choice> and
                  lowly in heart.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-7"/> And by: Let not the sun go
                  down upon your wrath,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-8"/> and by detesting the
                  madness of the will which happens together <pb n="35"/>with anger; for the members
                  of the body tremble, the tongue stammers and the mouth foams. And<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n35-1"/> if he is not able to attain his oppressor,
                  he scratches and scorns himself, rends his habit, beats the earth, smashes his
                  plate on a stone and crushes his table.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35-2"/> He
                  disdains his cattle and if they kick him, he kicks them, bites their ears, and
                  pulls their tails. If he is vituperated, he will apologize boastingly, saying: I
                  am not able to see and hear unbecoming things.</p>
               <p>Rancour is born from choler. Growing up it gives birth to eight daughters:<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n35-3"/> that a man envies him against whom he bears
                  rancour, that he hates him, that he rejoices at his damage, that he sycophantizes
                  him and seeks to damage him and to annul his profit, that he disregards and
                  ridicules him. One of the Fathers has said: he who bears rancour and thinks to be
                  a repentant, resembles a man who dreams that he is running.</p>
               <p>It is healed by quieting the choler and by honouring him that bears it, as
                     <persName>Euagrius</persName> the Great says: by presents
                     <persName>Jacob</persName> has reconciled <persName>Esau</persName>. But we,
                  the needy, have to fulfill our wants at a simple table.</p>
               <p>Envy.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35-4"/> A man envies only him, that
                  possesses any good<pb type="external" n="554"/> more copiously than himself. Every
                  one who perceives a good in <choice><sic>an other</sic><corr>another</corr></choice>, and hates its endurance and seeks
                  its disappearance, he is wickedly envious. But if, on the contrary, he desires the
                  same good for himself, his zeal is praiseworthy.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n35-1"/></p>
               <p>A man<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35-5"/> envies him whom he hates and him who
                  does not wish to be like himself or who is his superior. Envious is he also who
                  desires for himself the good which <choice><sic>an other</sic><corr>another</corr></choice> possesses, as well as he
                  who desires to be a unique man in his age. Envious is also the man of a bad
                  character who does <pb n="36"/>not love teachings or asceticism, but is sorry when
                  perceiving <choice><sic>an other</sic><corr>another</corr></choice> who is being taught or practising asceticism.</p>
               <p>Envy<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-1"/> is healed thereby, that a man knows
                  that to be envious is troublesome for himself, and to be envied makes glad on
                  account of the good possessed peculiarly.</p>
               <p>Desires<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-2"/> make temporal life pleasant for
                  man, but do not give the opportunity to prepare oneself for eternal life. They are
                  divided into desire of necessary things, as food and covering, wife and home; of
                  natural things, as family and affinity; of acquirable things, as dominion, wealth,
                  slaves and handmaids, gardens and estates. As <persName>Aba Poman</persName> has
                  said: even wisdom without behaviour belongs to them. Likewise teachings of
                  teachers who do not care for the salvation of their hearers, but for stealing
                  their money. In short: as a man is not able to see his likeness in troubled water,
                  so the mind cannot see its Lord within itself, if its mirror be not purified <pb
                     type="external" n="555"/>from desires.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-3"/>
                  In truth, man in the world<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-4"/> is like him who
                  dreams of desire and lust; but, awaking, does not find anything of them.</p>
               <p>Covetousness.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-5"/> If man knew the damages<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-6"/> of wealth he would not be very desirous of
                  gathering it. They are: artifices and ambushes prepared for him by governors,
                  thieves and robbers, envy of fellow brethren; the impure things perpetrated by
                  means of it, as wantonness, adultery and vain glory; and those by means of which
                  wealth is effectuated, as falsehood, oppression and forsaking spiritual service.
                  For no servant can serve two masters.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-7"/> If a
                  man inquires for what purpose gold has been created, the angelic deliberation <pb
                     n="37"/>answers:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-1"/> for the sake of
                  necessary maintenance; the demoniacal: for the sake of luxury and pleasure.</p>
               <p>Covetousness is healed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-1"/> by lessening the
                  expenses, by being content with little,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-2"/>
                  and by comparing the second hand enjoyments of the rich with the great honour of
                  the renouncers and by looking at his inferiors, not at his superiors.</p>
               <p>Vain glory.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-3"/> Love of vain glory is the
                  desire of honour<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-4"/> on account of one's
                  excellence being extolled.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-5"/> Hypocrites seek
                  to get praises on account of the hard labours of a false asceticism.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-6"/> Some do not seek praise, but they rejoice
                  at being praised. Others are troubled by praise,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n37-7"/> but they are silent without declining it. Others flee from
                  the place where they are praised. But the Perfect become angry<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-8"/> and declare those who praise them to be
                  liars. Some people are troubled<pb type="external" n="556"/> when being disdained
                     <ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-9"/>and guard rancour in their heart
                  against him who disdains them. Others are only troubled<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n37-9"/> without guarding rancour. Others reckon disdain as praise.
                  Others love him who disdains them because he reveals to them their stains and
                  becomes the cause of their being healed.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-10"
                  /></p>
               <p>The love of glory is healed by practising those things which render man simple and
                  lessen his [outward] honour and <pb n="38"/>by being like the dead, who do not
                  rejoice at praise nor are spiteful on account of disdain;<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n38-1"/> by working in secret and by appearing in public like every
                  man. An excellent man said to one who praised him: if you knew me, as I know
                  myself, you would not praise me.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38-2"/></p>
               <p>Deceitful attitude.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38-3"/> Assuming an attitude
                  is deception by concealing evil inward qualities and by showing outward virtues,
                  as is done by those who make hard their callosity, taking the appearance of having
                  become thus by frequent kneeling. They bind their hips with a rope, make their
                  voices mournful, their tongues silent, while they plan evil in their heart. They
                  procure themselves many flatterers, who draw the simple towards them in order to
                  acquire their blessing and their soothsayings.</p>
               <p>Its motive is to acquire honour or wealth. It is healed by hate of praise, by the
                  solitary's rejoicing at detraction and by his despairing of the profits of men.
                  For <persName>Aba Daniel</persName> says: I looked through the door of
                     <persName>Aba Poman</persName>'s cell and saw him <pb type="external" n="557"/>
                  sitting on the earth. When he perceived me, he hurried to sit down on his
                  mat.—Sometimes the excellent reveal their labours, but only if they know, that
                  their hearers will imitate them. As <persName>Aba Macarius</persName> said to
                     <persName>Aba Euagrius</persName>: for twenty years I have not known satiety of
                  bread, water and sleep.</p>
               <p>Haughtiness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38-4"/> is a psychic state, in which
                  man considers himself as being elevated above others. Pharao<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n38-3"/> elevated himself above God, saying: <placeName>The
                     Nile</placeName> is mine, I have made it. The persecutors [of
                     <placeName>Israel</placeName>] elevated themselves above his servants. People,
                  blind of mind, elevate themselves above <pb n="39"/>their fellows, thinking their
                  own <choice><sic>exellence</sic><corr>excellence</corr></choice> to be the deficiency of others.</p>
               <p>The causes of haughtiness are boast, rancour and envy; for these do not permit a
                  man to humble himself before his fellow, nor to be his equal in rank.</p>
               <p>Its signs are:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n39-1"/> love of finery and driving,
                  of being saluted in the streets, of sitting in a high place at meals; dislike of
                  going alone, of visiting a more excellent man; entertaining an aversion to lepers,
                  dropsical and ulcerous people; not to do a thing with one's own hands; not to
                  carry one's things, but to have them carried.</p>
               <p>Its healing has been mentioned in the section on humbleness.</p>
               <p>Boast<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n39-2"/> is man's self-exaltation on account
                  of a good that he possesses, be it knowledge, good works, beauty, wealth,
                  strength, affinity, righteousness, the pretended true confession. Haughtiness is
                  distinguished from boast thereby, that the former is<pb type="external" n="558"/>
                  caused by man's comparing himself with others, the latter not. The relation
                  between boast and haughtiness is like that between boy and man.</p>
               <p>The inclination to boast is healed by knowing that whatever accomplishment a man
                  may possess it comes from the Lord and not from himself. Therefore he shall not
                  boast and, if so, he shall boast in the Lord.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n39-3"/> When <persName>Aba Poman</persName> heard a brother saying:
                  since how many years have I not entered the village, he said to him: if I had
                  dwelled in its neighbourhood, I would have entered and circumambulated it during
                  the night, in order to prevent my deliberations to boast: I do not enter it.</p>
               <p>Reprehension.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n39-4"/> Directing others is the work
                  of the shepherds, not of the solitaries who have only to be charged with the care
                  of themselves. For <persName>Aba Poman</persName> said: when I see a brother
                  sinning, I do not vituperate him. And when <pb n="40"/>my Lord vituperates me, I
                  say to him: thou hast taught me: first cast out the beam out of thine eye, then
                  shalt thou see clearly to cast out the mote out of thy brother's eye.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n40-1"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
               <head>Section the Tenth</head>
               <head>On good Qualities</head>
               <p>Those ornaments by which the rational soul is made worthy of the spiritual
                  festival on which dawn rises and the Beautiful<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n40-2"/> spreads his rays, are the following as we have enumerated
                  them above: Teachings.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n40-3"/> There is nothing so
                  sufficient to banish bad customs from the soul, as burning with love of
                     teachings.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n40-4"/> He who is instructed shall
                  begin with the Psalms, then he shall train himself in the books of initiated
                  knowledge, the <pb type="external" n="559"/>aim of which we have described here
                  briefly. These will teach him to limit the care for the maintenance of his body,
                  and to subdue it by strict exercises; to eradicate from the roots of his soul
                  defiling stains and to supplant them by adorning customs.</p>
               <p>If he wants a teacher, he shall be a good one.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n40-5"/> His signs are: that he is not subject to desires;<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n40-6"/> that he does not visit governors[#n]; that
                  he is not quick to answer; that he teaches more by actions than by words;<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n40-7"/> that he teaches first what should not be
                  done; then what should be done.</p>
               <pb n="41"/>
               <p>Faith<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41-1"/> is, according to
                     <persName>Paul</persName> the blessed, conviction concerning things hoped for,
                  as if they existed really and the evidence of things not seen.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n41-2"/> It is clear that this definition applies to
                  all faith. If we intend to define our faith peculiarly, we say: Faith is the
                  concordance of the mind with the teachings of the Gospel, which is accomplished by
                  oral confession and the observance of the commandments. Because all Christians of
                  this our time concord with the orthodox faith as it has been established in the
                  Nicene confession, the solitary has to stick to it and to abstain from the
                  quarrels concerning the natures and the hypostases. The true solitaries speak
                  about behaviour only, without ever scrutinizing faith.</p>
               <p>Thanksgivings<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41-3"/> are thanks for grace shown
                  or expected.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41-4"/> Their cause consists therein
                  that man recognizes its quantity and quality, in order to thank its giver
                  accordingly.</p>
               <p>Grace is either essential or secondary. Essential grace is<pb type="external"
                     n="560"/> either sought for its own sake, as the indestructible enjoyment in
                  the spiritual world; or for the sake of some other thing, as true knowledge and
                  excellent practice which are sought for the sake of indestructible enjoyment.</p>
               <p>In the same way secondary grace is either sought for its own sake, as life,
                  strength, health and beauty; or for the sake of some other thing, as honour,
                  wealth, kindred, servants which are sought for the practice of life.</p>
               <p>As the knowledge of grace is the cause of thanksgivings, so ignorance of grace is
                  the cause of lack of thanksgivings,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41-5"/> just
                  as many people who do not perceive the good air, do not give thanks on account of
                  it. If it is withdrawn from them <pb n="42"/>they are suffocated;<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-1"/> when it returns to them they recognize the
                  gift of grace and give thanks on account of it.</p>
               <p>The excellent<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-2"/> thank God, even in trouble,
                  because they know that every trouble could have been a different, a greater one.
                  So they thank God because he has not exposed them to a greater trouble. They thank
                  God further, because by temporary trouble they are saved from eternal trouble.</p>
               <p>Hope<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-3"/> is the longing of the soul after
                  acquiring the possession of what it loves. And because the divine Beloved<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-4"/> is never-ceasing joy, we have first to
                  prepare its conditions which are: being content with little,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n42-5"/> ascetical subduing of the body, purification of the heart,
                  adornment of the soul; then we may expect it. Hope is strengthened by man's
                  deliberating and thinking: if God has bestowed endless acts of grace upon the <pb
                     type="external" n="561"/>maintenance of the body, which becomes worn out and is
                  to be destroyed, how should He withdraw His acts of grace from the soul which is
                  excellent? Fear of God<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-6"/> is the sorrow of
                  the heart on account of the consciousness of the trouble to come.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-7"/> Its cause is the knowledge of faults. Its
                  signs are, corporeal: a pale face and emaciation; or psychical: hate of sin, as
                  trouble is either corporeal or psychic. Fear of the former is rejected by the
                     Initiated<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-8"/> who say: we have not received
                  a spirit of fear,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-9"/> and <pb n="43"
                  />therefore we are not to be afraid even if heaven should cover the earth. But
                  fear of the latter trouble is praised by them; they say: he who does not fear God,
                  often fears his own shadow. If fear gets strong it even withholds man from many
                  actions which are not worthy of blame.</p>
               <p>Poverty<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-1"/> with patience is honoured by the
                  Initiated above opulence with compassion. They say: the rank of the solitaries is
                  higher than that of almsgivers. Lay people judge contrarily. The poor man who is
                  worthy of the beatification of the Gospel bears his poverty without grudging.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-2"/> He is magnanimous, not a flatterer.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-3"/> If he gets his want without asking, he will
                  not ask;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-4"/> if it is more than he wants, he
                  will give the indigent of it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-5"/> He does not
                  accept from evildoers and boasters.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-3"/> And on
                  seeing one more indigent than himself, he lets him accept. If he is able to work,
                  he does not accept.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-6"/></p>
               <p>If anyone gives alms<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-7"/> he shall bestow them
                  before being<pb type="external" n="562"/> asked. As far as is possible for him, he
                  shall conceal his aim,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-8"/> by putting it into
                  the hands of a blind man, or by throwing it in the way of the poor, or by binding
                  it in his garment. He shall take it from [what he has earned by] honest work. He
                  shall give it to those who have no strength to go out and ask.</p>
               <p>Asking<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-9"/> is sin, because he who asks does
                  not trust in God but in man; usually he is a cause of harm to other people.</p>
               <p>Confidence<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-10"/> is trusting the Creator's
                  government with the provision for human wants. Man's confidence in his Lord <pb
                     n="44"/> either resembles a youth's confidence in his tutor, as when the heir,
                  being still a boy, is under tutorship until the time fixed by his father; or a
                  boy's confidence in his mother, as in the case of him who has said: Thou art my
                  confidence from the womb, and my hope from my mother's breasts;<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n44-1"/> or the cattle's confidence in their master,
                  as in the case of him who has said: foolish was I and ignorant: I was a beast
                  before Thee.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44-2"/></p>
               <p>The first sort of confidence is weak; for the youth knows that when he shall grow
                  up, he shall no longer confide in his tutor. The second is stronger than the
                  first; for the boy does not know that he shall no longer confide in his mother
                  when growing up. The third is stronger than the second; for there comes no time
                  that cattle confide in themselves and not in their lord.</p>
               <p>The just confide in the Lord not under circumstances which necessarily will harm,
                  but under circumstances which possibly may do harm, being things which sometimes
                  are noxious, sometimes not; therefore God has commanded: make <pb type="external"
                     n="563"/>battlements for thy roof.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44-3"/> The
                  elect alone, however, confide in God their saviour under the former circumstances,
                  as <persName>Daniel</persName> in the lions' pit and <persName>Hananya</persName>
                  with his companions in the blazing furnace.</p>
               <p>Purity of deliberations.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44-4"/> Every
                  deliberation the object of which is not familiarity<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n44-5"/> with God and divine things, is not pure but troubled. To such
                  a degree that if he, whose deliberation is pure, deliberates on the purity of his
                  deliberation, it does not remain pure. So desire of the pleasures of
                     <placeName>Eden</placeName> rises from troubled deliberations.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n44-6"/>
                  <persName>Aba Poman</persName> has said: as flies do not come near to a boiling
                  kettle, so impure deliberations<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44-7"/> do not
                  come near to the heart that is fervent with <pb n="45"/>the love of God. The same
                  has said: Does the axe chop without one who chops with it? Do not minister unto
                  deliberations, then they will vanish. Further he has said: if you throw evil
                  deliberations, as if they were a snake or scorpion, into the vessel of the heart
                  and then shut it, they will die immediately. To <persName>Aba Arsenius</persName>
                  a certain brother said: why do you, who are wise, ask this villager, namely
                     <persName>Aba Macarius</persName>, concerning deliberations? He answered: I
                  know the lore of Greeks and Romans, but the alphabet of this villager I have not
                  yet learnt.</p>
               <p>Remembrance of death.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n45-1"/> No one who is
                  acquainted with the remembrance of death, will easily sin.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n45-2"/> A certain Father has said: when I let down the spindle, I put
                  my death before my eyes before pulling it up.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n45-3"/> The cause on account of which a man does not bethink him of
                  his death, is the love of temporary life; for he who loves a thing, whatever it
                  be, hates its opposite and does not like to meditate upon it.<pb type="external"
                     n="564"/> This sickness is healed thereby that a man bethinks him of the fact,
                  that man in this world resembles a dream and the flight of a bird, whose way
                  leaves no trace in the air; and a ship which makes no furrow in the water; and the
                  morning dew which vanishes and is exsiccated before the noon; and the flower
                  which, scarcely open, withers. So the love of temporary life decays, but death
                  does not vanish from the memory and so sin is rejected.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <pb n="46"/>
         <div type="chapter" n="3">
            <head>Chapter the Third</head>
            <head>On the Spiritual Rest of the Perfect</head>
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>Section the First</head>
               <head>On the Beginnings of the Inclinations<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46-1"/>
                  of Perfection</head>
               <p>When, by the hard labours of asceticism, the body has been cleansed and the mind
                     purified,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46-2"/> the windows of the senses
                  have been shut and the room, the heart, is enlightened,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n46-3"/> then the dove will show herself to the mind, not lastingly
                  however, but as a flash of lightning<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46-4"/> which
                  appears and vanishes, she shows her beauty, making sweet her fruit to the palate.
                  So [the mind] is stupefied by her appearance and captivated by desire of her, and
                  everything, even itself becomes to it as if not existing.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n46-5"/> And the soul, on account of the burning fire of love towards
                  her, thinks to perish. When it has reached this stage, great humbleness is sown in
                  it. Here the solitary estimates himself to be dust and ashes and he sheds tears of
                  joy and pain: of joy, because of the gift; of pain, from fear. Therefore he will
                  be zealous in frequent <pb type="external" n="565"/>reciting of Psalms and in
                  kneelings. During his long service, great delight will happen to him and the
                  recollection of the saints <pb n="47"/>will occur to him and he will be anxious to
                  imitate them. He will bestow care on comforting the troubled and nursing the ill.
                  Because these offices fall to his lot on account of his intercourse with the dove,
                  he will afterwards return unto solitude and silence. If he is questioned without
                  necessity, he will not answer. The speech of mortals he will hate like intercourse
                  with enemies.</p>
               <p>While he is practising these things, the youthful dove, which is older than
                  generations and families, will again visit him. And if he does not give himself
                  wholly to her, she will scold him severely.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-1"
                  /> Then, according to his warmth or coldness, she will remain with him or withdraw
                  from him. For also youths who are in love with worldly girls, know a token
                  resembling this fact, which is poetically described thus: if the beloved perceives
                  true love, this is the token: she comes on her head, not on her feet.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-2"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>Section the Second</head>
               <head>On the Progress of the Inclinations<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-3"/> of
                     Perfection<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-4"/></head>
               <p>After the inclinations of the initial actions of perfection, the dove changes her
                  workings on the mind and makes it apt to behold what every contemplative soul
                  beholds and to the receiving of revelations.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-5"
                  /> So she begins with illuminating<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-6"/> the
                  intellect by the distinction of the created things, in this way, that, as sensual
                     things<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-7"/> become visible to the bodily eye
                  by the medium of the visible sun, so intellectual things <pb n="48"/>are discerned
                  by the psychic eye by the medium of the <pb type="external" n="566"/>spiritual<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-1"/> dove. Then, the mind abhors the environing
                  things and turns its face away from all that is in heaven and on the earth.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-2"/> It burns with love of the dove and desires
                  to become familiar<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-3"/> with her alone. And
                  she, perceiving its burning love and its being tried like gold in fire,<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-4"/> will no longer appear unto it as lightning,
                  vanishing quickly, but as a star, [a star], however, hidden in a cloud; especially
                  at the time of prayer, which vision cuts off, enflaming the soul and stupefying
                  the mind, so that the solitary falls on the ground as dead. Then he will rise
                  again and prepare himself for vision and little by little the cloud will be
                  removed and the eye become enlightened. At this stage the perfect, when awake,
                  becomes as if he were sleeping; when sleeping, he is reckoned as being awake.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-5"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>Section the Third</head>
               <head>On the conclusive Inclinations of Perfection<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n48-6"/></head>
               <p>When, by the things mentioned, the soul has become cultivated and accustomed, the
                  mind acquires perfect freedom of speech<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-7"/>
                  with the dove and placidly gazes at her and has intercourse with her. And she does
                  no longer appear momentarily like lightning,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-8"
                  /> nor dimly, in a cloud, but as abiding in her nest, the heart. And as what she
                  is, namely life, the cause of all causes,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-9"/>
                  she shows her self to the mind and wonderful mysteries she speaks in it. Then the
                  mind acquires also knowledge of the word (which was in the beginning, and all <pb
                     n="49"/>has come into existence by it), namely of essential wisdom and of all
                  the angels of God, who are ministering spirits, that<pb type="external" n="567"/>
                  prostrate themselves before Him and praise Him. And while the mind is established
                  in the sight of them, their magnificence and their joy, it becomes like them. And
                  when the dove spreads her wings together with the angels and the souls of the just
                  administering her, the mind accompanies them in their flight<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n49-1"/> and in a moment it reaches with them the cloud<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n49-2"/> of inaccessible light, enters it, is hidden
                  in it and dignified with the state of <persName>Moses</persName>, being made
                     radiant<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49-3"/> in stupefaction, by the beauty
                  of the Lord, the Lord of the Universe.</p>
               <p>On account of the delight it possesses, it cannot return to its former place, save
                  only if its Lord loosens it from its union with Him.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n49-4"/> And when it returns it baptizes the members of the body with
                  the fire of the Divinity, which has remained in it. When it desires to ascend
                  again, the body is near to be dragged along with it, so that it can scarcely be
                  shaken off like a shoe.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49-5"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
               <head>Section the Fourth</head>
               <head>On the Unification of the Mind</head>
               <p>When<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49-6"/> the mind becomes united<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n49-7"/> with the Good one it <pb n="50"/>ascends
                  from glory to glory by the Lord the Spirit, forgetting not only the things of the
                  world, but also its self,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50-1"/> and in the
                  light, with which it is clad in that apartment, it sees itself in the likeness of
                     God.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50-2"/> And on account of the full cups it
                  drinks in that room, it looses its senses and in this drunkenness<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n50-3"/> it says: I and my Father are one, and my
                  Father is in me and I am in him, with other things which the Dove warns to
                     conceal,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50-4"/> saying concerning them: there
                  is a mystery <pb type="external" n="568"/>between me and my housemates.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n50-5"/> When <persName>the blessed
                     apostle</persName> became acquainted with these mysteries, he said that he had
                  heard unspeakable words which it is not lawful for a man to utter.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n50-6"/> And his disciple
                     <persName>Hierotheos</persName> has transmitted to his disciple
                     <persName>Dionysios</persName>: When the mind becomes united with the Good one,
                  it drops the name of love and affection, for here the lover and the friend become
                  the same person as the Beloved and the Comrade. So it is with all terms denoting
                  dualism, as fathership and sonship, praiser and praised, for at this stage the
                  mind is not praising nor being praised.</p>
               <p>The unification of the mind has been proved by the same Initiated with examples
                  from the material world: As water is collected in a number of vessels and the
                  sunrays in a number of windows and fire in different fuel in which it is enclosed,
                  and the air in a number of pouches in which it is retained—and when these
                  containing things are taken away their contents again become the one substance of
                  water, sunrays and so on— <pb n="51"/>so the minds, when the bodies are taken
                  away, all of them become one. And as the body has its origin in the elements and
                  returns to them, so the mind, which has its origin in the divine being, returns to
                  it, that God may be all in all,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-1"/> as our
                  teacher and our leader on the way has taught us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
               <head>Section the Fifth</head>
               <head>On the Causes of Love<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-2"/></head>
               <p>The causes of all love are five:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-3"/> the
                  maintenance of the<pb type="external" n="569"/> person; practising a good thing;
                  outward beauty; inward beauty;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-4"/> a hidden
                  likeness. That in view of all these, the Love of God is justified,<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-5"/> appears from the following. If man
                  naturally loves the maintenance of his person,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n51-6"/> he necessarily loves Him who maintains him, namely God in
                  whom we live and move and have our being.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-7"/>
                  And if man<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-6"/> loves his benefactor without
                  expecting remuneration, how much more must he love God the adorable who provides
                  him with innumerable good things, I mean the rise of the sun, the moon and the
                  stars, the variety of air, the water of clouds, rivers and fountains, the fruits
                  of the field, the animals and cattle and other things without end. And if outward
                     beauty<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-8"/> is loved, how should not He<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-9"/> be loved who shows himself to the pure in
                  heart in a habit shining like snow, with hair like pure wool, sitting on a flaming
                  throne with radiating wheels, a carriage with four sides? In truth, every one who
                  is deemed worthy to behold him, will reject the love of every creature, and his
                  desire will be unto Him alone.</p>
               <pb n="52"/>
               <p>And if inward beauty,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n52-1"/> which is caused by
                  the knowledge of hidden mysteries and by alienation from sinful passions and by
                  communion with the works of righteousness, is worthy of love, who should not love
                  Him who sanctifies the saints, who purifies the defiled, compared with whose
                  knowledge the <pb type="external" n="570"/>knowledge of all creatures is
                  ignorance? And if a hidden likeness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n52-2"/> is a
                  cause of love, then that man would be a wretch who did not love his Lord who has
                  made him in His image and after His likeness.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
               <head>Section the Sixth</head>
               <head>On the Delight of Knowledge<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n52-3"/></head>
               <p>As peculiar delight happens to man in concordance with the powers which make him
                  attain sensual things—namely touch, taste, sight, hearing and smell—so in
                  concordance with the mind which makes him attain intellectual things, peculiar
                  delight happens to him. And because in all intellectual things there is nothing
                  more wonderful, amazing, stupefying and perfect than the Lord and God of beings,
                  the delight caused by knowledge of Him surpasses all other delight.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n52-4"/> And he who has not tasted it, will not
                  desire it, as the deaf, who has never heard the sound of the cither, will not long
                  after hearing it. In the same way many persons will not suffer from the annoyance
                  of their not knowing God, though this ignorance causes more suffering than any
                  painful sorrow, just as a torpid member is not affected by fire or cold. <pb
                     n="53"/> Therefore no man whose mind has been captivated by the desire of his
                  Lord, can further be captivated by the desire of anything in the world. And nobody
                  who has found God, will not wholly forget the world.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n53-1"/> When the mind has been salted by the love of God, it will not
                  be troubled any more. He who serves the service of the Lord, will quickly put off
                  the habit of servants.</p>
               <p>This delight will eminently happen to the mind when it has separated itself wholly
                  from matter. As the blessed <persName>Paul</persName>, the apostle, says: for we
                  now see through a glass, darkly,<pb type="external" n="571"/> but then face to
                     face.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n53-2"/> And the holy
                     <persName>Gregorius</persName> says: every good, God loving soul will enjoy a
                  wonderful delight and exult when it is separated from the body, because what
                  caused darkness has been purified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
               <head>Section the Seventh</head>
               <head>On the Augmentation of the Love<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n53-3"/> of
                     God<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n53-4"/></head>
               <p>The love of God is augmented in the soul, when man proceeds in faith, hope and
                  love and is strengthened in his state of abstention; when he meditates upon the
                  wonderful works of the Creator; when his mind beholds the divine power that
                  penetrates the universe; when, without impediment, it pervades all the ends of the
                     earth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n53-5"/> and farther, above all heavens
                  and seas and oceans and all that is in them,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n53-6"
                  /> without attaching itself to them, without abiding in the darkness<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n53-7"/> of matter, on the contrary, hating every
                  desire, seeking and desiring the <pb n="54"/>Good one alone, purifying its inner
                  heart from all beside Him, in order to behold, albeit dimly, something of the rays
                  of the Essence. And by this glance, short like lightning,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n54-1"/> the small spark of love will become a mighty flame, making
                  the soul blaze.</p>
               <p>The friend of God thirsts to behold Him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54-2"/>
                  longing after [the time] when he shall come and see His face.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n54-3"/> And neither death, nor life, nor things
                  present, nor things to come, nor <pb type="external" n="572"/>any other creature
                  shall be able to separate him from the love of his Lord.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n54-4"/> He fulfills His will and his lips administer His name
                  perpetually. He consoles himself by solitude and by sitting in the narrow cell and
                  enjoys the labours of asceticism. He is meek towards the good and the evil. He
                  prays constantly that his love may not abate; he conceals his love as much as
                  possible and he loves nothing but Him. It is said<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n54-5"/> that the Egyptian woman, who loved
                     <persName>Joseph</persName>, when her husband had died, believed in God. And
                  when <persName>Joseph</persName> desired to marry her, she did not consent, for
                  she said: before I knew his Lord, I loved him; but now that I know his Lord, I
                  love Him and not His servant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
               <head>Section the Eighth</head>
               <head>On the Knowledge of God<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54-6"/></head>
               <p>That the knowing knows the Creator from the creatures, is the trodden way that has
                  been levelled by many with labours. The elect, however, who have been chosen by
                  God before to be the vocated and the saints, know the creatures from <pb n="55"
                  />the Creator.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-1"/> As one of them has said: By
                  the knowledge of my God I know my self and the world.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n55-2"/>
                  <persName>The divine Psalmist</persName> describes the former knowledge by: the
                  heavens declare the glory of God;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-3"/> the
                  latter he symbolically indicates with: in Thy light we see light.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-4"/></p>
               <p>The exoteric sages exalt the latter kind above the former. And because the
                  knowledge of God is the cause of loving Him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-5"
                  /> and some people know Him not as He is, consequently their love has no
                  foundation. Other people, however, confess Him as He is, but only in the way of
                  tradition and audience.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-6"/><pb type="external"
                     n="573"/> Their love, though it has a foundation, is built as upon sand, and
                  shaken by small trouble.</p>
               <p>The Initiated know His divinity by essential knowledge and the foundation of their
                  love is placed as upon a rock; neither trouble, nor persecutions, nor sword, nor
                  fire can overpower it.</p>
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-7"/> though all beings in heaven and earth
                  bear the sign of their maker,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-8"/> and there is
                  no speech nor language where their voice is not heard,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n55-9"/> many do not know Him; not on account of His being hidden, but
                  on account of His being so manifest, the mind becomes dull in His light which is
                  not to be perceived by the senses.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-10"/> For
                  the relation between the <pb n="56"/>human mind and essential light is the same as
                  that between the bat and the light of the sun. Therefore, as the bat, if it
                  possessed the visual strength of man, would be able to see in the sunlight, so the
                  human mind, if it possessed the mental strength of the angels, would be able to
                  see in the essential light.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n56-1"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
               <head>Section the Ninth</head>
               <head>On the varying States the Perfect have to go through<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n56-2"/></head>
               <p>From their first reaching the state of perfection until the loosening of their
                  tie, the Perfect have usually to go through twelve varying states.</p>
               <p>The first is that of the mind's being baptized in the heart. Here deliberation is
                  standing motionless; even the tongue does not murmur praise and man is not able to
                  bear even <pb type="external" n="574"/>the sound of a leaf, but silence dominates
                  the inclinations<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n56-3"/> of soul and body. The
                  second is that of distinction, the mind recognizing the height of its rank and its
                  being the offspring of God. Here too it guards solitude and silence. And if
                  distraction overwhelms it, it is concentrated by reciting the Scriptures and by
                  obeisances. The third is that of love of reciting Psalms, so, that the Perfect is
                  changed with the murmuring of every sentence. And while the words of the Psalms
                  are retained in the memory so as to become the propriety of the reciter,<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n56-4"/> even when silent it is as if <persName>the
                     divine Psalmist</persName>
                  <pb n="57"/>speaks to his ears, whilst he hears him playing on the cither.
                  Thereupon the words are retracted from the ear, but the thoughts remain behind in
                  the intellect.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n57-1"/> The fourth is that of
                  outbursts of tears, without compulsion and involuntarily. But the fire of love
                  warms the heart and makes tears flow from the eyes. The fifth is that of the
                  knowledge of Judgment. And here the love of mankind is born in the soul, which has
                  the same regards for all. Here is neither righteous nor sinner, neither slave nor
                  free man, neither circumcision nor foreskin, neither man nor woman, but it asks
                  mercy for all and concerning all. The sixth is that of the mind's becoming
                     radiant<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n57-2"/> with the rays of the angels,
                  rays composed of light and fire. The mind burns with desire to be united with
                  their hosts and to be mingled with their orders.</p>
               <p>The seventh is that of hearing the sanctifications of the Seraphs, which can not
                  be embodied in spoken<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n57-3"/> words, but are
                  defined in intellectual sounds. The eighth is that of likeness, while the mind is
                  illuminated by the light without<pb type="external" n="575"/> quality<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n57-4"/> and is changed into its likeness, as the
                  elegant and dense cloud near the sun is transformed into the likeness of the sun.
                  The ninth, that of becoming like fire, while the whole body is plunged into fire.
                  In this likeness <persName>Aba Arsenius</persName> was seen, while he stood
                  [praying in] his cell. The tenth, that of unification,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n57-5"/> is called undescribable by the Initiated, all numbers vanish
                  in it. Here no human weakness remains, nor prayer, nor beseeching; no remembrance
                  of what is on the earth nor of future things, because the mind has become here as
                  receiving all prayers, no longer praying itself; as granting questions, no longer
                  asking itself. The eleventh is that of joy without being conscious of its motive.
                  The mind only knows that it rejoices here, not why it rejoices. The twelfth <pb
                     n="58"/>is that of outbursts of speech, of explaining hidden things, of
                  searching the things to come which are written in the archbook which is the book
                  of the knowledge of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
               <head>Section the Tenth</head>
               <head>On the Fall of the Perfect</head>
               <p>Though the body is sanctified, the heart purified and the mind made bright in the
                  rank of perfection, still, if the perfect is not cautious against the snares laid
                  by the Evil one, he will quickly fall from that height of elevation, as also
                     <persName>Beliar</persName> has fallen. He is however drawn away from evil<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n58-1"/> deliberations, <pb type="external" n="576"
                  />as soon as he, beatified by wonderful revelations,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n58-2"/> rejoices at himself and desires to reveal those gifts which
                  no eye has seen, which no ear has heard<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n58-3"/>
                  and of which he has been deemed worthy. So<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n58-4"/>
                  he is zealous to go to towns and villages as a teacher and a redeemer of souls, as
                  an edification and an example to be imitated by many. And he imagines demons which
                  howl and complain of him, saying: What have we to do with you, servant of God,
                  that you are come hither to torment us<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n58-5"/>?
                  And further his imagination sees people being healed and a crowd pressing near to
                  touch his garments. And he places at his door those who seek him, and if he is not
                  willing to go with them, drag him along with ropes.</p>
               <p>If he is allured thus, he is on the way to return to the world. Then, if he sees
                  one of his colleagues, whose speeches are in better favour than his and whose
                  teaching is more beloved, he envies him and begins to hate him, as for instance
                     <persName>Heron of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName></persName>, the punctual
                  in behaviour, who used to take <pb n="59"/>food once every three days. When he was
                  captivated by self-exaltation, his intellect was blinded and he began to disdain
                     <persName>Aba Euagrius</persName>, saying: Those who follow your teaching, err;
                  for they want no teacher besides <persName>Christ</persName>. For He has said:
                  Call no man your master on the earth.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n59-1"/></p>
               <p>And when <persName>Satan</persName> incited him to go to
                     <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> and he had come there, he immersed himself in
                  the mud of fornication so that his genitals became rotten and had to be resecated.
                  And when he was healed, being without those members, he<pb type="external" n="557"
                  /> returned anew unto steadiness of mind.</p>
               <p>Therefore, even if a man reaches perfection, he has constantly to beseech his
                  Lord: Cast me not away from Thy presence; and take not Thy holy spirit from
                     me.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n59-2"/></p>
               <pb n="60"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter" n="4">
            <head>Chapter IV</head>
            <head>A Tale of the Author’s Progress in Teachings and some Sentences Communicated to
               Him in Revelations</head>
            <p>From my first youth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n60-1"/> burning with love of
               teachings, I was taught the holy scriptures with the necessary explanation, and from
               an exquisite teacher I heard the mysteries contained in the writings of the holy
               doctors. When I had reached the age of twenty, the then living patriarch compelled me
               to receive the dignity of a bishop. Then it was inevitable for me to engage myself in
               disquisitions and disputations with the heads of other confessions, interior and
               exterior. And when I had given my thoughts and meditations to this business during
               some time, I became convinced, that these quarrels of Christians among themselves are
               not a matter of facts but of words and denominations. For all of them confess
                  <persName>Christ</persName>, <persName>our Lord</persName>, to be wholly God and
               wholly man, without mixture, nivellation <pb type="external" n="578"/>or mutation of
               natures. This bilateral likeness is called by some nature, by others person, by
               others hypostasis. So I saw all Christian peoples, notwithstanding these differences,
               possessing one unvarying equality.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n60-2"/> And I
               wholly eradicated the root of hatred from the depth of my heart and I absolutely
               forsook disputation with anyone concerning confession. So I zealously turned to
               attain the power of Greek wisdom, viz. <pb n="61"/>logic, physics and metaphysics,
               algebra and geometry, science of the spheres and of the stars. And because life is
               short and teachings long and broad, I read concerning every branch of science what
               was the most necessary.</p>
            <p>During my studies in these teachings, I resembled a man who is immersed in the ocean
               and stretches forth his hands towards all sides in order to be saved. And because in
               all teachings, interior and exterior, I found not that which I sought, I almost fell
               into complete destruction.</p>
            <p>I feel not justified to describe the snares and nets in which I was entangled,
               because hearing this might do harm unto many feeble ones. In short, if the Lord had
               not sustained my little faith in those dangerous times, and if He had not led me to
               look in the writings of the Initiated, as <persName>Aba Euagrius</persName> and
               others, occidental and oriental, and if He had not picked me up from the gulf of
               destruction and ruin, I would ere long have despaired of psychical, if not of bodily
               life.</p>
            <p>I meditated on these works for seven years, during which<pb type="external" n="579"/>
               I hated other sorts of knowledge, though I had to occupy my thoughts superficially
               with some of them, not for my own sake, but for the sake of others who wished to
               profit by me. During this space of time, many offences made me miserable and caused
               me to stumble. Sometimes I fell into unbelief, saying: How loud is the sound of the
               bells of these solitaries, and how is their mill devoid of meal, viz. their words
               contain simple thoughts, remaining without effect. But sometimes my mind reprehended
               me, saying: Do not speak idle words and think not that all what you know not, does
               not exist. For what you know is much less than what you know not.</p>
            <p>During this dubitation I halted between two opinions,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n61-1"/> till some of the rays of the light without quality,<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n61-2"/> in the way of lightning<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n61-3"/> which does not remain, enlightened me, and <pb n="62"/>some of
               the scales which covered my eyes, fell off and they were opened, so that I saw,
               although partly. But without a break I pray, that I may see more, while I hope, that
               the screen which impedes my sight, may be destroyed wholly, that, no longer as in
               darkness, but eye to eye I may behold the unseen Beloved.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n62-1"/></p>
            <p>The following few sentences, which I arrange here, are a part of what the flash of
               lightning revealed unto me in the nightly darkness.</p>
            <p>1. The pure soul<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62-2"/> inquires into knowledge, not
               for the sake <pb type="external" n="580"/>of glory which the knowing acquire in the
               world, but that its longing after the face of the Lord<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n63-3"/> of the universe may be augmented, and that it may be able to
               enter and to be hidden within the divine cloud.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62-4"
               /></p>
            <p>2. Those, who penetrate into exoteric and esoteric teachings,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n62-5"/> without caring for the purification<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n62-6"/> of the heart,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62-7"/> and think
               to have reached the rank of perfection—err. For what is the profit of the wonderful
               structure of a mirror,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62-8"/> which is encompassed
               with pearls and jewels, if it is not cleansed from dirt? But the mirror which is
               cleansed, will perform its service well, even if it is of a simple structure.</p>
            <p>3. He who knows by hearsay<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62-9"/> the quality of the
               structure of the Solomonic temple, how could he be compared with him, <choice><sic>thas</sic><corr>that</corr></choice>
               has entered it himself, and has beheld it with his own eye, and has counted its
               winding stairs, its barred windows and its windows of narrow lights, its narrowed
               rests, its chambers in the walls, its carved work, its nets of checker <pb n="63"
               />work, the wings of its Cherubs, the covering of its porches?<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n63-1"/> 4. Many teachers and Fathers have occupied themselves with
               gathering riches and other desirable things, saying: We provide the cattle with
               straw, i. e., the body, which is the animal ridden by the soul,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n63-2"/> with food.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n63-3"/> These things
               cause no damage to people like them, as those who have a sound constitution are not
               harmed by food which is obnoxious to patients, especially those whose fever has
               become hectic and whose [pathological] diagnostics are caused by badness of
               constitution and who, moreover, are not aware of their suffering.</p>
            <p>5. He who thinks that the various colours of the rainbow<pb type="external" n="581"/>
               are the various rays of the sun, errs. They are only caused by the various parts of
               the cloud: density and rarefaction, compactness and transparency.</p>
            <p>6. He who thinks that the sun rises over the lightless things and illuminates them,
               in order to be glorified, praised and elevated, his opinion is false. For the
               illuminated acquires glory, praise and elevation by the illuminating, not the
               illuminating by the illuminated. 7. As hunger is not satisfied by water, nor thirst
               by bread, so the Initiated, who wishes to look within the Sinaitic cloud, gains small
               profit by hearing the Scriptures being read.</p>
            <p>8. The relation between God's knowledge and ours is the same as that between His
               strength and ours.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n63-4"/> 9. God is the
               all-governing, how could He be comprehended by the mind? For the included comprehends
               only a part of the including, not the whole. 10. As long as you think to know God
               from information, <pb n="64"/>signs and testimonies, you are forging cold iron<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-1"/> and as yet even no faith like a grain of
               mustard is in you. 11. Beholding God takes place by shutting the senses, by opening
               the windows of the heart and by withdrawing the veil from the inward eyes. This is
               what has been said: shut the windows, that the room may be lighted.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-2"/></p>
            <p>12. Those who enter the cloud<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-3"/> attain the
               depth and the abundance of God's wisdom, without the intermediary of complicated
               deliberations.</p>
            <pb type="external" n="582"/>
            <p>13. As the mind necessarily attains elementary knowledge here—that the whole is
               greater than a part, and that one is the half of two—so, when having penetrated into
               the divine cloud, with the same necessity it will know the hidden and
               incomprehensible judgments of the divinity.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-4"/>
               14. As the senses are not able to attain immaterial images, so the mind, as long as
               it has not yet loosened the shoes of the body from its feet<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n64-5"/> is not able to attain the images hidden in the cloud, but only
               dimly and pervertedly. 15. The mind in the cloud has unspeakable delight in beholding
               the Beautiful one. This happens also out of the cloud, but only as to one who hears
               the [description of the] beauty of the Beautiful one, not as to one who beholds
                  it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-6"/></p>
            <p>16. When the eyes of the mind are opened, according to its aptitude grace is poured
               out on it; it is illuminated<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-7"/> by the glorious
               and angelic rays, it becomes familiar<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-8"/> with
               the <pb n="65"/>members of the kingdom, it is ranged among their conspicuous hosts,
               and it rejoices and glorifies with them and it is alienated from the world and all
               that is in it.</p>
            <p>17. He who reckons himself among the faithful without having looked behind the door
               of the Holy of Holies of the cloud,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65-1"/> lies;
               even if he confesses with his tongue and believes with his heart.</p>
            <p>18. If the blindborn affirms that there exist colours—white, black, green, red—and if
               the deaf believes that the ear rejoices at the sound of concording strings and
               harmonious songs—yet their belief is nearer to unbelief than to belief.<pb
                  type="external" n="583"/></p>
            <p>19. If you possess not, o brother, the faith founded on revelations,<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n65-2"/> do not give sleep to your eyes, nor slumber to
               your eyelids, until you have found the place of the Lord; from there you will receive
               faith and you will be baptized with fire and spirit, not with water.</p>
            <p>20. The faith founded on revelations is found by the prophets and the apostles in the
               way of the day-spring from on high,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65-3"/> without
               labour or searching; by the solitaries however by searching, labour, efforts and
               apprenticeship. So they proceed from shadowy faith towards faith founded on
               revelations.</p>
            <p>21. Be cautious against stamping yourself with the coinage of the members of the
               kingdom, on account of your industrious reciting of the scriptures and steady labour.
               For many have laboured strenuously, but because they have not laboured with
               intelligence, they have not attained the way of truth, nor reached the harbour of
               life.</p>
            <p>22. Not by bodily labours alone, but by strife and struggle of the sound mind<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n65-4"/> perfection is acquired. Vary therefore your
               bodily service with spiritual intelligence, that you may understand that you work
               with your body and your mind. 23. Love is the lover's seeking the beloved. Essential
               seeking <pb n="66"/>is turning the gaze wholly towards the side of the sought. And
               then seeking and finding will become twins, viz. finding will follow seeking
               immediately. He who seeks thus, finds; who asks thus, receives. <pb type="external"
                  n="584"/></p>
            <p>24. As pure iron, no hindrance presenting itself, is attracted by a magnet, but when
               a foreign substance adheres to it, the attraction diminishes, so the pure mind is in
               its entirety attracted by the supreme Essence; but when the passions of the flesh
               adhere to it, the attraction is impeded. 25. As cleansing iron from a foreign
               substance—as gold, silver, brass and lead—is more difficult than delivering it from
               the grip of a hand and other outward impeding influences, which do not cohere with
               its substance, so it is more difficult to purify the mind from brutish customs and
               from animal inclinations, which are cohesive with its nature, than to loosen the ties
               with wife, children, talents and mina's.</p>
            <p>26. When the mind understands that there are words which it is not able to utter, and
               actions the like of which no eye has seen, no ear has heard, neither have they
               entered into the heart of man,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66-1"/> then it
               ascends above the highest rank outside the cloud<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n66-2"/> and it has set its foot upon the lowest stage within it. 27.
               When the mind hears unspeakable words which no mouth is able to explain, and when it
               sees things, the like of which no eye has seen, it rests already in the tabernacle of
               the Lord and it abides on His holy mountain.</p>
            <p>28. One in three and three in one, says the church. Not in such a way that one, in so
               far as it is one, becomes three; nor so, that three, in so far as it is three, is
               one. For this is impossible.</p>
            <p>29. What is three in itself possesses a unique, essential <pb type="external" n="585"
               />idea, which is not liable to be divided into many triads; and in this intelligence
               it is one. And because the unique supreme <pb n="67"/>being possesses essence and
               word and life, it is three. So it is one in nature and three in hypostases.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n67-1"/></p>
            <p>30. The cause of the word and the life of the essence cannot be outside the essence,
               otherwise that which were foreign<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n67-2"/> to the
               essence would have undergone the influence of <choice><sic>an other</sic><corr>another</corr></choice> being. Therefore
               theology calls the cause the Father; and the word and the life, produced by this
               cause, Son and Spirit. 31. Now the word, being hidden in the rational, is revealed as
               it were by being born from a womb. Life however reveals itself in the living as long
               as it lives. Therefore the Son is born but not emanated; the Spirit is emanated, but
               not born. 32. If God, the creator of the universe, acts according to His will, it is
               not impossible for the creatures to investigate Him by the intermediary of any
               [created] body, whatever it be.</p>
            <p>33. If it is not denied that God has revealed Himself unto <persName>Moses</persName>
               in the bush at <placeName>Sinai</placeName>, and that He has handed down to him laws
               and institutions<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n67-3"/> apt for
                  <placeName>Israel</placeName>, how can it be denied, that He has revealed himself
               unto the world in the complete son of man, who has become soul in the rational and
               recognizing initiated soul? 34. He, whose essence is not derived from himself, but
               from his cause, can not be the cause of the essence of <choice><sic>an other</sic><corr>another</corr></choice>, perhaps
               he can be a mediator. So God alone is the cause of all and He worketh all in all.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n67-4"/></p>
            <p>35. As the moon receives its light from the sun. and over the earth rises light
               during the night from the moon, how can the moon, which does not possess light in
               itself, be the<pb type="external" n="586"/> cause of the light of the earth? Indeed,
               it is not the cause, but rather the intermediary between the cause and the
               caused.</p>
            <p>36. As a mirror<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n67-5"/> is in itself devoid of all
               images and <pb n="68"/>reflexes, but, according to its purity and cleanness images of
               things outside it appear in it—so the mind is devoid of images, and according to its
               being purified<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n68-1"/> from the stains of matter,
               immaterial perceptions are reflected in it.</p>
            <p>37. The two kingdoms, that of heaven and that of earth are, compared with the king of
               kings, the god of gods, the lord of lords, as the figures in a mirror compared with
               those without it.</p>
            <p>38. As the reflexes of a mirror have no real essence in themselves, but their essence
               depends upon the essence of the things reflected, so the two kingdoms—that of
               corporeal and that of uncorporeal things—have no true essence in themselves, but
               their essence depends upon the first essence, their cause.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n68-2"/></p>
            <p>39. The real, first essence is not subject to the category of time, so that it could
               be said: It was, nothing being with it. But when this is said, it is said by
               uncultivated minds.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n68-3"/></p>
            <p>40. He who sucks milk like a babe, shall not use the food of the perfect. And he who
               sees in the wise of a bat,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n68-4"/> shall not look in
               the sun. He must leave the foregoing section, he shall not reject nor accept it. Or
               he may preserve it in his heart, till his time be fulfilled.</p>
            <pb type="external" n="587"/>
            <p>41. When the window of your heart is opened, you will fly towards the kingdom of God.
               There you will behold all these things eye to eye, without feeling the need of
               hearing <pb n="69"/>them described; and you will no longer be unbelieving, but
               believing.</p>
            <p>42. In accordance with the different positions of the moon regarding the sun, its
               radiance varies. And according to the duration of the position the light of the moon
               continues. But if the former vanishes, the latter vanishes too.</p>
            <p>43. As the position of the moon regarding the sun does not continually remain the
               same, but varies at every moment, so the radiance of the mind augments or diminishes
               according to the various states it is subjected to.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n69-1"/></p>
            <p>44. Though, in the two worlds, the essences of the beings are subjected to various
               states, yet the more the mind has intercourse with matter, the more its variations
               will be augmented on account of its manifold sensibility. But when it has been made
               free from its dependency upon matter, its various states will diminish and its
               radiance will not diminish but be augmented by the great sun of righteousness.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n69-2"/> 45. The essence which before appeared unto
               heaven, earth and all that is in them, is different from that, which appears now; the
               latter, from that which is expected to be. For the first has vanished; the present is
               renewed, the future one will be renewed.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n69-3"/></p>
            <p>46. In view of the fact that all essences which manifest themselves in time,
               participate, all of them, of ideas,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n69-4"/> it is
               falsely thought, that they have a personal identity. As when<pb type="external"
                  n="588"/> anybody, seeing John and afterwards James, would think James to be the
               same as John whom he had seen before, because they participate of the common human
               nature. <pb n="70"/> 47. Those who have a puerile intellect, when seeing the uniform
               flame of a lamp, think that the flame has one essence, from the beginning until the
               end. But the manly mind knows, that with every atom of oil which is extinguished, the
               essence is annihilated; and that with every atom which is attracted, the essence is
                  renewed.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n70-1"/></p>
            <p>48. It is very difficult for the mind to conceive the annihilation and renovation<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n70-2"/> of the essences. And after frequent exercise
               and steady study, it is scarcely able to attain these things, but only dimly. The
               Initiated however, on account of their glorious revelations,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n70-3"/> see manifestly and know clearly, that at every moment the
               creator is creating a new essence for all creatures. 49. Those who with their
               spiritual eyes behold the annihilation and the renovation of essences, cry with a
               voice like thunder: It is one God, which works all in all.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n70-4"/> And in Him we live, and move, and have our being.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n70-5"/> In Him and through Him are all standing still
               and motion, all life of mind and soul and that of all beings.</p>
            <p>50. The knowledge of the perfect is founded on revelations.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n70-3"/> All revealed knowledge is of a prophetic nature. 51. The
               knowledge of the perfect is of a prophetic nature. And no part of prophetic knowledge
               can be learned and acquired by reading the Scriptures. 52. The receiver of
                  revelations<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n70-3"/> is sometimes of blunt speech
               and of difficult tongue; sometimes however he is a <choice><sic>herold</sic><corr>herald</corr></choice> with a loud
               voice, who makes streams of living water flow <pb n="71"/>from mouth; all along with
               the various states to which he<pb type="external" n="589"/> is subjected.</p>
            <p>53. Who has not tasted the sweetness of the love of his Lord, cannot discern the
               power of the words of the Beloved,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n71-1"/> because
               they are of a designating nature. And spiritual words cannot be uttered but in
               mysterious designations.</p>
            <p>54. Who writes the mysteries of the spirit, without the spirit's dictating them to
               him, is a sounding brass or a tinkling cymbal,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n71-2"
               /> because the spirit does not mix its sweetness into his words. 55. Who learns the
               mysteries of the spirit from the spirit, his audience will gather all enjoyments from
               his words; and his utterances will eradicate all passions from their heart. 56. For
               the seeking, who wishes to knock at the gate of the kingdom, it will be sufficient to
               take with him a small portion of the words of the Initiated, in order to distinguish
               the marks on his way. On these he must frequently meditate and these he must
               constantly repeat in his mind. But with books of broad instructions and of long
               contents he shall not spend his days, nor waste his time.</p>
            <p>57. If he who has provided himself with a small portion of the instructions of the
               perfect, meets an Initiated, he shall let himself be guided on his way by his words.
               Else he must cleanse his inward pupil by asceticism, and it will see all ways, the
               smooth and the rough ones.</p>
            <p>58. How long will you seek a guide, in order to open in the wall of your heart the
               window towards the kingdom? Cleanse the mirror of your mind<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n71-3"/> from stains, then it will shew you the images of the two
               kingdoms and the ways that will lead you towards that of heaven and, further, towards
               that of God.</p>
            <p>59. As long as the thirsty is not able to go towards then <pb type="external" n="590"
                  /><pb n="72"/>fountain, the guide has no strength to lead him, nor to carry him.
               He can only teach him the nature of his pilgrimage and his way of proceeding.</p>
            <p>60. As a leaky ship does not profit by the wind even if it be propitious, so the
               heart, which is subjected to desires, does not profit by a guide, even if he be of a
               high quality.</p>
            <p>61. Water cannot be gathered in a bottle of which the opening is directed towards the
               ground. And in the soul whose thought<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n72-1"/> is
               directed towards earthly things, the heavenly gift will not endure.</p>
            <p>62. To be occupied with ministering unto the pure in heart,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n72-2"/> is highly profitable for him who wishes to resemble them. They
               are those who have purified their inward man from all stains and who have received
               every good and perfect gift which cometh down from above, from the father of
                  lights.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n72-3"/></p>
            <p>63. Blessed and worthy of all blessedness is he who has found an Initiated, the rays
               of whose sun rise over the flame of his lamp and whose light has been annihilated by
               the light of his Lord, who is dead to the world and living in his God.</p>
            <p>64. True life is this, that the perfect suck at the breasts of supreme providence.
               And in the teachers of the law and the scriptures there is nothing of this life,
               except the description and the name.</p>
            <p>65. If the Lord had not supported me and made me to concentrate my attention on
               meditating the writings of the Initiated during these seven years,<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n72-4"/> away from the divagations of manifold
               teachings and various occupations, the bad customs which I see adhering to many,
               would have adhered to me also.</p>
            <p>66. Perhaps you will say: Is there then a sign distinguishing <pb type="external"
                  n="591"/>the veritable Initiated from the deceiving hypocrite? I answer: <pb
                  n="73"/>These signs are many in number. But at the first glance they begin with
               being dim. And in course of time, having been observed sufficiently long, they are
               revealed.</p>
            <p>67. Who has not tasted, does not know. Who has not eaten is not satisfied by
               conversation with him that has eaten. Who has not drunk, his thirst is not quenched
               by the narration of him that has drunk. Who has not experienced, the experience of
               <choice><sic>an other</sic><corr>another</corr></choice> does not profit him.</p>
            <p>68. Some of the teachers who are sufficiently trained in the holy scriptures and
               their explanation are not willing to learn the way of the kingdom from the Initiated
               who are not trained in their professional knowledge. They do not understand that
               their knowledge, however clever they may be, is one of hearing; that of the
               Initiated, however crude they may be, one of seeing.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n73-1"/> 69. By the Lord of Lords, my Lord, I conjure you, wonderful
               teachers; as long as you are not converted and have become as babes, devoid<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n73-2"/> of all skill and sagacity, till then you even
               know not the direction towards the kingdom; how then could you dare to take the way
               towards it and wish to reach it? It will happen to you, that, thinking to be near it,
               you will be far from it.</p>
            <p>70. To recognize, on account of the understanding of the rational soul and its
               stimulating influence upon the body, its riding animal,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n73-3"/> the essence of the latter, is simple knowledge, because also the
               irrational animals possess the two. But the incorruptibility of the soul,
               <choice><sic>nothwithstanding</sic><corr>notwithstanding</corr></choice> the corruptibility of its riding animal, the
               body, on account of its being immaterial, is only to be affirmed by the subtle
                  speculation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n73-4"/><pb type="external" n="592"/>
               of the sages.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n73-5"/></p>
            <pb n="74"/>
            <p>71. The rational soul is a receptacle of material apperceptions; but no material
               thing is a receptacle of intellectual apperceptions, because the latter are
               indivisible, but every material thing is divisible. And the indivisible cannot dwell
               in divisible things.</p>
            <p>72. Not a single rational soul is material; but all that is corruptible is material.
               Because there necessarily must be in it something like an idea which will decay; and
               something like matter, which is the receptacle of the decay of the idea.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-1"/></p>
            <p>73. To recognize from the creatures their creator, as from the building its builder,
               is common and simple knowledge, for it is also found in the possession of the simple.
               But the subtle speculation of the sages possesses a different, peculiar knowledge, by
               which from the being he whose being is necessary<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n74-2"/> is recognized.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-3"/> In the
               same way, if he that is, is necessarily being, this is what is requisited. If he is
               potentially being, he wants a necessarily being; so there is a necessarily being.</p>
            <p>74. The Initiated possess another, more peculiar knowledge, which is acquired by
               purity of deliberations,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-4"/> by subjecting the
               body to asceticism, by shutting the senses,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-5"/>
               and by cutting the bonds. And when the tabernacle of their heart is illuminated<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-6"/> by it, the kingdom of God is represented in
               them, and it becomes existing within them; and it is not sought on this mountain, nor
               in Jerusalem.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-7"/></p>
            <p>75. When the mind that is enflamed by the love of its Lord, <pb n="75"/>is directed
               under Him as it were by the plummet, its flame will quickly become straight; and
               being set to flame in a<pb type="external" n="593"/> moment it will be enlightened,
               as an extinguished torch is kindled by one that burns.</p>
            <p>76. Above and beneath, before and behind belong to the peculiar qualities of bodily
               things, not of not-bodily things. But on account of the inevitability of names and
               the necessity of words, he who speaks must necessarily use these secondary
               things.</p>
            <p>77. He who is guided by the light of his lamp, will dwell in nightly darkness and
               walk in obscurity, without knowing where he goes to. But he whose lamp is outshone by
               his sun, will walk in daylight, without stumbling.</p>
            <p>78. How quick is the time and how fast passes the duration of this light, how short
               are its days, how few are its hours. And some only, the very few, have been deemed
               worthy of it. I, at least, have seen it in my present darkness as the sun at the
               beginning of day-break at the horizon, and as a flash of lightning that passes
                  away.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n75-1"/></p>
            <p>79. My sun is in relation to me still in the sign of Caper only, even more to the
               South than Caper, and its ascension has not yet reached my horizon. And I desire and
               beseech that somewhat of the true light of the Beautiful one<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n75-2"/> may dawn for me; in order that I may no longer adore Him that I
               know not, but Him, that I know in spirit and truth.</p>
            <p>80. A blessed Initiated told me, saying: When I was a novice, it happened to me that
               I imagined that I was in the inaccessible light.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n75-3"/> My limbs relaxed, my mind vanished, and I resembled a man who is
               riding a skittish stallion, that is running as fast as it can, and flies through the
               air, without<pb type="external" n="594"/> knowing whether he is in his body or
               without it. When this <pb n="76"/>emotion<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-1"/>
               abated, my wits came back to me and my tongue began to stammer, saying: there has
               passed what passed, but I do not say what has passed. Hear me, hear me and be silent.
               But say not to me: explain and describe.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-2"/></p>
            <p>81. The same told: When I became stronger, the love of my Lord burned more vehemently
               in me. And often it did not let me finish my service. But as dead I would fall on my
                  face,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-3"/> while my body burned and my sighs
               were multiplied. And my heart said to me: Till how long will this folly and torment
               of my spirit [last]? What does the remembrance of the Beloved<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n76-4"/> profit, while the lover is in the cage of separation? 82. The
               same said further: When I had reached the stage of perfection, there went out a
               decree from the highest king, whose power is everlasting, and whose kingdom is unto
               generations, that it should be permitted to me to enter. And at once the eagle, the
               mind, broke its cage as if being mad and flew to its former nest and stood before the
               king of kings, the God of Gods, the Lord of Lords and it was with Him in freedom of
                  speech.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-5"/></p>
            <p>83. Be cautious, that your youth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-6"/> may not
               deceive you and you should think that these words give you the possession of the
               [corresponding] insight. No my brother, no my brother. If you wish to be master of
               hidden mysteries, you must hate <pb type="external" n="595"/>the two worlds.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-7"/> Let the dead bury their dead, and seek the
               ever living alone. And if you have wearied yourself <choice><sic>for ever</sic><corr>forever</corr></choice> with seeking
               Him, you will live for ever and ever.</p>
            <pb n="77"/>
            <p>84. Those who are low seek this world; and those who are high the world to come. But
               those who are still higher, their Lord, not themselves, viz. Him, not what belongs to
                  Him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-1"/> And from His love neither things
               present, nor things to come, nor other creatures can separate him. The more they are
               scorned on account of the love of His beauty,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-2"/>
               the more they thirst after it.</p>
            <p>85. Every clear soul<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-3"/> seeks its original
               country, and directs itself towards it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-4"/> on the
               straight way, which is the nearest. The righteous pass as it were a bridge of fire,
               because fire burns upwards in a straight line, without impediment.</p>
            <p>86. The unstained mind<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-3"/> psalmodies on the way:
               Cause me to know the way wherein I should walk;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-5"
               /> and ‘save me in Thy ways’. And when it has reached the goal it beseeches its Lord:
               Keep me as the apple of Thy eye and hide me under the shadow of Thy wings,<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-6"/> against the forces of the body, those sinners
               that have plundered me, and against impure passions, the enemies of my soul, that
               have risen against me.</p>
            <p>87. The understanding of the eye is sometimes true, as for instance, when it observes
               the sea to be greater than a pool; sometimes however, false, as for instance, when it
               sees the sun as a shield and a star as a dareikos;<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n77-7"/> and this is because it sees them at a distance, not near.</p>
            <p>88. The knowledge of the mind is sometimes true: as for instance, that God is one,
               and necessarily being<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-8"/> and the eternal
               creator; sometimes however false, as for instance, that the mind, if freed from the
               yoke of the body, will see the<pb type="external" n="596"/> adorable highest as He
               is.</p>
            <pb n="78"/>
            <p>89. As the bat does not see the sun at all, and man, though he sees it, does not see
               it as it is, so he hears theories concerning the highest one, but he does not see
               Him. The Initiated, however, sees, but only some of His beauties; not all of them,
               for they are unlimited.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-1"/></p>
            <p>90. Accustom your soul to believe what you hear from the true one.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-2"/> And if you recognize not His true essence, do
               not search after His cause by syllogisms.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-3"/> For
               by this belief it will be apt for the gift<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-4"/>
               [which will be given] by the Paraclet, the spirit of truth, which will come to you
               and guide you into all truth;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-5"/> he will bring
               all things to your remembrance and <choice><sic>teech</sic><corr>teach</corr></choice> you all things.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-6"/></p>
            <p>91. The resurrection of the body takes place by the second unification with the soul.
               The resurrection of the soul<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-7"/> by the
               dissolution of the unification with the body. And the one as well as the other takes
               place after much trouble. Sun and moon—the eyes—will be obscurated; the stars—the
               senses—will fall from the sky—the head. The forces which move the body will be moved
               themselves and all the families—the limbs—will dance. And the pious soul, which has
               risen from its fall will be conducted by the light of the sign of the son of God,
               towards the apartment which it has been promised, in heaven. 92.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-8"/> From the bodies of the horse, the bull, the
               ape and man the differences of their souls are recognized. The Initiated recognize
               from the inclinations<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-9"/> of every human soul the
               apartment for which it is apt. They discern between that of <pb n="79"/>which the
               room will be the inner holy of holies, and that of<pb type="external" n="597"/> which
               the apartment will be far beyond the cloud.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n79-1"/>
               They also recognize those in the middle and the other, low ones which are wholly
               devoid of light and who will be miserable with the miserable, in places not visited
               by the Lord. 93. When, after the conjunct labours of soul and body, a simeonitic
               simplicity, natural or resembling to nature, will have happened to you, o
                  brother,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n79-2"/> then know that your night is
               over, and your lamentation has passed; your dawn has come, and your morning is near;
               and your Lord will send you light and faith and console you by His revelations.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n79-3"/></p>
            <p>94. By that which I have said, and say and shall say, I do not reject
                  speculation.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n79-4"/> How should this be, since
               esoteric teachers and exoteric sages, by their intricate ways of thought, have
               ascended to astonishing heights of knowledge? But when I see that some of them have
               dared to weigh all in their scale, their boast does not appear beautiful to me. For
               their scale is just and right, but it does not bear nor contain the multitude of
               things of the world to come. These are only to be partially understood by vision<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n79-5"/> acquired by revelation.</p>
            <p>95. When you wish to give rest to your mind from attaining profound questions by
               syllogistic intricacies,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n79-6"/> and you will acquire
               solitude and silence with steady labours, then be patient, and be not dejected on
               your way. Ere long your sun will rise and illuminate your evening and show you your
                  beauty<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n79-7"/> and liberate you from the slavery
               of time and place.</p>
            <p>96. When the sun of the Beloved rises for the lover, on <pb n="80"/><pb
                  type="external" n="598"/>the day without day, and he looks at the Solomonic bride
               in her splendour, while she shows herself to him without a cover, introducing him
               into her house with sevenfold columns, she will inform the beloved concerning all
               things and tame with him the beasts of wings and of prey, because they scent from him
               the odour of their creator; for even those beings which are not endowed with senses,
               perceive Him, so that the demons are subjected and the angels minister unto him.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n80-1"/></p>
            <p>97. When the blessed has reached this stage he will no longer drink from a rock or a
               fountain, but from the water his Lord will give him and he shall not be thirsty any
               more. But it shall be in him a well of water springing up into everlasting life.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n80-2"/></p>
            <p>98. Now these sentences are only profitable for him who is trained in the knowledge
               of divine and human practice, longing to see in revelations<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n80-3"/> those things which his speculation<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n80-4"/> has reached. But who is devoid of this longing, shall reiterate
               his meditation upon this book; with attentive intelligence however, not by brutish
               recitation; perhaps in this way it will make warm his heart. 99. The causes which
               abate the love unto the Beautiful one are many. To enumerate all of them is above my
               power and <pb n="81"/>too lengthy for my time. Speech already wearies me, while my
               heart tends towards that which is more expedient; therefore: who is able to stand on
               his feet in the struggle of love, let him stand. But who does not possess this
               strength, let him make his food according to his strength, and let him stretch his
               foot according to [the length of] his mantle.</p>
            <p>100. For this seed, though it be small as a mustard seed,<pb type="external" n="599"
               /> if it does not fall by the way side, or upon a stone, or among thorns, but it be
               sown on good ground,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n81-1"/> it will, when it is
               grown up, become a large tree, so that the birds of the air come, viz. the heavenly
               guests, and make their nests in the branches thereof.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n81-2"/> And further: A man can receive nothing, except it be given him
               from heaven.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n81-3"/> Here ends the Book of the
               Dove.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="83"/>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n3-1"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: our.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3-2">Introduction, p. LXVIII sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3-3">Introduction, p. XVI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3-4">Introduction, p. CIII sqq. And Glossary, s. v. ܥܪܦܠܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n3-5">Introduction, p. XCVIII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4-1">ܡܠܬܐ ܠܡܠܝ̈ܠ</note>
            <note xml:id="n4-2">Plural.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5-1">Johannes Climacus' Scala and the Imitatio Christi open with a
               section on the same subject.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5-2">ܡܪܢܝܬܐ, see Glossary.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5-3">Reading of P; the text has: despisable.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6-1">The passage has been borrowed from Johannes Climacus, Scala, p. 9:
               εἶδον σπόρον ἐν γῇ ἀκουσίως ἐκπέσοντα, καὶ καρπὸν πολὺν καὶ εὐθαλῆ πεποιηκότα[b].
               Gẖazālī does not reckon such persons among renouncers, Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 188 and
               205.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6-2">Scala, Gradus V; Paradisus Patrum, p. 670-678; Abū Ṭālib al-Makkī I,
               179; Iḥyāʾ IV, 1; Ethikon IV, 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6-3">This description of repentance is found in many mystic works:
               Ḳusẖairī, p. 53; Abū Ṭālib al-Makkī I, 179; Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 3; Ethikon, p. 355; Sefer
               Chasidim, fol. 10b.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6-4">Introduction, p. CXI sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6-5">Introduction p. CXII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6-6">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 28: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n6-7">Introduction, p. CXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6-8">James 5, 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7-1">1 John 1, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7-2">Scala, Gradus I; Paradisus Patrum, p. 495-504; Abū Ṭālib I, 242:
               Ḳusẖairī, p. 64; Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 163; Ethikon IV, 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7-3">Introduction, p. CXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7-4">Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh I, 67: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n7-5">Introduction, p. CXV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7-6">Introduction, l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7-7">Introduction, p. CXVI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8-1">Introduction, p. CXVII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8-2">Introduction, l.c. Renunciating the use of furniture is not a
               specially Christian or Mohammedan trait of asceticism: Porphyry relates it concerning
               the senator Rogatianus, a friend of Plotinus (Vita Plotini § 7).</note>
            <note xml:id="n8-3">Scala, Gradus XXV; Paradisus Patrum, p. 615-654; Ḳusẖairī, p. 79;
               Iḥyāʾ III, p. 285 sqq., 296 sqq.; Imitatio Christi II, p. 7, 377.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8-4">Paradisus Patrum, p. 525-531; Imitatio Christi I, 9; Scala, p. 80:
               ἐκ ὑπακοῆς ταπείνωσις[d].</note>
            <note xml:id="n8-5">Iḥyāʾ III, p. 309: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n8-6">Iḥyāʾ III, p. 309: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n8-7">Iḥyāʾ III, p. 298.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8-8">Introduction, p. XXI. The quotation is in Bedjan's edition, p.
               499.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8-9">Iḥyāʾ III, p. 286: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n8-10">Introduction, p. XX.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8-11">Iḥyāʾ III, p. 285: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n9-1">Scala, p. 317: ὁ ἑαυτὸν ἐπιγνοὺς ἐν πάσῆ αἰσθήσει ψυχῆς ἐπὶ τὴν γῆν
               ἔσπειρεν· οὐκ ἔστι γὰρ μὴ οὕτως σπείραντας ταπεινοφρωσύνην ἀνθῆσαι. Iliya' III. p.
               287: <!--Add Arabic-->. Cf. Ill, p. 300.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9-2">Pirḳe Abot III, 1; Iḥyāʾ III, p. 288: <!--Add Arabic-->. And III, p.
               303: <!--Add Arabic-->. Lehmann and Pedersen, Der Islam V, 54 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9-3">Introduction, p. CXVII sqq.; Paradisus Patrum, p. 504-525: Abū Ṭālib
               I. 193.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9-4">Ethikon, p. 369.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9-5">Ethikon, p. 372.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9-6">ܪܓܬ ܟܪܣܐ ܘܡܚܣܢܐ, Gẖazālī’s <!--Add Arabic--> (Iḥyāʾ III, p.
               70).</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-1">Matthew 24, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-2">Paradisus Patrum p. 588-614; Iḥyāʾ II, p. 130; Abū Ṭālib II, 213;
               Imitatio Christi II, p. 363. Ethikon IV, 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-3">Iḥyāʾ II, p. 133: Love between two persons becomes consolidated
               without a handsome appearance and without corporeal or moral beauty, but on account
               of inward consanguinity causing sympathy and harmony.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-4">In Cardahi's text only.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-5">Introduction, p. XXIII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-6">Introduction, p. CXIX.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-7">Introduction, p. CXX.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11-1">Introduction, p. CXX.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11-2">1 Timothy 5,8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11-3">Iḥyāʾ III, 4; Ethikon III, 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11-4">Basilios II, 527 A. Imitatio Christi, I, 10 (opp. II. p. 17).
               Introduction, p. CXXII sqq. Pythagoras is said to have accustomed his pupils to
               silence (Jamblichus, Vita Pythagorae, p. 56).</note>
            <note xml:id="n11-5">Solitude and silence, ܫܠܝܐ ܘܫܬܩܐ, <!--Add Arabic--> often combined,
               Imitatio Christi I, 20: De amore solitudinis et silentii.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11-6">Iḥyāʾ III, p. 97: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n12-1">Scala, Gradus XI: περὶ πολυλογίας καὶ σιωπής.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-2">Introduction, p. CXXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-3">Psalm 37, 38.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-4">Introduction, ib.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-5">Luke 3, 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-6">Matthew 5, 40.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-7">Matthew 5, 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-8">Introduction, ib.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-1">Romans 12, 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-2">Introduction, p. CXXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-3">Cf. section X.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-4">Luke 6, 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-5">Matthew 18, 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-6">Scala, Gradus X: περὶ καταλαλίας.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-7">Scala. p. 186: καταλαλία ἐστιν ἀποκύημα μίσους.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-8">Psalm 1,1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-9">Introduction, p, CXXV; Scala, Gradus XII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-10">Ps. 5,7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-11">Scala p. 196: τῆς Ραὰβ μιμητὴν ἑαυτὸν τεκμαίρεσθαι ψευδοπλάστης
               ἀνὴρ καὶ δι’ ἀπωλείας οἰκείας τὴν ἑτέραν σωτηρίαν λέγει πραγματεύεσθαι· ὁπόταν
               ψεύδους εἰς ἅπαν καθαρεύσωμεν τότε αὐτὸ μέτα φόβου καὶ καιροῦ καλοῦντος
               ὑπέλθωμεν.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-1">Introduction, p. CXXV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-2">Introduction, p. CXXVI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-3"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: divided lips. Introduction, l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-4">Ps. 12, 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-5">Introduction, l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-6">Reading with Cardahi and Ethikon, p. 269 ܚܘܝܒܐ instead of
               ܚܘܫܟܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-7">Introduction, p. l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-1">Reading of P.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-2">The same expression infra II, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-3">Cf. Iḥyāʾ III, p. 66 sqq.; Ethikon II, 10, 10. Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh's
               comentator II, 63 quotes from Ḳusẖairī: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n15-4">The following examples seem to have been the usual ones for this
               subject; see Reitzenstein. Historia Monachorum, p. 207, who cites G. Ficker,
               Amphilochiana I, 63.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-5">Ethikon II, 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-1">Gen. 1, 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-2">I Cor. 7, 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-3">Introduction, p. LXVIII sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-4">Iḥyāʾ III, p. 66: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n16-5"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: halting on his two knee-joints, the
               translation of I Kings 18, 21</note>
            <note xml:id="n17-1">Luke 9, 62.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17-2">Ethikon, p. 139.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17-3">By Johannes Climacus, Scala, p. 10: ὁ γὰρ ἄγαμος ἐν τῷ κόσμῳ μόνοις
               τοῖς πράγμασι δεδέμενος, τῷ ἐν χερσὶ τὰ κλοιὰ περικειμένῳ ἔοικε, διὸ τὲ ὅτε βούλεται
               δραμεῖν πρὸς τὸν μονήρη βίον οὐ κωλύεται, ὁ δὲ γήμας τῷ ἐν χερσὶ καὶ ποσὶ τοὺς
               δεσμοὺς περικειμένῳ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18-1">Cf. supra I, 7; Basilius II, 359 D; 425 E; 529 D: εἴ τις εὐτράπελα
               λαλῶν ἠ ἀργολογῶν γενέσθω ἀπ’ εὐλογίας. — The neo-Pythagoraeans also condemn
               laughing, Jamblichus, Vita Pythagorae, p. 58. Bar Hebraeus has written a collection
               of laughable stories himself.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18-2">ܙܘ̈ܥܐ, Introduction, p. LXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19-1">Quoted in the Ethikon, p. 99, from Isaac of Ninive. Cf. Basilius
               II, 341-343.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19-2">Introduction, p. LXXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19-3">The same sequence in the Ethikon, Book III and IV. and in the
               Iḥyāʾ. It seems to go back to Hellenistic examples. In Chapter XIII (XIV) § 7 sqq. of
               the Corpus Hermeticum twelve vices have to be banished before grace will fill man
               with godly things.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-1">Introduction, p. LXVIII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-2">Matthew 5, 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-3">Scala, Gradus XXVII; Iḥyāʾ II, 6; Ethikon I, 7; Thomas a Kempis: De
               custodia cellae (Opp. II, p. 430); Introduction, p. XXIV sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-4">Ethikon p. 93; Iḥyāʾ II, p. 183 gives the following definition of
               this profit: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n21-1"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: to lay the staff on.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-2">Verses of 7 syllables.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-3">The profits of solitude are also enumerated in the Ethikon, p.
               93-96 and the Iḥyāʾ, p. 183 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-4">Introduction, p. CXXVI sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-5">Cf. I, 7 and Abū Ṭālib I, 9: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n22-1">Reading with Cardahi's text ܕܥܬܝ̈ܕܬܐ instead of ܕܥܬܝܖ̈ܬܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-2">Cf. Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh's commentator ΙΙ, 64 who cites Suhrawardī:
               <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-3">This sequence is already in the Iḥyāʾ I, p. 279: <!--Add Arabic-->.
               Further Ethikon I, 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-4">Luke 18, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-5">Introduction, p. XCIII sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-6">Gẖazālī also reckons the <!--Add Arabic--> as consisting of ten
               sentences (Iḥyāʾ I, p. 277).</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-7">Daniel 3, 52-90.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-8">The last restriction is also added by Gẖazālī I, p. 276.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23-1">Introduction, p. LXXVII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23-2">Iḥyāʾ I, 4: Ethikon I, 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-1">Introduction, p. LXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-2">Introduction, p. XCVI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-3">Introduction, p. XXXII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-4">Matthew 6, 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-5">ܒܥܘܬܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-6"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice> so in Ghazali I, p. 280:
               <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n24-7">Basilius II, 383: Εἰ ἐν τὲ τῇ ἕκτῃ ὥρᾳ κατὰ μίμνησιν τῶν ἁγίων
               ἀναγκαίαν εἶναι τὴν προσευχὴν ἀκκρίναμεν, τῶν λεγόντων ἑσπέραν καὶ πρῶι καὶ
               μεσημβρίας διηγήσομαι καὶ ἀπαγγελῶ καὶ εἰσακούεται τῆς φωνῆς μου καὶ ὥστε ῥυσθῆναι
               ἀπὸ συμπτώματος καὶ δαιμονίου μεσημβρινοῦ ἅμα καὶ τοῦ ψαλμοῦ τοῦ ἐννεηκοστοῦ
               λεγομένου. Cf. Houtsma in Verslagen en Mededeelingen IVe Reeks, 2e deel, p. 22 sqq.;
               further Theol. Tijdschrift 1913, p. 258 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-1">ܒܥܘܬܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-2">Cf. Iḥyāʾ I, p. 284: <!--Add Arabic-->: And Ibn al-ʿArabī, Fī kunh
               mā lā budd lilmurīd minhu, p. 44: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-3"> Jamblichus, Vita Pythagorae, p. 13: ὡς εἶχεν ἐν τῇ ἑδραίᾳ καὶ
               ἀσαλευτω ἐπιμονῇ κατέδαρθε βραχύ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-4">Also combined in Scala, p. 267; Thomas a Kempis, Opp. II, 424. Cf.
               further Iḥyāʾ I, 10; Ethikon I, 3 and 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-5">Jamblichns, Vita Pythagorae, p. 13: ἐφ ἑνός τε καὶ τοῦ αὐτοῦ
               σχήματος διέμεινε δύο νύκτας καὶ τρεῖς ἡμέρας μήτε τροφῆς μήτε ποτοῦ μετασχῶν μήτε
               ὕπνου. Cf. p. 56.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26-1">Introduction, p. CXXVII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26-2">Cf. Ḳorʾān 4, 33: <!--Add Arabic-->, and Bukẖārī, Tayammum, b. 7.
               Gẖazālī I, p. 284 has the same argument on behalf of sleep: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26-3">Psalm 117, 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-1">Iḥyāʾ I, 6; Ethikon I, 6: Paradisus Patrum. p. 465-479.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-2">Introduction, p. LXXIV sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-3">The sentence is in its essential points in Porphyry, De abstinentia
               ab esu animantium I § 47: τῆς δὲ τοῦ πολλῶν δεῖσθαι ἀρθείσης αἰτίας καὶ τοῦ πλήθους
               τῶν εἰσαγομένων εἰς τὸ σῶμα περιαιρεθέντων τοῦ τε βάρους τῶν ἀραδιδομένων
               κουφισθέντων, ἐλεύθερον τὸ ὄμμα καπνοῦ καὶ κύματος τοῦ σωματικοῦ ἐκτὸς καθωρμισμένον
               γίγνεται. Jamblichus, Vitae Pythagorae, p. 10: τῇ γάρ τῶν λεπτῶν καὶ εὐαναδότων ἐδωδῇ
               συμμετρηθεῖς κἀκ τούτου ὀλιγοϋπνίαν καὶ ἐπαγρίαν καὶ ψυχῆς καθαρότητα
               κτησάμενος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-4">Introduction, p. CXXVIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-1">Also a Muslim precept.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-2">Introduction, p. CXXVIII; Abū Ṭālib I, 74; II, 113.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-3">Verses of 12 syllables.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-4">The Jewish law also forbids fasting on the Sabbath, Islām at
               official, religious feasts.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-5">Basilius II, 381 sqq.; Iḥyāʾ II, 3; Ethikon II, 5; Introduction,
               l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29-1">As, for instance, Isaac of Ninive, p. 566 sqq.; cf. Reitzenstein,
               Historia Monachorum, p. 195.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29-2">I Corinthians 9, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-1">Scala, Gradus III; Ḳusẖairī, p. 152 sqq.; Iḥyāʾ II, 7; Ethikon I,
               8; cf. Reitzenstein, Historia Monachorum, p. 50 sqq., 196.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-2">Introduction, p. CXXIX.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-3">Iḥyāʾ II, p. 200: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-4"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: to cleanse his heart.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-5">Scala, p. 33: ἡ τῶν τόπων ἡμῶν ἀναχώρησις ἔστω εἰς τὰ
               ἀπαρακλητικώτερα καὶ ἀκενοδοξότερα καὶ ταπεινότερα μέρη. Iḥyāʾ II, p. 200:
               <!--Add Arabic--> and II, p. 240.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-6">Scala, p. 30; Ihya' II, p. 200: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-1">Iḥyāʾ II, p. 200: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-2">Also in Iḥyāʾ II, p. 200.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-3">Gẖazālī distinguishes three categories of travels; that which is
               blamable, that <choice><sic>wich</sic><corr>which</corr></choice> is praised and that which is allowed (Iḥyāʾ II, p.
               203).</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-4">Scala, p. 30: ξενιτεύων ἀσφαλίζου τὸν γυρευτὴν καὶ φιλήδονον
               δαίμονα. ἡ γὰρ ξενιτεία ἀφορμὴν αὐτῷ δίδωσι. The passage in the text has been
               borrowed from Euagrius, see Ethikon, p. 105.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-5">Introduction, p. CXXX.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-6">Cf. Ḳusẖairī, p. 153: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-7">Gẖazālī II, p. 209 says that the traveller shall not remain longer
               than a week or ten days in any place; if he visits a brother, not longer than three
               days.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-8">Introduction, l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32-1">John 4, 21, 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32-2">Scala, Gradus XIII: περὶ ἀκηδίας.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-1">Iḥyāʾ III, 3; Ethikon III, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-2">Introduction, p. CXXX.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-3">Abū Ṭālib I, 98: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-4">Introduction, l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-5">Ethikon III, 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-6">Gẖazālī III, p. 92-94 recommends abstention from marriage to the
               novices; he relates many stories warning against the intercourse with women and boys
               and looking at them. Cf. Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh I, 55 and Ḳusẖairī, p, 216.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34-1">Scala, p. 217: ἀρχὴ μὲν ἁγνείας ἀσυγκατάθετος λογισμὸς καὶ
               ἀνείδωλοι διὰ χρόνων ἐκκρίσεις. μεσότης ἁγνείας φυσικαὶ κινήσεις ἐπὶ πλήθει βρωμάτων
               καὶ μόνων ἀνειδώλως συνιστάμεναι καὶ ῥεύσεως ἀπηλλαγμέναι. τέλος δὲ νέκρωσις σώματος
               προθανόντων λογισμῶν.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34-2">Iḥyāʾ III, 5: Ethikon III, 6,3; Introduction, p. CXXX sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34-3"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: he who does him harm.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34-4">Ethikon, p. 273. Almost <choice><sic>litterally</sic><corr>literally</corr></choice> in Iḥyāʾ III, p.
               139.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34-5">Introduction, p. CXXXI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34-6">Matthew 1 1. 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34-7">Ephesians 4, 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35-1">Introduction, p. CXXXI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35-2">Cf. Sefer Chasidim, fol. 17a: <!--Add Hebrew --></note>
            <note xml:id="n35-3">Ethikon III, 6,4; Iḥyāʾ III, p. 150 where also eight daughters of
               rancour are enumerated.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35-4">Iḥyāʾ III, p. 154; Ethikon, III, 6,5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35-5">Introduction, l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-1">Iḥyāʾ III, p. 162 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-2">Iḥyāʾ III, p. 166 sqq.; Ethikon, III, 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-3">Taken from Euagrius, as appears in the Ethikon, p. 278.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-4">Introduction, p. CXXXI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-5">Scala, Gradus XVI; Iḥyāʾ III, 7; Ethikon III, 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-6">Introduction, p. CXXXII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-7">Matthew 6, 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-1">Introduction, p. CXXXII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-2"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: obsonia.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-3">Iḥyāʾ III, 8; Ethikon III, 9; Thomas a Kempis, Opp. II, 362: De
               contemptu vanae gloriae.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-4">Introduction, p. CXXXIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-5">Scala, p. 276. The sentence has found its way into the Iḥyāʾ II. p.
               228: <!--Add Arabic-->: in this form it occurs in the Scala and the Ethikon, p.
               293.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-6">Scala, p. 278.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-7">Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh I, 101: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-8">Scala, p. 277: εἶδον πενθοῦντας ἐπαινεθέντας καὶ εἰς ὀργὴν
               ἐξαφθέντας καὶ ὡς ἐν πανηγύρει πάθει πάθος συναλλάξαντας.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-9">Only in Cardahi's text</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-10">Scala, p. 277: ὅταν ἀκούσῃς ὅτι ὁ πλησίον σου ἢ ὁ φίλος ἐλοιδώρησέ
               σε ἀπόντα ἢ παρόντα τότε τὴν ἀγάπην ἔνδεξαι ἐπαινέσας αὐτὸν. With the above passage
               cf. Ethikon, p. 295 sq.; Iḥyāʾ III, p. 242.</note>
            <note xml:id="n38-1">Cf. the story in the <choice><sic>Etikon</sic><corr>Ethikon</corr></choice>, p. 291.</note>
            <note xml:id="n38-2">Iḥyāʾ III, p. 229: <!--Add Arabic-->. And Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh I, 100:
               <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n38-3">Introduction, p. CXXXIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n38-4">Ethikon III, 11; Iḥyāʾ III, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39-1">Introduction, p. CXXXIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39-2">Ethikon III, 12; Iḥyāʾ III, 10; Introduction, l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39-3">1 Cor. 1,31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39-4">Ethikon IV, 2 this feature is considered in bonam partem.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40-1">Matthew 7, 5; Luke 6, 42.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40-2">Introduction, p. XLV sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40-3">Ethikon IV, 1; Iḥyāʾ I, 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40-4">Introduction, p. CXXXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40-5">Introduction, l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40-6">Johannes Climacus, Opp., p. 470: τελείως αὐτὰ ὀφείλει τὰ πάθη ὁ
               ἰατρὸς ἐκδύσασθαι. Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh II, 64: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40-7">Iḥyāʾ I, p. 61; Ibn al 'Arabi, Kunh ma la budda minhu lilmurld, p.
               48.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40-8">Already in Basilius II, 389 E.; Iḥyāʾ I. p. 53, 56.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41-1">Ethikon IV, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41-2">Hebrews 11, 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41-3">Ethikon IV, 6: Iḥyāʾ IV, 2b.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41-4">Introduction, p. CXXXV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41-5">Abū Ṭālib I, 208: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-1">Even this example has been taken from the Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 109. In the
               Ethikon, p. 390, concerning this point an anecdote is told, that is also found in the
               Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 110.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-2">Ethikon, p. 391; Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 112 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-3">Ethikon, IV, 7; Iḥyāʾ IV, 3; Abū Ṭālib I, 213 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-4">Introduction, p. XLV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-5"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: obsonia.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-6">Ethikon IV, 8; Iḥyāʾ IV, 3; Abū Ṭālib I, 225 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-7">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 134: <!--Add Arabic-->. The Ethikon (IV, 8, 3) and the
               Iḥyāʾ (IV, p. 136) have parallel sections on the degrees of fear.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-8">Scala, Gradus XXI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-9">Cf. Romans 8, 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-1">Scala, Gradus XVII; Ethikon IV, 9; Iḥyāʾ IV, 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-2">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 176; Abū Ṭālib II, 193.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-3">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 177.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-4">Abū Ṭālib II, 193.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-5">Cf. Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 177.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-6">Cf. Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 181: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-7">Ethikon II. 6; Iḥyāʾ I, 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-8">Iḥyāʾ I, p. 195 sqq.: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-9">Introduction, p. CXXXV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-10">Introduction, p. CXXXV sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-2">Psalm 22, 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-2">Psalm 73, 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-3">Deut. 22, 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-4">Ethikon IV, 14; Iḥyāʾ IV, 7b.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-5">Introduction, p. C sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-6">Introduction, p. XXXVI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-7">In the Ethikon, p. 470 sq. the following evil deliberations are
               enumerated: wantonness, fornication, love of money, trouble, anger, tediousness, vain
               glory, haughtiness. Euagrius, p. 472 gives saturation instead of wantonness. Some
               Fathers of the church give seven principal sins: the discrepancy is mentioned by
               Johannes Climacus, Scala, p. 275. He speaks of the ὀκτὼ λογισμοί[l]; this is the
               origin of the Syriac term ܚܘ̈ܫܒܐ. The subject has penetrated into Islām; cf. Muslim,
               Ṣaḥīḥ, Kitāb al Īmān, tradd. 141-149.</note>
            <note xml:id="n45-1">Ethikon IV, 16; Iḥyāʾ IV, 10; Scala, Gradus VI: Imitatio Christi I,
               23 (Opp., II p. 44): De meditatione mortis. Introduction, p. CXXXVI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n45-2">Jesus Sirach 7, 36.</note>
            <note xml:id="n45-3">Ḳusẖairī, p. 161: <!--Add Arabic-->. And Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh II, p. 66:
               <!--Add Arabic-->. Introduction, p. LII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-1">Introduction, p. LXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-2">Introduction, p. LXXVII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-3">Introduction, p. LXXXI sqq. Beneath, sentence 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-4">Introduction, p. CIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-5">Introduction, p. CVI sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-1">Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh II, 60: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-2">Verses of 12 syllables.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-3">Introduction, p. LXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-4">Ethikon IV, 15, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-5">Introduction, p. Will sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-6">Introduction, p. I. XXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-7"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: natures.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-1">ܡܬܗܘܢܢܝܬܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-2">Enneades VI, 7 § 34: ἀλλὰ καὶ τὰ ἄλλα πάντα οἷς πρὶν ἥδετο, ἀρχαῖς
               ἢ δυνάμεσιν ἢ πλούτοις ἢ κάλλεσιν ἢ ἐπιστήμαις ταῦτα ὑπεριδοῦσα λέγει.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-3">Introduction, p. C sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-4">Cf. above p. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-5">Introduction, p. XCI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-6">Ethikon IV, 15, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-7">Introduction, p. CII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-8">Introduction, p. XCIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-9">The Cause that spreads life is also in the Theology of Aristoteles,
               p. 104.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-1">Cf. Corpus Hermeticum I § 26 (cf. XIII § 17) where the voyage of
               the soul is described: καὶ τότε γυμνωθεὶς ἀπὸ τῶν τῆς ἁρμονίας ἐνεργημάτων γίνεται
               ἐπὶ τὴν ὀγδοαδικῆν φύσιν τὴν ἰδίαν δύναμιν ἔχων καὶ ὑμνεῖ σὺν τοῖς οὖσι τὸν πατέρα.
               συγχαίρουσι δὲ οἱ παρόντες τῇ τούτου παρουσίᾳ καὶ ὁμοιωθεὶς τοῖς συνοῦσιν ἀκούει καί
               τινων δυνάμεων ὑπὲρ τὴν ὀγδοαδικὴν φύσιν οὐσῶν φωνῇ τινι ἰδία ὑμνουσῶν τὸν θεόν, καὶ
               τότε τάξει ἀνέρχονται πρὸς τὸν πατέρα καὶ αὐτοὶ εἰς δυνάμεις ἑαυτοὺς παραδιδόασι καὶ
               δυνάμεις γενόμενοι ἐν θεῷ γίνονται. The parallelism is evident.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-2">Introduction, p. CIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-3">Introduction, p. LXXXI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-4">Dieterich, Mithrasliturgie, p. 10: ὥστε ἀπὸ τῆς τοῦ θεάματος ἡδονῆς
               καὶ τῆς χαρᾶς τὸ πνεῦμα σου συντρέχειν καὶ ἀναβαίνειν. And Enneades VI, 9 § 7: … εἰ
               ἐθέλει μένειν ἄνω, ὅπερ καὶ τῷ πολὺ ἰδόντι γένοιτ’ ἂν πάθημα.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-5">Introduction, p. LXXVI sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-6">Ethikon, p. 499,</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-7">Introduction, p. CVI II sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-1">Introduction, p. CVI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-2">Introduction, p. CVIII sqq. Cf. the Theology of Aristoteles, p. 8:
               <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-3">Introduction, p. XC.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-4">Introduction, p. XXVII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-5">Abū Ṭālib II, 59: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-6">2 Cor. 12, 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-1">1 Cor. 15. 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-2">Ethikon IV, 15, 2; Iḥyāʾ IV, 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-3">Also in the Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 253 — 256.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-4">On outward and inward beauty cf. the Theology of Aristoteles, p 49
               sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-5">Ethikon IV, 15, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-6">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 257.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-7">Acts 17, 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-8">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 258.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-9">Introduction, p. XLVI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n52-1">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 259.</note>
            <note xml:id="n52-2">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 262.</note>
            <note xml:id="n52-3">Ethikon IV, 15,4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n52-4">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 263: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n53-1">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 265: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n53-2">1 Cor. 13, 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n53-3">Read: ܕܪܗܡܬ</note>
            <note xml:id="n53-4">Iḥyāʾ IV. p. 270 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n53-5">Reading of P.</note>
            <note xml:id="n53-6">Cf. several parallel passages in the Corpus Hermeticum XIII (XIV) §
               11 and 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n53-7">P. reads: love.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-1">Introduction, p. XCIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-2">Introduction, p. L sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-3">Ps. 42, 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-4">Romans 8, 38.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-5">See Ethikon, p. 489.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-6">Ethikon IV, 15,6 and Sentence 73.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-1">The two kinds of knowledge also Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 271:
               <!--Add Arabic-->. And cf. Abū Ṭālib II, 3: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-2">See Ethikon, p. 484.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-3">Ps. 19, 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-4">Ps. 36, 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-5">Introduction, p. XLII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-6">Introduction, p. XLVIII sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-7">Ethikon IV, 15,8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-8">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 275: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-9">Ps. 19, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-10">Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh II, 9: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n56-1">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 275: <!--Add Arabic-->. The same idea is expressed by
               Jamblichus (De mysteriis, p. 86): καὶ μὴν τήν γε λεπτότητα τοῦ φωτὸς οἱ μὲν θεοὶ
               τοσαύτην ἐπιλάμπουσιν ὡς μὴ δύνασθαι χωρεῖν αὐτὴν τοὺς σωματικοὺς ὀφθαλμοὺς.</note>
            <note xml:id="n56-2">Ethikon IV, 15, 14. Introduction, p. XCV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n56-3">Introduction, p. LXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n56-4">ܐܟܣܝܣܐܝܬ</note>
            <note xml:id="n57-1">Cf. Introduction, p. XCIII sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n57-2">Introduction, p. LXXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n57-3"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: breathed forth.</note>
            <note xml:id="n57-4">Introduction, p. LXXXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n57-5">Introduction, p. CVIII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n58-1"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: left-hand.</note>
            <note xml:id="n58-2">Introduction, p. XCVIII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n58-3">I Cor. 2, 9; cf. Introduction, p. XXVII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n58-4">Cf. with the following passage the description by Gẖazālī, Iḥyāʾ
               IV, p. 327.</note>
            <note xml:id="n58-5">Matthew 8, 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n59-1">Cf. Matth. 23, 8 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n59-2">Psalm 51, 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-1"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: from tender nails. The following tale of
               Bar Hebraeus' conversion has a strong likeness with Gẖazālī’s religious experiences
               as told in his Munḳidẖ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-2">Bedjan says in a note: this theory is not true.</note>
            <note xml:id="n61-1">Cf. above, p. 16, note 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n61-2">Introduction, p. LXXXIV</note>
            <note xml:id="n61-3">Introduction, p. XCIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-1">Introduction, p. XLIV sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-2">Introduction, p. LXXVII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-3">Muslim expression.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-4">Introduction, p. CIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-5">Introduction, p. XXIX sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-6">Introduction, p. LXXVII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-7">ܬܐܪܬܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-8">Introduction, p. LXXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-9">Introduction, p. XLVIII sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n63-1">Most of these terms are borrowed from the description of the temple
               in the first book of Kings.</note>
            <note xml:id="n63-2">Introduction, p. LXXVI sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n63-3">A similar expression occurs in the Jewish philosopher Abraham ibn
               Dāʾud as cited by Husik, Medieval Jewish Philosophy, p. 203.</note>
            <note xml:id="n63-4">Cf. Corpus Hermeticum I §31: ἅγιος εἶ ὁ πάσης δυνάμεως ἰσχυρότερος;
               and the tradition in the Introduction, p. XXVII, where it is defended to meditate
               upon God, because we do not possess His power.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-1">The expression is also in Abū Ṭālib I, 100:
               <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-2">Corpus Hermeticum XIII § 7: κατάργησον τοῦ σώματος τὰς αἰσθήσεις
               καὶ ἔσται ἡ γένεσις τῆς θεότητος. Cf. Introduction, p. LXXXI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-3">Introduction, p. CIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-4">Imitatio Christi III, 14 (Opera II, p. 170): de occultis Dei
               judiciis considerandis ne extollamur in bonis. Cf. III, 58 (Opp. II, p. 256): de
               altioribus rebus et occultis judiciis Dei non scrutandis.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-5">Introduction, p. LXXVI sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-6">Introduction, p. XLVIII sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-7">Introduction, p. LXXXI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-8">Introduction, p. C sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-1">Introduction, p. CIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-2">Introduction, p. XCVIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-3">Luke 1,78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-4"> Introduction, p. LXVIII sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-1">1 Cor. 2, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-2">Introduction, p. CIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n67-1">With sentence 29-31 cf. Theology of Aristoteles, pp. 777, 85 sq.,
               89, 104; Introduction, p. XXXV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n67-2">ܫܟܝܪܐ, <choice><sic>litterally</sic><corr>literally</corr></choice>: impure.</note>
            <note xml:id="n67-3">ܕܝ̈ܢܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n67-4">I Cor. 12, 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n67-5">Introduction, p. LXXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n68-1">Introduction, p. LXXXVI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n68-2">This theory which considers the universe as a reflex of God is
               already found in the Corpus Hermeticum I § 31: ἅγιος εἶ οὗ πᾶσα φύσις εἰκὼν ἔφυ. And
               XVIII: τὰ ἐν τοῖς ἐσόπτρποις φαινόμενα σώματα ἀσώματα οὐ δοκεῖ σοι εἶναι; Abū Ṭālib
               says (II, 14): <!--Add Arabic--> and Ibn Gabirol, Fountain of Life (ed. Munk, Memar 5
               § 64) has the following passage: <!-- Add Hebrew --></note>
            <note xml:id="n68-3">This sentence seems to contain a polemical tendency against a
               Muslim tradition: <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n68-4">Cf. above, p. 56.</note>
            <note xml:id="n69-1">Cf. Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh I, 104: <!--Add Arabic--> and Introduction, p.
               XCV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n69-2">Malachi 4, 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n69-3">Cf. the diverging sentence of Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh (I, p. 32):
               <!--Add Arabic--></note>
            <note xml:id="n69-4">ܐܕܫ̈ܐ = ἰδέαι</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-1">This and the following sentences as well as sentence 45 seem to
               have been written under the influence of Muslim atomistic doctrine.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-2">Cf. <!--Add Arabic-->, a term frequently found in Muslim
               philosophers and going back to the Greek γένεσις καὶ φθορά.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-3">Introduction, p. XCVIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-4">I Cor. 12,6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-5">Acts 17, 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71-1">Introduction, p. XLIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71-2">1 Cor. 13, 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71-3">Introduction, p. LXXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n72-1">In Bedjan's text ܚܝܪܗ follows, which is not Cardahi's text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n72-2">Introduction, p. LXXVII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n72-3">James 1, 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n72-4">Cf. above, p. 61.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-1">Introduction, p. XLVIII sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-2">ܣܖ̈ܝܩܐ in Cardahi's text only.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-3">Introduction, p. LXXVI sq. and sentence 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-4">Introduction, p. XXIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-5">All the elements of this sentence are already in the opening
               sentence of the section ‘On the Soul’ in the Theology of Aristoteles, p. 4:
               <!--Add Arabic-->. Cf. further p. 30, 120 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-1">Cf. with this sentence the Theology of Aristoteles, p. 120
               sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-2">= <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-3">Cf. III, 8 and Ethikon IV, 15, 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-4">Introduction, p. LXXVII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-5">Introduction, p. LXXX sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-6">Introduction, p. LXXXI sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-7">Cf. John 4, 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-1">Introduction, p. XCIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-2">Introduction, p. XLIV sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-3">Introduction, p. LXXXIV</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-1">ܙܘܥܐ Introduction, p. LXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-2">Introduction, p. XXVII. These words go back to an Arabic verse
               quoted by Gẖazālī in his Munḳidẖ p. <!--Add Arabic-->, cf. Barbier de Meynard,
               Journal Asiatique VII, 9, p. 63: <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-3">Cf. above, p. 48.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-4">Introduction, p. XLIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-5">Introduction, p. CII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-6">Spiritual youth; cf. Barhebraeus' 'On the youth of the
               mind'.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-7">Introduction, p. XXXVI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-1">Introduction, p. XXXVI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-2">Introduction, p. XLIV sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-3">Introduction, p. LXXVII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-4">Introduction, p. LXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-5">Psalm 143, 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-6">Psalm 17, 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-7">This example is also given by Gẖazālī as a proof of the senses
               being untrustworthy, Munḳidẖ. p. <!--Add Arabic-->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-8">Cf. sentence 73.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-1">Introduction, p. LI sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-2">= <!-- Add Arabic --></note>
            <note xml:id="n78-3">Introduction, p. XLI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-4">So Cardahi's text; Bedjan: ardour.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-5">John 16,13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-6">John 14, 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-7">Scala, Gradus XXX.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-8">Cf. with this sentence the Theology of Aristoteles, p. 156 sq.; De
               Boer, Geschichte der Philosophie im Islam, p. 85.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-9">Introduction, p. LXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n79-1">Introduction, p. CIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n79-2"><choice><sic>Litterally</sic><corr>Literally</corr></choice>: our brother.</note>
            <note xml:id="n79-3">Introduction, p. XCVIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n79-4">Introduction, p. XXIII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n79-5">Introduction, p. XLI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n79-6">Introduction, p. LXIV sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n79-7">Cf. Plotinus, Enneades V, 5 § 8: διὸ οὐ χρὴ διώκειν, ἀλλ’ ἡσυχῇ
               μένειν ἕως ἂν φανῇ παρασκευάσαντα ἕαυτον θεατὴν εἶναι ὥσπερ ὀφθαλμὸς ἀνατολὰς ἡλίου
               περιμένει, ὁ δὲ ὑπερφανεῖς τοῦ ὁρίζοντος ἐξ ὠκεανοῦ φασὶν οἱ ποιηταὶ ἔδωκεν ἕαυτον
               θεάσασθαι τοῖς ὄμμασιν.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-1">The dominion of the Initiated over other beings is expressed by Ibn
               ʿAṭāʾallāh (II, 68) in this way: <!--Add Arabic-->. And his commentator relates:
               <!--Add Arabic-->, with which may be compared the other stories he tells. The subject
               goes back to Christian and neo-Pythagorean examples. Jamblichus, Vita Pythagorae, p.
               46 and Porphyry in his biography of the master, p. 31, relate that a bear which was
               of constant harm to the inhabitants of the place, was tamed by Pythagoras who stroked
               her and conjured her not to touch living beings any more; then she vanished in the
               mountains and was never seen again.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-2">John 4, 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-3">Introduction, p. XCVIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-4">Introduction, p. XXIII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n81-1">Matth. 13, 4 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n81-2">Matth. 13, 32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n81-3">John 3, 27.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
