<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en">Select Chapters of the Ethikon of
               <persName>Barhebraeus</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR cleaning and initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus">Evangelos
                  Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <title>Bar Hebraeus's Book of the Dove Together with some chapters from his
                  Ethikon</title>, translated by A. J. Wensinck, Leyden: E. J. Brill, 1919. </p>
            <p>Published in 1919, this translation is in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="title">Ethikon</head>
         <pb n="85"/>
         <div type="chapter" n="4.15">
            <head>Book IV, Chapter XV</head>
            <head>On the Love of God</head>
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>Section the First</head>
               <head>Sayings of the Fathers concerning the Love unto God</head>
               <p><persName>Aba Amon of <placeName>Nitria</placeName></persName> went to
                     <persName>Aba Antonius</persName> and said to him: I see, that my labour is
                  more than yours, how is it that<pb type="external" n="474"/> your name has more
                  splendour among men than mine? <persName>Aba Antonius</persName> answered: This is
                  because I love <persName>our Lord</persName> more than you.</p>
               <p>The holy <persName>Basilius</persName>: The love of benefactors is more than
                  natural love. This is not only the case with men, but also with all animals. For
                  the ox knoweth his owner and the ass his master's crib.[#n85-1] If we strive
                  strenuously to repay love, which has not been taught us, to our benefactors, what
                  word can repay the bounties of God unto us, as they deserve? They are innumerable
                  and in their multitude so praiseworthy, that one of them is sufficient to claim
                  all remunerations which we are able to give. Sunrise namely, the circumambulation
                  of the moon, the mixture of the air, the variation of the times, the water of the
                  clouds, all that comes forth from the earth and the sea, all sorts of animals
                  which are appointed to serve our <pb n="86"/>life,—to be silent on all these would
                  be absolutely impossible, even if we were willing to be so. And to utter our
                  thanksgivings, as it would be truly becoming, is beyond our power. But He is so
                  good as not even to expect from us any reward, but it is sufficient for Him, if in
                  view of all these bounties we only love Him.</p>
               <pb type="external" n="475"/>
               <p><persName>Aba Euagrius</persName>: If anyone is accomplished in the love of God,
                  he is a drunken[#n86-1] man. He is constantly captivated by the love of his Lord,
                  so that he does not see this world, but his thoughts abide continually in heaven.
                  Blessed he who has been deemed worthy of this.</p>
               <p>The same: If a man is gifted with grace or with the gift of prophecy, or works
                  forces or signs, but has not reached the complete love of God—if he will sleep a
                  little, Satan will quickly throw him down, for he is still a child and living with
                  fear.</p>
               <p><persName>John de Dalyata</persName>: Those in whom has shone Thy love, puerile,
                  not as in the Initiated, have rejected and cast away family and race and all
                  bodily love, and have alienated themselves from all, in order to run, naked, to
                  attain Thy holy love. And they have turned away their faces from what they
                  possessed, without seeing that which they were going to possess. But what they
                  search, they know not yet. For they are not acquainted with Him they are running
                  to attain. They are still seeking what belongs to Him, without being aware that He
                  will give Himself to them.</p>
               <p><persName>Mar Isaac</persName>: The soul that loves God, has its rest in Him only.
                  First loosen from yourself the outward bonds, then strive to tie your heart to
                  God. When the child has been weaned <pb type="external" n="476"/>from milk, bread
                  is given it as food. A man, who wishes to excel in [knowledge of] divine things,
                  first weans himself from the world, as a babe is weaned from its mother's
                  breasts.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="87"/>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>Section the Second</head>
               <head>The Definition of Love, its Divisions and its Causes</head>
               <p>Love is the tendency of the soul towards communion with some object which it
                  understands; for who does not understand the nature of <choice>
                     <sic>some thing</sic>
                     <corr>something</corr>
                  </choice> or its character, will not long after establishing communion with it or
                  after being in communion with it.[#n87-1]</p>
               <p>The object loved is either to be attained with the sense of the eye, as outward
                  beauty; or with the smell, as perfumes; or with the ear, as sweet melodies; or
                  with taste, as delicious food or drink; or with touch as touching soft
                  objects.[#n87-2] Or it is to be attained with the rational power in us, as the
                  delight which happens to us by the knowledge of what was unknown to
                  us.[#n87-3]</p>
               <p>That the love of this latter enjoyment is natural, appears from the fact, that
                  every man is inclined to listen to novel tales, and desirous to scrutinize the
                  rumours concerning other people.</p>
               <p>Wisdom[#n87-4] knows five causes of love. The first is the continuation of being
                  and the existence of the self. For all beings naturally long after maintaining
                  their self. Therefore man loves his own person more than what is outside it. He
                  occupies himself with the health of his limbs and the opulence of his possessions,
                  because his maintenance depends upon them. He loves also his children, because
                  they are the seed that has grown in his earth, also his sprout brought forth by
                  his trunk.</p>
               <pb type="external" n="477"/>
               <pb n="88"/>
               <p>The second is that of doing well. As it has been said: By the water of the love of
                  those who do well, souls are modelled.[#n88-1] So, by the natural power which has
                  been implanted in us, we form, by our will, a beautiful thought unto our
                  benefactors.</p>
               <p>The third is that of outward beauty. That it is loved for its own sake and not for
                  any other's,[#n88-2] is known from the fact, that by the sight alone of glorious
                  trees and beautiful flowers, and a current of clear and pure water, the soul is
                  gladdened and we exult with joy, the senses rejoice and the limbs leap up, though
                  no food or drink is to be acquired from these things.[#n88-3]</p>
               <p>The fourth is that of inward beauty. That the beautiful is not attained by the
                  eyes only, is known from the fact, that a voice is also called beautiful,[#n88-4]
                  though it is clear that sight has no part in it. So the beauty of a thing is its
                  intrinsic perfection when this happens to it by any influence. Therefore, when it
                  acquires perfection in all points, the more beautiful it will be, and so it is
                  said to be. If it acquires only partial perfection, its beauty is measured by it.
                  And on account of this sort of beauty, teachings are liked, and character[#n88-5]
                  and excellent customs[#n88-6] are loved. On account of it, further, we love
                  prophets and apostles, Fathers and teachers, true and exquisite
                  philosophers,[#n88-7] because their perfections are not hidden from us, though
                  invisible to us and without connection with us.</p>
               <pb type="external" n="478"/>
               <p>The fifth is that of a hidden consanguinity and a secret resemblance, which is the
                  peculiar bond between some men, as we have shown in the chapter on the love of the
                  brethren.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="89"/>
            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>Section the Third[#n89-1]</head>
               <head>On the Love of God as being justified in view of all Causes mentioned</head>
               <p>When we scrutinize the five causes of love which we have enumerated in our
                  foregoing section, we find that God alone possesses them all; what is outside Him,
                  only a part of them, not the whole. And on account of this question and its
                  affirmative answer the thoughts of those are to be reprehended, who are not able
                  to love God, because they are not acquainted with His name.</p>
               <p>The first cause (love of man, his maintenance and his person) is known to justify
                  the love of God, because every man who is acquainted with his own nature and with
                  the power of Him, who has created him, will know that without his God he has no
                  strength to remain standing during one moment. Therefore, if the love of his self
                  is necessary to him, the love of Him, in whose hand his self is, must be even more
                  necessary to him.[#n89-2]</p>
               <p>The second cause, doing well, justifies all creatures, endowed with mind, in
                  loving nothing excepted the creator, because He alone is their natural benefactor;
                  and all that is besides Him, is only an intermediary and a mediator, by whom good
                  is conducted from the Good one.</p>
               <p>He, for instance, who gives alms and makes a meal and the<pb type="external"
                     n="479"/> like, spends his wealth in view of the remuneration he will acquire
                  here or there, so he does well to others in order to acquire good for himself. And
                  because his benefactor and that of the man mentioned is really God, who does not
                  expect <pb n="90"/>any remuneration, the Initiated will not hesitate to love Him
                  alone, with all his heart, with all his soul and with all his strength.</p>
               <p>The third cause, that of outward beauty, though only found with corporeal beings,
                  not with incorporeal, still, to the saints, pure in heart,[#n90-1] who have not
                  yet been loosened from the bonds of the body, the Good one will show Himself, when
                  He appears with majesty in such a form that His beauty excells all other beauty:
                  in a habit shining like snow, with hair like pure wool, on a flaming throne with
                  radiating wheels, the chariot with four sides on which He is pompously borne; a
                  thousand thousands of powers, and ten thousand myriads of angels stand before Him,
                  repeating three times and redoubling the sanctifications which are becoming to
                  Him, though not sufficient. Therefore he who has been deemed worthy to cast a
                  short glance on such things, looking through the crevice of the gate, will
                  resecate and reject all race and family and become a stranger to all other love,
                  that, on swift wings, he may fly to reach the love of the amazing beauty. Also the
                  use of food is estimated superfluous by him, because the sight of his Lord
                  fulfills his need.</p>
               <p>The fourth cause, that of inward beauty, is that which <pb type="external" n="480"
                  />is found with the blessed prophets, apostles and the other perfect. We see that
                  a beauty like this has three causes, on account of which it is loved.[#n90-2] The
                  first is their profound knowledge of the divine mysteries. The second is their
                  having power to show the way, without erring, to the common people. The third is
                  their being adorned with the property of accepting excellent qualities and of
                  pushing away bad ones. And as the knowledge of all creatures is ignorance with
                  God, and their wisdom folly, and their strength exhaustion as compared with His
                  and all their righteousness is as the cloth of an unclean woman before Him,
                  according to the opinion <pb n="91"/>of <persName>Isaiah</persName>—how should not
                  the Initiated love Him more than them? And if this is the case with the beautiful,
                  what love can be attributed by the intelligent to those who are not beautiful? The
                  fifth cause, that of a hidden consanguinity and a secret likeness between God and
                  mankind, is found to be a more intrinsic one, as is justified by the divine word,
                  which shows man to have been created in the image of God. Therefore, if the nature
                  of all beings, animated and inanimated, longs after what resembles Him, wretched
                  is the man who, in love of his Lord who has honoured him with His image, is
                  inferior to inanimate and irrational beings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
               <head>Section the Fourth</head>
               <head>On the Delight of the Knowledge of God being greater than any other
                  Delight[#n91-1]</head>
               <p>It is clear that delight is caused by attaining a delicious thing.[#n91-2] That
                  the living possess such powers of attaining in<pb type="external" n="481"/>
                  multitude, is likewise known.[#n91-3] Therefore they get peculiar delight
                  according to the power of attainment they possess.[#n91-4] And since the adorable
                  creator has raised the nature of poor man above the dunghill of the irrational
                  beings,[#n91-5] and by the recognizing[#n91-6] soul, with which He has endowed
                  him, has made him sit among the grandees of spiritual people, He has made <pb
                     n="92"/>him, by the delight of this exalted knowledge, a fellow and colleague
                  of the angels. And because, in accordance with the greatness of the beauty of the
                  recognized, knowledge becomes more opulent and delight more abundant, anyone who
                  knows that among all beings there is none more admirable and amazing, more exalted
                  and wonderful, more complete and perfect than the Lord and the God of the beings,
                  it is not possible to deny that the knowledge of the greatness of the Highest, is
                  higher than all other knowledge, and that the delight, caused by the knowledge of
                  the mysteries of His wisdom, is more desirable and exalted than any other delight.
                  As <persName>Euagrius</persName> the Great says: If among things to be tasted,
                  there is none sweeter than honey and honeycomb and the knowledge of God is much
                  sweeter than these, it is clear that nothing among all things on the earth gives a
                  delight to the soul as the knowledge of God does.</p>
               <p>And another Initiated has said: If any one's mind has been captivated by the
                  beauty of the lord of the universe, it is impossible that it should be captivated
                  anymore by the love of anything in the world. If anyone's mind has been bound <pb
                     type="external" n="482"/>by care for God, it never will be bound by passing
                  care. There is nobody who has found God and become acquainted with Him, without
                  having forgotten the world wholly. Another has said: When the mind has been salted
                  in the sea of God's love, it will not be troubled after having reached the harbour
                  of life. If it has stripped off the habit of the servants of the desire of matter,
                  it has acquired its warrant of liberty, which never will be rent asunder.[#n92-1]
                  The same has said: When my lips serve Thy honoured name when reciting, it begins
                  to show to the mind, Thy captive, the wonder of my reciting Psalms. My lords have
                  become my servants, since Thou hast become my lord; and since they know this, they
                  have absolutely not further attacked me.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="93"/>
            <div type="section" n="5">
               <head>Section the Fifth</head>
               <head>On the Delight of the Knowledge of God which happens after rather than before
                  Departure</head>
               <p>Things to be attained are of two kinds, sensual and intellectual.[#n93-1] Sensual
                  things are again of two classes; the first is that of things, which, being far
                  off, become sensual by secondary imagination; the second is that of things, which,
                  being near, become really sensual by sight, hearing and the other senses. In the
                  same way intellectual things are of two classes; the first is that of things,
                  which, being far off, become intellectual in this world, but dimly; the other is
                  that of things, which, being near, become really intellectual in the spiritual
                  world. As,[#n93-2] by shutting the eyelids, the seeing is shut off from the seen,
                  in the same way, the soul, as long as it is included within the body, is precluded
                  from beholding intellectual things in their essence; as God said to
                     <persName>Moses</persName>: Thou<pb type="external" n="483"/> [cannot
                  not](cannot) see my face: for there shall no man see me and live.[#n93-3] This
                  means: when thou hast departed this body, then thou wilt see . The same is
                  expressed by the divine apostle <persName>Paul</persName>, saying: For now we see
                  as through a glass, darkly, but then face to face: now I know in part, but then I
                  shall know even as also I am known.[#n93-4] And the holy <persName>Gregorius
                     Theologus</persName> says: I am convinced of the words of the sages: <pb n="94"
                  />Every good and God-loving soul, as soon as it will have been loosened from the
                  body to which it was bound and have been liberated from this world, will be
                  abiding at once in the apperception and the contemplation of the good which
                  awaited it; because that which obscured its vision, has been purified away and put
                  aside. Else I should not know that it is becoming to say: this amazing delight is
                  delicious and exuberating.[#n94-1]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
               <head>Section the Sixth</head>
               <head>On the Causes corroborating the Love of God[#n94-2]</head>
               <p>It must be known, that no single believing heart is devoid of the root of the love
                  of God. But as to the growth of the tree of the love of God, the splendour of its
                  flowers and the burden of its fruits, of these things many faithful are devoid.
                  According to the Initiated, there are two causes by which the root of love sprouts
                  from the heart of the righteous as a palm and its sprigs and twigs shoot forth as
                  the cedars of <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>. The first is,[#n94-3] that man turns
                  his face away from <pb type="external" n="484"/>all that is on the earth, and
                  hates all desire, seeking and desiring the One only, growing in hope and belief,
                  becoming strong in abstention and patience. So, while his inner being[#n94-4] is
                  cleansed, his mind is purified, he becomes one of the pure in heart,[#n94-5] that
                  see God. And by this sight, the fire of love is kindled. The second is,[#n94-6]
                  that man proceeds on and becomes strong in the knowledge of God,[#n94-7] being
                  illuminated[#n94-8] <pb n="95"/>and instructed by it, after the purification of
                  the heart from impure passions.[#n95-1] For the knowledge of God in a pure soul
                  resembles the pure seed thrown on good ground. And from the seed of knowledge love
                  is born and grows up.</p>
               <p>The knowledge of God is acquired in a twofold wise; either the creator is known
                  first, then, through Him the creatures. Or the creatures are recognized first,
                  then, from them, the mind is exalted towards Him.[#n95-2] Though the first way is
                  difficult and steep and even the athletes of the knowing are scarcely able to go
                  it, it is more essential, high and exalted. One of the Initiated has described it
                  with these words: Through my God I have known my God; and, but for my God, I would
                  not have known my God.[#n95-3] Another has said: I knew before the worlds. For His
                  knowledge, which has called the worlds into existence, has dawned in my mind, and
                  has founded my knowledge, before the universe came into existence. The same has
                  said: I knew <persName>Christ</persName> before I knew myself.<pb type="external"
                     n="485"/> The knowledge of Him has preceded in me the knowledge of what has
                  come into existence by His spirit. The truth of this is mysteriously affirmed by
                  the divine <persName>David</persName>, in this word: With Thee is the fountain of
                  life: in Thy light we see light.[#n95-4]</p>
               <p>It is clear, that the second way is easy and everyone who is zealous will be able
                  to use it, even if he be weak and dark of mind. It is described by the same
                     <persName>Psalmist</persName> with the words: The heavens declare the glory of
                  God[#n95-5] etc.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="96"/>
            <div type="section" n="7">
               <head>Section the Seventh</head>
               <head>On the different Ranks of those who love God[#n96-1]</head>
               <p>It has already been shown that the knowledge of God is the cause of His
                  love.[#n96-2] Therefore, in accordance with knowledge being more or less, love is
                  more or less.[#n96-3] And because men have set up opinions contrary to truth,
                  concerning the denominations of God they found in the holy scriptures, some of
                  them have believed in these denominations as they have accepted them from their
                  teachers, in the way of simple tradition, without their distinction. But others,
                  though few, have been deemed worthy of mastering the height of essential
                  knowledge, through the good gift, with which they have been endowed in fulness
                  from above, by the father of lights.[#n96-4] There are found three ranks of those
                  who love God.</p>
               <p>The first, the lowest, is that of heretics who do not glorify the truth in truth.
                  They are those of the left hand.[#n96-5]</p>
               <pb type="external" n="486"/>
               <p>The second, the middle one, is that of the simple faithful. Though they belong to
                  the lambs, those of the right hand, yet, in accordance with their simple
                  knowledge, their love is superficial. And because it has no firm root in their
                  heart, they are in danger of becoming rotten.[#n96-6]</p>
               <p>The third, the highest, is that of the Initiated, who are even higher than those
                  of the right hand. Because they know the good one as He is, and they are not
                  stained with conflicting thoughts and they are really elevated above traditional
                  blindness, neither fire nor sword is able to separate them from the love of their
                  Lord.[#n96-7]</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="97"/>
            <div type="section" n="8">
               <head>Section the Eighth</head>
               <head>Why the Creatures do not know the Creator[#n97-1]</head>
               <p>That the adorable God is more manifest and clear than any of the existing
                  things,[#n97-2] is known from the fact[#n97-3] that there is no part of the world
                  that does not hear a sign of its maker. This is mysteriously denoted by
                     <persName>David</persName> the harpist when he says: There is no speech nor
                  language where their voice is not heard.[#n97-4] This proves that the knowledge of
                  God is necessary and natural to us like the other kinds of necessary
                  knowledge.[#n97-5] As all that is unknown to us, is either hidden from us on
                  account of its deep darkness, or because our mind shrinks from observing it on
                  account of its being too manifest[#n97-6]—as our eye shrinks from looking at the
                  sun—so the last reason hinders us from knowing God, as has been<pb type="external"
                     n="487"/> taught by the great <persName>Dionysius the Areopagite</persName>,
                  who says: The divine cloud is the inaccessible light, wherein God is said to
                  abide.[#n97-7] And though He is, He is invisible because of His being illuminated
                  to a high degree. This proves that our mind, as compared with essential
                  light,[#n97-8] is like the bat as compared <pb n="98"/>with this eradiated light.
                  Therefore, just as the bat would be able to look into eradiated light, if it
                  possessed the visual power of man, so man would be able to look towards essential
                  light, if he possessed the mind of an angel. Concerning the fact that psychic eye
                  is blinded by the manifestation of God,[#n98-1] when it is illuminated by it, the
                  poet says: Thou art manifest and clear, o my Lord, much more than the sun at
                  midday; Thou art not hidden but from the blind who do not see the moon. At Thy
                  splendour the mind of every intelligent being is astonished and amazed, whereas
                  the eye that is not blinded by Thee, has no light.[#n98-2] And in the same metre:
                  If light makes manifest all visible things, detecting the veil that is spread over
                  their faces, how should it be becoming for the eye, which is accustomed to matter,
                  to see Him, who is concealed and withheld from the eyes by light?.[#n98-3]</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="99"/>
            <div type="section" n="9">
               <head>Section the Ninth</head>
               <head>On the Manners in which the Soul longs after God</head>
               <p>It is known that longing necessarily follows love. Everyone, therefore, who loves
                  God, will necessarily desire to see Him.[#n99-1]<pb type="external" n="488"/>
                  Among bodily friends the lover longs after his beloved in a twofold wise. When the
                  beloved is absent and the image of his beauty is recollected, the lover desires to
                  see him, that his joy may be complete by meeting the beloved.[#n99-2] Or, when the
                  beloved is near, but his face is only visible to his friend, while his other
                  inward beauties, which are shown in intercourse, are hidden, the lover longs after
                  being consoled also by the sight of what is hidden.[#n99-3] In the same way the
                  Initiated are necessarily acquainted with these two sorts of longing, in view of
                  the love of their Lord.[#n99-4] With the first, because that which they see here
                  of the beauty of the Lord in revelations and visions, shows its magnificence as it
                  were from behind an outspread veil.[#n99-5] Therefore they long after seeing Him
                  eye to eye and with <persName>David</persName> they sing: My soul thirsteth for
                  Thee, the living God; when shall I come and appear before <pb n="100"/>
                  Thee[#n100-1]? With the second manner of longing, because the ways of divine
                  perfection are indefinite and endless.[#n100-2] And it is not unknown to the
                  Initiated that what he has attained in respect of them, is much less than what he
                  has not attained. Therefore he longs constantly after acquiring what he has not
                  acquired.[#n100-3] And so a right spirit is frequently renewed[#n100-4] within
                  them. It is becoming to know that the former kind of longing is accomplished and
                  vanishing in the spiritual world; <pb type="external" n="489"/>because there the
                  Initiated meets his beloved.[#n100-5] The second kind cannot be imagined as
                  reaching perfection because the exalted and glorious beauties of the Lord of the
                  universe are indefinite.[#n100-6] Therefore, every desire which reaches its aim,
                  is succeeded anew by another one; and every longing which comes to perfection is
                  followed by a new one at its heels. Therefore the Initiated call such a longing
                  ‘heel’; and those who stand aloof call it concatenation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
               <head>Section the Tenth</head>
               <head>On the distinctive Marks of those who love God[#n100-7]</head>
               <p>There are ten distinctive marks which are symptoms of the Initiated's love of
                  God.</p>
               <pb n="101"/>
               <p>The first[#n101-1] is, that he longs after seeing his Lord. And because essential
                  seeing takes place only after departure from this life, it is necessary for him
                  who seeks his Lord, to resemble <persName>Paul</persName> and like him to desire
                  to depart, in order to be with <persName>Christ</persName>.[#n101-2] The
                  second[#n101-3] is, that he does not fulfill his own will, but that of his Lord,
                  as the true one has said: If ye love me, keep my commandments.[#n101-4] The third
                  is, that he hates the whole world in order to possess the One only; as we have
                  found in some Hebrew[#n101-5] book: When <persName>Joseph</persName> had become
                  ruler in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, the wife of his lord, who had slandered
                  him, believed in God. And when her husband was dead, <persName>Joseph</persName>
                  sought to marry her; but she would not. When her kindred asked her: where is now
                  all your love of him, she answered: the love of him burned in me, before I knew
                  his Lord. But now that I know Him, the love of Him burns in me, and I care no
                  longer for the love of His servant.[#n101-6] The fourth[#n101-7] is that the lips
                  constantly administer the name of<pb type="external" n="490"/> his Lord. For every
                  one who loves something, often thinks of it and his tongue does not cease to
                  mention it; as <persName>David</persName> who loved the law of his Lord meditated
                  upon it the whole day. The fifth[#n101-8] is, that he finds consolation in
                  solitude and the abode in the small cell, rejecting the sight of the world, and
                  hating intercourse and speech. Because, as <persName>Mar Isaac</persName> says,
                  the consummation of excellency is lonely intercourse, and <pb n="102"/>the quiet
                  dwelling of the mind upon God. The sixth[#n102-1] is that he is not spiteful on
                  account of the worldly things which escape him, but that he regrets, on the
                  contrary, every hour he passes in idleness. The seventh[#n102-2] is that he finds
                  enjoyment in the labours of asceticism, though they be heavy and wearying; as that
                  brother, concerning whom the excellent Master[#n102-3] <persName>John de
                     Dalyata</persName> tells, that he, in the time of the first heat of love, when
                  grace kindled his heart with the love of God, was nightly standing naked, during
                  four years, also in wintertime, in snow, rain and ice. In the first year the blood
                  dried up in his limbs and life vanished from his body; then he no longer perceived
                  the cold even when he buried himself naked in the snow; because his body was like
                  fire. The eighth[#n102-4] is that he is full of mercy towards the good, and
                  scornful and severe against the bad;[#n102-5] as also his Lord is just and loving
                  justness and His face looks towards <pb type="external" n="491"/>uprightness, but
                  His soul hates the unjust and those who love unjustness. The ninth is that he
                  prays constantly, that his love may not abate and his gifts may not diminish. For,
                  as an Initiated[#n102-6] has said: he whose yesterday that has passed, is better
                  than to-day which is present, he is cursed. And he whose days are equal, he is
                  devoid of excellency. But he whose end is better than his beginnings, he is wise.
                  The tenth[#n102-7] is that he conceals his love as much as he can, though the
                  signs thereof are not concealed in him.</p>
               <pb n="103"/>
               <p>It has been said: Two brethren had fallen into a severe illness in the desert.
                  When the fellow brethren asked the former: what do you think of yourself, he
                  answered: he who is aware of his plague does not love Him. When they asked the
                  latter: how are you? he answered: he who does not find enjoyment in his plague,
                  does not love Him. When their master heard their words he said: but I say: he who
                  shows his love, does not love Him.[#n103-1] And from that time the brethren began
                  to conceal their excellence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
               <head>Section the Eleventh</head>
               <head>On Consolation in God and Freedom of Speech with Him[#n103-2]</head>
               <p>The joy and the gladness which happen to the Initiated on account of the multitude
                  of divine revelations[#n103-3] and the frequency of spiritual visions, is called
                  consolation in God. When this consolation has taken hold of the enviable, the
                  friend of God, he is only content with quiet solitude[#n103-4] and he cannot<pb
                     type="external" n="492"/> bear even the sound of a leaf.[#n103-5] Such solitude
                  is called by the teachers a solitude which makes gods;[#n103-6] for through it the
                  mind acquires complete unification and perfect mingling with God, and vision and
                  knowledge of Him, whose glory is exalted over the world, without visible vision
                  and without knowable knowledge. Therefore, he who has been deemed worthy of this
                  grace, will shut his eyes before all the beauties of the creatures and close his
                  ears before every human sound <pb n="104"/>and restrain his senses from all cares
                  of passions. And he will be on his guard that evil may not assail him, and God may
                  not pass him. And he will not desist nor take rest from caring for God. From the
                  so called consolation freedom of speech is born. Though it is bad, because of the
                  boldness which accompanies it, and, by the sages, called a scorching wind, still,
                  when it is practised by those who are experienced in paracletic consolations in
                  God, it is not to be rejected. This freedom of speech is further made complete
                  when God sends the spirit of His son into the hearts of the perfect, the spirit
                  that calls Aba, Our Father, as <persName>Paul</persName>, the blessed, says. When
                  the spirit of the son dwells in the perfect, it speaks through him, as through the
                  son of God, to the father. And here is no human weakness, nor prayer, nor
                  beseeching, nor recollection of things of this world or of things to come. But the
                  son of God knows himself in a divine way, and as the son with his father, so <pb
                     type="external" n="493"/>he speaks freely with God. And then he becomes as
                  receiving all prayers, not as one who prays, as answering all questions, not as
                  one who asks,[#n104-1] because the rich one, his Father, has given him power over
                  His riches and he has become the same as the person who dwells within him. And
                  while he neither knows himself nor any thing,[#n104-2] he cries many times: Aba,
                  my father, and other bold utterances, which it is not allowed to write down and to
                  embody in paper.[#n104-3] Some Initiated, for instance, have used even trials, in
                  bold freedom of speech. As the excellent <persName>Job</persName>, who disputed
                  with his Lord as a man with his fellow-man, saying: Am I a sea, or a whale, that
                  Thou settest a watch over me[#n104-4]? Wilt Thou break a leaf driven to and fro?
                  and wilt Thou pursue the dry stubble[#n104-5]? When I say: Thou shalt comfort me,
                  then Thou terrifiest me through <pb n="105"/>visions.[#n105-1] If there were an
                  umpire between us, that might lay his hand on our mouth[#n105-2]! with other
                  sayings of the same kind. Some have escaped danger by them; for grace does not
                  bear everyman in the same way.[#n105-3] <persName>Saul</persName>, for instance,
                  was rejected from the royal rank and the flame of prophecy, being hated because he
                  had shown mercy towards <persName>Agag</persName> the king of the Amalekites and
                  he had not slain him; and he had spared the beauty of the oxen and lambs and he
                  had not destroyed them. Whereas <persName>David</persName> had stained himself
                  with bad adultery and spilt the innocent blood of <persName>Uriya</persName> the
                  Hittite; but as soon as he said: I have sinned before the Lord, through
                     <persName>Nathan</persName> it was said to him: The Lord also hath put away thy
                  sin, thou shalt not die.[#n105-4]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
               <head>Section the Twelfth</head>
               <pb type="external" n="494"/>
               <head>On the Troubles the Initiated bear through the Love of God[#n105-5]</head>
               <p>The exoteric sages define philosophy as meditation upon death. With this the
                  esoteric Initiated concord, saying: Excellence is meditation upon death, for the
                  sake of the love of God; namely: this is excellence, to bear troubles for the sake
                  of the love of God. And with words, broad and long, they have proved this, saying:
                  He who is clad with zeal on the way of excellence, does not know that he is
                  invested with a body, but he seems to be incorporeal in view of all the
                  difficulties. Even to renunciate life will be light to him and not too burdensome.
                  So the deliberations of him, whose soul has received the taste of divine
                  consolation, will be borne by love of Him at all times, and his heart will
                  constantly be elevated[#n105-6] by <pb n="106"/>recollection of Him. And he is
                  already, as it were, in the kingdom of heaven, and it is as if he does not abide
                  on the earth. And continually the word of <persName>the apostle</persName> is
                  vivid in his heart: <choice>
                     <sic>Wat</sic>
                     <corr>What</corr>
                  </choice> shall separate me from the love of <persName>Christ</persName>? shall
                  tribulations or persecutions, or sword, or nakedness[#n106-1]? And he thinks also
                  further, with <persName>Paul</persName>: For I am persuaded that neither death,
                  nor life, nor things present with their terrors, nor things to come with their
                  glory, nor any other creature shall be able to separate us from the love of my
                  Lord.[#n106-2] The Initiated bear oppressions for two reasons:[#n106-3] either
                  they do not perceive them, because they burn with love of their Lord. As
                     <persName>Aba Benjamin</persName>, who healed many who were swollen and
                  hydropsic, without thinking of his being swollen and hydropsic himself. When he
                  was asked concerning this, he said: my brother, the blow from the beloved one
                  gives no pain. Or they bear them because they are complying with the will of their
                  beloved, when He will put them to trial. As in the case of the excellent
                     <persName>Job</persName>, who endured innumerable blows without murmuring. It
                  is also said, that one of the faithful, during the persecution of the pagan
                  emperor <persName>Maximinos</persName> was beaten with a thousand blows without
                  crying or weeping. When some one said to him: Why have you not cried? he answered:
                  I saw <persName>Christ</persName>, for whose sake I was beaten, standing before me
                  and looking at me, while he admonished me not to weep.</p>
               <p>Though this strenuous patient one was great, yet he was not so great as
                     <persName>Stephanus</persName>, the first deacon. For this firstborn of martyrs
                  did not only refrain from shrieking, but when dying he prayed for those who stoned
                  him, who were the cause of his being crowned with martyrdom.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="107"/>
            <div type="section" n="13">
               <head>Section the Thirteenth</head>
               <head>On the Stages of the Initiated concerning their Love</head>
               <p>The holy solitaries teach that there are three measures, namely states of the
                  Initiated concerning the growth of their love: the first, the middle, and the
                  third, the last one being<pb type="external" n="496"/> that of accomplishment. And
                  as they have found that at any of the three there are peculiar experiences, they
                  have taught us concerning them. Therefore, borrowing their words, we give
                  concerning any of them a passage as short as possible. The first state.[#n107-1]
                  When, in the beginning, grace casts a small spark of the love of the Lord in the
                  heart of the novice, it sows in him great humbleness, so that he thinks himself
                  dust and ash, and remembering his trespasses he sheds tears of sorrow and joy, of
                  sorrow, because of his stains; of joy, because grace has born and sustained him
                  like a compassionate mother. Then it makes reciting of Psalms and frequent bending
                  of the knees sweet to his heart and it gives him delight during his long service;
                  and it makes him to remember the saints and incites him to imitate their labours.
                  Then it incites him to love deeds which serve to give rest to his brethren, and
                  pity towards the oppressed, and serving the sick. It gives him silence and
                  solitude in order to cut off the passionate inclinations[#n107-2] in his heart.
                  Some solitaries are, on account of their care, made perfect by grace in all these
                  things, others in some only. But from time to time it withdraws from the solitary
                  its workings, in order that he may be chastised by trials and become exercised;
                  then troubles and evil passions direct their power against him. But if he be
                  cautious against trespassing, grace will visit him anew with consolations, much
                  more <pb n="108"/><pb type="external" n="497"/>profitable and elevated than the
                  former ones, because it exercises him and does not withdraw from him. In this
                  state the novice is in great need of a leader, because many are brought to fall by
                  this trial and stray away from the place they occupy.</p>
               <p>The middle state.[#n108-1] After its workings of the former kind, grace changes
                  its influences upon the soul, purifies and sanctifies it and makes it apt for
                  spiritual sight and the receiving of revelations. In the first place it enlightens
                  the intellect by distinction of the creatures. Then the mind will be brought to
                  giving up the distraction of deliberations and be fascinated by the creator only.
                  And the intellect of the Initiated will meditate upon the highest one, to such a
                  degree that, when being awake he will seem to be asleep, and, when sleeping he
                  will be thought to be awake.[#n108-2] And when he has passed a space of time with
                  such meditations, his Lord will show Himself to him. But only as a flash of
                  lightning[#n108-3] which bursts forth and disappears; or as a star which of a
                  sudden is covered by a cloud. This happens especially during prayer; so that sight
                  often breaks off his service and stupefies him. Then his spirit is tormented
                  continually[#n108-4] by hot inclinations[#n108-5] and the love of his Lord burns
                  in his heart as the fire in a furnace seven times fiercer than it is
                  wont,[#n108-6] so that his soul is enflamed, his limbs are relaxed and he falls on
                  the ground. Then he rises again and prepares himself for vision and it is not
                  withheld from him; but he begins to lengthen the duration [of this state] from day
                  to day, and his mind is enlightened[#n108-6] so as to see hidden things and
                  gradually he becomes familiar[#n108-8] with hidden mysteries and <pb n="109"
                  />unspeakable visions. And the feverish inclination of the first<pb
                     type="external" n="109"/> state is changing into calmness and accomplished
                  love.</p>
               <p>The state of accomplishment.[#n109-1] From here, then, begins the entrance into
                  the bridechamber,[#n109-2] and abiding in the apartment and lying down in the room
                  and intercourse with Him,[#n109-3] who appeared to the eye like a flash of
                  lightning, but at whom the mind is gazing now peacefully.[#n109-4] The inhabitants
                  of that place are enlightened by the sight of the beauty of the king, with a light
                  not mingled with a reminiscence of darkness. There to the soul its natural
                  beauty[#n109-5] is revealed and it sees itself as it is, namely in the likeness of
                  its creator. And from sight to sight it is changed, and by the essential
                  light,[#n109-6] with which the universe is clad and which penetrates the
                  universe,[#n109-7] it beholds without impediment all the ends of the creation and
                  farther, and is elevated above all heavens.[#n109-8] And as the bodily eye, by the
                  created light, sees the bodily objects, so the eye of the mind, by the uncreated
                  light, sees the angels in their nature. And when the soul is established in the
                  sight of the glory of their classes and their beauties, their harmony and joy, it
                  becomes with them like them. And in a moment it passes towards the cloud of
                  inaccessible light, where God is said to dwell.[#n109-9] And while the face of its
                  Lord is detected before it, it becomes stupefied and is made <pb n="110"/>radiant
                  by the rays of His beauty. And there takes place transition,[#n110-1] which is
                  described by our holy Fathers, so that it is impossible for the soul to return
                  from its delight. And <pb type="external" n="499"/>if its Lord loosened it not
                  from union, it would forget its partner, the body. And when it returns to it, it
                  imparts to the limbs some of the divine fire, which has remained in it, so that
                  they also participate in the enjoyment of the spirit. And when the mind returns
                  again [to the Lord] the body is almost borne along with it, and the soul can
                  scarcely shake it off when it is elevated. And so it ascends[#n110-2] from glory
                  to glory through the Lord, the spirit, and it forgets not only what is here, but
                  also <choice>
                     <sic>its self</sic>
                     <corr>itself</corr>
                  </choice>. And because of the divine light with which it is clad, it sees itself
                  in the likeness of God.[#n110-3] And it does not shun saying, in freedom of
                  speech:[#n110-4] I am in my Father and my Father is in me, and I and the Father
                  are one, together with other things which [#n110-5]perhaps Master
                     <persName>Hierotheos</persName> and the like-venture to interpret.[#n110-5] But
                  concerning these things the Holy Ghost says: There is mystery between me and my
                  housemates, and it warns them to hide such things and not to divulge them, and it
                  does not permit them to scrutinize them, except in personal intercourse[#n110-6]
                  with the housemates.[#n110-7] And this last stage is called by the exoteric sages
                  ‘likeness with God as much as this is possible for man.’</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
               <head>Section the Fourteenth</head>
               <head>On the varying States the Perfect have to go through[#n110-8]</head>
               <p>When the perfect have reached the state of perfection, <pb n="111"/>grace works in
                  them twelve varying states caused by its amazing influence, from their first
                  reaching the apartment till their definite entering the bride-room and their lying
                  with the beloved in the room.[#n111-1]</p>
               <p>These varying states are the following. The first is that <pb type="external"
                     n="500"/>of the baptism of the mind. For as soon as transition[#n111-2] takes
                  place, the mind is baptized in the heart, and deliberation stands motionless, even
                  without stammering glorifications, but silence dominates the inclinations[#n111-3]
                  of the soul and the body. And by the food the mind receives from within, the body
                  is sustained too. With this same baptism <persName>Moses</persName> has been
                  baptized on the top of the mountain. Being in this state, the perfect is not only
                  not able to meet any creature, but he can even not bear the sound of a
                  bird.[#n111-4] The second is that of the influence of distinctions. When the mind
                  has acquired purity of deliberations, it recognizes itself and it distinguishes
                  the height of its rank and the loftiness of its race. And here too it guards
                  silence and it does not permit itself to divagate upon distinctions without it.
                  And when it is overwhelmed by divagation, it forces itself to the reciting of the
                  scriptures and the Psalms and obeisance before the cross. And when it has been
                  strengthened thus, it binds itself within the inner gate of the heart. The third
                  is that of the love of reciting Psalms.[#n111-5] This love burns so strongly in
                  the heart, that even at the time of the meals the mind is occupied with the
                  Psalms. The fourth is that of outbursts of tears. These tears are not caused by
                  compulsion, and the will has no dominion over them. But when the fire of love
                  burns the soul within, the body sheds tears without. The fifth is that of the
                  knowledge of Judgment and of care. And from this <pb n="112"/><pb type="external"
                     n="501"/>understanding there is born in the soul the love of mankind and
                  constant prayer <choice>
                     <sic>in behalf</sic>
                     <corr>on behalf</corr>
                  </choice> of their conversion, because he sees them all as his equals and like
                  himself. In this state there is no righteous and no sinner, no slave and no free
                  man, no circumcision and no foreskin, no man and no woman, but
                     <persName>Christ</persName> appears to be all and in every man. The sixth is
                  that of the emotions of the heart, in which the mind is made radiant by the
                  angelic rays, which are composed of light and fire. Then it burns with desire to
                  be united with the spiritual hosts and it is ardent to be mingled with the orders
                  of fiery beings. The seventh is that of simple[#n112-1] apperception. Here the
                  mind hears the voice of the spiritual beings who glorify with subtle sounds,
                  sounds which cannot be embodied in composed spoken[#n112-2] words and are only to
                  be denoted in intellectual, simple sounds. Of these sounds the new glorification
                  in the new world is made up, and with this glorification the spirit prays, as
                     <persName>Paul</persName> says, for the saints.[#n112-3] The eighth is that of
                  likeness.[#n112-4] In this state the mind is brought to silence; when it sees the
                  True one[#n112-5] eye to eye and it is illuminated by His light and is changed
                  into His likeness. And as the elegant and dense cloud, when it is near the sun
                  receives its light and its form and appears like it, so the pure mind,[#n112-6]
                  even though tied in the dense body, will become like essential light,[#n112-7]
                  when <pb type="external" n="502"/>it has become familiar with it. The ninth is
                  that of becoming like fire. In this state man is kindled by fire, from the sole of
                  his foot to his brain arid his body is made glowing like iron in fire. The blessed
                     <persName>Palladius</persName> says concerning <persName>Aba
                     Arsenius</persName>, that while he stood praying in his cell, a brother, <pb
                     n="113"/>looking through the window, saw him being wholly like fire. The tenth
                  is that of unification.[#n113-1] This state is called undescribable by the
                  Initiated. They say that the sign thereof is, that there are no longer two or
                  three, but one is solved and two is subtilized and the sustenance of the two
                  becomes one.[#n113-2] The eleventh is that of joy which also knows tears. Its
                  cause is unknown to the Initiated; he knows only that he rejoices, but not why.
                  The twelfth is that of outbursts of speech and prominence of the scrutinizing of
                  things to come and explaining of things hidden, those which are written in the
                  archbook, which is the book of the knowledge of God. And to the mind, when reading
                  them, they are here revealed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
               <head>Section the Fifteenth</head>
               <head>A Collection of scattered Sayings concerning Love[#n113-3]</head>
               <p>One of the Initiated, being asked what love is, answered: Love is the divine fire
                  which burns in the elect and banishes and destroys from their hearts every other
                  desire which is impure. <choice>
                     <sic>An other</sic>
                     <corr>Another</corr>
                  </choice> has said: Love is fulfilling the will of the beloved. Another: Love is
                  the power which springs from nature and superates the will. The mind cannot attain
                  it, nor can the tongue explain it.</p>
               <p>Another wept till he had become blind, stood till he was <pb type="external"
                     n="503"/>bent, fasted till he was wholly abstinent, and prayed till he was
                  exhausted. During all this he did not become weary nor tedious, but he said: I
                  swear by Thee, Lord of Lords, if there were a stream of fire between me and Thee,
                  I would pass through it towards Thee as if it were water. The same said: <pb
                     n="114"/>The love of my Lord has alienated me to mankind and human things.</p>
               <p>The same said: At the banquet of Love I have drunk goblets as it were from a
                  flood; and as wine was not exhausted and I did not get drunk, I was overwhelmed by
                  ecstasy.[#n114-1] From desire of Thee I watched the whole night until twilight.
                  And if I had looked at anything besides Thee, I would have been blinded.</p>
               <p><choice>
                     <sic>An other</sic>
                     <corr>Another</corr>
                  </choice> has said: When the love of God is awake in the heart, it is wholly
                  filled with burning fire, and in an insupportable way it is kindled with joy, and
                  it longs after the sight of the hidden things.</p>
               <p>A certain brother said: When paternal mercy[#n114-2] dawned unto me and
                  took[#n114-3] my mind from me, it was, before being swallowed up in ecstasy and
                  stupefaction, swimming in a sea of light and plunging into and emerging from its
                  waves, ascending and lying down, rejoicing and exalting at the floods of its
                  greatness. It beheld there radiating angels who were praising and it became
                  familiar with them and said: Holy, holy, holy is the Lord Zebaoth.[#n114-4] And
                  again the mind was <pb type="external" n="504"/>taken[#n114-5] and penetrated into
                  the light of many rays and was stupefied by the sight of the Beautiful[#n114-6]
                  and captivated by the love of the High one and all, even itself, became as not
                  existing.[#n114-7] This state of the mind, namely the entrance without <pb n="115"
                  />knowledge and the absence of impulses[#n115-1] will sometimes last a short
                  moment, sometimes one hour, or a whole day, according to the will of the spirit.
                  Also after its return from that state it will remain without inclinations during
                  nearly a whole week. And now the mind will be dark, and then it will be radiant.
                  At first there will dawn in the heart something like a star with many rays and of
                  wonderful beauty, then it will appear as a column of light and thereupon the mind
                  will ascend and enter and be hidden in the cloud.[#n115-2] And from that time
                  gifts consisting in revelations[#n115-3] and visions, prophecy and power of
                  healing, are given to it.</p>
               <p>Another has said: Morning dawns and gives joy, light radiates and gladdens, the
                  friend speaks and enflames, the good incites and exalts and shows Himself and what
                  is His, in joy.</p>
               <p>Another has said: The fire of love does not permit him who burns with it, to
                  accomplish his service. For as soon as he is standing to pray, his heart will
                  begin to glow till it burns and enflames the whole body, so that he is not able to
                  stand upon his feet but falls on the earth as dead; and his cither is broken and
                  he lives only in madness;[#n115-4] he thinks himself and what environs him to be
                  in a fire, because of the living fire which is blown in him by Him who lives
                     eternally.<pb type="external" n="505"/> For the Lord is my witness, that
                  several times I have heard one of the brethren crying, when he was in the
                  drunkenness[#n115-5] of the love of <persName>Christ</persName>, so that he could
                  not restrain himself because of the divine fire that burned in him: O, how burning
                  is Thy love, my Lord and my God, my life perishes from love of Thee, I cannot bear
                  it! O, for Thy unspeakable beauty[#n], let me enter Thy chamber, o king, that I
                  may rejoice and exult with Thee!—with other things which are not to be <pb n="116"
                  />described. Further it has been said: Love makes the body and the senses silent,
                  it elevates the mind so as to gaze on the inaccessible light of the beauty of the
                  Desired. Mercy dawns unto it and takes it to the place without place, the world
                  without denomination, the nature without beginning. And when the solitary reaches
                  the divine cloud[#n116-1] and enters the harbour of all service, and sees with his
                  mind, face to face, the glory of the Lord and is made radiating by it, and is
                  transformed into His likeness—then his mercy is poured out over all, like that of
                  God. And the beloved above all shows him love, and the beasts of prey, cattle, the
                  birds and obnoxious reptiles do not harm him, because they smell from him the
                  scent of their creator.[#n116-2] Even stones and wood and all inanimate beings are
                  dominated by him. Even rebellious demons show themselves obsequious unto him,
                  because of the fear which is laid upon them. Wonderful is also the love shown <pb
                     type="external" n="506"/>unto him by the angels and the cry they utter unto
                  him: Now let the heart rejoice of those who have sought the Lord in distress.</p>
               <p>It has further been said: Look at the fire which becomes one with the iron in the
                  furnace. The iron alone is not to be recognized there, because it has assumed the
                  likeness of the fire, by their union. So you see not two images but one, no
                  discrimination being possible, though the two substances remain separated. In the
                  same way[#n116-3] the children of God see themselves as the image of God; so they
                  become, all of them, gods, by the grace of their creator. And when their nature
                  grows in glory, they are not aware of increase, even as those who grow up are not
                  aware of the growth of their bodily stature; but they observe only that the glory
                  of their person has become greater. And as it proceeds on, love increases. It has
                  further been said:[#n116-4] If anyone writes the mysteries <pb n="117"/>of the
                  spirit, without the spirit's dictating them to him, it will not mix its sweetness
                  into his words and therefore they will not be loved by those who read them nor
                  give delight to those who hear them. But if anyone learns the mysteries of the
                  spirit from the spirit, writing what it dictates to him, then the spirit will mix
                  itself into all his words and all those who hear him will smell its odours and
                  their hearts will be filled by these words with life and their sound will
                  eradicate the passions from them. And this is the pen of the ready writer[#n117-1]
                  with which he writes his holy book.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <pb n="118"/>
         <div type="chapter" n="1.5">
            <head>Book I, Chapter V</head>
            <head>On Music[#n118-1]</head>
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <head>Section the First</head>
               <head>On the Views of those Solitaries who reject Music[#n118-2]</head>
               <p>They say, that every bodily delight, which does not serve unto the necessary
                  maintenance of the body, is from the evil one. And that music belongs to the kinds
                  of delight which are not necessary, is known from the fact, that continual
                  deprivation of it, does not harm the body in any way. And <pb type="external"
                     n="59"/>when the divine word has permitted the ancients the use of songs, this
                  has not been done on account of the spiritual profit to be gained from them, but
                  on account of the heathen leaven with which they were leavened. For he who is
                  accustomed to a thing is difficult to be changed and he does not comply with a
                  sudden transition. Therefore God has for instance permitted the children of
                     <placeName>Israel</placeName> to make use of every kind of offerings, on
                  account of their imperfection and their inclination towards the fear of the idols
                  caused by their long abode in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>. For He knew that if He
                  absolutely forbade them offerings they would not have obeyed. Therefore He
                  commanded, that they should offer to Him alone and thereby He restrained the
                  unbridled impulses towards polytheism. Till, when they had reached the
                  accomplished view, He said to them, as it were, <pb n="119"/>by the mouth of
                     <persName>David</persName>: I will take no bullock out of thy folds.[#n119-1]
                  And further: I will not eat the flesh of bulls, nor drink the blood of goats.
                  Offer unto God thanksgiving.[#n119-2] And further: For Thou desirest not
                  sacrifice: Thou delightest not in burnt offering. The sacrifices of God are a
                  humble spirit.[#n119-3]</p>
               <p>Likewise God allowed them musical performances with cymbals, harps, cithers and
                  other musical instruments, because they had been brought up with songs and
                  banquets, with demoniacal insanity, with feasts and festivals and dances. At last
                  however He had proclaimed by the prophet openly: I will cause the sound of thy
                  songs to cease; and the sound of thy<pb type="external" n="60"/> harps shall be no
                  more heard.[#n119-4]</p>
               <p>And from all these things it appears, according to them, that musical performances
                  and songs are not allowed, and that we have to praise without any songs, as
                     <persName>our Lord</persName> has taught his disciples and as also
                     <persName>Moses</persName> cried to God in silence, and as it is becoming to
                  make comparisons with unspeakable words and with those groanings with which the
                  spirit prays on behalf of the saints,[#n119-5] as <persName>the divine
                     apostle</persName> denotes it mysteriously. On account of this, they say, those
                  monks are reprehensible, which descend into the world because of the impure sign
                  of desolation which is love of money, a phenomenon which is to be seen in all holy
                  places. But because they are accustomed to boisterous music from their youth
                  onward and have splendid voices, they do not care much about blessed mourning, but
                  they are only anxious to celebrate common festivals and feasts. They know not
                  that, on the contrary, it is becoming for us to worship God in spirit and truth
                  and in holy silence, of which sanctifications are stronger than all voices.</p>
               <p>Therefore, if it is allowed to speak frankly, we advise them not to indulge
                  indecently in musical outbursts, but to strive after occupying their mind with
                  mystic understanding, which <pb n="120"/>directs them towards being insatiate with
                  the teachings of <persName>the Saviour</persName> and towards heavenly praises
                  which are more to the good pleasure of <persName>Christ</persName>.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="external" n="61"/>
            <div type="section" n="2">
               <head>Section the Second</head>
               <head>On the worldly[#n120-1] View of those who, along with Music, also declare
                  musical Instruments and Dance allowed</head>
               <p>These people say, that every class of rejected things, is rejected either on
                  account of deliberation, or on account of the scriptures.[#n120-2] That
                  deliberation[#n120-3] does not reject music is known from the fact, that the
                  relation between sound and ear is the same as that between colour and eye, or
                  between odour and smell. Therefore, as the sight of a superb colour and the smell
                  of a delicious odour does not bring guilt upon the seeing and the smelling, so
                  hearing agreeable sounds does not bring guilt upon the hearer.</p>
               <p>They further say:[#n120-4] Every sort of music proceeds either from the throat of
                  irrational birds, or from that of rational man, or it is caused by playing musical
                  instruments. Now it is manifest that to hear the voice of a bird does <choice>
                     <sic>note</sic>
                     <corr>denote</corr>
                  </choice> guilt; so the same holds true in the case of the human voice and the
                  musical instrument.</p>
               <p>That the scriptures do not reject music either, appears, according to their
                  opinion, from the fact, that in Hebrew traditions it is written, that
                     <persName>David</persName>, the elect, appointed four singers, skilled in
                  various sorts of music, and that he caused every one of them to join with himself
                  seventy two singers in order to praise with glorifications.</p>
               <pb n="121"/>
               <p>Concerning instrumental music they say, that if it were impure, the holy Fathers
                  would not have made use of it, and that they have made use of it, is manifest. For
                     <persName>Miriam</persName>, the prophetess, the sister of
                     <persName>Aaron</persName>, took a timbrel in her hand and all the women went
                  out after her with timbrels and with<pb type="external" n="62"/> drums. And
                     <persName>Miriam</persName> sang to them.[#n121-1] And
                     <persName>David</persName> says: The chiefs advanced, holding harps, among
                  maidens which beat timbrels, namely those Hebrew women which sang:
                     <persName>Saul</persName> has slain thousands, and <persName>David</persName>
                  tens of thousands.[#n121-2] And further he says: Praise Him with the sound of the
                  trumpet: praise Him with the psaltery and harp. Praise Him with the timbrel and
                  cymbal: praise Him with the sweet stringed instruments. Praise Him upon the loud
                  cymbals: praise Him with the loud voice.[#n121-3] And many other utterances.</p>
               <p>Concerning dance they further say: How should we reject it? For he who is more
                  excellent than we, has danced: <persName>David</persName>, who has been surnamed
                  the heart of God, when he went before the ark of the Lord and played.[#n121-4] And
                  because of the words:[#n121-5] We have piped unto you, and ye have not danced; we
                  have mourned unto you, and ye have not lamented,[#n121-6] which are spoken
                  reprehensively in the Gospel, they say: these words prove, that it is becoming to
                  accompany the song with dance, and the bewailing of the dead with lamentation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
               <head>Section the Third</head>
               <head>On the true View of those who declare Music partly allowed, partly
                  forbidden</head>
               <p>These people say: Not every kind of music is apt for the divine sheepfolds;
                  neither is the church to be alienated from <pb n="122"/>every song. For some
                  melodies are spiritual, and these are apt for the church. Others have only
                  artistic value and these are not apt for the church, but alien. Spiritual musical
                  texts are demur, mournful and causing sadness and afterwards a <pb type="external"
                     n="63"/>chaste desire, while the soul washes away with tears the stains of sin.
                  Sometimes however they even cause encouragement and raise the deliberations unto
                  fortitude. In this way <persName>Jeremiah</persName> sang sadly and lamented over
                  the devastation of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, mysteriously denoting thereby
                  the intellectual struggle of souls. The same holds true for every one of the
                  prophets, which have sung spiritually.</p>
               <p>Artistic melodies are effeminate and voluptuous and the passion of lasciviousness
                  is lurking and hidden in them, till it lays a net for the soul in which it becomes
                  luxuriant and effeminate. As a doctor has said: Till the present day I never saw
                  an artist who repented from the depth of his heart or beat his breast or, on
                  account of a plague, upbraided the inward inclinations which make impure, or bent
                  his knees and moistened the earth with his tears; on the contrary: they stand
                  upright, move their head, turn their neck in all directions, gesticulate, beat and
                  clap their fingers one at the other and often stamp the ground with their foot.
                  And those who listen to them or sing with them, being inwardly effeminate, look
                  upwards with a yawning palate, and are transported with a false and foreign
                  delight, without showing any of the fruits of a repentant heart.</p>
               <p><persName>Euagrius</persName> the great has further said, distinguishing between
                  demoniac songs and the canticles of the church: Demoniac songs excite our desire
                  and throw the soul into impure imaginations. But Psalms and glorifications and
                  spiritual songs direct our intellect towards the recollection of excellent things,
                     <pb type="external" n="64"/> quench the fire of our anger and extinguish the
                  desires. Therefore it is not becoming to mix together things which are not to be
                  mixed, but we have to sing our glorifications chastely, like that great man
                     <persName>Moses</persName>, and the children of <placeName>Israel</placeName>
                  who <pb n="123"/>sang a wonderful song of praise, saying: We will praise the
                  majestic Lord, for He is to be praised gloriously.[#n123-1] Further from that
                  great song of praise in which he says: I will publish the name of the
                  Lord,[#n123-2] while he shows that <persName>Enosh</persName>, who was the first
                  to call upon the name of the Lord and to sing praises, assumed and made songs of
                  praise—the church has been taught to make use of spiritual songs. Proceeding with
                  the history of <persName>Moses</persName> one will further find a small song
                  entitled: On the well.[#n123-3] Reading it, one will understand clearly, that they
                  sang not only accompanied by the timbrel, as it was played by
                     <persName>Miriam</persName>, but also with a plain song, which beautifully
                  ascends unto the godhead, encouraging and exhorting one another, singing: Spring
                  up, o well! Concerning musical instruments it is to be acknowledged, that the holy
                  ghost inspired <persName>David</persName>, his servant, when he was the youngest
                  among his brothers and a boy in the house of his father, so that his hands made a
                  flute and his fingers played the harp harmoniously, as he says.[#n123-4] But
                  because they are used nowadays at voluptuous festivals and drinkingbouts, it is
                  not becoming to use them. Perhaps it is no cause of guilt if one rarely makes use
                  of that pipe-organ, which is sometimes found in Roman churches.</p>
               <p>And that dance in a circle, which is performed by the Greeks,<pb type="external"
                     n="65"/> the Romans, the Syrians and the inhabitants of Tagrit, is allowed to
                  boys, but only to those who belong to the lay-people. Not however always, but only
                  on feastdays, on which joy is wanted.</p>
               <p>Of the women only those who belong to the clergy are ordered by the canons to sing
                  songs and hymns among themselves in the church.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="124"/>
            <div type="section" n="4">
               <head>Section the Fourth</head>
               <head>Since when and by whom singing has been introduced into the Syriac
                  Church</head>
               <p>Since the time of the holy synod which assembled at <placeName>Nicea</placeName>,
                  the holy <persName>Mar Ephraim</persName>, our compatriote, began to produce holy
                  musical songs and homilies against the heresies of his days.[#n124-1] And also
                  other doctors, as Isaac[#n124-2] and a certain Balai,[#n124-3] composed a
                  multitude of hymns based on texts taken from <persName>David</persName>. And also
                  in the time of the synod of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, some potters, who were
                  exquisitely pious, burned spiritually and produced a multitude of songs. Then,
                  after the synod which assembled at <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, our Master
                     <persName>Severus</persName>, that exquisite dogmatic, composed from all his
                  Greek hymns which had been translated into Syriac, the responses to be sung, after
                  he had corrected them and endowed them with sound views. <pb type="external"
                     n="66"/>And in the time of the pious <persName>Jacob of
                        <placeName>Edessa</placeName></persName> and of the elect <persName>George,
                     the bishop of the Arab tribes</persName>, originated those glorifications,
                  which are called the Greek canons, from a Damascene author, called
                     <persName>Cyrene bar Manṣūr</persName>, and from a monk, who among monks was
                  surnamed <persName>Aba Ḳusma</persName>, who was the inventor of the cyclic hymns,
                  hymns which are more delightful than those by the former. And because
                     <persName>Cyrene</persName>, though belonging to the party of
                     <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, was not minded to mention the points of
                  dispute which have given rise to the schism, in his songs, his canons have
                  gradually found their way into our church, into its Eastern and Western section,
                  as we learn from the pious Eleazar bar Sābta.[#n124-4]</p>
               <p>How it may be, the accomplished, who possess the spirit of
                     <persName>Christ</persName>, do not want any kind of boisterous music, because
                     <pb n="125"/>they constantly cry unto their Lord only with unspeakable, namely
                  intellectual words, and so have intercourse with Him. But to those among us who
                  are in the puerile stage, being still somewhat material[#n125-1] and partly sick,
                  and in want of accessory musical clamour,—the holy Fathers have allowed music, the
                  condition that they should praise God, that <persName>Christ</persName> might he
                  preached, be it under a pretext or in truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
               <head>Section the Fifth</head>
               <head>On the Causes through which Music has been introduced into the Church</head>
               <p>There are known to me two causes on account of which the holy Fathers have
                  permitted spiritual glorifications to be performed with musical accompaniment in
                  the holy churches.<pb type="external" n="67"/> The first is, that music, by the
                  delight it causes, makes light and easy the burden of the labours of asceticism;
                  because it occupies the senses so as not to be aware of time and inclination. And
                  when man is not aware of time and inclination, he is not aware of trouble itself
                  either. This conclusion can be promptly observed in the case of troublesome babes
                  who, when crying on account of annoying pain, cease to cry and become quiet by the
                  soft melodies sung by their mother. And, as regards the irrational animals, we see
                  manifestly that camels, loaded with heavy burdens, accompanied by the regular of
                  their Midianite drivers, travel over vast plains without perceiving the trouble of
                  the way.[#n125-2] The second cause is this, that music is very profitable unto
                  understanding the words of spiritual glorifications. And this on account of two
                  reasons. The first is, that a canon, while the text is uttered slowly and the <choice>
                     <sic>enuntiation</sic>
                     <corr>enunciation</corr>
                  </choice> is prolonged, not being murmured superficially and hastily, gives the
                  intellect the opportunity of <pb n="126"/>understanding the spirit of the text and
                  of grasping its meaning. The second is, that the text, being pronounced with the
                  delight inherent to it, is more easily accepted by the soul <pb type="external"
                     n="68"/>and so becomes an object of love. On account of this the soul will not
                  shrink from scrutinizing the sense of the text, it will be zealous to examine it,
                  being unsatiable in contemplating its tenor.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
               <head>Section the Sixth</head>
               <head>On the Cause of the Delight springing from Music</head>
               <p>Concerning the cause of the delight springing from harmonious music, the sages
                  say, that every delight happens by sensual apperception to him that receives
                  sensual impressions and is akin to the delight. Akin as a master is he who is in
                  the possession of all his accomplishments. But if anyone does not possess all, but
                  only a part of them, the delight he is able to grasp will be greater or lesser
                  according to the accomplishments being greater or lesser.</p>
               <p>The delight gathered from harmonious music will be attained in a higher degree by
                  the souls which are trained and exercised in subtle distinctions than by those
                  rude and fool ones, which are material, because an increased delight is caused by
                  the returning of the delightful after the pain of separation. Therefore, when a
                  sweet melody touches the senses and vanishes, another, similar one takes its place
                  and drives away the pain caused by the vanishing of the former. And when the
                  latter disappears also, the companion which follows it, consoles him that has been
                  bereft of it. So every pain is followed by a consolator, and after every trouble
                  delight will be corroborated. So the trained souls, which have been subtilized by
                  their essential attaining the departure and return of the delightful thing, will
                  grasp the delight effused by music. But the troubled <pb type="external" n="69"
                  />souls which are material, being devoid of apperception, will neither groan over
                  that which departs, nor be calmed by that which returns.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="127"/>
            <div type="section" n="7">
               <head>Section the Seventh</head>
               <head>On the natural Foundation of Music</head>
               <p>The ancients, who were the inventors of the musical art, have founded it upon four
                  elements, according to the number of the four qualities: heat, cold, humidity and
                  drought.[#n127-1] Now none of these can occur in simplicity, without being mixed
                  up with another one, as is to be seen in the physical and chemical elements. For
                  that which is hot, is either humid, as air and blood, or hot,[#n127-2] as fire and
                  brown gall. And again, that which is cold, is either humid, as water and phlegm,
                  or dry, as earth and black gall. So the kinds of music are necessarily limited
                  within the number of twelve. For music which is akin to heat and humidity, will be
                  either composed of the two equally, or it will possess moderate heat and plentiful
                  humidity, or vice versa. And that which is cognate with heat and drought, will
                  either be abundant with the two equally, or it will possess moderate heat and much
                  of drought, or vice versa. And that further, which participates of cold and
                  humidity, will be akin to both of them equally, or to cold moderately and to
                  humidity plentifully, or vice versa. And that further, which is composed of cold
                  and drought, imparts equal strength to both of them, or to cold in a moderate
                  measure, to drought<pb type="external" n="70"/> in a large measure or vice versa.
                  And so Persian musical artists have discovered twelve sorts of music, which it is
                  however not apt to mention and to enumerate with their designations, in this
                  place. The churchmen however, Greeks, Syrians and others, have hated and rejected
                  those sorts which contain two of the qualities without moderation of strength. as
                  being unchaste and voluptuous excitements. They have given their sanction only to
                  eight sorts of music and called them akadias[#n127-3] and have tried them
                  practically.</p>
               <pb n="128"/>
               <p>The first and the fifth give a large place to heat and humidity. But in the first,
                  humidity, weak and soft, which is very delightful and exhilarating, is found. And
                  therefore the canon of Christmas is composed in it, because it is a feast of joy,
                  of which the gladness is abundant and exultation is plentiful, and in it the joy
                  which is imparted to the whole world, is proclaimed. Likewise the canon of Easter,
                  because on it the women have proclaimed [the resurrection of
                     <persName>Christ</persName>] to the disciples. And because mournful heat is
                  strong in the fifth sort, the canon of Ascension is composed in it; for when
                     <persName>the Lord</persName> had been separated from His disciples and had
                  been taken up into heaven, they burned with the fire of longing and blazed with
                  desire of Him and glowed with love. But for the burden of their body they would
                  have been elevated in the air with Him.</p>
               <p>The second and the sixth have a strong mixture of cold and humidity. But the cold,
                  which makes humble in a moderate measure, is found to a larger degree in the
                  second. And <pb type="external" n="71"/>therefore the canon of Baptism is composed
                  in it. For though on this occasion <persName>the Lord</persName> condescended to
                  be baptized by a servant, the height of His greatness was attested through the
                  ghost of God which came upon Him and through the voice which was heard, saying:
                  This is my beloved son. And because humidity, which is more tending towards
                  sorrow, and more weak and tearful, is stronger in the sixth, the canon of the holy
                  Pentad is tuned in it, likewise that of Good Friday and the Saturday following it;
                  because they are days of sorrow.</p>
               <p>In the third and the seventh heat and drought are abundant. But harsh and angry
                  drought is strong in the third. And therefore the canon of <persName>our
                     Lord</persName>'s entrance into the temple is composed in it, because on that
                  occasion old <persName>Simeon</persName> spoke with the virgin with words which
                  were very harsh, as for instance: A lance shall pierce through thy own soul. And
                  because fiery heat, urging forth with force, is strong in the seventh the canon of
                  Whitsuntide is set in it. For on this occasion <pb n="129"/>the holy ghost
                  manifested himself unto the disciples in the likeness of tongues of fire, and took
                  possession of them.</p>
               <p>The fourth and the eighth have strong elements of cold and drought. But cold akin
                  to fear is prevalent in the fourth. Therefore the canon of Annunciation is
                  composed in it. For on it the virgin who had never experienced marriage was
                  frightened by hearing of pregnancy and birth, fearing that the serpent which had
                  seduced her mother should also seduce her. For, said she to the angel of the
                  annunciation, as the serpent has taken possession of my mother between the trees,
                  so I fear that you speak words of seduction to me. <pb type="external" n="72"
                  />Likewise the canon of Hosanna. For on it the king who was wont to ride pompously
                  on Cherubs, rode in his humiliation on a miserable colt.</p>
               <p>And because benumbing and harsh drought is prevalent in the eighth, the canons of
                  the Martyrs, who despised torments and showed heroism of soul, have been tuned in
                  it.</p>
               <p>These are the foundations upon which have been built the sorts of music by the
                  ancient sages. But those who came after them and who had not mastered the height
                  of knowledge of their predecessors, have been zealous to be abundant and broad in
                  this art and so they have composed for every sort of tune a canon, haphazardly,
                  without asking whether it was akin to the tune.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
               <head>Section the Eighth</head>
               <head>On the Ranks of Intelligence concerning the reciting of Psalms and their
                  Sentences[#n129-1]</head>
               <p>Three are the ranks of intelligence concerning the reciting of Psalms. The first
                  is that of plain people, those whose simple soul is only delighted at the text
                  which is sung without <pb n="130"/>intending to fix its intelligence on any of the
                  sentences. The like will not gain the least profit nor in any way be damaged by a
                  change of the tendency of the texts. The second rank is that of those who enjoy
                  the text in the same measure as the harmonious music. If they are youths who are
                  ensnared in bodily desires, they will apply the words of love which are sung, not
                  to divine love and the longing of the soul after <pb type="external" n="73"/>its
                  Lord, but to the human passions which lurk in their heart; especially when their
                  ears are struck by those hymns, taken from <persName>David</persName> and
                     <persName>Solomon</persName>, which in a symbolic way describe the beauty of
                  women, and are composed in view of the church and the soul, such as: 'the daughter
                  of the king which rose in glory, and her maiden companions which followed her with
                  offerings'. And 'the beauty of the cheeks, as beds of spices'.[#n130-1] And 'locks
                  like the king's purple'. And 'the elevated neck, like a tower'.[#n130-2] And
                  'hair, like a flock of goats and teeth like a flock of shorn sheep, which go up
                  from the washing, whereof every one beareth twins, and there is not one barren
                  among them'.[#n130-3] And 'eyes like the pools of
                  <placeName>Heshbon</placeName>'.[#n130-4] And 'the roof of the mouth like the best
                  wine'.[#n130-5] And 'return, return, O Shulamite, that we may look upon
                  thee'.[#n130-6] And 'thou hast encouraged me with the look of one of thy eyes,
                  which have frightened me'[#n130-7] and so on,—they apply them to a peculiar
                  person; and thus desire becomes mighty in them and the spirit of voluptuousness
                  rages in them. So, instead of profit, they gather no small loss from hearing
                  music.</p>
               <p>The third rank[#n130-8] is that of accomplished and perfect people, such as
                  possess the spirit of <persName>Christ</persName> and whose thoughts are <pb
                     n="131"/>girded with the love of God. These persons apply every word of love
                  they hear, to the love of the soul unto its Lord and to that of the church unto
                  its Saviour. Therefore the words 'the maidens love thee' are understood by them in
                  connection with the praised souls which love Christ; and 'I am black'[#n131-1] in
                  connection with the stains caused to the soul by<pb type="external" n="74"/>
                  passions. 'I am beautiful'[#n131-2] in connection with its elevated nature, being
                  offspring of God as appears from: 'Let us make man in our image, after our
                  likeness'.[#n131-3] And in 'they brought me to the wine-house, they fixed over me
                  love',[#n131-4] they find mysteriously denoted the drunkenness of the soul of the
                  Initiated. And by 'behold, he standeth behind our wall' they are taught, that the
                  body is a veil between the soul and its Lord; by 'he looketh forth through the
                  windows, bending through the lattice',[#n131-5] that divine revelations and
                  visions take place by clarifying the heaviness[#n131-6] of the body. By 'the
                  watchmen that went about the city found me, they smote me, they wounded
                  me',[#n131-7] they understand the demons which observe the heel of the soul and
                  bereave it of its glory; by the 'little foxes that spoil the vines'[#n131-8] the
                  excitations of the body. So every word they meet, they connect and explain by some
                  spiritual distinction, though he who spoke these words did not intend such a
                  connection. As <persName>Aba Macarius</persName> did: when he passed through the
                  streets of <placeName>Kairo</placeName>, he heard a boy saying to his mother: A
                  rich one loves me, but I hate him; and a poor one hates me, but I love him. Then
                  he said to the disciples with him: Indeed; for God is the rich one, and He loves
                  us, but we are not willing to listen to Him. And <persName>Satan</persName> is
                  poor and he hates us, but we love his evil deeds. And a certain excellent brother,
                  who heard a boy murmuring the<pb type="external" n="75"/> sentence: 'Return, o my
                  soul, to thy rest' sighed, saying: How <pb n="132"/>often I say to it: Return, but
                  it returns not. And when a certain Initiated heard the song: 'To the moon which
                  changes constantly, and whose light varies from day to day, resemble the beautiful
                  beauties of my friend, the superb of splendour'—he said: The beautiful beauties of
                     <persName>Christ</persName> are without change, nor is there any variation in
                  the splendour of His images; but in the change of the intellects which receive Him
                  there arise changes by His revelations. And all along with the variations of those
                  who see Him, change the images in His visions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
               <head>Section the Ninth</head>
               <head>On the Influence of Music on the Souls</head>
               <p>Apart from the delight caused to the soul by hearing music and understanding the
                  words on which it is composed, various workings appear in it, workings which vary
                  all along with the preparation and the aptitudes the soul possesses. For instance:
                  encouragement and intimidation, joy and exaltation, sorrow and distress,
                  repentance and consolation, dilatation and contraction[#n132-1] and other painful
                  qualities and pains. And so strong are these workings in it, that it compels the
                  limbs of the body to participate in its emotions. Thus man enters a state which
                  resembles madness; as the holy Fathers say, that at times of ecstasy, in which the
                  heart is transported with <pb type="external" n="76"/>the divine love which unites
                  it to <persName>Christ</persName>, man leaves his state, so that he cannot
                  restrain his soul, which is ardent to fly away, from the supernatural delight and
                  heat, in its ardour to abide in that glorious vision towards which it is striving.
                  So it also draws along with it the limbs of the body: the flesh, the bones, the
                  joints, so that they are also plunged into that sweetness. It is clear that this
                  same love influenced <persName>David</persName> to order all peoples and tribes of
                     <placeName>Israel</placeName> to clap their hands <pb n="133"/>and to rejoice
                  and to exult and to play before the ark of the Lord on the wood of cedar and
                  cypress, on cithers and harps, on timbrels and drums and cymbals.</p>
               <p>But, because moving the limbs is a token of madness, though it be not an impure
                  one, as the love of the Lord is its efficient, and their being in rest is a token
                  of the mind [being sane], he who exults with joy has the duty to keep his limbs
                  quiet as much as it is possible for him, especially if he belongs to the priestly
                  rank.[#n133-1]</p>
               <p>That dancing makes those who practise it, foolish and voluptuous, and bereaves and
                  deprives them of their honour, is known from the fact that
                     <persName>Mikal</persName>, the daughter of <persName>Saul</persName>, when she
                  looked from the window and saw <persName>David</persName> rejoicing and playing
                  before the ark of the Lord, despised him and ridiculed him saying: How glorious
                  was the king of <placeName>Israel</placeName> to-day, who uncovered himself in the
                  eyes of the handmaids of his servants, as one of the vain fellows. And because she
                  spoke the truth, he did not accuse her of lying, but he inculpated her in another
                  way saying: It was before the Lord, which chose me before thy father, and before
                  all his house, to appoint me ruler over the people of the Lord, over
                     <placeName>Israel</placeName>:<pb type="external" n="77"/> therefore I have
                  made mirth before the Lord. And I have been still more vile than thus and I have
                  been base in mine own sight: and with the maidservants which thou hast spoken of I
                  shall be had in honour.[#n133-2] And from these things it appears, that play and
                  dance are tokens of want of honour and of voluptuousness.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n85-1">Is. 1,3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n86-1">Introduction, p. XC.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-1">This is also Gẖazālī’s definition (Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 252). It also
               declares that love is only possible on account of knowledge: <!-- Add Arabic -->.
               Further love is <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-2">This passage is in Iḥyāʾ IV. p. 253.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-3">Cf. Iḥyāʾ IV, P. 253.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-4">Cf. Book of the Dove, III. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-1">A verse of 12 syllables.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-2">This is Gẖazālī’s definition of the third cause (IV, p.
               254).</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-3">This example is given and explained by Ghazali in the same way IV,
               p. 254.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-4">Also one of Gẖazālī’s examples (IV, p. 255).</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-5">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 255.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-6">Ibidem.</note>
            <note xml:id="n89-1">Cf. the Book of the Dove III, 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n89-2">The thoughts of this passage are expressed also in two sentences of
               Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh I, 71: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n90-1">Introduction, p. LXXVII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n90-2"><choice>
                  <sic>Litterally</sic>
                  <corr>Literally</corr>
               </choice>: its beauties are loved.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-1">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 263.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-2">Cf. Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 263: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-3">Iḥyāʾ, ib.: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-4">Iḥyāʾ, ib.: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-5">Isaac of Ninive, p. 32 speaks of bodily man, who has left his
               dunghill and seeks heavenly things: ܘܬܗܪܝܢ ܒܟ ܟܕ ܚܙܝܢ ܠܦܓܪܢܐ ܕܐܪܦܝ ܠܩܩܠܬܗ ܘܫܐܠ
               ܫܡܝܢܝ̈ܬܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-6">ܝܕܘܥܬܢܝܬ</note>
            <note xml:id="n92-1">Verses of 12 syllables, like the following.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-1">With the following passage is to be compared Iḥyāʾ IV. p.
               267.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-2">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 267: <!-- Add Arabic -->. It is clear, that the whole
               passage in Bar Hebraeus was taken from the Iḥyāʾ, inclusive the example of Moses. See
               Introduction, p. LII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-3">Ex. 33, 20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-4">1 Cor. 13, 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-1">Gẖazālī speaks in nearly the same terms; but he maintains that this
               clear sight of the soul will only be reached after resurrection[ch] (Iḥyāʾ IV, p.
               268, 10 sqq.). Cf. with the whole passage Plotinus, Enneades VI, 9 § 9 and 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-2">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 70.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-3">Also Gẖazālī’s first cause, Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 270.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-4">ܬܐܪܬܐ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-5">Introduction, p. LXXVII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-6">Also Gẖazālī’s second cause, (Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 271).</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-7">Introduction, p. XXXIX.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-8">Introduction, p. LXXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-1">Iḥyāʾ IV. p. 271: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-2">With the following passage compare the Book of the Dove III,
               8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-3">Even this sentence is in the Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 272: <!-- Add Arabic -->.
               Ḳusẖairī, p. 167 ascribes it to Dẖu ʾl-Nūn.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-4">Psalm 36, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-5">Psalm 19, 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n96-1">Cf. Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 274.</note>
            <note xml:id="n96-2">Section VI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n96-3">Introduction, p. XLII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n96-4">James I, 17. The above passage concords almost <choice>
                  <sic>litterally</sic>
                  <corr>literally</corr>
               </choice> with Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 274.</note>
            <note xml:id="n96-5">This class is mentioned by Gẖazālī in less strong terms IV, p.
               274.</note>
            <note xml:id="n96-6">Ibidem.</note>
            <note xml:id="n96-7">Ibidem.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-1">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 275.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-2">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 275: <!-- Add Arabic -->. Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh II, 98:
               <!-- Add Arabic --> and II, 99: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-3">Cf. Book of the Dove III, 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-4">Psalm 19, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-5">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 275: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-6">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 275: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-7">Introduction, p.CIII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-8">Introduction, p. LXXXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-1">Cf. Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh, I, 18: <!-- Add Arabic -->. And I, 28:
               <!-- Add Arabic -->. And Abū Ṭālib II, 59: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-2">Verses of 12 syllables. The original is in the Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 277:
               <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-3">Cf. Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh II, 9: apparently the original of Bar Hebraeus'
               verses.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-1">Cf. Abū Ṭālib II, 51: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-2">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 277: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-3">Ibidem: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-4">Ibidem: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-5">Ibidem: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-1">Ps. 42, 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-2">Iḥyāʾ iv, P. 277: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-3">Ibidem: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-4">Ps. 51, 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-5">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 277: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-6">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 278: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-7">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 283.</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-1">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 283.</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-2">Philippians 1, 23. Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh, 66: <!-- Add Arabic -->.
               Introduction, p. LII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-3">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 285.</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-4">John 4, 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-5">Perhaps; but the story is also to be found in the corresponding
               chapter of the Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 284. And it occurs already in Abū Ṭālib II. 52, who
               introduces it with the words: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-6">Above, p. 54.</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-7">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 285.</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-8">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 286.</note>
            <note xml:id="n102-1">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 286.</note>
            <note xml:id="n102-2">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 287.</note>
            <note xml:id="n102-3">Saba.</note>
            <note xml:id="n102-4">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 287.</note>
            <note xml:id="n102-5">Cf. section XIV; and Book of the Dove III, 9, fifth state.</note>
            <note xml:id="n102-6">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 288: <!-- Add Arabic -->. The third part of the
               sentence is not in the Iḥyāʾ; so there seems to be a common source.</note>
            <note xml:id="n102-7">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 290. Cf. Abū Ṭālib II, 67:
               <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n103-1">This anecdote is already in Abū Ṭālib II, 67 and Iḥyāʾ IV. p. 290
               where the master is Dẖu ʾl-Nūn.</note>
            <note xml:id="n103-2">Cf. Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 292 and Introduction, p. CII sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n103-3">Introduction, p. XCVIII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n103-4">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 292: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n103-5">Cf. section XIV, first state; and Book of the Dove III, 6 first
               state.</note>
            <note xml:id="n103-6">=θεοποίος; Dionysius Areopagita, Opera, p. 281.</note>
            <note xml:id="n104-1">Cf. Book of the Dove, III, 9, tenth state.</note>
            <note xml:id="n104-2">Introduction, p. CVI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n104-3">Introduction, p. XXVII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n104-4">Job 7, 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n104-5">Job 13, 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n105-1">Cf. Job 7, 13 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n105-2">Cf. Job 9, 33.</note>
            <note xml:id="n105-3">Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 294: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n105-4">2 Sam. 12, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n105-5">Cf. Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 298.</note>
            <note xml:id="n105-6"><choice>
                  <sic>Litterally</sic>
                  <corr>Literally</corr>
               </choice>: fly.</note>
            <note xml:id="n106-1">Cf. Rom. 8, 35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n106-2">Cf. Rom. 8, 37 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n106-3">This is also in the Iḥyāʾ IV, p. 298.</note>
            <note xml:id="n107-1">Cf. Book of the Dove III. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n107-2">Introduction, p, LXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-1">Cf. Book of the Dove III, 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-2">Introduction, p. XCI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-3">Introduction, p. XCIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-4">ܬܟܝܒܐ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-5">Introduction, p. LXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-6">Daniel 3, 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-7">Introduction, p. LXXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-8">Introduction, p. C.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-1">Book of the Dove III, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-2">Plotinus, Enneades VI, 9 § n, compares this moment with entering
               the asylum of a temple.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-3">Cf section XIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-4">Introduction, p. XCIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-5">Introduction, p. I. XIV sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-6">Introduction, p. LXXXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-7">The idea is already expressed by Jamblichus, De mysteriis, p. 31:
               οὕτω καὶ τῶν θεῶν τὸ φῶς ἐλλάμπει χωριστῶς, ἐν ἑαυτῷ τε μονίμως ἱδρυμένον προχωρεῖ
               διὰ τῶν ὄντων ὅλων.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-8">Book of the Dove III, 7. How familiar such ideas are to
               neo-Platonic philosophers may appear from the following quotation from Ibn Gabirol's
               Source of Life (ed. Munk. Mélanges I. 4): <!-- Add Hebrew -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-9">Introduction, p. CIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n110-1">Introduction, p. CV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n110-2">Book of the Dove III, 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n110-3">Introduction, p. CVIII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n110-4">Introduction, p. CII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n110-5">This is the reading of some Mss. The text has: ‘the soul dares to
               utter in such a drunkenness; and perhaps they will disdain Master Hierotheos and the
               like who venture to interpret.’</note>
            <note xml:id="n110-6"><choice>
                  <sic>Litterally</sic>
                  <corr>Literally</corr>
               </choice>: a living word.</note>
            <note xml:id="n110-7">Cf. Section XL</note>
            <note xml:id="n110-8">Cf. Book of the Dove III, 9. Introduction, p. XCV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n111-1">Cf. the previous section.</note>
            <note xml:id="n111-2">Introduction, p. CV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n111-3">Introduction, p. LXXI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n111-4">Cf. Section XI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n111-5">Read ܕܡܙܡܘܖ̈ܐ cf. Book of the Dove III, 9, third state.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112-1">Here used in the sense of direct, immediate.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112-2"><choice>
                  <sic>Litterally</sic>
                  <corr>Literally</corr>
               </choice>: <choice>
                  <sic>breated</sic>
                  <corr>breathed</corr>
               </choice> forth.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112-3">Cf. Romans 8, 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112-4">Introduction, p. CVIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112-5">= <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112-6">Introduction, p. LXXVII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112-7">Introduction, p. LXXXIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n113-1">Introduction, p. CVIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n113-2">Cf. Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh I, 32: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n113-3">Gẖazālī’s chapter also ends with a collection of sayings
               concerning love.</note>
            <note xml:id="n114-1">Cf. Ibn ʿAṭāʾallāh II, 81: <!-- Add Arabic --> and Ḳusẖairī, p. 45
               <!-- Add Arabic --> and Abū Ṭālib I, 235: <!-- Add Arabic -->. Introduction, p.
               XC.</note>
            <note xml:id="n114-2">Psalm 103, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n114-3">ܚܛܦܝܢ, Introduction, p. XCVI sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n114-4">Cf. Corpus Hermeticum, p. 336.</note>
            <note xml:id="n114-5">ܡܬܚܛܦ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n114-6">Introduction, p. XLIV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n114-7">Cf. Ḳusẖairī, p. 39 who quotes the following verses:
               <!-- Add Arabic --> And cf. Introduction, p. CVII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-1">Introduction, p. LXXI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-2">Introduction, p. CIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-3">Introduction, p. XCVIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-4">Introduction, p. XC.</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-5">Introduction, l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-6">Introduction, p. XI. V.</note>
            <note xml:id="n116-1">Introduction, p. CIII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n116-2">Cf. Book of the Dove, Sentence 96.</note>
            <note xml:id="n116-3">Introduction, p. CVIII sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n116-4">Book of the Dove, Sentences 54 and 55.</note>
            <note xml:id="n117-1">Ps. 45, 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n118-1">Iḥyāʾ II, p. 219 sqq.; Ḳusẖairī, p. 177 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n118-2">Gẖazālī also opens his chapter with the views of those who reject
               music.</note>
            <note xml:id="n119-1">Ps. 50,9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n119-2">Ps. 50,13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n119-3">Ps. 51, 16 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n119-4">Ezekiel 26, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n119-5">Rom. 8, 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n120-1">Reading of P. The text has: puerile.</note>
            <note xml:id="n120-2">This passage is parallel to the opening passage of Gẖazālī’s
               section on music being allowed (Iḥyāʾ II, p. 221).</note>
            <note xml:id="n120-3">This is what Gẖazālī calls <!-- Add Arabic -->; the following
               passage reproduces exactly Gẖazālī's view Iḥyāʾ II, p. 221.</note>
            <note xml:id="n120-4">Parallel to Iḥyāʾ II, p. 222.</note>
            <note xml:id="n121-1">Exodus 15, 20 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n121-2">1 Sam. 18, 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n121-3">Ps. 150, 3 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n121-4">2 Sam. 6, 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n121-5">These words are also quoted by Gẖazālī, Iḥyāʾ II, p. 230 in favour
               of music.</note>
            <note xml:id="n121-6">Matth. 11, 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n123-1">Cf. Ex. 15, 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n123-2">Ex. 32,3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n123-3">Numbers 1 1 17</note>
            <note xml:id="n123-4">Ps 151, 1 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n124-1"> Cf. Ephraim's Biography, in his Opera, ed. Benedictus and
               Assemani III, p. LII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n124-2">Of Antioch</note>
            <note xml:id="n124-3">Cf. Overbeck, S. Ephraemi Syri, Rabulae, Balaei... opera and
               Zettersteen, Beiträge zur Kenntnis der religiösen Dichtung Balai's.</note>
            <note xml:id="n124-4">Flourished 829 A.D.</note>
            <note xml:id="n125-1"><choice>
                  <sic>Litterally</sic>
                  <corr>Literally</corr>
               </choice>: thick.</note>
            <note xml:id="n125-2">Even the examples of the babe and the camel are in Gẖazālī, Iḥyāʾ
               II, p. 224</note>
            <note xml:id="n127-1">Cf. Zeller III, I, 186.</note>
            <note xml:id="n127-2">read: dry.</note>
            <note xml:id="n127-3">From Greek ἠχειν.</note>
            <note xml:id="n129-1">Iḥyāʾ II, p. 235 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-1">Cf. Cant. 5, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-2">Cant. 7, 4; cf. 4, 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-3">Cant. 6, 5 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-4">Cant. 7, 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-5">Cant. 7, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-6">Cant. 6, 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-7">Cf. Cant. 4, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-8">Iḥyāʾ II, p. 235 concords nearly laterally with the following
               sentences, save only that they are applied by Gẖazālī chiefly on the novices.</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-1">Cant. I, 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-2">Ibidem.</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-3">Gen. 1,26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-4">Cant. 2,4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-5">Cant. 2, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-6"><choice>
                  <sic>Litterally</sic>
                  <corr>Literally</corr>
               </choice>: thickness.</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-7">Cant. 5, 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-8">Cant. 2, 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n132-1">ܦܫܛܐ ܘܩܦܣܐ, cf. List of technical terms.</note>
            <note xml:id="n133-1">Iḥyāʾ II, p. 249: <!-- Add Arabic -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n133-2">2 Sam. 6, 20-22.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
