<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Epiphany 5</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Hymns for Epiphany</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_V"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_V
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 5</head>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He that ordained baptism, for the atonement of the sons of
               <persName>Adam</persName>!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Descend, my brethren, put on from the waters of baptism the Holy Spirit;—be joined
               with the spirits that minister to the Godhead!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>For lo! He is the fire that secretly, seals also His flock,—by the Three spiritual
               Names, wherein the Evil One is put to flight.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab><persName>John</persName> when he cried and said <quote>This is the Lamb of God,</quote>—thereby showed concerning the
               Gentiles that they are <persName>Abraham</persName>’s children.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>This is he that testified of our Saviour, that with fire and the Spirit He should
               baptize.—Lo! the fire and the Spirit, my brethren, in the baptism of truth.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>For greater is Baptism than <placeName>Jordan</placeName> that little river;—for that in streams of water
               and oil, the misdeeds of all men are washed out.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab><persName>Elisha</persName> by seven times washing, cleansed <persName>Naaman</persName>’s leprosy:—in Baptism are cleansed
               the secret misdeeds in the soul.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab><persName>Moses</persName> baptized the People in the midst of the sea, yet availed not—to wash their
               heart within, that was full of the defilements of misdeeds.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Lo! the priest in the likeness of <persName>Moses</persName> purges the defilements of the soul;—and with
               oil of anointing, lo! he seals new lambs for the Kingdom.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab><persName>Samuel</persName> anointed <persName>David</persName> to be king among the People:—but lo! the priest anoints you to
               be heirs in the Kingdom.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>For with the armour that <persName>David</persName> put on, after the anointing he fought—and laid low
               the giant who sought to subdue <placeName>Israel</placeName>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Lo! again in the chrism of Christ, and in the armour that is from the water—the
               haughtiness of the Evil One is humbled, who sought to subdue the Gentiles.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>By the water that flowed from the rock, the thirst of the People was quenched. Lo!
               in the fountain of Christ, the thirst of the peoples is quenched.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>The rod of <persName>Moses</persName> opened the rock, and the streams flowed forth; and they were
               refreshed by its draught, who had grown faint with thirst.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Lo! from the side of Christ flowed the stream that bestowed life.—The Gentiles drank
               that were weary, and in it forgot their pains.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>With Thy dew besprinkle my vileness, and my crimes in Thy blood shall be atoned!—And
               I shall be, O my Lord, at Thy right hand, and with Thy Saints I shall be joined!</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
