<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Epiphany 4</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Hymns for Epiphany</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_IV"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_IV
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 4</head>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He that blots out in water misdeeds that are without
               measure!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Descend my sealed brethren, put ye on our Lord,—and be rejoined to His lineage, for
               He is son of a great lineage,—as He has said in His Word.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>From on high is His Nature, and from beneath His Vesture.—Each that puts off his
               vesture, commingled is that vesture, with His Vesture forever.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Ye too in the water, receive from him the vesture,—that wastes not or is lost for it
               is the vesture that vests—them that are vested in it forever.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>But the blessed Priest, is daysman between two:—the covenant shall be made before
               Him, He is daysman of his Lord,—and surety on our part.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>The Godhead in the water, lo! has mingled His leaven;—for the creatures of dust,
               that leaven raises up,—and the Godhead joins them.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>For it is the leaven of the Lord, that can glide into the bondman,—and raise him to
               freedom; it has joined the bondman to the lineage,—of Him the Lord of all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>For the bondman who has put on Him, Who makes all free in the waters,—though bondman
               he be on earth, is son of the free on high,—for freedom he has put on.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>The freeman who has put on, that Angel in the waters,—is as the fellow of servants,
               that he may be made like to the Lord,—Who became bondman unto bondmen.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>He Who enriches all came down, and put on poverty,—that He might divide to the poor,
               the stores that were hidden,—out of the treasure-house of the water.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>The lowly one again that has put on, the Giver of all greatness, in the water,—even
               though he be base in the sight of fools, yet is great in the sight of the
               Watchers,—for that he is clad in greatness.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>For like as He Who is great, Who became lowly in His love,—by the unbelievers was
               persecuted, and by the Watchers was worshipped,—was made lowly and makes the lowly
               great.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>Thus let him be lowly who is great, that in him the lowly may be great:—Let us be
               like to Him Who is greater than all, Who became less than all:—He was made lowly, and
               makes all men great.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>The meek man who has put on Him Who is great, in the water,—though humble be his
               countenance, very great is his discernment,—for He Who is exalted above all dwells in
               him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>For who could be found to despise the bush of thorn,—the despised and humble,
               wherein the Majesty in fire,—made its dwelling within?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>Who again could be found, to despise Moses,—the meek and slow of speech,—when that
               excelling glory—dwelt upon his meekness?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>They that despised him despised his Lord; the wicked that despised him—the earth
               swallowed up in anger; the Levites who scorned Him,—the fire devoured in fury.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>Of Him Christ commanded, <quote>Thou shalt not call him Raca,</quote> who is baptized and has put
               Him on; for whoso despises the despised, despises with him the Mighty.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>In Eden and in the world, are parables of our Lord;—and what tongue can gather, the
               similitudes of His mysteries?—for He is figured all of Him in all things.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>In the Scriptures He is written of; on Nature He is impressed;—His crown is figured
               in kings, in prophets His truth, His atonement in priests.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>In the rod was He of Moses, and in the hyssops of Aaron,—and in the crown of David:
               to the prophets pertains His similitude, to the Apostles His Gospel.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>Revelations beheld Thee, proverbs looked for Thee,—mysteries expected Thee,
               similitudes saluted Thee, parables showed types of Thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>The Covenant of Moses looked forward to the Gospel:—all things of old time, flew on
               and alighted thereon, in the new Covenant.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>Lo! the prophets have poured out on Him, their glorious mysteries;—the priests and
               kings have poured out upon Him, their wonderful types:—they all have poured them out
               on all of Him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>Christ overcame and surpassed, by His teachings the mysteries,—by His
               interpretations the parables; as the sea into its midst—receives all streams.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>For Christ is the sea, and He can receive—the fountains and brooks, the rivers and
               streams, that flow from the midst of the Scriptures.</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
