<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Epiphany 10</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Hymns for Epiphany</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_X"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_X
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 10</head>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Glory to Him Who came and restored it!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Adam sinned and earned all sorrows;—likewise the world after His example, all
               guilt.—And instead of considering how it should be restored,—considered how its fall
               should be pleasant for it.—Glory to Him Who came and restored it!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>This cause summoned Him that is pure,—that He should come and be baptized, even He
               with the defiled,—Heaven for His glory was rent asunder.—That the purifier of all
               might be baptized with all,—He came down and sanctified the water for our
               baptism.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>For that cause for which He entered into the womb,—for the same cause He went down
               into the river.—For that cause for which He entered into the grave,—for the same
               cause He makes us enter into His chamber.—He perfected mankind for every cause.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>His Conception is the store of our blessings;—His Birth is the treasury of our
               joys;—His Baptism is the cause of our pardon;—His Death is the cause of our
               life.—Death He alone has overcome in His Resurrection.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>At His Birth a star of light shone in the air;—when He was baptized light flashed
               from the water;—at His Death the sun was darkened in the firmament;—at His Passion
               the luminaries set along with Him;—at His Epiphany the luminaries arose with
               Him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Revealed was His Glory because of His Majesty;—revealed was His Passion because of
               His Manhood;—revealed was His Love because of His Graciousness;—revealed was His
               Judgment because of His Justice.—He has poured forth His attributes, on them that
               were His.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>That whoso has looked on His Glory and despised Him,—may look again on His Glory and
               worship Him;—and whoso has scorned to taste of His Graciousness,—may fear lest he be
               made to feel His justice;—He has poured forth His helps on His worshippers.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Lo! the East in the morning was made light!—lo! the South at noonday was made
               dark!—The West again in turn at eventide was made light.—The three quarters represent
               the one Birth;—His Death and His Life they declare.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>His Birth flowed on and was joined to His Baptism;—and His Baptism again flowed on
               even to His Death;—His Death led and reached to His Resurrection,—a fourfold bridge
               unto His Kingdom; and lo! His sheep pass over in His footsteps.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>And like as, save by the door of birth,—none can enter into creation;—so, save by
               the door of resurrection,—none can enter into the Kingdom,—and whoso has cut off his
               bridge, has brought to nought his hope.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>He put on His armour and conquered and was crowned;—He left His armour on earth and
               ascended,—that if any man desires the crown,—he may resort to the armour and win by
               it—the crown of victory which he yearns after.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>He fulfilled righteousness on earth, and ascended.—But if He, the All-cleanser, was
               baptized,—What man is there that shall not be baptized?—for grace has come to
               baptism—to wash away the foulness of our wound.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>The compulsion of God is an all-prevailing force;—[but that is not pleasing to Him
               which is of compulsion,]<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/>—as that which is of discerning will.—Therefore in our
               fruits He calls us—who live not as under compulsion, by persuasion.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Good is He, for lo! He labours in these two things;—He wills not to constrain our
               freedom—nor again does He suffer us to abuse it.—For had he constrained it, He had
               taken away its power;—and had He let it go, He had deprived it of help.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>He knows that if He constrains He deprives us;—He knows that if He casts off He
               destroys us;—He knows that if He teaches He wins us.—He has not constrained and He
               has not cast off, as the Evil One does:—He has taught, chastened, and won us, as
               being the good God.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>He knows that His treasuries abound:—the keys of His treasuries He has put into our
               hands.—He has made the Cross our treasurer—to open for us the gates of Paradise,—as
               Adam opened the gate of Gehenna.</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <!-- Please add footnote numbers. -->
            <note xml:id="n">The rendering of this line is very conjectural.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
