<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Epiphany 2</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Hymns for Epiphany</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_II"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_II
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 2</head>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: To Thee be praise Who in this feast makest all to exult!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>In the time of the King whom they called by the name <persName>Semha</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/>—our Lord was
               manifested among the Hebrews.—Thus <persName>Semha</persName> and <persName>Denha</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> reigned together,—the King on
               earth and the Son on high—blessed be His power!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>In the days of the King who wrote down men in the taxing,—our Saviour came down and
               wrote down men in the Book of Life; He wrote and was written;—on high He wrote us, on
               earth He was written; glory to His Name!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>His Birth was in the days of the King whose name was <persName>Semha</persName>.—Symbol and truth met one
               another;—King and King, <persName>Semha</persName> and <persName>Denha</persName>.—That kingdom bore His Cross; blessed be He
               Who took it up!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Thirty years abode He on earth in poverty.—Voices of praise in all measures,—let us
               weave my brethren for our Lord’s years;—thirty crowns for thirty years; Blessed be
               His number!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>In the first year, mistress of treasure and filled with blessings,—let the Cherubin
               give thanks with us, they who bear—the Son in glory Who gave up His glorious
               state,—and toiled and found the sheep that was lost;—to Him be thanksgiving!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>In the second year let the Seraphin multiply thanksgiving with us;—they who cried
               <quote>Holy</quote> to the Son, and turned and saw Him—among unbelievers put to shame.—He endured
               scorn and taught us glory; to Him be glory given!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>In the third year let <persName>Michael</persName> and his hosts give thanks with us;—they who were wont
               to serve the Son on high,—and saw Him on earth doing service.—He washed men’s feet
               and cleansed men’s souls; blessed be His meekness!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>In the fourth year let all the heavens give thanks with us! Too narrow for the Son
               it shall burst to see—how He lay on the couch of despised <persName>Zaccheus</persName>.—He filled the
               couch and had filled the heavens;—to Him be thanksgiving!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>In the fifth year let the Sun that burns the earth with its heat—give thanks to our
               Sun that He straitened His largeness,—and tempered His force that the eye might
               endure to see Him;—the inward eye of a pure soul; blessed be His radiance!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>In the sixth year again let all the air give thanks with us,—in the vastness whereof
               all things exult.—It saw its great Lord that He became—a little babe in a lowly
               bosom; blessed be His honour!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>In the seventh year let the clouds and winds sound the trumpet with us,—they whose
               dew sprinkles the faces of the flowers,—yet saw they the Son that He subdued His
               brightness,—and endured scorn and shameful spitting;—blessed be His salvation!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>Yet again in the eighth year let Creation give glory,—from whose fountain the fruits
               draw nurture.—She adored when she saw the Son at the breast,—pure babe nurtured by
               pure milk; blessed be His good pleasure!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>In the ninth year let the earth give glory, which when her lap is watered then
               brings forth the root.—She saw <persName>Mary</persName> an unwatered soil—whose fruit that she yielded is
               a mighty sea; to Him be exultation!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: To Thee be glory, Son of the Lord of all, Who givest life to all!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>In the tenth year let <placeName>Mount Sinai</placeName> give glory, which melted—before its Lord! It saw
               against its Lord—stones taken up: but He took stones—to build the Church upon the
               Rock; blessed be His building!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>In the eleventh year let the great sea give thanks—to the hand of the Son Who
               measured it! And it wondered to see how He came down and was washed—in humble waters,
               He that cleanses Creation; blessed be His triumph!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>In the twelfth year let the holy Temple give thanks—which beheld the Child as He
               sat—among the elders: the doctors were silenced—as the Lamb of the feast bleated in
               the feast; blessed be His atonement!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>In the thirteenth year let diadems with us give thanks—to the King Who triumphed and
               was crowned—with a crown of thorns: He wove for man—a mighty diadem at His right
               hand; blessed be He That sent Him!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>In the fourteenth year let the Passover of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> give thanks—to the Passover that
               came and made passover for all,—and instead of <!-- Not sure Pharoah is a name or title-->Pharaoh overwhelmed Legion,—and
               instead of horsemen drowned demons; blessed be His retribution!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>In the fifteenth year let the lamb of the flock give thanks,—that our Lord slew it
               not as did <persName>Moses</persName>,—but redeemed by His Blood mankind.—He the Shepherd of all died for
               all; blessed be He That begat Him!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>In the sixteenth year let the seed-corn in mystery give thanks—to that Husbandman
               Who gave His Body for seed—in a barren soil that corrupts all things.—It proved
               fertile and yielded new bread; blessed be He that is pure!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>In the seventeenth year let the Vine give thanks to our Lord,—the Vineyard of truth,
               wherein souls were—as the scions. He gave peace to this vineyard, but laid waste that
               vineyard which bare wild grapes; blessed be the Uprooter!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>In the eighteenth year let our leaven give thanks—to the leaven of truth that
               penetrates and draws—all minds and makes them to become—one mind in one doctrine;
               blessed be His doctrine!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>In the nineteenth year let the Salt give thanks for Thy Body.—O blessed Babe it is
               the soul—that is the salt of the Body, and Faith—the salt of the soul whereby it is
               preserved; blessed be Thy preservation!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Glory to Thy Epiphany, O God and Man!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>In the twentieth year let temporal wealth with us give thanks,—which men that are
               perfect have cast off and abandoned—because of the <quote>Woe</quote>; and have gone and
               loved—poverty because of its beatitude; blessed be He Who desired it!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>In the one-and-twentieth year let the waters give thanks that were sweetened—in a
               mystery of the Son. In the honey of <persName>Samson</persName>—the nations tasted bitterness therein that
               destroyed them:—they had life in the Cross that redeemed them; blessed be its
               pleasantness!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>In the two-and-twentieth year let arms and the sword give thanks,—for they could not
               slay our Adversary.—Thou art He Who slew him as Thou art He Who restored—the ear that
               <persName>Simon</persName>’s sword cut off; blessed be Thy healing!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>In the three-and-twentieth year let the ass likewise give thanks,—that gave the colt
               whereon He should ride;—He opens likewise the mouth of wild asses,—the offspring gave
               Him praise; blessed be the praise of Thee!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <ab>In the four-and-twentieth year let wealth give thanks to the Son!—Treasures were
               amazed at the Lord of treasures,—how He grew up among the poor.—He made Himself poor
               that He might make all rich; blessed be His participation!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="29">
            <ab>In the five-and-twentieth year let <persName>Isaac</persName> give thanks to the Son—Who in the mount
               saved him from the knife,—and became in his stead the lamb to be slain.—The mortal
               escaped, and He died Who gives life to all; blessed be His offering!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="30">
            <ab>In the six-and-twentieth year let <persName>Moses</persName> with us give thanks,—who feared and fled
               from the slayers;—let him give thanks to the Son, for He it was Who on His
               feet—entered <placeName>Sheol</placeName> and spoiled it and came forth; blessed be His Resurrection!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="31">
            <ab>In the seven-and-twentieth year let the eloquent Orators—give thanks to the Son, for
               they could not find—means whereby we should prevail in our judgment:—He was silent in
               judgment and made our judgment prevail; to Him be applause!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="32">
            <ab>In the seven and twentieth year let all Judges give thanks,—who as being just have
               put to death illdoers;—let them give thanks to the Son Who instead of the evil—died
               as being good, though He was Son of the Just One; blessed be His mercies!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="33">
            <ab>In the eight-and-twentieth year let them give thanks to the Son,—all the mighty men
               who saved us not—from the captors. One is to be worshipped,—Who was slain and laid
               hold and saved us; blessed be His deliverance!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="34">
            <ab>In the nine-and-twentieth year let <persName>Job</persName> with us give thanks,—who bare sufferings in
               his own behalf:—but our Lord bare on our behalf—the spitting and the stripes, the
               thorns and the nails; blessed is His compassion!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="35">
            <ab>In the year that is the thirtieth let them give thanks with us;—the dead that have
               lived through His dying,—the living that were converted in His Crucifixion,—and the
               height and the depth that have been reconciled in Him! Blessed be He and His
               Father!</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <!-- Please add footnote numbers. -->
            <note xml:id="n1">Equivalent to Augustus.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">i.e., Dayspring.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
