<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Epiphany 1</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Hymns for Epiphany</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_I"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_I
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 1</head>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: To Thee be praise from Thy flock in the day of Thy Epiphany!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>The heavens He has renewed, for that fools worshipped all the luminaries:—He has
               renewed the earth, for that in Adam it was wasted.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/>—That which He fashioned has
               become new by His spittle:—and the All-Sufficing has restored bodies with souls.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Gather yourselves again ye—sheep and without labour receive cleansing!—for one needs
               not as Elisha—to bathe seven times in the river, nor again to be wearied as the
               priests are wearied with sprinklings.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Gather yourselves again ye—sheep and without labour receive cleansing!—for one needs
               not as Elisha—to bathe seven times in the river, nor again to be wearied as the
               priests are wearied with sprinklings.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Moses sweetened in Marah the waters that were bitter,—because the People complained
               and murmured:—Thus he gave a sign of baptism,—wherein the Lord of life makes sweet
               them that were bitter.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>The cloud overshadowed and kept off the burning heat from the camp;—it showed a
               symbol of the Holy Spirit, which overshadows you in baptism—tempering the flaming
               fire that it harm not your bodies.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Through the sea the People then passed, and showed a symbol—of the baptism wherein
               ye were washed. The People passed through that and believed not:—the Gentiles were
               baptized in this and believed and received the Holy Ghost.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>The Word sent the Voice to proclaim before His Coming,—to prepare for Him the way by
               which He came,—and to betroth the Bride till He should come,—that she might be ready
               when He should come and take her from the water.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>The voice of prophecy stirred the son of the barren woman,—and he went forth
               wandering in the desert and crying,—<quote>Lo! the Son of the Kingdom comes!—prepare ye the
               way that He may enter and abide in your dwellings!</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>John cried, <quote>Who comes after me, He is before me:—I am the Voice but not the Word;—I
               am the torch but not the Light;—the Star that rises before the Sun of
               Righteousness.</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>In the wilderness this John had cried and had said,—<quote>Repent ye sinners of your
               evils,—and offer the fruits of repentance;—for lo! He comes that winnows the wheat
               from the tares.</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>The Lightgiver has prevailed and marked a mystery, by the degrees he ascended:—Lo!
               there are twelve days since he ascended,—and to-day this is the thirteenth:—a perfect
               mystery of Him, the Son, and His twelve!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>Darkness was overcome to make it manifest that Satan was overcome;—and the Light
               prevailed that he should proclaim—that the Firstborn triumphs: darkness was
               overcome—with the Dark Spirit, and our Light prevailed with the Lightgiver.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>In the Height and the Depth the Son had two heralds.—The star of light proclaimed
               Him from above;—John likewise preached Him from beneath:—two heralds, the earthly and
               the heavenly.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>The star of light, contrary to nature, shone forth of a sudden;—less than the sun
               yet greater than the sun.—Less was it than he in manifest light;—and greater than he
               in secret might because of its mystery.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>The star of light shed its rays among them that were in darkness,—and guided them as
               though they were blind;—so that they came and met the great Light:—they gave
               offerings and received life and adored and departed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>The herald from above showed His Nature to be from the Most High;—likewise he that
               was from beneath showed His Body to be from humankind, mighty marvel!—that His
               Godhead and His Manhood by them were proclaimed!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>Thus whoso reckons Him as of earth, the star of light—will convince him that He is
               of Heaven: and whoso reckons Him as of spirit,—this John will convince him that He is
               also bodily.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>John drew near with his parents and worshipped the Sun,—and brightness rested on His
               Face.—He was not moved as when in the womb.—Mighty marvel! that here he worships and
               there he leaped!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>The whole creation became for Him as one mouth and cried out concerning Him.—The
               Magi cry out in their gifts;—the barren cry out with their children;—the star of
               light, lo! it cries out in the air, <quote>Behold the Son of the King!</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>The heavens are opened, the waters break forth, the dove is in glory!—The voice of
               the Father is stronger than thunder,—as it utters the word, <quote>This is My Beloved</quote>;—the
               Watchers brought the tidings, the children acclaimed Him in their Hosannas.</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <!-- Please add footnote numbers. -->
            <note xml:id="n">See p. 177.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
