<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Epiphany 3</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Hymns for Epiphany</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_III"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Hymns_For_the_Feast_of_the_Epiphany/Hymn_III
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 3</head>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: <persName>Christ</persName> <!--Not sure if Christ should be marked-->with chrism, lo! He is sealing the newborn lambs in His flock!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab><persName>Christ</persName> and chrism are conjoined; the secret with the visible is mingled: the chrism
               anoints visibly,—<persName>Christ</persName> seals secretly, the lambs newborn and spiritual, the prize of
               His twofold victory; for He engendered it of the chrism, and He gave it birth of the
               water.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>How exalted are your Orders! For she that was a sinner anointed, as a handmaid, the
               feet of her Lord. But for you, as though His minister, <persName>Christ</persName> by the hand of His
               servants, seals and anoints your bodies. It befits Him the Lord of the flock, that in
               His own person He seal His sheep.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Since then she, that sinner, stood in need of forgiveness, the anointing was for her
               an offering, and by it her love reconciled her Lord. But you who are the flock, among
               the profane and unbelievers, the Truth by the chrism is your seal, to separate you
               from the strayed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>From the peoples he separated the People, by the former seal of circumcision; but by
               the seal of anointing, the peoples He separates from the People. When the peoples
               were in error, the People He separated from the peoples; now when the People has
               erred from Him, He separates the peoples from thence.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Of the dust of the pure soil, <persName>Naaman</persName> bore away and returned to his place; that he by
               this holy dust, might be separated and known from the unclean. The chrism of <persName>Christ</persName>
               separates, the sons of the mystery from strangers: and by it they that are within are
               separated, and known from them that are without.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>The oil which <persName>Elijah</persName> multiplied, might be tasted with the mouth; for the cruse was
               that of the widow, it was not that of the chrism. The oil of our Lord that is in the
               cruse, it is not food for the mouth: the sinner that was a wolf without, it makes him
               a lamb in the flock.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>The chrism of the meek and lowly One, changes the stubborn to be like its Lord. The
               Gentiles were wolves and feared, the severe rod of <persName>Moses</persName>. Lo! the chrism seals them
               and makes, a flock of sheep out of the wolves! And the wolves that had fled from the
               rod, lo! they have taken refuge in the Cross!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>The leaf of olive arrived, brought as a figure of the anointing; the sons of the Ark
               rejoiced to greet it, for it bore good tidings of deliverance. Thus also ye rejoiced
               to greet it, even this holy anointing. The bodies of sinners were glad in it, for it
               brought good tidings of deliverance.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>The oil again that Jacob poured, upon the stone when he sealed it, that it should be
               between him and God, and that he might offer there his tithes; lo! in it is a symbol
               of your bodies, how by chrism they are sealed as holy, and become temples for God,
               where He shall be served by your sacrifices.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>When <persName>Moses</persName> had sealed and anointed, the sons of <persName>Aaron</persName> the Levite, the fire consumed
               their bodies; the fire spared their vestments. But ye my brethren blessed are ye, for
               the fire of grace has come down, has consumed utterly your offences, and cleansed and
               hallowed your bodies!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>As for the anointing of <persName>Aaron</persName> my brethren, it was the vile blood of beasts, that it
               sprinkled in the horns of the altar. The anointing of truth is this; wherein the
               living and all-lifegiving Blood, is sprinkled inwardly in your bodies, is mingled in
               your understandings, is infused through your inmost chambers.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>The anointed priests used to offer, the slain bodies of beasts; Ye, O anointed and
               excelling, your offerings are your own bodies. The anointed Levites offered, the
               inward parts taken, from beasts: ye have excelled the Levites, for your hearts ye
               have Consecrated.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>The anointing of the People was—a foreshadowing of <persName>Christ</persName>; their rod a mystery of
               the Cross; their lamb a type of the Only begotten; their tabernacle a mystery of your
               Churches; their circumcision a sign of your sealing. Under the shadow of your goodly
               thing, sat the People of old.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Thus the truth is likened, to a great shadowing tree: it cast its shade on the
               People; it struck its root among the peoples. The People abode under its shadows,
               whose shadows were its mysteries; but the Gentiles lodged on its bough, and plucked
               and ate of its fruits.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>As for the anointing of <persName>Saul</persName> to be king; the sweeter was its savour, so much fouler
               was the savour of his heart. The Spirit struck him and fled. Your anointing which ye
               have is greater; for your minds are censers, in your temples the Spirit exults, a
               chamber forever shall ye be unto Him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>As for the anointing of <persName>David</persName> my brethren; the Spirit came down and made sweet
               savour, in the heart of the man wherein He delighted; the savour of his heart was as
               the savour of his action. The Spirit dwelt in him and made song in him. Your
               anointing which ye have is greater, for Father and Son and Holy Ghost, have moved and
               come down to dwell in you.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>When the leper of old was cleansed, the priest used to seal him with oil, and to
               lead him to the waterspring. The type has passed and the truth is come; lo! with
               chrism have ye been sealed, in baptism ye are perfected, in the flock ye are
               intermixed, from the Body ye are nourished.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>What leper when he has been cleansed, turns again and desires his leprosy? Ye have
               put off transgressions—forsake it! None puts on the leprosy he had put off. It has
               fallen and sunk—let it not be drawn out! It is wasted and worn—let it not be renewed!
               Let not corruption come out upon you, whom the chrism of <persName>Christ</persName> has anointed!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>The vessel moulded of clay, gains beauty from the water, receives strength from the
               fire; but if it slips it is ruined, it cannot be afresh renewed. Ye are vessels of
               grace; be ye ware of it, even of justice, for it grants not two renewals.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>How like are ye in comparison, with the Prophet whom the fish yielded up! The
               Devourer has given you back for he was constrained, by the Power Which constrained
               the fish. <persName>Jonah</persName> was for you as a mirror, since not again did the fish swallow him,
               let not again the Devourer swallow you: being yielded up be ye like <persName>Jonah</persName>!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>Goodly ointment on the head of our Lord did <persName>Mary</persName> pour; its savour was fragrant
               through all the house. Likewise the savour of your anointing, has been fragrant and
               perfumed the heavens, to the Watchers on high; doing pleasure to <persName>Satan</persName> its savour is
               overpowering; to God its odour is sweet.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>The crowds in the desert were like unto sheep that have no shepherd. The Merciful
               became their shepherd, and multiplied to them the pasture of bread. Yea, blessed are
               ye that are perfect, that are sealed as lambs of <persName>Christ</persName>, that of His Body and Blood
               are made worthy; the Pastor Himself is become pasture for you!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>Out of water He made the wine, He gave it for drink to the youths in the feast. For
               you who are keeping the fast, better is the unction than drink. In His wine the
               betrothed are wedded, by His oil the wedded are sanctified. By His wine is union; by
               His oil sanctification.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>The sheep of <persName>Christ</persName> leaped for joy, to receive the seal of life, that ensign of
               kings which has ever put sin to flight. The Wicked by Thy ensign is routed,
               iniquities by Thy sign are scattered. Come, ye sheep, receive your seal, which puts
               to flight them that devour you!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>Come, ye lambs, receive your seal, for it is truth that is your seal! This is the
               seal that separates, them of the household from strangers. The steel circumcised
               alike, the gainsayers and the sons of <persName>Hagar</persName>. If circumcision be the sign of the
               sheep, lo! by it the goats are signed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>But ye, who are the new flock, have put off the doings of wolves, and as lambs are
               made like to the Lamb. One by changing has changed all; the Lamb to the wolves gave
               Himself to be slain; the wolves rushed and devoured Him and became lambs; for the
               Shepherd was changed into a Lamb; likewise the wolf forgot his nature.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>Look on me also in Thy mercy! be not branded on me the seal, of the goats the sons
               of the left hand! let not Thy sheep become a goat! For though to justify myself I
               sufficed not, yet to be a sinner I willed not. Turn thine eyes, O my Lord, from what
               I have done, and seek not only what I have willed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <ab>From them that write and them that preach, from them that hear and them that are
               sealed, let glory go up to <persName>Christ</persName>, and through Him to His Father be exaltation! He
               Who gives words to them that speak, and gives voice to them that preach, has given
               understanding to them that hear, and consecrates chrism for him that is sealed.</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
