<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8508" n="6"> Demonstration
               6: On the Bnay Qyama - <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܚܘܝܬܐ ܕܒ̈ܢܝ ܩܝܡܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8501">The
               Demonstrations</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/10">Aphrahat</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
               target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Select_Demonstrations_of_Aphrahat/Of_Monks"
                  >
               https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Select_Demonstrations_of_Aphrahat/Of_Monks
               </ref>. This transcription available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <head type="editorial">1</head>
            <p> Expedient is the word that I speak and worthy of acceptance:—Let us now awake from
               our sleep,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> and lift up both our hearts and hands to God towards heaven; lest
               suddenly the Lord of the house come, that when He comes He may find us in
               watchfulness.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> Let us observe the appointed time of the glorious bridegroom,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/>
               that we may enter with Him into His bride-chamber. Let us prepare oil for our lamps
               that we may go forth to meet Him with joy. Let us make ready provision for our
               abiding-place, for the way that is narrow and strait. And let us put away and cast
               from us all uncleanness, and put on wedding garments. Let us trade with the silver
               that we have received,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> that we may be called diligent servants. Let us be constant
               in prayer, that we may pass by the place where fear dwells. Let us cleanse our heart
               from iniquity, that we may see the Lofty One in His honour. Let us be merciful, as it
               is written, that God may have mercy upon us.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> Let there be peace amongst us, that
               we may be called the brethren of Christ. Let us hunger for righteousness, that we may
               be satisfied<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> from the table of His Kingdom. Let us be the salt of truth, that we
               may not become food for the serpent. Let us purge our seed from thorns, that we may
               produce fruit a hundred-fold. Let us found our building on the rock,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> that it may
               not be shaken by the winds and waves. Let us be vessels unto honour<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> that we may be
               required by the Lord for His use. Let us sell all our possessions, and buy for
               ourselves the pearl,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/> that we may be rich. Let us lay up our treasures in
               heaven,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/> that when we come we may open them and have pleasure in them. Let us
               visit our Lord in the persons of the sick,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> that He may invite us to stand at His
               right hand. Let us hate ourselves and love Christ, as He loved us and gave Himself up
               for our sakes.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12"/> Let us honour the spirit of Christ, that we may receive grace from
               Him. Let us be strangers to the world,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> even as Christ was not of it. Let us be
               humble and mild, that we may inherit the land of life. Let us be unflagging in His
               service, that He may cause us to serve in the abode of the saints. Let us pray His
               prayer in purity, that it may have access to the Lord of Majesty. Let us be partakers
               in His suffering, that so we may also rise up in His resurrection.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/> Let us bear
               His sign upon our bodies, that we may be delivered from the wrath to come. For
               fearful is the day in which He will come, and who is able to endure it?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15"/> Furious
               and hot is His wrath, and it will destroy all the wicked. Let us set upon our head
               the helmet of redemption,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16"/> that we may not be wounded and die in the battle. Let
               us gird our loins with truth, that we may not be found impotent in the contest. Let
               us arise and awaken Christ, that He may still the stormy blasts from us. Let us take
               as a shield against the Evil One, the preparation of the Gospel of our Redeemer. Let
               us receive power from our Lord to tread upon snakes and scorpions.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17"/> Let us lay
               aside from us wrath, with all fury and malice. Let no reviling proceed out of our
               mouth, with which we pray unto God. Let us not be cursers, that we may be delivered
               from the curse of the law. Let us be diligent workers, that we may obtain our reward
               with those of old. Let us take up the burden of the day, that we may seek a more
               abundant reward. Let us not be idle workers, for lo! our Lord has hired us for His
               vineyard.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18"/> Let us be planted as vines in the midst of His vineyard, for it is the
               true vineyard. Let us be fruitful vines, that we may not be uprooted out of His
               vineyard. Let us be a sweet odour, that our fragrance may breathe forth to all
               around. Let us be poor in the world, and let us enrich many by the doctrine of our
               Lord. Let us not call anyone our father in the earth,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19"/> that we may be the children
               of the Father which is in heaven. Though we have nothing, yet we possess all
               things.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20"/> Though no man know us, yet they that have knowledge of us are many. Let
               us rejoice in our hope at every time,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21"/> that He Who is our hope and our Redeemer
               may rejoice in us. Let us judge ourselves righteously and condemn ourselves, that we
               may not hang down our faces before the judges who shall sit upon thrones and judge
               the tribes.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22"/> Let us take to ourselves, as armour for the contest,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23"/> the
               preparation of the Gospel. Let us knock at the door of heaven,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24"/> that it may be
               opened before us, and we may enter in through it. Let us diligently ask for mercy,
               that we may receive whatsoever is necessary for us. Let us seek His Kingdom and His
               righteousness,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25"/> that we may receive increase in the land. Let us think upon the
               things which are above,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n26"/> on the heavenly things, and meditate on them, where
               Christ has been lifted up and exalted. But let us forsake the world which is not
               ours, that we may arrive at the place to which we have been invited. Let us raise up
               our eyes on high, that we may see the splendour which shall be revealed. Let us lift
               up our wings as eagles, that we may see the body there where it is. Let us prepare as
               offerings for the King desirable fruits, fasting and prayer. Let us guard His pledge
               in purity, that He may trust us over all His treasury. For whosoever deals falsely
               with His pledge, they suffer him not to enter into the treasure-house. Let us be
               careful of the body of Christ, that our bodies may rise at the sound of the trumpet.
               Let us hearken to the voice of the bridegroom, that we may go in with Him into the
               bride-chamber. Let us prepare the marriage-gift for His bridal day, and let us go
               forth to meet Him with joy. Let us put on holy raiment, that we may recline in the
               chief place of the elect. Whosoever puts not on wedding raiment,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27"/> they cast him
               out into outer darkness. Whosoever excuses himself from the wedding shall not taste
               the feast.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28"/> Whosoever loves fields and merchandise, shall be shut out of the city
               of Saints. Whosoever does not bear fruit in the vineyard, shall be uprooted and cast
               out to torment. Whosoever has received money from his Lord, let him return it to its
               Giver with its increase.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29"/> Whosoever desires to become a merchant, let, him buy for
               himself the field and the treasure that is in it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30"/> Whosoever receives the good
               seed, let him purge his land from thorns.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31"/> Whosoever desires to be a fisherman,
               let him cast forth his net at every time. Whosoever is training for the conflict, let
               him keep himself from the world. Whosoever wishes to gain the crown, let him run as a
               winner in the race. Whosoever wishes to go down into the course to contend, let him
               learn to (contend) against his adversary. Whosoever wishes to go down to the battle,
               let him take unto him armour wherewith to fight, and let him purify himself at every
               time. Whosoever adopts the likeness of angels, let him be a stranger to men.
               Whosoever takes upon him the yoke of the saints, let him remove from him getting and
               spending. Whosoever desires to gain himself, let him remove from him the gain of the
               world. Whosoever loves the abode that is in heaven, let him not toil at the building
               of clay that will fall. Whosoever is expectant of being caught up in the clouds, let
               him not make for himself adorned chariots. Whosoever is expectant of the
               marriage-feast of the Bridegroom, let him not love the feast of this present time.
               Whosoever wishes to have pleasure in the banquet reserved there, let him remove
               drunkenness from himself. Whosoever prepares himself for the supper, let him not
               excuse himself,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n32"/> nor be a merchant. Whosoever he be on whom the good seed falls,
               let him not allow the Evil One to sow tares in him. Whosoever has begun to build a
               tower, let him count up all the cost thereof.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33"/> Whosoever builds ought to finish,
               that he be not a laughing-stock to them that pass by the way. Whosoever sets his
               building on the rock, let him make its foundations deep, that it may not be cast down
               by the billows. Whosoever wishes to fly from the darkness, let him walk while he has
               light.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34"/> Whosoever fears to fly in winter,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35"/> let him prepare himself from the
               summer-time. Whosoever looks forward to enter into rest,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36"/> let him make ready his
               provision for the Sabbath. Whosoever begs forgiveness of his Lord, let him also
               forgive his debtor.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37"/> Whosoever does not demand back a hundred dinars, his Lord
               forgives him ten thousand talents. Whosoever casts down his Lord’s money on the
               banker’s table,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38"/> will not be called an unprofitable servant. Whosoever loves
               humility, shall be heir in the land of life. Whosoever wishes to make peace, shall be
               one of the sons of God.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n39"/> Whosoever knows the will of his Lord, let him do that
               will, that he may not be beaten much.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n40"/> Whosoever cleanses his heart from deceits,
               His eyes shall behold the King in his beauty.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41"/> Whosoever receives the Spirit of
               Christ, let him adorn his inner man. Whosoever is called the temple of God,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42"/> let
               him purify his body from all uncleanness. Whosoever grieves the Spirit of Christ,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43"/>
               shall not raise up his head from griefs. Whosoever receives the body of Christ, let
               him keep his body from all uncleanness. Whosoever casts off the old man,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44"/> let him
               not turn back to his former works. Whosoever puts on the new man, let him keep
               himself from all filthiness. Whosoever has put on armour from the water (of baptism),
               let him not put off his armour that he may not be condemned. Whosoever takes up the
               shield<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n45"/> against the Evil One, let him keep himself from the darts which he hurls
               at him. Whosoever shall draw back, his Lord has no pleasure in him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46"/> Whosoever
               thinks upon the Law of his Lord, shall not be troubled with the thoughts of this
               world. Whosoever meditates on the Law of his Lord, is like a tree planted by the
               waters.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47"/> Whosoever again has trust in his Lord, is like a tree that is set out by
               the river. Whosoever puts his trust in man shall receive the curses of Jeremiah.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48"/>
               Whosoever is invited to the Bridegroom, let him prepare himself. Whosoever has
               lighted his lamp, let him not suffer it to go out. Whosoever is expectant of the
               marriage-cry, let him take oil in his vessel.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49"/> Whosoever is keeper of the door,
               let him be on the watch for his Master. Whosoever loves virginity, let him become
               like Elijah. Whosoever takes up the yoke of the Saints, let him sit and be silent.
               Whosoever loves peace, let him look for his Master as the hope of life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <head type="editorial">2</head>
            <p> For, my beloved, our adversary is skilful. He that contends against us is crafty.
               Against the brave and the renowned does he prepare himself, that they may be
               weakened. For the feeble are his own, nor does he fight with the captivity that are
               made captive to him. He that has wings flees from him and the darts that he hurls at
               him do not reach him. They that are spiritual see him when he assails, and his
               panoply has no power upon their bodies. All the children of light are without fear of
               him, because the darkness flies from before the light. The children of the Good fear
               not the Evil, for He hath given him to be trampled by their feet. When he makes
               himself like darkness unto them, they become light. And when he creeps upon them like
               a serpent, they become salt, whereof he cannot eat. If he makes himself like the asp
               unto them, then they become like babes. If he comes in upon them in the lust of food,
               they, like our Redeemer, conquer him by fasting. And if he wishes to contend with
               them by the lust of the eyes, they lift up their eyes to the height of heaven. If he
               wishes by enticements to overcome them, they do not afford him a hearing. If he
               wishes openly to strive with them, lo! they are clothed in panoply and stand up
               against him. If he wishes to come in against them by sleep, they are wakeful and
               vigilant and sing psalms and pray. If he allures them by possessions, they give them
               to the poor. If he comes in as sweetness against them, they taste it not, knowing
               that he is bitter. If he inflames them with the desire of Eve, they dwell alone, and
               not with the daughters of Eve. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <head type="editorial">3</head>
            <p> For it was through Eve that he came in upon Adam,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50"/> and Adam was enticed because
               of his inexperience. And again he came in against Joseph through his master’s
               wife,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51"/> but Joseph was acquainted with his craftiness and would not afford him a
               hearing. Through a woman he fought with Samson,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n52"/> until he took away his
               Nazariteship. Reuben was the first-born of all his brethren, and through his father’s
               wife,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n53"/> (the adversary) cast a blemish upon him. Aaron was the great high-priest of
               the house of Israel, and through Miriam<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54"/> his sister he envied Moses. Moses was
               sent to deliver the people from Egypt, and took with him the woman who advised him to
               shameful acts,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55"/> and the Lord met with Moses, and desired to slay him, till he sent
               back his wife to Midian. David was victorious in all his battles, yet through means
               of a daughter of Eve<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n56"/> there was found a blemish in him. Amnon was beautiful and
               fair in countenance, yet (the adversary) took him captive by desire for his
               sister,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n57"/> and Absalom slew him on account of the humbling of Tamar. Solomon was
               greater than all the kings of the earth, yet in the days of his old age his wives led
               his heart astray.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n58"/> Through Jezebel, daughter of Ethbaal, the wickedness of Ahab
               was increased,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n59"/> and he became altogether a heathen. Furthermore, the adversary
               tempted Job through his children and his possessions,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n60"/> and when he could not
               prevail over him, he went and brought against him his armour, and he came, bringing
               with him a daughter of Eve, who had caused Adam to sink, and through her mouth he
               said to Job, her righteous husband:—Curse God.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n61"/> But Job rejected her counsel. King
               Asa also conquered the Accursed-of-life, when he wished to come in against him,
               through his mother.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62"/> For Asa knew his craftiness and removed his mother from her
               high estate, and cut in pieces her idol and cast it down. John was greater than all
               the prophets, yet Herod slew him because of the dancing of a daughter of Eve.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n63"/>
               Haman was wealthy and third in honour from the King, yet his wife counselled him to
               destroy the Jews.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64"/> Zimri was head of the tribe of Simeon, yet Cozbi, daughter of
               the chiefs of Midian, overthrew him, and because of one woman twenty-four thousand of
               Israel fell in one day.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65"/> </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <head type="editorial">4</head>
            <p> Therefore, my brethren, if any man who is a monk or a saint, who loves the solitary
               life, yet desires that a woman, bound by monastic vow like himself, should dwell with
               him, it would be better for him in that case to take (to wife) a woman openly and not
               be made wanton by lust. So also again the woman, if she be not separated from the
               solitary, it is better for her to marry openly. Woman then ought to dwell with woman,
               and man to dwell with man. And also whatever man desires to continue in holiness, let
               not his spouse dwell with him, lest he turn back to his former condition, and so be
               esteemed an adulterer. Therefore this counsel is becoming and right and good, that I
               give to myself and you, my beloved solitaries, who do not take wives, and to the
               virgins who do not marry, and to those who have loved holiness. It is just and right
               and becoming, that even if a man should be distressed, he should continue alone. And
               thus it becomes him to dwell, as it is written in the Prophet Jeremiah:—Blessed is
               the man who shall take up Thy yoke in his youth, and sit alone and be silent, because
               he has taken upon him Thy yoke.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66"/> For thus, my beloved, it becomes him who takes up
               the yoke of Christ, to preserve his yoke in purity. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <head type="editorial">5</head>
            <p> For thus it is written, my beloved, concerning Moses, that from the time the Holy
               One was revealed to him, he also loved holiness. And from the time he was sanctified,
               his wife ministered not to him. But it is thus written:—Joshua, the son of Nun, was
               the minister of Moses from his childhood.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n67"/> And of Joshua again it is thus written
               concerning him, that he used not to depart from the tabernacle.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n68"/> And the temporal
               tabernacle was not ministered to by a woman, because the Law did not allow women to
               enter the temporal tabernacle, but even when they came to pray, they used to pray at
               the door of the temporal tabernacle, and then turn back. Moreover, he commanded the
               Priests, that at the time of their ministry they should continue in holiness, and
               should not know their wives. And also concerning Elijah it is thus written, that at
               one time he dwelt in Mount Carmel, and at another he dwelt at the brook Cherith, and
               was ministered to by his disciple; and because his heart was in heaven, the bird of
               heaven used to bring sustenance to him; and because he took upon him the likeness of
               the angels of heaven, those very angels brought him bread and water when he was
               fleeing from before Jezebel.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n69"/> And because he set all his thought in heaven, he was
               caught up in the chariot of fire to heaven,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n70"/> and there his dwelling-place was
               established for ever. Elisha also walked in the footsteps of his Master. He used to
               dwell in the upper chamber of the Shunamite, and was ministered to by his disciple.
               For thus the Shunamite said;—He is a holy Prophet of God and passes by us
               continually, for thus it becomes his holiness that we should make for him an upper
               chamber and do for him the service that is (necessary) in it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n71"/> Now what was the
               service necessary in the upper chamber of Elisha? Clearly the bed and table and stool
               and lamp-stand only. But what shall we say of John? He also used to dwell amongst
               men, and preserved his virginity honourably, and received the Spirit of God.
               Moreover, the blessed Apostle said concerning himself and concerning Barnabas:—Had we
               then not power to eat and to drink and to lead about wives with us? But it was not
               becoming or right.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n72"/> </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <head type="editorial">6</head>
            <p> Therefore, brethren, because we know and have seen that from the beginning it was
               through woman that the adversary had access unto men, and to the end he will
               accomplish it by her—for she is the weapon of Satan, and through her he fights
               against the champions. Through her he makes music at every time, for she became as a
               harp for him from the first day. For because of her the curse of the Law was
               established, and because of her the promise unto death was made. For with pangs she
               bears children and delivers them to death. Because of her the earth was cursed, that
               it should bring forth thorns and tares. Accordingly, by the coming of the offspring
               of the Blessed Mary the thorns are uprooted, the sweat wiped away, the fig-tree
               cursed,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n73"/> the dust made salt,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74"/> the curse nailed to the cross,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n75"/> the edge of
               the sword removed from before the tree of life and it given as food to the faithful,
               and Paradise promised to the blessed and to virgins and to the saints. So the fruit
               of the tree of life is given as food to the faithful and to virgins, and to those
               that do the will of God has the door been opened and the way made plain. And the
               fountain flows and gives drink to the thirsty. The table is laid and the supper
               prepared. The fatted ox is slain and the cup of redemption mixed. The feast is
               prepared and the Bridegroom at hand, soon to take his place. The apostles have given
               the invitation and the called are very many. O ye chosen, prepare yourselves. The
               light has shone forth both bright and fair, and garments not made with hands are
               prepared. The marriage cry is at hand. The tombs will be opened and the treasures
               laid bare. The dead shall rise and the living shall fly to meet the King. The banquet
               is laid, and the cornet shall encourage and the trumpets shall hasten (them). The
               Watchers of heaven shall speed, and the throne shall be set for the Judge. He that
               laboured shall rejoice, and he that was unprofitable shall fear. He that did evil
               shall not draw nigh unto the Judge. Those on the right hand shall exult, and those on
               the left shall weep and wail. Those that are in the light shall be glorified, and
               those that are in the darkness shall groan that they may moisten their tongue. Grace
               has gone by, and justice reigns. There is no repentance in that place. Winter is at
               hand; the summer has passed away. The Sabbath of rest has come; toil has ceased.
               Night has passed away; the light reigns. As to death, its sting is broken and it is
               swallowed up in life.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76"/> Those that return to Sheol shall weep and gnash their
               teeth, and those that go to the Kingdom shall rejoice and exult and dance and sing
               praises. For those that take not wives shall be ministered to by the Watchers of
               heaven. Those that preserve chastity shall rest in the sanctuary of the Most High.
               The Only Begotten Who is from the bosom of His Father shall cause all the solitaries
               to rejoice. There is there neither male nor female, neither bond nor free,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77"/> but
               they all are the children of the Most High. And all the pure virgins who are
               betrothed to Christ shall light their lamps<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78"/> and with the Bridegroom shall they go
               into the marriage chamber. All those that are betrothed to Christ are far removed
               from the curse of the Law, and are redeemed from the condemnation of the daughters of
               Eve; for they are not wedded to men so as to receive the curses and come into the
               pains. They take no thought of death, because they do not deliver children to him.
               And in place of a mortal husband, they are betrothed to Christ. And because they do
               not bear children, there is Given to them the name that is better than sons and
               daughters.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n79"/> And instead of the groans of the daughters of Eve, they utter the
               songs of the Bridegroom. The wedding-feast of the daughters of Eve continues for but
               seven days; but for these (virgins) is the Bridegroom who departs not for ever. The
               adornment of the daughters of Eve is wool that wears out and perishes, but the
               garments of these wear not out. Old age withers the beauty of the daughters of Eve,
               but the beauty of these shall be renewed in the time of the Resurrection. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <head type="editorial">7</head>
            <p> O ye virgins who have betrothed yourselves to Christ, when one of the monks shall
               say to one of you, “I will live with thee and minister thou to me,” thus shalt thou
               say unto him:—“To a royal husband am I betrothed, and Him do I serve; and if I leave
               His service and serve thee, my betrothed will be wroth with me, and will write me a
               letter of divorce, and will send me away from His house; and while thou seekest to be
               honoured by me, and I to be honoured by thee, take heed lest hurt come upon me and
               thee. Take not fire into thy bosom,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n80"/> lest it burn thy garments; but be thou in
               honour alone, and I also alone will abide in my honour. And as concerning these
               things which the Bridegroom has prepared for the eternity of his marriage feast, do
               thou make thee a wedding-gift and prepare thyself to meet Him. And as for me, I will
               make me ready oil, that I may enter in with the wise virgins and may not be kept
               outside the door with the foolish virgins.” </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <head type="editorial">8</head>
            <p> Hearken then, my beloved, unto that which I write unto thee, namely, whatsoever
               things become solitaries, monks, virgins, saints. Before all things it beseems the
               man on whom the yoke is laid, that his faith should be firm; as I wrote to thee in
               the first epistle; that he should be zealous in fasting and prayer; that he should be
               fervent in the love of Christ; and should be humble and mild and wise. And let his
               speech be peaceful and pleasant, and his thought be sincere with all. Let him speak
               his words duly weighing them, and set a barrier to his mouth from harmful words, and
               let him put far from him hasty laughter. Let him not love the adornment of garments,
               nor again does it become him to let his hair grow long and adorn it, or to anoint it
               with sweet-scented unguents. Let him not recline at feastings, nor does it become him
               to wear gorgeous apparel. Let him not dare to exceed at wine. Let him put far from
               him proud thoughts. It does not become him to look upon gorgeous apparel, or to wear
               fine raiment. Let him put away from him a crafty tongue; let him drive from him envy
               and wrath, and cast away from him crafty lips. The words that are spoken about a man,
               when he about whom they are spoken is not near, let him not hear nor receive, that he
               sin not, until he search them out. Mockery is a hateful fault, and to bring it up
               upon the heart is not right. Let him not lend and take interest, and let him not love
               avarice. Let him suffer wrong and not do wrong. Furthermore, let him put away from
               him turmoil, and words of jesting let him not utter. Let him not scorn any man who is
               repenting of his sins, and let him not mock his brother who is fasting, and him that
               cannot fast let him not put to shame. Where he is received, let him reprove, and
               where they receive him not, let him understand his own honour. In an acceptable time
               let him speak his word; otherwise, let him be silent. Let him not for his belly’s
               sake make himself despised by his begging, and to such an one as fears God let him
               reveal his secret; but let him keep himself from the evil (man). Let him not speak in
               complaisance with a wicked man, nor with his enemy. And so let him contend as to have
               no enemy at all. When men envy him in that which is good, let him add to his
               goodness, and let him not be harmed because of envy. When he has, and gives to the
               poor, let him rejoice; and when he has not, let it not grieve him. With a wicked man
               let him have no converse and with a contemptuous man let him not speak, lest he give
               himself to contempt. With a blasphemer let him not dispute, lest his Lord be
               blasphemed on his account. Let him depart from a slanderer, and let no man please
               another man with speciousness of words. These things beseem solitaries who take up
               the heavenly yoke, and become disciples of Christ. For thus it befits the disciples
               of Christ to be like unto Christ their Master. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <head type="editorial">9</head>
            <p> Let us take pattern, my beloved, from our Saviour, Who though He was rich, made
               Himself poor;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n81"/> and though He was lofty, humbled His Majesty; and though His
               dwelling place was in heaven, He had no place to lay His head;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n82"/> and though He is
               to come upon the clouds,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n83"/> yet rode on a colt and so entered Jerusalem;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n84"/> and
               though He is God and Son of God, He took upon Him the likeness of a servant;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n85"/> and
               though He was (for others) rest from all weariness, yet was Himself tired with the
               weariness of the journey; though He was the fountain that quenches thirst, yet
               Himself thirsted and asked for water;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n86"/> though He was abundance and satisfied our
               hunger, yet He Himself hungered when He went forth to the wilderness to be
               tempted;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n87"/> though He was a Watcher that slumbers not, He yet slumbered and slept in
               the ship in the midst of the sea;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n88"/> and though He was ministered to in the
               Tabernacle of His Father, yet let Himself be served by the hands of men; though He
               was the healer of all sick men, yet nails were fastened into His hands; though His
               mouth brought forth things that were good, yet they gave Him gall to eat;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n89"/> though
               He injured no man and harmed none, yet He was beaten with stripes and endured shame;
               and though he was Saviour of all mortals, He delivered Himself to the death of the
               cross. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <head type="editorial">10</head>
            <p> All this humility did our Saviour show us in Himself. Let us then also humble
               ourselves, my beloved. When our Lord went outside of His nature,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n90"/> He walked in our
               nature. Let us abide in our nature, that in the day of judgment He may cause us to
               partake of His nature. Our Lord took from us a pledge when He went, and He left us a
               pledge of His own when he ascended. He that was without need, because of our need
               devised this expedient. What was ours was His even from the beginning, but that which
               was His, who would have given us? But true is that which our Lord promised us:—Where
               I am there ye also shall be.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n91"/> For whatsoever He took of ours, is in honour with
               Him, and (as) a diadem is bound upon His Head. So also that, which of His we have
               received, we ought to honour. That which is ours is held in honour with Him who was
               not in our nature: let us honour that which is His in His own nature. If we honour
               Him, we shall go to Him, Who took upon Him of our nature and so ascended. But if we
               despise Him, He will take away from us that which He has given us. If we deal
               fraudulently with His pledge, He will there take away that which is His, and will
               deprive us of all that He has promised us. Let us magnify gloriously the King’s Son
               Who is with us, because a hostage for Him has been taken from us. Whoso holds the
               King’s Son in honour, shall obtain many gifts from the King. That of ours, that is
               with Him, has sat down in honour and a diadem is bound upon His head, and He has sat
               down with the King. And we who are poor, what shall we do to the King’s Son Who is
               with us? He needs nothing from us, but that we should adorn our temples for Him; that
               when the time is accomplished and He goes to His Father, He may give thanks to Him
               because of us, because we have honoured Him. When He came to us, He had nothing of
               ours, and also we had nothing of His, though the two natures were His and His
               Father’s. For when Gabriel made announcement to the Blessed Mary who bore Him, the
               word from on high set out and came, and the word became flesh and dwelt in us.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n92"/>
               And when He returned to Him that sent Him, He took away, when He went, that which He
               had not brought, as the Apostle said:—He has taken us up and seated us with Himself
               in the heavens.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n93"/> And when He went to His Father, He sent to us His Spirit and said
               to us I am with you till the world shall end. For Christ sitteth at the right hand of
               His Father, and Christ dwelleth among men.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n94"/> He is sufficient above and beneath, by
               the wisdom of His Father. And He dwells in many, though He is one, and all the
               faithful each by each He overshadows from Himself, and fails not, as it is written:—I
               will divide Him among many.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95"/> And though He is divided among many, yet He sits at
               the right hand of His Father. And He is in us and we are in Him, as He said:—Ye are
               in Me and I am in you.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n96"/> And in another place He said:—I and Father are one.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n97"/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <head type="editorial">11</head>
            <p> And if anyone, whose conscience lacks knowledge, should dispute about this and
               say:—“Since Christ is one and His Father is one, how does Christ dwell, and His
               Father dwell, in faithful men? And how do righteous men become temples for God that
               He should dwell in them? If then it is thus, that to each several faithful man there
               comes a several Christ, and God Who is in Christ,—if it is so, there are for them
               Gods many and Christs without number.” But hear, my beloved, the defence that is
               suited to this argument. From that which is visible let him that has thus said
               receive instruction. For every man knows that the sun is fixed in the heavens, yet
               its rays are spread out in the earth, and (light) from it enters by many doors and
               windows of houses; and wherever the sunshine falls, though it be but as (the measure
               of) the palm of the hand, it is called the sun. And though it fall in many places, it
               is thus called, but the real sun itself is in heaven. Therefore, if it is so, have
               they many suns? Also the water of the sea is vast, and when thou takest one cup from
               it, that is called water. And though thou shouldest divide it into a thousand
               vessels, yet it is called water by its name. Also when thou kindlest fire from fire
               in many places, the place from whence thou takest it, when thou kindlest it, lacks
               not, and the fire is called by one name. And because thou dividest it into many
               places, it does not on that account become possessed of many names. And when thou
               takest dust from the earth, and castest it into many places, it is not a whit
               diminished, and also thou canst not call it by many names. Thus also God and His
               Christ, though they are One, yet dwell in men who are many. And they are in heaven in
               person, and are diminished in nothing when they dwell in many; as the sun is not a
               whit diminished in heaven, when its power is poured out in the earth. How much
               greater then is the power of God, since by the power of God the very sun itself
               subsists. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <head type="editorial">12</head>
            <p> Again I will remind thee, my beloved, also of that which is written. For thus it is
               written, that when it was a grievous burden to Moses to lead the camp alone, the Lord
               said to him:—Lo! will take away of the Spirit that is upon thee, and will put it upon
               seventy men, elders of Israel.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n98"/> But when He took away some of the Spirit of Moses,
               and the seventy men were filled with it, Moses nothing lacked, nor could it be known
               that anything was taken away from his Spirit. Moreover the blessed apostle also
               said:—God divided of the Spirit of Christ and sent it into the Prophets.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n99"/> And
               Christ was in nothing injured, for it was not by measure that His Father gave unto
               Him the Spirit.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n100"/> By this reflection thou canst comprehend that Christ dwells in
               faithful men; yet Christ suffers no loss though He is divided among many. For the
               Prophets received of the Spirit of Christ, each one of them as he was able to bear.
               And of the Spirit of Christ again there is poured forth to-day upon all flesh,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n101"/>
               and the sons and the daughters prophesy, the old men and the youths, the men-servants
               and the hand-maids. Something of Christ is in us, yet Christ is in heaven at the
               right hand of His Father. And Christ received the Spirit not by measure, but His
               Father loved Him and delivered all into His hands, and gave Him authority over all
               His treasure. For John said:—Not by measure did the Father give the Spirit to His
               Son, but loved Him and gave all into His hands.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n102"/> And also our Lord said:—All
               things have been delivered unto Me by My Father.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n103"/> Again he said:—The Father will
               not judge any man, but all judgment will He give unto His Son.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n104"/> Again also the
               Apostle said:—Everything shall be made subject unto Christ except His Father Who hath
               subjected all unto Him. And when everything is made subject unto Him by the Father,
               then He also shall be made subject to God His Father Who subjected all to Him, and
               God shall be all in all, and in every man.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n105"/> </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <head type="editorial">13</head>
            <p> Our Lord testifies concerning John, that he is the greatest of the Prophets. Yet he
               received the Spirit by limit, because in that measure in which Elijah received the
               Spirit, (in the same) John obtained it. And as Elijah used to dwell in the
               wilderness, so also the Spirit of God led John into the wilderness, and he used to
               dwell in the mountains and caves. The birds sustained Elijah, and John used to eat
               locusts that fly. Elijah had his loins girded with a girdle of leather; so John had
               his loins girded with a cincture of leather. Jezebel persecuted Elijah, and Herodias
               persecuted John. Elijah reproved Ahab, and John reproved Herod. Elijah divided the
               Jordan, and John opened up baptism. The spirit of Elijah rested twofold upon Elisha,
               so John laid his hand on our Redeemer, and He received the Spirit not by measure.
               Elijah opened the heavens and ascended; and John saw the heavens opened, and the
               Spirit of God which descended and rested upon our Redeemer. Elisha received twofold
               the Spirit of Elijah; and our Redeemer received that of John and that of heaven.
               Elisha took the mantle of Elijah, and our Redeemer the imposition of the hand of the
               priests. Elisha made oil from water, and our Redeemer made wine from water. Elisha
               satisfied with a little bread a hundred men only; and our Redeemer satisfied with a
               little bread five thousand men besides children and women. Elisha cleansed Naaman the
               leper, and our Redeemer cleansed the ten (lepers). Elisha cursed the children and
               they were devoured by bears, but our Redeemer blessed the children. The children
               reviled Elisha, but the children glorified our Redeemer with Hosannas. Elisha cursed
               Gehazi his servant, and our Redeemer cursed Judas His disciple and blessed all His
               (other) disciples. Elisha raised to life one dead man only, but our Redeemer raised
               up three to life. On the bones of Elisha one dead man revived, but when our Saviour
               descended to the abode of the dead, He quickened many and raised them up. And many
               are the signs that the Spirit of Christ wrought, which the Prophets received from
               Him. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <head type="editorial">14</head>
            <p> Therefore, my beloved, we also have received of the Spirit of Christ, and Christ
               dwelleth in us, as it is written that the Spirit said this through the mouth of the
               Prophet:—I will dwell in them and will walk in them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n106"/> Therefore let us prepare
               our temples for the Spirit of Christ, and let us not grieve it that it may not depart
               from us. Remember the warning that the Apostle gives us:—Grieve not the Holy Spirit
               whereby ye have been sealed unto the day of redemption. For from baptism do we
               receive the Spirit of Christ. For in that hour in which the priests invoke the
               Spirit, the heavens open and it descends and moves upon the waters.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n107"/> And those
               that are baptized are clothed in it; for the Spirit stays aloof from all that are
               born of the flesh, until they come to the new birth by water, and then they receive
               the Holy Spirit. For in the first birth they are born with an animal souls which is
               created within man and is not thereafter subject to death, as he said:—Adam became a
               living soul.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108"/> But in the second birth, that through baptism, they received the
               Holy Spirit from a particle of the Godhead, and it is not again subject to death. For
               when men die, the animal spirit is buried with the body, and sense is taken away from
               it, but the heavenly spirit that they receive goes according to its nature to Christ.
               And both these the Apostle has made known, for he said:—The body is buried in animal
               wise, and rises again in spiritual wise.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n109"/> The Spirit goes back again to Christ
               according to its nature, for the Apostle said again:—When we shall depart from the
               body we shall be with our Lord.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n110"/> For the Spirit of Christ, which the spiritual
               receive, goes to our Lord. And the animal spirit is buried in its nature, and sense
               is taken away from it. Whosoever guards the Spirit of Christ in purity, when it
               returns to Christ it thus addresses him:—“The body into which I went, and which put
               me on from the water of the baptism, has kept me in holiness.” And the Holy Spirit
               will be earnest with Christ for the resurrection of that body which kept Him with
               purity, and the Spirit will request to be again conjoined to it that that body may
               rise up in glory. And whatever man there is that receives the Spirit from the water
               (of baptism) and grieves it, it departs from him until he dies, and returns according
               to its nature to Christ, and accuses that man of having grieved it. And when the time
               of the final consummation shall have come, and the time of the Resurrection shall
               have approached, the Holy Spirit, that was kept in purity, receives great power from
               its nature and comes before Christ and stands at the door of the tombs, where the men
               are buried that kept it in purity, and awaits the (resurrection) shout. And when the
               Watchers shall have opened the doors of heaven before the King,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n111"/> then the cornet
               shall summon, and the trumpets shall sound, and the Spirit that waits for the
               (resurrection) shout shall hear, and quickly shall open the tombs, and raise up the
               bodies and whatsoever was buried in them, and shall put on the glory that comes with
               it. And (the Spirit) shall be within for the resurrection of the body, and the glory
               shall be without for the adornment of the body. And the animal spirit shall be
               swallowed up in the heavenly Spirit, and the whole man shall become spiritual, since
               his body is possessed by it (the Spirit). And death shall be swallowed up in
               life,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n112"/> and body shall be swallowed up in Spirit. And by the power of the Spirit,
               that man shall fly up to meet the King and He shall receive him with joy, and Christ
               shall give thanks for the body that has kept His Spirit in purity. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <head type="editorial">15</head>
            <p> This is the Spirit, my beloved, that the Prophets received, and thus also have we
               received. And it is not at every time found with those that receive it, but sometimes
               it returns to Him that sent it, and sometimes it goes to him that receives it.
               Hearken to that which our Lord said:—Despise not one of these little ones that
               believe on Me, for their angels in heaven do always behold the face of My
               Father.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n113"/> This Spirit then goes frequently and stands before God and beholds His
               face, and whosoever injures the temple in which it dwells, it will accuse him before
               God. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <head type="editorial">16</head>
            <p> I will instruct thee of that which is written, that the Spirit is not at every time
               found with those that receive it. For thus it is written about Saul, that the Holy
               Spirit, which he received when he was anointed, departed from him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n114"/> because he
               grieved it, and God sent to him instead of it a vexing spirit. And whenever he was
               afflicted by the evil spirit, David used to play upon the harp, and the Holy Spirit,
               which David received when he was anointed, would come, and the evil spirit that was
               vexing Saul, would flee from before it. So the Holy Spirit that David received was
               not found with him at every time. As long as he was playing the harp, then it used to
               come. For had it been with him always, it would not have allowed him to sin with the
               wife of Uriah. For when he was praying about his sins, and was confessing his
               offences before God, he said thus:—Take not Thy holy spirit from me.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n115"/> Also
               concerning Elisha it is thus written, that, while he played upon his harp, then the
               spirit came to him and he prophesied and said:—Thus saith the Lord, ye shall not see
               wind nor rain, yet this valley shall be made many pits.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n116"/> And also when the
               Shunamite came to him because of her son that was dead, he said thus to her:—The Lord
               hid it from me and did cause me not to know it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n117"/> Yet, when the King of Israel
               sent against him to slay him, the Spirit informed him before the messenger came upon
               him, and he said:—Lo! this son of iniquity has sent to take away my head.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n118"/> And
               again he made known about the abundance that came about in Samaria the day after. And
               again the Spirit informed him when Gehazi stole the silver and concealed it. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <head type="editorial">17</head>
            <p> Therefore, my beloved, when the Holy Spirit departs from a man who has received it,
               until it returns and comes to him, then Satan draws near unto that man, to cause him
               to sin, and that the Holy Spirit may leave him altogether. For as long as the Spirit
               is with a man, Satan fears to come near him. And observe, my beloved, that our Lord
               also, Who was born from the Spirit, was not tempted by Satan until in baptism He
               received the Spirit from on high. And then the Spirit led him forth to be tempted by
               Satan. This, then, is the way with man; that in the hour in which he perceives in
               himself that he is not fervent in the Spirit, and that his heart is inclining to the
               thought of this world, he may know that the Spirit is not with him, and may arise and
               pray and keep vigil that the Spirit of God may come to him, that he be not overcome
               by the adversary. A thief does not dig into a house, until he sees that its master is
               departing from it. Thus also Satan cannot draw near to that house which is our body,
               until the Spirit of Christ departs from it. And be sure, my beloved, that the thief
               does not certainly know whether the master of the house is within or not, but first
               he applies his ear, and looks. If he hears the voice of the master of the house
               within it saying:—“I have a journey to go,” and when he has searched out and seen
               that the master of the house has set out to perform his business, then the thief
               comes and digs into the house and steals. But if he hears the voice of the master of
               the house admonishing and commanding his household to watch and guard his house, and
               saying to them, “I also am within the house,” then the thief will fear and flee, that
               he may not be taken and captured. Thus also Satan, he has not the knowledge
               beforehand to know or see when the Spirit will depart, that so he may come to rob the
               man; but he too listens and watches, and so assails. But if he hears a man in whom
               Christ dwells speaking shameful words, or enraged, or quarrelling, or contending,
               then Satan knows that Christ is not with him, and he comes and accomplishes his will
               in him. For Christ dwells in the peaceful and the meek, and lodges in those that fear
               His word, as He says through the prophet:—On whom shall I look, and in whom shall I
               dwell, but in the peaceful and the meek who fear My word?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n119"/> And our Lord
               said:—Whoever walks in My commandments and keeps My love, We will come to him and
               make Our abode with him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n120"/> But if he hears from a man that he is on his guard and
               is praying and meditating in the Law of his Lord by day and by night, then he turns
               back from him, for he knows that Christ is with him. And if thou shouldest say, “How
               manifold is Satan! for lo! he fights with many;” then hear and learn from that which
               I proved to thee above concerning Christ, that no matter to what extent He is divided
               amongst many, yet He is not a whit diminished. For, as the house, through the window
               of which a little sunlight enters, is altogether illumined, so the man into whom a
               little of Satan enters, is altogether darkened. Hear that which the Apostle said:—If
               Satan is transfigured to an angel of light, it is no wonder if his ministers also are
               transfigured to ministers of righteousness.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n121"/> And again our Lord said to His
               disciples:—Lo, I have given you authority to tread upon the power of the
               adversary.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n122"/> And the Scriptures have made known that he has power and also
               ministers. Moreover Job said concerning him:—God made him to wage his war.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n123"/> These
               ministers then that he has, he causes to run in the world, to wage war. But be sure
               that he will not fight openly; because from the time of the coming of our Saviour,
               (God) has given authority over him. But he will surely plunder and steal. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <head type="editorial">18</head>
            <p> But I will explain to thee, my beloved, concerning that word which the Apostle said,
               by which can be weighed the doctrines that are instruments of the Evil One and
               doctrines of deceit. For the Apostle said:—There is an animal body and there is a
               spiritual body, seeing that it is thus written:—The first Adam became a living soul
               and the second Adam a quickening spirit.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n124"/> So they<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n125"/> say that there will be two
               Adams. But he said:—As we have put on the image of that Adam who was from the earth,
               so we shall put on the image of that Adam who is from heaven.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n126"/> For Adam who was
               from the earth was he that sinned, and the Adam who is from heaven is our Saviour,
               our Lord Jesus Christ. They then that receive the Spirit of Christ, come into the
               likeness of the heavenly Adam, Who is our Saviour, our Lord Jesus Christ. For the
               animal shall be swallowed up in the spiritual, as I wrote unto thee above. And the
               man that grieves the spirit of Christ, will be animal in his resurrection; because
               the heavenly spirit is not with him, that the animal might be swallowed up in it. But
               when he shall arise he shall continue in his natural state, naked of the Spirit.
               Because he stripped off from him the Spirit of Christ, he shall be given over to
               utter nakedness. And whosoever honours the Spirit, and it is guarded in him in
               purity, in that day the Holy Spirit shall protect him, and he shall become altogether
               spiritual, and shall not be found naked; as the Apostle said:—And when we shall have
               clothed ourselves, may we not be found naked.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n127"/> And again he said:—We shall all
               sleep, but in the resurrection we shall not all be changed.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n128"/> And again he
               said:—This which dies shall put on that which dies not, and this which is corruptible
               that which is incorruptible, and when this which dies shall have put on that which
               dies not, and this corruptible that which is incorruptible, then shall be
               accomplished that word which is written that death is swallowed up by victory.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n129"/>
               Again he said:—Suddenly as the twinkling of an eye, the dead shall rise incorruptible
               and we shall be changed.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n130"/> And they who shall be changed shall put on the form of
               that heavenly Adam and shall become spiritual. And those who shall not be changed,
               shall continue animal in the created nature of Adam, namely, of dust; and shall
               continue in their nature in the earth below. And then the heavenly shall be caught up
               to heaven and the Spirit that they have put on shall cause them to fly, and they
               shall inherit the kingdom that was prepared for them from the beginning. And they
               that are animal shall remain on the earth by the weight of their bodies, and shall
               turn back to Sheol, and there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <head type="editorial">19</head>
            <p> In writing this I have reminded myself, and also thee, my beloved; therefore love
               virginity, the heavenly portion, the fellowship of the Watchers of heaven. For there
               is nothing comparable with it. And in those that are thus, in them Christ dwells. The
               time of summer is at hand, and the fig-tree has budded and its leaves have come
               out<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n131"/>—the signs that our Redeemer gave have begun to be fulfilled. For he
               said:—People shall rise against people and kingdom against kingdom. And there shall
               be famines and pestilences and terrors from heaven.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n132"/> And lo! all these things are
               being accomplished in our days. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <head type="editorial">20</head>
            <p> Therefore read in this whatever I have written unto thee, thou and the brethren, the
               monks that love virginity. And be on thy guard against scorners. For whosoever scorns
               and mocks his brother, the word that is written in the Gospel fitly applies to him;
               namely, when our Lord wished to take account with the avaricious and with the
               Pharisees. For it is written:—Because they loved money, they mocked Him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n133"/> So also
               now those that do not agree with these things mock in the same way. Read then and
               learn. Be zealous for reading and for doing. And let the Law of God be thy meditation
               at every time. And when thou hast read this epistle, on thy life (I adjure thee), my
               beloved, arise and pray, and remember my sinfulness in thy prayer. </p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1"/>
            <note xml:id="n2"/>
            <note xml:id="n3"/>
            <note xml:id="n4"/>
            <note xml:id="n5"/>
            <note xml:id="n6"/>
            <note xml:id="n7"/>
            <note xml:id="n8"/>
            <note xml:id="n9"/>
            <note xml:id="n10"/>
            <note xml:id="n11"/>
            <note xml:id="n12"/>
            <note xml:id="n13"/>
            <note xml:id="n14"/>
            <note xml:id="n15"/>
            <note xml:id="n16"/>
            <note xml:id="n17"/>
            <note xml:id="n18"/>
            <note xml:id="n19"/>
            <note xml:id="n20"/>
            <note xml:id="n21"/>
            <note xml:id="n22"/>
            <note xml:id="n23"/>
            <note xml:id="n24"/>
            <note xml:id="n25"/>
            <note xml:id="n26"/>
            <note xml:id="n27"/>
            <note xml:id="n28"/>
            <note xml:id="n29"/>
            <note xml:id="n30"/>
            <note xml:id="n31"/>
            <note xml:id="n32"/>
            <note xml:id="n33"/>
            <note xml:id="n34"/>
            <note xml:id="n35"/>
            <note xml:id="n36"/>
            <note xml:id="n37"/>
            <note xml:id="n38"/>
            <note xml:id="n39"/>
            <note xml:id="n40"/>
            <note xml:id="n41"/>
            <note xml:id="n42"/>
            <note xml:id="n43"/>
            <note xml:id="n44"/>
            <note xml:id="n45"/>
            <note xml:id="n46"/>
            <note xml:id="n47"/>
            <note xml:id="n48"/>
            <note xml:id="n49"/>
            <note xml:id="n50"/>
            <note xml:id="n51"/>
            <note xml:id="n52"/>
            <note xml:id="n53"/>
            <note xml:id="n54"/>
            <note xml:id="n55"/>
            <note xml:id="n56"/>
            <note xml:id="n57"/>
            <note xml:id="n58"/>
            <note xml:id="n59"/>
            <note xml:id="n60"/>
            <note xml:id="n61"/>
            <note xml:id="n62"/>
            <note xml:id="n63"/>
            <note xml:id="n64"/>
            <note xml:id="n65"/>
            <note xml:id="n66"/>
            <note xml:id="n67"/>
            <note xml:id="n68"/>
            <note xml:id="n69"/>
            <note xml:id="n70"/>
            <note xml:id="n71"/>
            <note xml:id="n72"/>
            <note xml:id="n73"/>
            <note xml:id="n74"/>
            <note xml:id="n75"/>
            <note xml:id="n76"/>
            <note xml:id="n77"/>
            <note xml:id="n78"/>
            <note xml:id="n79"/>
            <note xml:id="n80"/>
            <note xml:id="n81"/>
            <note xml:id="n82"/>
            <note xml:id="n83"/>
            <note xml:id="n84"/>
            <note xml:id="n85"/>
            <note xml:id="n86"/>
            <note xml:id="n87"/>
            <note xml:id="n88"/>
            <note xml:id="n89"/>
            <note xml:id="n90"/>
            <note xml:id="n91"/>
            <note xml:id="n92"/>
            <note xml:id="n93"/>
            <note xml:id="n94"/>
            <note xml:id="n95"/>
            <note xml:id="n96"/>
            <note xml:id="n97"/>
            <note xml:id="n98"/>
            <note xml:id="n99"/>
            <note xml:id="n100"/>
            <note xml:id="n101"/>
            <note xml:id="n102"/>
            <note xml:id="n103"/>
            <note xml:id="n104"/>
            <note xml:id="n105"/>
            <note xml:id="n106"/>
            <note xml:id="n107"/>
            <note xml:id="n108"/>
            <note xml:id="n109"/>
            <note xml:id="n110"/>
            <note xml:id="n111"/>
            <note xml:id="n112"/>
            <note xml:id="n113"/>
            <note xml:id="n114"/>
            <note xml:id="n115"/>
            <note xml:id="n116"/>
            <note xml:id="n117"/>
            <note xml:id="n118"/>
            <note xml:id="n119"/>
            <note xml:id="n120"/>
            <note xml:id="n121"/>
            <note xml:id="n122"/>
            <note xml:id="n123"/>
            <note xml:id="n124"/>
            <note xml:id="n125"/>
            <note xml:id="n126"/>
            <note xml:id="n127"/>
            <note xml:id="n128"/>
            <note xml:id="n129"/>
            <note xml:id="n130"/>
            <note xml:id="n131"/>
            <note xml:id="n132"/>
            <note xml:id="n133"/>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
