<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8502" n="0">Prefatory
               Letter</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8501">The
               Demonstrations</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/10">Aphrahat</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: 
               <ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Select_Demonstrations_of_Aphrahat/Letter_of_an_Inquirer">
               https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Select_Demonstrations_of_Aphrahat/Letter_of_an_Inquirer
               </ref>. This transcription available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <head type="editorial">1</head>
            <p> Beloved, I send thee inquiries and questions, for I am compelled to seek further
               instruction of thee on many points. Do not thou refuse to hear me. My spirit urges me
               to warn thee about many topics<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> that thou mayest unfold for me the spiritual
               perceptions of thy mind, and mayest show me of all that thou hast apprehended from
               the holy books, that so my deficiency may be supplied by thee and my hunger satisfied
               by thy doctrine, and that thou mayest assuage my thirst from the fountain of thine
               instruction. Yet though many things are set in my thought to ask thee, they all are
               notwithstanding reserved with me, that when I come to thee, thou mayest instruct me
               on all subjects. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <head type="editorial">2</head>
            <p> But before all things I desire that thou wouldst write and instruct me concerning
               this that straitens me, namely, concerning our faith; how it is, and what its
               foundation is, and on what structure it rises, on what it rests, and in what way is
               its fulfilment and consummation, and what are the works required for it. For I of
               myself firmly believe that God is one, Who made the heavens and the earth from the
               beginning; that He adorned the world by His handiwork; that He made man in His image;
               He it is that accepted the offering of Abel. He translated Enoch because of his
               excellence. He preserved Noah because of his righteousness. He chose Abraham because
               of his faith. He spake with Moses on account of his meekness. He it is that spake in
               all the prophets, and furthermore He sent His Christ into the world. Since then, my
               brother, I thus believe in these things that so they are, I therefore, brother,
               request of thee that thou wouldest write and show me what are the works required for
               this our faith, that so thou mayest set me at rest. </p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">The beginning to this point is lost in the Syriac but has been
               preserved in the Armenian translation. We have borrowed it thence through the Latin
               translation of Graffin (Patrologia Syriaca, Tom. I.).</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
