<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8503" n="1">
               Demonstration 1: On Faith -
               <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܚܘܝܬܐ ܕܗܝܡܢܘܬܐ</foreign>
            </title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8501">The Demonstrations</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/10">Aphrahat</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: 
               <ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Select_Demonstrations_of_Aphrahat/Of_Faith">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Select_Demonstrations_of_Aphrahat/Of_Faith
               </ref>. This transcription available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <head type="editorial">1</head>
            <p> I have received thy letter, my beloved, and when I read it, it greatly gladdened me
               that thou hast turned thy thoughts to these investigations. For this thing that thou
               hast asked of me shall be freely granted,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> for freely it was received. And
               whosoever has, and desires to withhold from him that seeks, whatsoever he withholds
               shall be taken away from him. Whoever of free grace receives, of free grace also does
               it behove him to give. And so, my beloved, as to that which thou hast asked of me, so
               far as my insignificance has apprehended, I will write to thee. And also whatsoever
               thou hast not sought of me, invoking God, I will explain to thee. Hear then, my
               beloved, and open the inward ears of thy heart unto me, and the spiritual perceptions
               of thy mind to that which I say unto thee. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <head type="editorial">2</head>
            <p> Faith is compounded of many things, and by many kinds is it brought to perfection.
               For it is like a building that is built up of many pieces of workmanship and so its
               edifice rises to the top. And know, my beloved, that in the foundations of the
               building stones are laid, and so resting upon stones the whole edifice rises until it
               is perfected. Thus also the true Stone, our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>,
               is the foundation of all our faith. And on Him, on [this] Stone faith is based. And
               resting on faith all the structure rises until it is completed. For it is the
               foundation that is the beginning of all the building. For when any one is brought
               nigh unto faith, it is laid for him upon the Stone, that is our <persName>Lord Jesus Christ</persName>.
               And his building cannot be shaken by the waves, nor can it be injured by the winds.
               By the stormy blasts it does not fall, because its structure is reared upon the rock
               of the true Stone. And in this that I have called Christ the Stone, I have not spoken
               of my own thought, but the Prophets beforehand called Him the Stone. And this I shall
               make clear to thee. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <head type="editorial">3</head>
            <p> And now hear concerning faith that is based upon the Stone, and concerning the
               structure that is reared up upon the Stone. For first a man believes, and when he
               believes, he loves. When he loves, he hopes. When he hopes, he is justified. When he
               is justified, he is perfected. When he is perfected, he is consummated. And when his
               whole structure is raised up, consummated, and perfected, then he becomes a house and
               a temple for a dwelling-place of Christ, as Jeremiah the Prophet said:—The temple of
               the Lord, the temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord are ye, if ye amend your
               ways and your works.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> And again He said through the Prophet:—I will dwell in them
               and walk in them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> And also the Blessed Apostle thus said:—Ye are the temple of God
               and the spirit of Christ dwelleth in you.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> And also our Lord again thus said to His
               disciples:—Ye are in Me and I am in you.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <head type="editorial">4</head>
            <p> And when the house has become a dwelling-place, then the man begins to be anxious as
               to that which is required for Him Who dwells in the building. Just as if a king or an
               honourable man, to whom a royal name is given, should lodge in the house, there would
               be required for the King all the appurtenances of royalty and all the service that is
               needed for the King’s honour. For in a house that is void of all good things, the
               King will not lodge, nor will he dwell in the midst of it; but all that is choicest
               in the house is required for the King and that nothing in it be deficient. And if
               anything be deficient there in the house in which the King lodges, the keeper of the
               house is delivered over to death, because he did not make ready the service for the
               King. So also let the man, who becomes a house, yea a dwelling-place, for Christ,
               take heed to what is needed for the service of Christ, Who lodges in him, and with
               what things he may please Him. For first he builds his building on the Stone, which
               is Christ. On Him, on the Stone, is faith based, and on faith is reared up all the
               structure. For the habitation of the house is required pure fasting, and it is made
               firm by faith. There is also needed for it pure prayer, and through faith is it
               accepted. Necessary for it too is love, and with faith is it compounded. Furthermore
               alms are needed, and through faith are they given. He demands also meekness, and by
               faith is it adorned. He chooses too virginity, and by faith is it loved. He joins
               with himself holiness, and in faith is it planted. He cares also for wisdom, and
               through faith is it acquired. He desires also hospitality, and by faith does it
               abound. Requisite for Him also is simplicity, and with faith is it commingled. He
               demands patience also, and by faith is it perfected. He has respect also to
               long-suffering, and through faith is it acquired. He loves mourning also, and through
               faith is it manifested. He seeks also for purity, and by faith is it preserved. All
               these things does the faith demand that is based on the rock of the true Stone, that
               is Christ. These works are required for Christ the King, Who dwells in men that are
               built up in these works. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <head type="editorial">5</head>
            <p> And if perchance thou shouldest say:—If Christ is set for the foundation, how does
               Christ also dwell in the building when it is completed? For both these things did the
               blessed Apostle say. For he said:—I as a wise architect have laid the foundation.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/>
               And there he defined the foundation and made it clear, for he said as follows:—No man
               can lay other foundation than that which is laid, which is Jesus Christ.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> And that
               Christ furthermore dwells in that building is the word that was written above—that of
               Jeremiah who called men temples and said of God that He dwelt in them. And the
               Apostle said:—The Spirit of Christ dwelleth in you.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> And our Lord said:—I and My
               Father are one.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/> And therefore that word is accomplished, that Christ dwells in
               men, namely, in those who believe on Him, and He is the foundation on which is reared
               up the whole building. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <head type="editorial">6</head>
            <p> But I must proceed to my former statement that Christ is called the Stone in the
               Prophets. For in ancient times David said concerning Him:—The stone which the
               builders rejected has become the head of the building.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/> And how did the builders
               reject this Stone which is Christ?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> How else than that they so rejected Him before
               Pilate and said—This man shall not be King over us.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12"/> And again in that parable
               that our Lord spake that a certain nobleman went to receive kingly power and to
               return and rule over them; and they sent after Him envoys saying:—This man shall not
               be King over us.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> By these things they rejected the Stone which is Christ. And how
               did it become the head of the building? How else than that it was set up over the
               building of the Gentiles and upon it is reared up all their building. And who are the
               builders? Who but the priests and Pharisees who did not build a sure building, but
               were overthrowing everything that he was building, as is written in Ezekiel the
               Prophet:—He was building a wall of partition, but they were shaking it, that it might
               fall.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/> And again it is written:—I sought amongst them a man who was closing the
               fence and standing in the breach over the face of the land, that I might not destroy
               it and I did not find.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15"/> And furthermore Isaiah also prophesied beforehand with
               regard to this stone. For he said:—Thus saith the Lord, Behold I lay in Zion a chosen
               stone in the precious corner, the heart of the wall of the foundation.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16"/> And he
               said again there:—Every one that believeth on it shall not fear.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17"/> And whosoever
               falleth on that stone shall be broken, and every one on whom it shall fall, it will
               crush.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18"/> For the people of the house of Israel fell upon Him, and He became their
               destruction for ever. And again it shall fall on the image and crush it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19"/> And the
               Gentiles believed on it and do not fear. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <head type="editorial">7</head>
            <p> And He shows thus with regard to that stone that it was laid as head of the wall and
               as foundation. But if that stone was laid as the foundation, how did it also become
               the head of the wall? How but that when our Lord came, He laid His faith in the earth
               like a foundation, and it rose above all the heavens like the head of the wall and
               all the building was finished with the stones, from the bottom to the top. And with
               regard to the faith about which I said that He laid His faith in the earth, this
               David proclaimed beforehand about Christ. For He said:—Faith shall spring up from the
               earth.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20"/> And that again, it is above, he said:—Righteousness looked down from the
               heavens. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <head type="editorial">8</head>
            <p> And again Daniel also spoke concerning this stone which is Christ. For he said:—The
               stone was cut out from the mountain, not by hands, and it smote the image, and the
               whole earth was filled with it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21"/> This he showed beforehand with regard to Christ
               that the whole earth shall be filled with Him. For lo! by the faith of Christ are all
               the ends of the earth filled, as David said:—The sound of the Gospel of Christ has
               gone forth into all the earth.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22"/> And again when He sent forth His apostles He spake
               thus to them:—Go forth, make disciples of all nations and they will believe on
               Me.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23"/> And again the Prophet Zechariah also prophesied about that stone which is
               Christ. For he said:—I saw a chief stone of equality and of love.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24"/> And why did he
               say <quote>chief</quote>? Surely because from the beginning<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25"/> He was with His Father. And again
               that he spoke of love, it was because when He came into the world, He said thus to
               His disciples:—This is My commandment, that ye love one another.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n26"/> And again He
               said:—I have called you My friends (lovers).<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27"/> And the blessed Apostle said
               thus:—God loved as in the love of His Son.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28"/> Of a truth Christ loved us and gave
               Himself for us.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29"/> </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <head type="editorial">9</head>
            <p> And definitely did He show concerning this stone:—Lo! on this stone will I open
               seven eyes.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30"/> And what then are the seven eyes that were opened on the stone?
               Clearly the Spirit of God that abode on Christ with seven operations, as Isaiah the
               Prophet said:—The Spirit of God shall rest and dwell upon Him, (a spirit) of wisdom
               and understanding, of counsel and of courage, of knowledge and of the fear of the
               Lord.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31"/> These were the seven eyes that were opened upon the Stone, and these are
               the seven eyes of the Lord which look upon all the earth.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n32"/> </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <head type="editorial">10</head>
            <p> And also with reference to Christ was this (which follows) said. For he said that He
               was given as a light to all the Gentiles as the Prophet Isaiah said:—I have given
               Thee as a light to all the Gentiles, that Thou shouldest be My redemption to the ends
               of the earth.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33"/> And furthermore David also said;—Thy word is a lamp unto my feet
               and a light unto my paths.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34"/> And also the word and discourse of the Lord is Christ,
               as is written in the beginning of the Gospel of our Saviour:—In the beginning was the
               Word.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35"/> And with regard to the light there again he bore witness:—The light was
               shining in the darkness and the darkness comprehended it not.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36"/> What then is
               this:—The light was shining in the darkness and the darkness comprehended it not?
               Clearly Christ, Whose light shone in the midst of the people of the house of Israel,
               and the people of the house of Israel did not comprehend the light of Christ, in that
               they did not believe on Him, as it is written:—He came unto His own, and His own
               received Him not.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37"/> And also our Lord Jesus called them darkness, for He said to
               His disciples;—Whatsoever I say unto you in the darkness, that speak ye in the
               light,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38"/> namely, let your light shine among the Gentiles;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n39"/>because they received
               the light of Christ, Who is the Light of the Gentiles. And He said again to His
               Apostles:—Ye are the light of the world.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n40"/> And again He said unto them;—Let your
               light shine before men, that they may see your good works and glorify your Father
               which is in heaven.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41"/> And again He showed with regard to Himself that He is the
               light, for He said to His disciples:—Walk while the light is with you, ere the
               darkness overtake you.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42"/> And again He said to them:—Believe on the light that ye
               may be children of light.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43"/> And again He said:—I am the light of the world.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44"/> And
               again He said:—No man lighteth a lamp and putteth it under a bushel or under a bed,
               or putteth it in a hidden place, but putteth it upon the lamp-stand that every one
               may see the light of the lamp.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n45"/> And the shining lamp is Christ, as David said;—Thy
               word is a lamp unto my feet and a light to my paths.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46"/> </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <head type="editorial">11</head>
            <p> And furthermore the Prophet Hosea also said:—Light you a lamp and seek ye the
               Lord.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47"/> And our Lord Jesus Christ said:—What woman is there who has ten drachmos
               and shall lose one of them, and will not light a lamp and sweep the house and seek
               her drachma that she lost?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48"/> What then does this woman signify? Clearly the
               congregation of the house of Israel, to which the ten commandments were given. They
               lost the first commandment—that in which He warned them saying:—I am the Lord your
               God, Who brought you up from the land of Egypt.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49"/> And when they had lost this first
               commandment, also the nine which are after it they could not keep, because on the
               first depend the nine. For it was an impossibility that while worshipping Baal, they
               should keep the nine commandments. For they lost the first commandment, like that
               woman who lost one drachma from the ten. So the Prophet cried unto them:—Light you a
               lamp and seek ye the Lord.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50"/> And furthermore the Prophet Isaiah also said:—Seek ye
               the Lord and when ye shall have found Him, call upon Him; and when He is near let the
               sinner abandon his way and the wicked man his thought.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51"/> For that lamp shone and
               they did not by it seek the Lord their God. And its light shone in the darkness and
               the darkness did not comprehend it. And the lamp was set up on the lamp-stand and
               those who were in the house did not see its light. And what then means this, that the
               lamp was set up on the lamp-stand? Clearly His being raised up upon the cross. And by
               this all the house was made dark over them. For when they crucified Him, the light
               was darkened from them, and shone amongst the Gentiles, because that from the time of
               the sixth hour (of the day) on which they crucified Him even unto the ninth hour
               there was darkness in all the land of Israel. And the sun set in midday and the land
               was darkened in the shining daytime, as is written in Zechariah the Prophet:—It shall
               come to pass in that day, saith the Lord, I will cause the sun to set in midday, and
               will make dark the land in the shining daytime.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n52"/> </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <head type="editorial">12</head>
            <p> Now I must proceed to my former subject of faith, that on it are reared up all the
               good works of the building. And again, in what I said with regard to the building, it
               was in no strange fashion that I spoke, but the blessed Apostle wrote in the first
               Epistle to the Corinthians, saying;—I as a wise master-builder have laid the
               foundation, but every one buildeth on it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n53"/> One builds silver and gold and goodly
               stones; another builds reed and straw and stubble. In the last day that building
               shall be tried by fire; for the gold and silver and goodly stones shall be preserved
               in the midst of the fire, because they are a firm building. But as for the straw and
               reed and stubble, the fire shall have power upon them and they shall be burned. And
               what is the gold and silver and goodly stones by which the building is raised up?
               Clearly the good deeds of faith, which shall be preserved in the midst of the fire;
               because Christ dwells in that secure building, and He is its preserver from the fire.
               And let us consider and understand (this) from the example that God has given us also
               in the former dispensation, because the promises of that dispensation will abide sure
               for us. Let us then understand from (the case of) those three righteous men who were
               cast into the midst of the fire and were not burned, namely, Hananiah, Azariah and
               Misael, over whom the fire had no power, because they built a secure building and
               rejected the commandment of Nebuchadnezzar the king and did not worship the image
               that he made. And as for those who transgressed the commandment of God, the fire at
               once prevailed over them and burned them, and they were burned without mercy. For the
               Sodomites were burned like straw and reed and stubble. Furthermore, Nadab and Abihu
               were burned, who transgressed the commandment of God. Again, two hundred and fifty
               men were burned, who were offering incense. Again, two princes and a hundred who were
               with them were burned, because they approached the mountain on which Elijah was
               sitting, who ascended in a chariot of fire to heaven. The calumniators also were
               burned because they dug a pit for righteous men. Accordingly, beloved, the righteous
               shall be tried by the fire, like gold and silver and goodly stones, and the wicked
               shall be burned in the fire like straw and reed and stubble, and the fire shall have
               power upon them and they shall be burned; even as the Prophet Isaiah said:—By fire
               shall the Lord judge and by it shall He try all flesh.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54"/> And again he said:—Ye
               shall go out and see the carcases of the men who offended against Me, whose worm
               shall not die, nor shall their fire be quenched, and they shall be an astonishment to
               all flesh.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55"/> </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <head type="editorial">13</head>
            <p> And again the Apostle has commented for us upon this building and upon this
               foundation; for he said thus;—No man can lay another foundation than that which is
               laid, which is <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n56"
               /> Again the Apostle said about faith that it is conjoined with hope and love, for he
               said thus:—These are three which shall abide, faith and hope and love.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n57"/> And he showed with regard to faith that first it
               is laid on a sure foundation.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n58"/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <head type="editorial">14</head>
            <p> For Abel, because of his faith his offering was accepted. And Enoch, because he was
               well-pleasing through his faith, was removed from death. Noah, because he believed,
               was preserved from the deluge. Abraham, through his faith, obtained blessing, and it
               was accounted to him for righteousness. Isaac, because he believed, was loved. Jacob,
               because of his faith, was preserved. Joseph, because of his faith, was tried in the
               waters of contention, and was delivered from his trial, and his Lord established a
               witness in him, as David said:—Witness hath he established in Joseph.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n59"/> Moses also
               by his faith performed many wonderful works of power. By his faith he destroyed the
               Egyptians with ten plagues. Again, by faith he divided the sea, and caused his people
               to cross over and sank the Egyptians in the midst of it. By faith he cast the wood
               into the bitter waters and they became sweet. By faith he brought down manna and
               satisfied his people. By faith he spread out his hands and conquered Amalek, as is
               written:—His hands continued in faith till the setting of the sun.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n60"/> Also by faith
               he went up to Mount Sinai, when he twice fasted for the space of forty days. Again by
               faith he conquered Sihon and Og, the Kings of the Amorites. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <head type="editorial">15</head>
            <p> This is wonderful, my beloved, and a great prodigy that Moses did in the Red Sea,
               when the waters were divided by faith, and stood up on high like mountains or like
               mighty cliffs. They were checked and stood still at the commandment; they were closed
               up as in vessels, and fast bound in the height as in the depth. Their fluidity did
               not overflow the boundary, but rather they changed the nature of their creation.
               Irrational creatures became obedient. The billows became rigid and were awaiting the
               vengeance, when the people should have passed over. Wonderful was it how the waves
               stood still and expected the commandment and the vengeance. The foundations (hidden)
               from the ages of the world were revealed, and that which from the beginning had been
               liquid suddenly became dry. The gates lifted up their heads and the everlasting gates
               were lifted up.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n61"/> The pillar of fire entered and illuminated the entire camp. The
               people passed over by faith. And the judgment of righteousness was wrought upon
               Pharaoh and upon his host and upon his chariots. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <head type="editorial">16</head>
            <p> Thus also Joshua the son of Nun divided Jordan by his faith, and the children of
               Israel crossed over as in the days of Moses. But know, my beloved, that this passage
               of the Jordan was three times laid open by its being divided. First through Joshua
               the Son of Nun, and secondly through Elijah, and then through Elisha. For the word of
               the Book makes known that over against this passage of Jericho, there Elijah was
               taken up to heaven; for when Elisha turned back from following him and divided the
               Jordan and passed over, the children of the Prophets of Jericho came out to meet
               Elisha and said:—The spirit of Elijah rests upon Elisha.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62"/> Furthermore when the
               people crossed over in the days of Joshua the son of Nun (it was there), for thus it
               is written:—The people passed over, over against Jericho.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n63"/> Also Joshua the son of
               Nun by faith cast down the walls of Jericho, and they fell without difficulty. Again
               by faith he destroyed thirty-one kings and made the children of Israel to inherit the
               land. Furthermore by his faith he spread out his hands towards heaven and stayed the
               sun in Gibeon and the moon in the valley of Ajalon.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64"/> And they were stayed and
               stood still from their courses. But enough! All the righteous, our fathers, in all
               that they did were victorious through faith, as also the blessed Apostle testified
               with regard to all of them:—By faith they prevailed.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65"/> Again Solomon said:—Many men
               are called merciful, but a faithful man who can find?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66"/> Also Job thus said:—My
               integrity, shall not pass from me, and in my righteousness will persist.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n67"/> </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <head type="editorial">17</head>
            <p> Also our Saviour used thus to say to every one who drew near to Him to be
               healed:—According to thy faith be unto thee.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n68"/>
               And when the blind man approached Him, He said to him:—Dost thou believe that I am
               able to heal thee? That blind man said to Him:—Yea, Lord, I believe.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n69"/> And his faith opened his eyes. And to him whose
               son was sick, He said:—Believe and thy son shall live. He said to Him:—I believe,
               Lord; help thou my feeble faith.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n70"/> And by his
               faith his son was healed. And also when the nobleman<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n71"/> came near to Him, by his faith was his boy healed, when he said to
               our Lord:—Speak the word and my servant will be cured.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n72"/> And our Lord was astonished at his faith, and according to his
               faith it happened to him. And also when the chief of the Synagogue requested Him
               concerning his daughter, He said thus to him:—Only firmly believe and thy daughter
               shall live.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n73"/> So he believed and his daughter
               lived and arose. And when Lazarus died, our Lord said to Martha:—If thou believest,
               thy brother shall rise. Martha saith unto Him;—Yea, Lord, I believe.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n74"/> And He raised him after four days. And also
               Simon who was called Cephas because of his faith was called the firm rock.<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n75"/> And again when our Lord gave the Sacrament of
               Baptism to His apostles, He said thus to them:—Whosoever believeth and is baptized
               shall live, and whosoever believeth not shall be condemned.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n76"/> Again He said to his Apostles:—If ye believe and doubt not, there
               is nothing ye shall not be able to do.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77"/> For when
               our Lord walked on the billows of the sea, Simon also by his faith walked with Him;
               but when in respect of his faith he doubted, and began to sink, our Lord called him,
               thou of little faith.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78"/> And when the Apostles
               asked of our Lord, they begged nothing at His hands but this, saying to Him:—Increase
               our faith. He said to them:—If there were in you faith, even a mountain would remove
               from before you.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n79"/> And He said to them:—Doubt ye
               not, lest ye sink down in the midst of the world, even as Simon when he doubted began
               to sink in the midst of the sea.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n80"/> And again He
               said thus;—This shall be the sign for those that believe; they shall speak with new
               tongues and shall cast out demons, and they shall lay their hands on the sick and
               they shall be made whole.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n81"/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <head type="editorial">18</head>
            <p> Let us draw near then, my beloved, to faith, since its powers are so many. For faith
               raised up to the heavens (Enoch), and conquered the Deluge. It caused the barren to
               bring forth. It delivered from the sword. It raised up from the pit. It enriched the
               poor. It released the captives. It delivered the persecuted. It brought down the
               fire. It divided the sea. It cleft the rock, and gave to the thirsty water to drink.
               It satisfied the hungry. It raised the dead, and brought them up from Sheol. It
               stilled the billows. It healed the sick. It conquered hosts. It overthrew walls. It
               stopped the mouths of lions, and quenctarhed the flame of fire. It humiliated the proud,
               and brought the humble to honour. All these mighty works were wrought by faith. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <head type="editorial">19</head>
            <p> Now thus is faith; when a man believes in God the Lord of all, Who made the heavens
               and the earth and the seas and all that is in them; and He made Adam in His image;
               and He gave the Law to Moses; He sent of His Spirit upon the prophets; He sent
               moreover His Christ into the world. Furthermore that a man should believe in the
               resurrection of the dead; and should furthermore also believe in the sacrament of
               baptism. This is the faith of the Church of God. And (it is necessary) that a man
               should separate himself from the observance of hours and Sabbaths and moons and
               seasons, and divinations and sorceries and Chaldæan arts and magic, from fornication
               and from festive music, from vain doctrines, which are instruments of the Evil One,
               from the blandishment of honeyed words, from blasphemy and from adultery. And that a
               man should not bear false witness, and that a man should not speak with double
               tongue. These then are the works of the faith which is based on the true Stone which
               is Christ, on Whom the whole building is reared up. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <head type="editorial">20</head>
            <p> Furthermore, my beloved, there is much besides in the Holy Books about faith. But
               these few things out of the much have I written to recall them to thy love that thou
               mayest know and make known and believe and also be believed. And when thou hast read
               and learned the works of faith, thou mayest be made like unto that tilled land upon
               which the good seed fell, and produced fruit a hundred-fold and sixty-fold and
               thirty-fold. And when thou comest to thy Lord, He may call thee a good servant and
               prudent and faithful, who on account of His faith, that abounded, is to enter into
               the Kingdom of his Lord. </p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">S. Matt x. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">Jer. vii. 4, 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">Levit. xxvi. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">1 Cor. iii. 16, etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">John xiv. 20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">1 Cor. iii. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">1 Cor. iii. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8">1 Cor. iii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9">John x. 30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10">Ps. cxviii. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11">Luke xix. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12">John xix. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13">Luke xix. 13, 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14">Ez. xiii. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15">Ez. xxii. 30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16">Is. xxviii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17">Is. xxviii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18">Matt. xxi. 44.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19">Dan. ii. 34.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20">Ps. lxxxv. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21">Dan. ii. 34, 35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22">Ps. xix. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23">Matt. xxviii. 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24">Zach. iv. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25">The words for chief and for beginning are almost identical in the
               Syriac.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26">John xv. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27">John xv. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28">Cf. Eph. ii. 4. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29">Cf. Eph. v. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30">Zech. iii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31">Is. xi. 1, 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32">Zech. iv. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33">Is. xlix. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34">Ps. cxix. 105.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35">John i. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36">John i. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37">John i. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n38">Matt. x. 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39">Cf. Matt. v. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40">Matt. v. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41">Matt. v. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42">John xii. 35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43">John xii. 36.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44">John viii. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n45">Matt. v. 15; Mark iv. 21; Luke viii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46">Ps. cxix. 105.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47">Hos. x. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48">Luke xv. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49">Ex. xx. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50">Hos. x. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51">Is. lv. 6, 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n52">Am. viii. 9. (Cf. the commentary ascribed to Ephrem in loco.) Cf. Zech.
               xiv. 6, 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n53">1 Cor. iii. 10, 12, sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54">Is. lxvi. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55">Is. lxvi. 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n56">1 Cor. iii. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n57">1 Cor. xiii. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n58">The allusion is to Heb. xi. This sentence, connecting sections 13 (which
               relates to 1 Corinthians iii. and xiii.) and 14 (which echoes Hebrews xi.), seems to
               imply (<quote>he showed</quote>) that they are written by the same author,—in other words, to
               ascribe Hebrews to St. Paul.</note>
            <note xml:id="n59">Ps. lxxxi. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60">Ex. xvii. 12. (Pesh.)</note>
            <note xml:id="n61">Ps. xxiv. 7, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62">2 Kings ii. 8–15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n63">Jos. iii. 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64">Jos. x. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65">Heb. xi. 33.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66">Prov. xx. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n67">Job xxvii. 5, 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n68">e. q. Matt. ix. 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n69">Matt. ix. 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70">Mark ix. 22, 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71">Lit. <quote>king’s servant,</quote> John iv. 46, which is here confused with Matt.
               viii. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n72">Matt. viii. 8, 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73">Mark v. 23–36.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74">John xi. 23–27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75">Kipha—rock.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76">Mark xvi. 16. Note that Aphrahat here cites the disputed conclusion of
               St. Mark’s Gospel.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77">Matt. xxi. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78">Matt. xiv. 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n79">Luke xvii. 5, and Matt. xvii. 19; xxi. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80">(Apocryphal.)</note>
            <note xml:id="n81">Mark xvi. 17, 18.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
