<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/srophe/translations-app/refs/heads/main/documentation/schema/out/translations.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en" level="m">Metrical Catalogue of Syriac Writers</title>
        <!-- series URI needed -->
        <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/310">ʿAbdishoʿ bar Brikha</author>
        <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel
          L. Schwartz</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
          <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
            Schwartz</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Publication Information</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title>The Syriac Sourcebook</title>
        <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel
          L. Schwartz</editor>
        <idno type="URI"><!-- URI NEEDED! --></idno>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>
          'Abdisho' bar Brika (Ebed-Jesu), <title>Metrical Catalogue of Syriac Writers</title>. From G.P.Badger, 
          <title>The Nestorians and their rituals</title> (1852) vol. 2, pp.361-379. Published in 1852, 
          this translation is in the public domain.
        </p>
        <p>
          Initial transcription of this text performed by Roger Peerse in 2005 and released into the 
          public domain:  
          <ref target="https://www.tertullian.org/fathers/abdisho_bar_brika_syriac_writers_01_text.htm">
            https://www.tertullian.org/fathers/abdisho_bar_brika_syriac_writers_01_text.htm
          </ref>. The text was downloaded on 20 April 2026.
        </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="work" xml:id="work">
        <head type="main"> Index of Biblical and Ecclesiastical Writings Drawn up by <persName>Mar
            Abd Yeshua</persName>, Metropolitan of <placeName>Nisibis</placeName> and
            <placeName>Armenia</placeName>, A.D. 1298. </head>
        <div type="section" xml:id="section-1" n="1">
          <head type="main">
            <title>Old Testament Scriptures</title>
          </head>
          <ab xml:id="section-1.1" n="1"> Moses wrote the Law in five books, viz.:
              <title>Genesis</title>, <title>Exodus</title>, <title>Leviticus</title>,
              <title>Numbers</title>, and <title>Deuteronomy</title>. After these follow <title>the
              book of Joshua</title> the son of <persName>Nun</persName>, <title>Judges</title>,
              <title>Samuel</title>, <title>the book of Kings</title>, the
            <title>Chronicles</title>, the <title>Psalms</title> of <persName>David</persName>, the
              <title>Proverbs</title> of <persName>Solomon</persName>, <title>Ecclesiastes</title>,
              <title>the Song of Songs</title>, the <title>Great Wisdom</title>, <title>the Wisdom
              of the son of Sirach</title>, <title>Job</title>, <title>Isaiah</title>, <pb n="362"/>
            <title>Hosea</title>, <title>Joel</title>, <title>Amos</title>, <title>Obadiah</title>,
              <title>Jonah</title>, <title>Micah</title>, <title>Nahum</title>,
              <title>Habbacuc</title>, <title>Zephaniah</title>, <title>Haggai</title>,
              <title>Zechariah</title>, <title>Malachi</title>, <title>Jeremiah</title>,
              <title>Ezekiel</title>, <title>Daniel</title>, <title>Judith</title>,
              <title>Esther</title>, <title>Susanna</title>, <title>Ezra</title>, <title>Daniel the
              Less</title>, <title>the Epistle of Baruch</title>, the <title>Traditions [or
              Expositions] of the Elders</title>, <title>Josephus the historian</title>, the book of
              <title>Proverbs</title>, the <title>Narrative of the sons of Solomona</title>, the
              <title>Maccabees</title>, <title>an account of Herod the king</title>, <title>the book
              of the destruction of the latter Jerusalem</title> by <persName>Titus</persName>,
              <title>the book of Asenath</title> the <persName>wife of Joseph</persName>
            <persName>the son of Jacob the righteous</persName>, and <title>the book of Tobias and
              Tobit the Israelites</title>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a1" target="#n1" n="1"/>
          </ab>
        </div>
        <div type="section" xml:id="section-2" n="2">
          <head type="main">
            <title>New Testament Scriptures</title>
          </head>
          <ab xml:id="section-2.1" n="2"> Having enumerated the books of the <title>Old
              Testament</title>, we shall now record those of the <title>New Testament</title>.
            First, <title>Matthew</title> wrote in <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, in the Hebrew
            tongue. After him comes <title>Mark</title>, who wrote in Latin at
              <placeName>Rome</placeName>. <title>Luke</title>, in
            <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, spoke and wrote in Greek. <title>John</title> also
            wrote his Gospel in Greek at <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>. <title>The Acts of the
              Apostles</title> were written by <persName>Luke</persName> to
              <persName>Theophilus</persName>; and the three Epistles of <title>James</title>,
              <title>Peter</title>, and <title>John</title>, were written in all languages, and
            called Catholic. Besides these there are fourteen Epistles of the great
              <persName>Apostle Paul</persName>, viz., <title>the Epistle to the Romans</title>,
            written from <placeName>Corinth</placeName>; <title>the First Epistle to the
              Corinthians</title>, written from <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> and sent by the <pb
              n="363"/>hands of <persName>Timothy</persName>; <title>the Second to the
              Corinthians</title>, written from <placeName>Philippi of Macedonia the
              great</placeName>, and sent by the hands of <persName>Titus</persName>; <title>the
              Epistle to the Galatians</title>, written at <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and sent by
            the same person; <title>the Epistle to the Ephesians</title>, also written at
              <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and sent by <persName>Tychicus</persName>; <title>the
              Epistle to the Philippians</title>, written at the same place, and sent by the hands
            of <persName>Epaphroditus</persName>; <title>the Epistle to the Colossians</title>,
            written at <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and sent by <persName>Tychicus</persName> the
            true disciple; <title>the First Epistle to the Thessalonians</title>, written at
              <placeName>Athens</placeName>, and sent by the hands of <persName>Timothy</persName>;
              <title>the Second to the Thessalonians</title>, written at <placeName>Laodicea of
              Pisidia</placeName>, and sent also by <persName>Timothy</persName>; <title>the First
              Epistle to Timothy</title>, also written from <title>Laodicea of Pisidia</title>, and
            sent by the hands of <persName>Luke</persName>; <title>the Second to Timothy</title>,
            written from <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and sent by the hands of <persName>Luke, the
              Physician and Evangelist</persName>; <title>the Epistle to Titus</title>, written at
              <placeName>Nicapolis</placeName>, and sent by the hands of
              <persName>Epaphroditus</persName>; <title>the Epistle to Philemon</title>, written at
              <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and sent by <persName>Onesimus</persName>, the slave of
              <persName>Philemon</persName>; <title>the Epistle to the Hebrews</title>, written in
              <placeName>Italy</placeName>, and sent by the hands of <persName>Timothy</persName>,
            the spiritual son. And the [Harmony of the] Gospels, called the
              <title>Diatesseron</title>, collated by a man of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>
            named Amonis, who is <persName>Tatian</persName>. </ab>
        </div>
        <div type="section" xml:id="section-3" n="3">
          <head type="main">Writing of the Western Fathers</head>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.1" n="3"> The following were written by disciples of
            the Apostles : the book of Dionysius, the heavenly philosopher; the book of Clemens, one
            of the Seventy; the Narratives of Peter, Paul, and John, and the other Apostles ; and
            the Apostolic Constitutions. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.2" n="4"> Africanus the Happy, Bishop of Emmaus,
            wrote a Commentary on the New Testament and a Chronicon. </ab>
          <pb n="364"/>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.3" n="5"> Hippolytus, Bishop and Martyr, wrote a book
            on the Life and Actions of Christ, an Exposition of Daniel the Less and Susanna, also
            Sentences against Gaius, an Introduction on the Advent of Christ, and an Exposition of
            the Gospel of S. John. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.4" n="6"> Damasus, Bishop of Rome, wrote an account
            of the Faith, and drew up several Canons, as did also Ignatius. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.5" n="7"> Symmachus is mentioned by the Expositor
            [Theodorus of Mopsuestia] as having written several works, one of which is entitled the
            Distinction of the Commandments. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.6" n="8"> Eusebius of Caesarea wrote a history in two
            volumes, a treatise on the Divine Advent, a Chronicon, a book solving the contradictions
            contained in the Gospels, another entitled a Picture of the World, an account of
            Constantine and of the Martyrs of the West, and an epic poem in their praise, a
            narrative of a drought of rain, and a defence of Origen which was condemned by
            Theodorus. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.7" n="9"> Athanasius the Great, Patriarch of
            Alexandria, wrote many epistles and treatises on the orthodox faith, an account of his
            flight, and a narrative of S. Anthony, which was sent by him to Epictetus. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.8" n="10"> Basil the Great wrote a work on the Six
            days of Creation, besides many other dissertations, narratives, and epistles. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.9" n="11"> Gregory of Nyssa wrote many treatises,
            among which are an Exposition of the Lord's Prayer and of the Beatitudes, a book of
            poems, a dissertation on the Resurrection, a dissertation on the Creation of Man which
            he sent to his sister, another on Natural Philosophy, one against the Gentiles, an
            exposition of the Song of Solomon in two volumes, and a treatise on the soul. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.10" n="12"> Gregory Nazianzen the Great wrote five
            volumes, and a collection of Poems, several Essays for Caesar, a work called Tragoedia,
            and a book against the Theopaschites. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.11" n="13"> John Chrysostom wrote an exposition of
            the Gospels of SS. Matthew and John, each consisting of two volumes, an Exposition of
            the Apostolic writings, a book on the Priesthood, another on Baptism, a treatise against
            the Jews, a book on the Monks of Egypt, a book of Consolations, a treatise on <pb
              n="365"/>Repentance, a treatise written to Justinian, another to Mitidus the Bishop,
            another on Generations, besides many epistles on various subjects. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.12" n="14"> Diodorus of Tarsus wrote sixty books,
            most of which were burnt by the Arians; among those remaining are the book entitled the
            Division of Food, one written against Chaldeanism, one against the Eunomians, another
            against the Manicheans, another against Apollinaris, and an exposition of a portion of
            S. Matthew's Gospel. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.13" n="15"> Theodorus the Expositor wrote forty-one
            volumes containing one hundred and fifty prophecies, each prophecy divided into thirty
            chapters. He also wrote a theoretical and practical exposition of Genesis in three
            books, which he sent to Elipia the great; an exposition of the Psalms in five books,
            sent by him to Cedron and his brother; an exposition of the Twelve Prophets in two
            volumes for Maurice; an exposition of Samuel in one book, which he sent to Marius; an
            exposition of Job, sent to Cyril of Egypt; an exposition of Ecclesiastes in one book,
            written at the request of Porphyry ; also an exposition of Isaiah, Ezekiel, Jeremiah,
            and Daniel, each in one book. These were his labours on the Old Testament. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.14" n="16"> On the New Testament, he wrote an
            exposition of S. Matthew to Julia in one book, and another of SS. Luke and John, in two
            books, to Eusebius; an exposition of the Acts in one book, to Basil; on the Epistle to
            the Romans, also to Eusebius; on the Epistles to the Corinthians, in two books, at the
            request of Theodora; and on the Epistles to the Galatians, Ephesians, Philippians, and
            Colossians, for Staurachius. The Epistles to the Thessalonians he expounded for Jacob,
            and the two Epistles to Timothy for Peter, and those to Titus and Philemon for Corinne,
            and the Epistle to the Hebrews he expounded for the same person. All his expositions of
            the Apostle Paul he collected in five volumes, and he wrote, besides these, a work on
            the Sacraments, and another on Faith, and another on the Priesthood, also two books on
            the Holy Spirit, and one on the Incarnation, in two volumes; and two other books against
            such as say that man cannot help sinning, and two against the Magians, and one addressed
            to the Monks, and one on Perfection, and another for Basil, and another on the union of
            the two <pb n="366"/>natures and persons in Christ, and a book of Jewels in which he
            collected all his epistles, and a treatise on the enacting of Laws, with which he
            concluded his writings. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.15" n="17"> Nestorius the Patriarch wrote many
            celebrated works, most of which were destroyed by the blasphemers. Of those remaining,
            one is entitled the Tragoedia, one dedicated to Heraclides, and an epistle to Cosmas,
            which was written in the time of Paul. He wrote, moreover, a large liturgy which was
            translated [into Syriac] by Tooma and Mar Awa. There is also of his a book of epistles,
            an Antiphonary, and a collection of epic poems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.16" n="18"> Theodotus, the disciple of Theodorus the
            Expositor, wrote an exposition of Isaiah in two volumes, and in another work he has
            explained the occasion of the writing of the different Psalms of David, and to what
            occasions their use is adapted. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.17" n="19"> Aquilinus wrote a commentary on S.
            Matthew and S. John the son of Zebedee after the traditions of the ancients. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.18" n="20"> Basilius wrote several Antiphonaries, and
            other treatises. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.19" n="21"> Chiore wrote on the different kinds of
            worship, and several narratives. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.20" n="22"> Irenaeus of Tyre wrote five histories on
            the persecution of Mar Nestorius, and on all the events which transpired during that
            period. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.21" n="23"> Phileteus expounded Ezekiel in two
            volumes, and wrote a book named, from its subject, the Healer. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.22" n="24"> Theodoret of Cyprus wrote a book entitled
            "Phileteus," one against Origen, another called the "Division of Food," an exposition of
            Daniel, excellent histories, Apologies for our righteous Fathers in two volumes, a
            solution of the Sentences of Cyril, a book against the Philosophers, and many epistles
            containing much learning and knowledge. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.23" n="25"> Socrates wrote two volumes of History,
            and an account of the Emperors Constantine and Jovian. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.24" n="26"> Titus wrote a work against Manes. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.25" n="27"> Arniastataeus also wrote a work against
            Manes. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.26" n="28"> Theophilus, the Persian, wrote against
            Dostseus, and another work in which he solved the Sentences of Cyril. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.27" n="29"> Eutheris wrote a book against the
            Patripassians, several narratives, antiphonae, and expositions of the Gospel. </ab>
          <pb n="367"/>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.28" n="30"> Epiphanes wrote a work on the Divine
            Advent, and another on the different heresies which had arisen up to his time. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.29" n="31"> Zenobius wrote against Marcion and
            Pamphilus, and epistles to Isidore, Lycullus, Abraham and Job. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.30" n="32"> Eusebius of Emesa wrote a book against
            the Jews, and on the ceremonies of the Old Testament, and a narrative of Stephen. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.31" n="33"> Father Macarius wrote three books on the
            right mode of living. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.32" n="34"> Marcus wrote a book of chapters. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.33" n="35"> John wrote histories. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.34" n="36"> Evagrius wrote three books. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.35" n="37"> Father Isaiah wrote one book. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.36" n="38"> Ammonius wrote epistles. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.37" n="39"> Macarius, not the same just mentioned,
            wrote several narratives. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.38" n="40"> Xistus wrote a book of sacred poems, and
            a work on the Lovers of God. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.39" n="41"> Nilus the Monk wrote two wonderful
            volumes. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.40" n="42"> Palladius and Hierome wrote the book of
            Paradise, and the sayings and injunctions of the Elders in three volumes. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.41" n="43"> John of Apamea, wrote three books, and
            several epistles on the Spiritual Life, on the Effects of Sin, and on Perfection. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-3.42" n="44"> Jacob, the disciple, wrote a short
            exposition of S. Matthew, of the Epistles, and of the Prophet Jeremiah. </ab>
        </div>
        <div type="section" xml:id="section-4" n="4">
          <head type="main">Writing of the Syrian Fathers</head>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.1" n="45"> After having enumerated the writings of
            the Greek Fathers we now begin to record the writings of the Syrian<ptr
              type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a2" target="#n2" n="2"/> Fathers. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.2" n="46"> Shimeon Barsabbaï wrote epistles to Mar
            Acac. </ab>
          <pb n="364"/>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.3" n="47"> Meelis wrote epistles and treatises on
            various subjects. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.4" n="48"> Mar Yaw-ahui wrote an epistle to the
            Eastern Papa, in whose days a letter was written by the Westerns raising this Eastern
              <pb n="368"/>See into a Patriarchate. The letter was sent, with all honour, by the
            hands of Agepta of Elam. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.5" n="49"> Ephraem the Great, called the Prophet of
            the Syrians, wrote a commentary on Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Joshua, Judges, Samuel,
            the Kings, the Psalms, Isaiah, the Twelve Prophets, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, and Daniel;
            besides other books and Epistles on the faith of the Church, poems, anthems, and hymns,
            and the Anneedhé, [Services for the dead]. He wrote also on the alphabet, a controversy
            with the Jews, and treatises against Manes, Bardassenes, and Marcion, and an answer to
            the blasphemy of Julian. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.6" n="50"> Narsai, the Harp of the Soul, wrote an
            exposition of Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, Joshua, Judges, Ecclesiastes, Isaiah,
            the twelve minor Prophets, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, and Daniel. He wrote also twelve other
            books, three hundred and sixty poems, a Liturgy, an exposition of the Sacraments, and a
            treatise on Baptism. He wrote, moreover, Consolations, Antiphonae, hymns, litanies,
            homilies, and a treatise on an Evil Life. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.7" n="51"> Barsoma wrote homilies, anthems, and other
            poems : also a liturgy, and many epistles. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.8" n="52"> Auraham of Beit Rabban wrote an exposition
            of Joshua, Judges, Kings, the Wisdom of the son of Sirach, and Isaiah, in two volumes;
            also a Commentary on the twelve minor Prophets, on Daniel, and the Song of Solomon, and
            a book of Moutwé,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a3" target="#n3" n="3"/> divided into
            chapters. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.9" n="53"> Johanan of Beit Rabban, wrote a commentary
            on Genesis, Leviticus, Numbers, Job, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, Proverbs, a book against the
            Magi, one on the Customs of the Jews, and another against heretics. He wrote also a poem
            on the humiliation of the Ninevites, one on the death of Chosroes, and another on the
            plague which visited Nisibis, together with consolations for all conditions of men, a
            Catechism on the Old and New Testament, hymns, poems, and a treatise on Chanting. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.10" n="54"> Marootha, Bishop of Meiparket, the
            learned physician, wrote a book of Evidences, Antiphonae, and hymns in honour of the <pb
              n="369"/>Martyrs. He also expounded the Canons of the 318 [of Nice], and wrote a full
            account of that Holy Synod. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.11" n="55"> Mar Awa the Great translated the entire
            Old Testament from the Greek into this Syriac tongue; he also wrote an exposition of
            Genesis, the Psalms, Proverbs, the Epistle to the Romans, the second to the Corinthians,
            the three following Epistles, and that also to the Hebrews. He wrote, moreover, several
            poems and anthems for the Canons<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a4" target="#n4" n="4"/>
            of the Psalter, a synodal epistle on the Discipline of the Church, and other
            Ecclesiastical Rules and Canons. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.12" n="56"> Hnâna of Hdheiyyeb wrote a Commentary on
            the Psalms, Genesis, Job, the Proverbs, Ecclesiastes, the Song of Solomon, the Twelve
            Prophets, on the Gospel of S. Mark, and the Epistles of S. Paul. Also an exposition of
            the Faith and Sacraments, a Catechism and a Treatise on the Origin of the Festival of
            Palms, with poems thereon. Besides these he wrote on the origin of the festivals of
            Golden Friday,<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a5" target="#n5" n="5"/> of that in
            commemoration of the Humiliation of the Ninevites, and on the Invention of the Cross,
            with many other works condemned by Theodorus of Mopsuestia. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.13" n="57"> Eprahat, the wise Persian, of happy
            memory, wrote two books, and many poems alphabetically arranged. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.14" n="58"> Heeba, Comar, and Proba, translated the
            writings of Theodorus of Mopsuestia from Greek into Syriac, as they did also the works
            of Aristotle. This same Heeba wrote also a commentary on the Proverbs, Antiphons, and
            other poems, and a polemical work against the heretics. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.15" n="59"> The Disciples of Mar Awa wrote many
            poems, and an exposition of the prophecy of Daniel. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.16" n="60"> Tooma of Edessa wrote on the origin of
            the Feasts of the Nativity and Epiphany, an epistle to Kâlé, a work against astrology, a
            book of Consolations, and a polemical treatise against heretics. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.17" n="61"> Serghees of Reish Aina wrote a treatise
            on Logic. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.18" n="62"> Paul of Nisibis wrote a Commentary on the
            Bible, a treatise against Caesar, and various epistles. </ab>
          <pb n="370"/>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.19" n="63"> Babai the Great wrote eighty-three books,
            in one of which he gives an account of the origin of the Feast of Palms, a dissertation
            on the union of Christ's humanity and divinity, and an exposition of the Book of
              Hundreds.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a6" target="#n6" n="6"/> He also expounded the
            book written by the Father Marcos, wrote an account of Diodorus and his followers, of
            the Feast of the Cross, and of the Saints for the cycle of the year, such as the Feasts
            of S. Mary, S. John, and the other feasts and commemorations. He moreover wrote a book
            for conventual Novices, an epistle to Joseph the Seer, rules for Monks, and an
            exposition of the whole Bible. Also a work on the Causes of Things, in which he speaks
            of Mattai who was translated, of Auraharn of Nisibis, and of Gawrièl of Kutr [or Kutra.] </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.20" n="64"> Dad-Yeshua expounded the "Paradise" of
            the Westerns, and the work of Father Isaiah, and wrote other books on the right mode of
            living. He also wrote a hymn on the consecration of a Cell, a funeral Dirge, several
            Epistles, and a Catechism on the Spiritual Life and Quiet. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.21" n="65"> Joseph the Seer wrote 1900 chapters on
            various theological subjects, and a book called the "Treasure," in which he solves many
            difficult questions. He also wrote a work on Calamities, an Exposition of the work
            entitled the "Merchant's Book," and another, in two volumes, on the Paradise of the
            Easterns, which contains many historical notices. Besides these, he composed a
            commentary on the Prophet Ezekiel, a treatise on the Festivals, and an exposition of the
            Heads of Knowledge, and of the works of Dionysius. He moreover expounded the Vision of
            Mar Gregorius, and wrote epistles on the life of Anchorites. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.22" n="66"> John of Dilyâtha wrote two books, besides
            epistles on the monastic life. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.23" n="67"> Ishâk of Nineveh wrote seven books on the
            spiritual and divine Sacraments, and one on the Distribution of Food. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.24" n="68"> Yeshua-yau, of Gadhla, wrote a commentary
            on the Psalms, together with epistles, dissertations, and poems on various subjects. </ab>
          <pb n="371"/>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.25" n="69"> Yeshua-yau, of Erzona, wrote a work
            against Eunomius, and another against an heretical Bishop. Also twenty-three Queries on
            the Sacraments of the Church, a Synodal Preface, Epistles, and Canons. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.26" n="70"> Cyprian, of Nisibis, expounded the
            Theology of Gregory the Great, and compiled an Ordination Office. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.27" n="71"> Yeshua-yau, of Hdheyyeb, wrote on a
            Change of Mind, and an Advice to Monastic Novices. He also arranged the Khudhra, and the
            Baptismal Office, and wrote an Office for the Consecration of a New Church, as also an
            Ordination Office, and the Office of Hoosâyé. He wrote, moreover, many antiphons, epic
            poems, epistles, anthems, and Consolations, in the most beautiful style, and a
            controversial treatise against certain persons. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.28" n="72"> Hnan-Yeshua wrote a treatise on Chanting. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.29" n="73"> Michael composed a book of Inquiries into
            the Bible, in three volumes. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.30" n="74"> Theodore, Metropolitan of Marro, wrote an
            account of Mar Eughène, and of the Greek doctors, in poetry; also an Exposition of the
            Psalms, and other poems, in which he answered the ten theses of Serghees. He composed
            another excellent book, moreover, at the instance of Mar Awa, the Catholicos. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.31" n="75"> Gawrièl, brother of the above, and Bishop
            of Hormuzdshir, wrote a work against Manes, and another against the Chaldeans, besides
            Homilies and other treatises on various subjects, to the extent of about three hundred
            chapters. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.32" n="76"> Elîa, Metropolitan of Marro, wrote
            antiphons, Consolations, and a Commentary on all the Gospel Lessons; also epistles, and
            an account of the origin of the Moutwé, and an Exposition of the Proverbs, Genesis, the
            Psalms, Ecclesiastes, the Song of Solomon, the Wisdom of the Son of Sirach, Isaiah, the
            Twelve Prophets, and the Epistles of the Apostle Paul. He also compiled an authentic
            History. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.33" n="77"> Gheorghees, Catholicos, wrote hymns,
            anthems, a Litany for the Fast of the Ninevites, and a few other Canons and poems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.34" n="78"> Gawrièl Arya, of the family of Ishâk of
            Nineveh, wrote an Exposition of many extracts taken from the whole Bible. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.35" n="79"> Hnan-Yeshua, surnamed Hgheera [the lame]
            wrote <pb n="372"/>antiphons, epistles, Consolations, homilies, poems, and several
            catechisms: also a book of Thanksgiving, on account of Serghees Doda, Two Reasons for
            Schools, and an Analogical exposition. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.36" n="80"> Awa, of Cashgar, wrote several homilies
            and epistles, a book on the rules of Logic, and another in which he explains the Logic
            of Aristotle. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.37" n="81"> Hnan-Yeshua, Catholicos, wrote a
            collection of epistles, Consolations, and anthems, in five books, besides other poems
            and ten dissertations. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.38" n="82"> Awa bar Brikh Sowyâne wrote a work on
            Strategy, several expositions, and antiphons full of wisdom. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.39" n="83"> Timatheos wrote a book on the Stars,
            another against the Mehdi, another on Church Matters, with many Synodal Canons, two
            hundred epistles collected into two volumes, a catechism, and a dissertation against
            heretics. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.40" n="84"> Ephràm, of Elam, wrote a work on the
            Faith. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.41" n="85"> Tooris, the Anchorite, composed a book in
            two volumes. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.42" n="86"> Hoonein, the physician, the son of Ishâk,
            wrote a book on the fear of God, a Grammar, and a Vocabulary. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.43" n="87"> Yeshua bar Nun wrote a work called
            "Theologia," Inquiries into the Bible, in two volumes, a book of sentences, of the
            Causes of things, Consolations, and epistles. He wrote also on the different Church
            Services, antiphons, and anthems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.44" n="88"> Elisha, the Expounder, wrote a Commentary
            on Job, and on the Second Epistle to the Corinthians, and on the three following
            epistles. He also composed an account of the Moutwé, and another of the Martyrs, a book
            of Thanksgivings, and a poem on Shimoon of Germakh. Besides which he explained the
            Chronicon of Eusebius. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.45" n="89"> Soreen, the Expounder, wrote in Greek
            against the heretics, and a book of evidences. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.46" n="90"> Bar Had-Bshabba, the Arab, wrote a work
            entitled "The Book of Treasures," in three volumes, and other polemical treatises,
            against the Gentiles, such as idolaters and others. He also wrote a history, and an
            account of Mar Diodorus and his followers, and an exposition of Mark the Evangelist, and
            of the Psalter. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.47" n="91"> Mikha, the Doctor, wrote Five Causes of
            the Moutwé, a poem <pb n="373"/>on Cantropos [?], and another on Mar Sawr-Yeshua, of
            Lashum. Also an exposition of the books of the Kings of Israel. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.48" n="92"> Kioré wrote various dissertations,
            homilies, and anaphoras. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.49" n="93"> Paulona wrote poems, a dissertation
            against inquirers, a treatise against Marcion, a book on Believers, and another on the
            Creed. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.50" n="94"> Serghees wrote an exposition of Jeremiah,
            Ezekiel, and of Daniel, after the style of the ancients. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.51" n="95"> Mari, the Persian, wrote a Commentary on
            Daniel, an explanation of the epistle of Akak, and a work against the Magi of Nisibis. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.52" n="96"> Auraham, of Mahozé, wrote Consolations,
            Epistles, an account of all the Festivals, and a book of Antiphons. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.53" n="97"> Paulos, of Ambar, wrote a work against
            the epistle of Omar, Consolations, and Antiphons, and a treatise against different
            persons. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.54" n="98"> Gawrièl, of Kotra, wrote a poem on the
            union of Christ, and a solution of the difficulties of the Faith. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.55" n="99"> Yakoob, of Kelta, wrote an exposition of
            the Proverbs, poems on Diodorus, and a book on the Faith of the Church. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.56" n="100"> Barsoma, of Kerkook, wrote a work called
            "the Liver," and another containing thanksgivings, Consolations, and Antiphons. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.57" n="101"> Ab Yeshua, Bar Bahrees, Metropolitan of
            Athur, wrote on the Division of Inheritances, and an Explanation of the different Church
            Services. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.58" n="102"> Daniel, of Toowaneetha, Bishop of Tahl,
            wrote a work entitled "the Book of Lilies," Consolations, and Antiphons. Also a book
            solving the difficulties contained in Holy Scripture, Replies to different Queries, one
            of Thanksgiving, another of Poems, a Solution of the difficulties in the writings of Mar
            Ishak of Nineveh, and an exposition of the Heads of Knowledge. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.59" n="103"> Auraham, Metropolitan of Basra, wrote
            several epistles. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.60" n="104"> Ahoob, of Kotra, wrote a Commentary on
            the Old and New Testaments with the exception of the Pentateuch. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.61" n="105"> Dinha expounded the Psalms, and wrote
            Consolations, and other treatises on Church subjects. He also explained the two books of
            Gregory, and the Logic of Aristotle. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.62" n="106"> Shallecta, Bishop of Reish Aina, wrote
            Antiphons, <pb n="374"/>Consolations, Prayers, Canons, and hootamât, [collects for the
            conclusion of Divine Service]. He also expounded two Litanies. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.63" n="107"> Babai, the Persian, who became Bishop of
            Riu Ardsheer, wrote a work solving various difficult questions. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.64" n="108"> Shehdost, of Teheran, wrote several
            Synodal Epistles and Letters, besides many small poems and Antiphons. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.65" n="109"> Habeeb, the Anchorite, wrote Meditations
            on the Life of Christ, Elements of Knowledge, and made several chants and tunes for
            Anthems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.66" n="110"> Babai of Nisibis, wrote poems, epistles,
            hymns, narratives, and several homilies. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.67" n="111"> Shimoon of Taibootha, wrote a work
            entitled "the way to live," another on Medicine, and an Exposition of the Sacraments. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.68" n="112"> Yohanan el-Ezrak, of Heerta, wrote a
            book of Homilies, a Guide, and two hundred and eighty epistles. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.69" n="113"> Yohanan of Deilom wrote nine poems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.70" n="114"> Mar Yau, wrote an epistle and an
            exposition of the same for Epni Mâran. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.71" n="115"> Yeshua Pâna, of Kotra, wrote hortatory
            poems, an exposition of the "Book of Hundreds," another on the Philosophy of the Soul,
            and many poems, anthems, epistles, Consolations, and hymns, arranged alphabetically. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.72" n="116"> Babai, the Scribe, of Maarra, wrote a
            work on the Distinction of Things. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.73" n="117"> The Turkish Expounder wrote a work on
            the Joys of Heaven. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.74" n="118"> Mar Shooha'l Mâran, of Seleucia, wrote a
            work called the "Book of Portions," another on Elements of Knowledge, besides many
            useful epistles. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.75" n="119"> Yohanan bar Pinkhâyé wrote seven books,
            one on the Education of Children, a controversial treatise against the "Words of a
            Merchant," one against Idolatry, one on the Seven Eyes of the Lord, one on Perfection,
            and a Catechism. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.76" n="120"> Auraham, of Nethpra, wrote many works. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.77" n="121"> Gregorius, of Deir, wrote one book and
            several epistles. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.78" n="122"> Akb-Shma wrote homilies, Consolations,
            anthems, on the Principles of Knowledge and Proverbs. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.79" n="123"> Akhoodemé wrote against the Philosophers
            and Magi, and on the limits of things. He also wrote a book on Logic, another on the
            Persons [of Christ], and a third on the inquiry : "Has <pb n="375"/>the will power over
            the nature of man?" in two parts. He also wrote on the Soul, showing that man is a small
            world in himself, besides many other instructive treatises in beautiful style and
            language. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.80" n="124"> Auraham bar Dishended, wrote a Book of
            Advice, an exposition of the writings of Father Marcos, a treatise against the Jews,
            another entitled "the Way of the King," poems on Repentance, and many epistles on
            various subjects. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.81" n="125"> Yeshua-Bukht wrote a book on All Things,
            and another on Church Matters, and poems on the Air. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.82" n="126"> Yeshua-Dnah, of Basra, wrote three books
            of History, an exposition of Logic, Consolations, Anthems, and Poems, and a treatise on
            Chastity, in which he collected an account of all the Saints. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.83" n="127"> Auraham bar Lipah wrote a Rationale of
            the different Services. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.84" n="128"> Alexandros wrote a work against the
            blasphemy of Julian. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.85" n="129"> Poplius wrote two books, one on Holy
            Things, and a Remembrancer. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.86" n="130"> Abd Mesheeh, of Heerta, wrote a book
            rich in meaning. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.87" n="131"> Theodorus bar Coozai wrote a Scholion, a
            History, and many other dissertations. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.88" n="132"> Abd Yeshua bar Akarwé wrote several
            anthems, and a work on the origin of Things. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.89" n="133"> Andraos wrote antiphons, and a work on
            the diacritical and vowel points. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.90" n="134"> Gawrièl, of Basra, collected all the
            Synodal Canons, in two volumes, and added thereto several dissertations. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.91" n="135"> Yohanan, of Germaka, wrote on the
            Principles of Knowledge, Rules for Novices, a short Chronicon, an account of Mar
            Koodehwi, and many poems and anthems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.92" n="136"> Auraham, of Beit Hâlé, wrote a treatise
            against the Tai [Arabs.] </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.93" n="137"> Mar Shlemon, Bishop of Hdhetta near
            Mosul, wrote several narratives, and a treatise on the Monastic Life. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.94" n="138"> Yeshua-dad, also of Hdhetta, wrote a
            Commentary on the New Testament, and a short exposition of the Pentateuch. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.95" n="139"> Aboo-Nuah wrote a work against the
            Koran, a treatise against Heretics, and on several other subjects. </ab>
          <pb n="376"/>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.96" n="140"> Kindi wrote an excellent work on
            Polemics, and another on the Faith. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.97" n="141"> Dad-Yeshua wrote a wonderful exposition
            of Daniel, of the Kings, and of the book of Wisdom, in three volumes. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.98" n="142"> Yohanan, of Nineveh, wrote a work on
            Controversy. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.99" n="143"> Kuriakòs wrote an exposition of the
            Faith and Sacraments, another work on the Nativity and Epiphany, and a Commentary on the
            Epistles of S. Paul. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.100" n="144"> Shimoon bar Tabbâhé wrote a History. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.101" n="145"> Meshikha Skha also wrote a History. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.102" n="146"> Mar Athken, the Anchorite, wrote a
            Controversy with the Wise Brother, and many epistles on the right way of living. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.103" n="147"> Gheorghees, of Nishra, wrote a book on
            Obedience. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.104" n="148"> Anos, of Piros-Shaboor, wrote poems,
            Consolations, and many other works. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.105" n="149"> Bood Piryadotha wrote poems on the
            Faith, a treatise against the Manichees, and another against the followers of Marcion.
            He also wrote a work in Greek, entitled "Alep-Megheen," and it was he who translated
            "Kleilagh oo Dimnagh"<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a7" target="#n7" n="7"/> from the
            Indian language. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.106" n="150"> Danièl, of Reish Aina, wrote poems
            against the Marcionites, Manichees, Heretics, and Chaldeans. </ab>
          <pb n="377"/>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.107" n="151"> Auraham bar Kardâkhé wrote anthems,
            Consolations, poems, and homilies, and an Epistle against Shisban. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.108" n="152"> Nathnièl wrote against the followers of
            Severus, against Manes, and against the Kanthi and Mandri [Sabaeans], and an Exposition
            of the Psalms. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.109" n="153"> Elisha bar Sabîné wrote an Exposition
            of the Psalter, on Different Opinions, and a chapter of Proverbs. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.110" n="154"> Auraham Katteena wrote Catechisms. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.111" n="155"> Shimoon, of Kurdlah, wrote 1,028 poems
            and anthems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.112" n="156"> Father Yazeedad wrote a vocabulary
            called "Lookaté." </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.113" n="157"> Bar Shhak wrote one book. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.114" n="158"> Damanis wrote poems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.115" n="159"> Susai, of Sus, wrote a book of
            Thanksgivings. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.116" n="160"> Auraham Saba wrote a beautiful
            Catechism. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.117" n="161"> Gregor, of Shushtre, wrote a work
            against Heathenism, on Natural Evidences, Consolations, anthems, a narrative of Auraham
            of Shushtre, a History, and an account of the different Festivals. It was he who
            originated the chant "Ittayyeb b'awadheicon."<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a8"
              target="#n8" n="8"/>
          </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.118" n="162"> Bar Sehde, of Kerkook, wrote a History,
            and a work against the Magi, the disciples of Zoroaster. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.119" n="163"> Jacob, of Edessa, wrote a Book of the
            Times, and a Chronicon. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.120" n="164"> Shimoon, of Bedhka, wrote a History. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.121" n="165"> Ara wrote a work against the Magi, and
            another against Bardassenes, entitled "Beetles." </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.122" n="166"> Pâkor wrote one book. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.123" n="167"> Bar Dkôsi wrote two volumes against the
            Chaldeans, and another against Porphyry the heretic. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.124" n="168"> Danièl ibn Mariam wrote a History in
            four volumes, and another expounding the Chronicon. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.125" n="169"> Zacchai, of Supna, wrote on the Wonders
            of the World. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.126" n="170"> Bar Daknâna wrote poems for the
            consolation of the sorrowing. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.127" n="171"> Yohanan bar Abgaré wrote Canons and
            Homilies on Church matters, and on the Division of Inheritances. </ab>
          <pb n="378"/>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.128" n="172"> Mar Daweedh, of Beit Rabban, wrote on
            the Boundaries of countries, and on the Changes of nights and days. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.129" n="173"> Yohanan, of Estooni, wrote a Grammar. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.130" n="174"> Yohanan bar Khâmees, Bishop of Temnoon,
            also wrote a Grammar. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.131" n="175"> Bar Bahlool collated a Lexicon from
            many books, assisted by Yeshua bar Ali the Physician, Marozi, and Gawrièl. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.132" n="176"> Elîa, of Azak, wrote three books of
            poetry, questions, epistles, prefaces and anthems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.133" n="177"> Dad-Yeshua, Bishop of Heerta, called
            Mattushuah, wrote a Catechism on the Holy Scriptures, and Anthems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.134" n="178"> Andor, the Scholar, wrote a
            dissertation on many things, arranged alphabetically, which he sent to his friend
            Koorta. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.135" n="179"> Elîa bar Kanosh wrote Benedictions,
            Narratives, a treatise on the use of the Psalms, and on the Sacraments of the Church. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.136" n="180"> Mar Elîa, the First, wrote Decrees, a
            treatise on Church matters, and a Grammar. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.137" n="181"> Yohanan bar Keldon wrote a valuable
            work called "Busnâya," another on the Most Beautiful, and a third on the Merchandize of
            the Monks. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.138" n="182"> Elîa bar Yeshnâya, Metropolitan of
            Nisibis, wrote a History, a Grammar, poems, four books of Church rules, and epistles on
            various subjects in Syriac and Arabic. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.139" n="183"> Behishua, of Kamool, wrote on the
            Monastic life. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.140" n="184"> Yohanan Hermis wrote poems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.141" n="185"> Emmanuèl, the Doctor, wrote a work on
            the six days of Creation in poetry, homilies, and expositions. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.142" n="186"> Gawrièl, Bishop of Shabookhwest, wrote
            a catechism, homilies, controversies, Consolations, and anthems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.143" n="187"> The Greek Emperors Constantine, Leo,
            and Theodosius the Great, convened the Synods of the Westerns, that of the Apostles, of
            Nice, of Byzantium, of Gangra, the false one of Ephesus, that of Chalcedon, of Antioch,
            and the -- -- of the Greek Emperors.<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a9" target="#n9"
              n="9"/>
          </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.144" n="188"> And we possess the Eastern Synods of
            Ishâk, of Barsoma, of Mar Awa, of Mar Hezkièl, of Yosep, of Yeshua-yau, of Mar <pb
              n="379"/>Timataos, of Yeshua bar Nun, of Yohanan, the Acts of Shimoon, the Acts of
            Yeshua-Bukht, Metropolitan of Persia, and those of Abd Yeshua and of Gheorghees,
            Metropolitans of Athor, besides two volumes of Synods collated by Gawrièl, Metropolitan
            of Basra, and another of the Catholicos Mar Elîa the First, and four of Elîa of Nisibis,
            surnamed Bar Ishnâya. We possess, moreover, many other books whose authors' names are
            unknown; such as the book entitled "the Enlightenment," and the book on the Union. [Here
            several lines of the original are destroyed.] </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.145" n="189"> Shlemon, of Khlàt, of Basra [prob.
            Metrop.], wrote a work entitled Debboreetha [lit. The Bee], another on the Heavens and
            the Earth, and several poems. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.146" n="190"> Abd Yeshua, my vile self, wrote a
            Commentary on the Bible [MS. defaced], the book of the Paradise of Eden, a collection of
            Synods in Arabic, the book entitled Marghianeetha<ptr type="noteAnchor" xml:id="a10"
              target="#n10" n="10"/> on the Truth of the Faith, a treatise on the Mysteries of the
            Grecian Philosophers, and another called "Scholasticus," against heresy. I also collated
            a book of Church Laws and Discipline, and another consisting of twelve treatises on
            knowledge in general, besides Consolations, antiphons, and anthems, for various
            occasions, an explanation of the Epistle sent by Aristotle to Alexander the Great [MS.
            defaced], also a work solving many difficult questions, and one of arguments, proverbs,
            and riddles. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.147" n="191"> After the best of our ability we have
            recorded the books which we have seen, our object being to show that the perusal of them
            is profitable. The authors spake by the Spirit, according to the testimony of Paul the
            Apostle; may their prayers keep and invest with glory us, the sheep of Christ, and may
            their memory endure for ever, inasmuch as they enlightened the Church by their wisdom,
            and enriched her children by their attainments. Glory be to that Spirit by whom they
            themselves were enriched. </ab>
          <ab type="section" xml:id="section-4.148" n="192"> Here endeth the catalogue of all the
            Church books, written by the undeserving Abd Yeshua, Metropolitan of Nisibis and
            Armenia. To God be thanksgiving and glory for ever. Amen. </ab>
        </div>
      </div>
      <noteGrp>
        <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">
          <choice>
            <reg/>
            <orig>p. 362, n. *</orig>
          </choice>The " Narratives," and several of the other works enumerated in the latter part
          of this paragraph, are probably legends such as are frequently met with in the East. Some
          of these are written with much pathos, and form epic poems, set to the most plaintive
          chants. The Legend of Joseph is very common among Mohammedans as well as Christians, and
          many strolling derweeshes obtain a living by reciting it from house to house.</note>
        <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">
          <choice>
            <reg/>
            <orig>p. 367, n. *</orig>
          </choice>"Syro-Nestorian" Fathers are doubtless intended. The Syrian authors in this list
          who existed prior to the Council of Ephesus, are claimed as co-religionists by the
          Nestorians.</note>
        <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">
          <choice>
            <reg/>
            <orig>p. 368, n. *</orig>
          </choice>Literally, "Thrones," as in Coloss. i. 16, of the Syriac version. The term is
          here applied to certain prayers appointed to be used at the Nocturns, and which are
          recited alternately by priest and people, all being seated on the ground.</note>
        <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">
          <choice>
            <reg/>
            <orig>p. 369, n. *</orig>
          </choice>Canons here signify the occasional collects introduced into the Psalms as used in
          the Church.</note>
        <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">
          <choice>
            <reg/>
            <orig>p. 369, n. †</orig>
          </choice>The first Friday after Whitsunday: so called from the answer of S. Peter to the
          impotent man : "Silver and gold have I none," etc. Acts iii. 6.</note>
        <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">
          <choice>
            <reg/>
            <orig>p. 370, n. *</orig>
          </choice>Kthâwa d'Mawâtha, a learned but very difficult treatise, of which there are a few
          copies still extant. It is divided into a hundred sections, and is supposed to have been
          written by Evagrius.</note>
        <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">
          <choice>
            <reg/>
            <orig>p. 376, n. *</orig>
          </choice>
          <p>This famous collection of Fables is recorded by all Arabian historians to have been
            translated from the original into Pehlvi by one Barzooyah, who was commissioned to
            execute the task by the then reigning king of Persia Nooshirwan, about the year a.d.
            510. Baron de Sacy, who published in 1816 an excellent edition of the Arabic Version
            translated from the Pehlvi by Abdallah bin 'ool Mukatta, after expressing his doubt of
            this testimony to Bood's labour as recorded by Mar Abd-Yeshua, suggests the following
            adjustment of the apparent contradiction existing between him and the Arabian historians
            : "On the other hand, we may suppose that Barzooyah was a Christian monk, who had been
            employed in the Indian territory bordering on Persia, and that to a knowledge of his own
            native tongue, and the Syriac of his Church, he joined an acquaintance with the language
            of India, and hence was employed by Nooshirwan to translate the work called Calila oo
            Dimna. Abd-Yeshua does not state that the translation made by Bood was into Syriac ; he
            moreover speaks of it as a fact generally known ; hence it is not improbable that he
            understood Bood and Barzooyah to be the same person." De Sacy adduces several plausible
            reasons in support of this hypothesis, in his "Memoire Historique," appended to his
            Arabic edition of the work in question.</p>
          <p>Assemanni, as quoted by the learned Baron, states that Bood lived during the
            patriarchate of Ezekiel. This is a mistake, since the name of the Patriarch who filled
            the Eastern See during the reign of Chosroes Anooshirwan was "Sheela" [Silas.]</p>
          <p>"Piryadotha," the title given to Bood, signifies "Presbyter circuitor, seu visitator;"
            and seems to be cognate with our "Dean." I have so translated it wherever it has
            occurred throughout this work.</p>
        </note>
        <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">
          <choice>
            <reg/>
            <orig>p. 377, n. *</orig>
          </choice>This chant is still in use among the Nestorians.</note>
        <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">
          <choice>
            <reg/>
            <orig>p. 378, n. *</orig>
          </choice>The meaning of the original is somewhat obscure in this passage, but I conceive
          the writer to signify that the Nestorians possess the Acts of these Councils and
          Synods.</note>
        <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">
          <choice>
            <reg/>
            <orig>p. 379, n. *</orig>
          </choice>For a translation, see the next page.</note>
      </noteGrp>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
