<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Questions By The Pupils And The Answers [To The Same] By
               The Holy Fathers And Monks</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_2/Questions_By_The_Pupils_And_The_Answers_To_The_Same_By_The_Holy_Fathers_And_Monks"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_2/Questions_By_The_Pupils_And_The_Answers_To_The_Same_By_The_Holy_Fathers_And_Monks
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Questions By The Pupils And The Answers [To The Same] By The Holy Fathers And
            Monks</head>
         <div type="saying" n="541">
            <p>Brother: How is love (or charity) acquired by men of understanding?</p>
            <p>Old Man. True and pure love is the way of life, and the haven of promises, and the
               treasure of faith, and the interpreter of the kingdom, and the herald of that which
               is hidden.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="542">
            <p>Brother: I do not know the power of the word.</p>
            <p>Old Man: If a man loveth not God, he cannot believe in Him, and His promises are not
               true [to him], and he feareth not His judgement, and he followeth Him not. Now
               because love is not in him [he cannot] be free from iniquity, and await the life
               which is promised, but he performeth at all times the plans of sin; and this
               [happeneth] because the judgement of God is [too] exalted in his sight. Therefore let
               us run after love, wherewith the holy fathers have enriched themselves, for it is
               able to pay back [what is due] to its nature and its God. This then is praise.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="543">
            <p>Brother: How doth wisdom dwell in man?</p>
            <p>Old Man: Now when a man hath gone forth to follow after God with a lowly mind, grace
               bestoweth itself upon him, and his conduct becometh strengthened in the spirit, and
               when he hateth the world he becometh sensible of the new conduct of the new man,
               which is more exalted than the impurity of the human abode; and he meditateth in his
               mind the humility of the rule of the life which is to come, and he becometh a man of
               greater spiritual excellence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="544">
            <p>Brother: How is love made known?</p>
            <p>Old Man: By the fulfilment of works, and by spiritual care, and by the knowledge of
               faith.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="545">
            <p>Brother: What are the works?</p>
            <p>Old Man: The keeping of the commandments of the Lord with the purity of the inner
               man, together with the labour of the outer man.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="546">
            <p>Brother: Is he who is destitute of work also destitute of love?</p>
            <p>Old Man: It is impossible that he who is of God should not love, and it is impossible
               for him that loveth not to work, and it is impossible to believe that he who teacheth
               but worketh not is a true believer, for his tongue is the enemy of his action, and
               though he speaketh life he is in subjection unto death.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="547">
            <p>Brother: And is he who is in this state free from retribution?</p>
            <p>Old Man: Such a man who speaketh the things of the spirit, and performeth the things
               of the body, and supplieth his own wants, is not deprived of reward, but he is
               deprived of the crown of light, because the guidance of the spirit refuseth to rule
               him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="548">
            <p>What are fasting and prayer?</p>
            <p>Old Man: Fasting is the subjugation of the body, prayer is converse with God, vigil
               is a war against Satan, abstinence is the being weaned from meats, humility is the
               state of the first man, kneeling is the inclining of the body before the Judge, tears
               are the remembrance of sins, nakedness is our captivity which is caused by the
               transgression of the command, and service is constant supplication to and praise of
               God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="549">
            <p>Brother: Are these able to redeem the soul?</p>
            <p>Old Man: When internal things agree with external, and manifest humility appeareth in
               the hidden works which are from within, verily, a man shall be redeemed from the
               weight of the body.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="550">
            <p>Brother: And what is internal humility?</p>
            <p>Old Man: The humility of love, peace, friendship, purity, restfulness, tranquillity,
               subjection, faith, remoteness from envy, and a soul which is free from the heat of
               anger, and is far from the grade of arrogance, and is redeemed from the love of
               vainglory, and is full of patient endurance like the great deep, and whose motion is
               drawn after the knowledge of the spirit, and before whose eyes are depicted the fall
               of the body, and the greatness of the marvel of the Resurrection, and the demand for
               judgement which shall come after the revivification, and its standing before the
               awful throne of God. [If the soul hath these things] redemption shall be unto it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="551">
            <p>Brother: Is there any man who fasteth that shall not be redeemed?</p>
            <p>Old Man: There is one [kind of] fasting which is from habit, and another from desire,
               and another from compulsion, and another from sight, and another from the love of
               vainglory, and another from affliction, and another from repentance, and another from
               spiritual affection; for although each of these seems to be the same as the other in
               the mind externally, yet in the word of knowledge they are distinct. Now the way in
               which each is performed by the body is the same, and the way in which each is to be
               undertaken is wholly the same by him who travelleth straightly on the path of love,
               and who beareth his burden with patient endurance spiritually, and who doth not
               rejoice in his honour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="552">
            <p>Brother: Who is the true [monk]?</p>
            <p>Old Man: He who maketh his word manifest in deeds, and beareth his passion with
               patient endurance; with such a man life is found, and the knowledge of the spirit
               dwelleth in him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="553">
            <p>Brother: Who is the pure habitation?</p>
            <p>Old Man: He who is destitute of the good things of the body, and who rejoiceth in the
               love of his neighbours in the love of God; for spiritual relaxation is produced in
               proportion as need ruleth over the soul.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="554">
            <p>Brother: With what is a man able to overcome lust?</p>
            <p>Old Man: With spiritual remembrance. If the desire for the delights which are to come
               doth not obliterate that of the things which are here, a man cannot conquer; for if
               the ship of the merchant did not arrive over and over again by means of hope, he
               could not endure the storms, and he would go on his way of tribulation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="555">
            <p>Brother: How doth a man go forth from the world?</p>
            <p>Old Man: By forsaking entirely the gratification of desire, and by running to the
               utmost of his power in the fulfilment of the commandments; for he who doth not act in
               this way falleth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="556">
            <p>Brother: Behold, through what have the men of old triumphed?</p>
            <p>Old Man: Through the fervour of their supernatural love, and through the death of the
               corruptible man, and through the contempt for pride, and through the abatement of the
               belly, and through the fear of the judgement, and through the promise of certainty;
               through the desire for these glorious things the fathers have acquired in the soul
               the spiritual body.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="557">
            <p>Brother: How can I conquer the passions which trouble me when they are fixed in me by
               nature?</p>
            <p>Old Man: By thy death to this world; for if thou dost not bury thy soul in the grave
               of persistent endurance the spiritual Adam can never be quickened in thee. When a
               dying man hath departed from this temporary life he hath no consciousness of this
               world, and all his perceptions are at rest and are abated. Now if thou forsakest that
               which is of nature naturally, and thou dost not perform it voluntarily in thy person,
               thou art dead; but if thy desire dieth in repentance, the whole of [thy] nature
               ceaseth from this temporary life by the death of the spirit just as do the motions of
               the body at the natural end of time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="558">
            <p>Brother: To what extent is a man held capable of revelation?</p>
            <p>Old Man: To the same extent as a man is capable of stripping off sin, both internally
               and externally. For when a man dieth by spiritual sacrifice, [he dieth] to all the
               words and deeds of this habitation of time, and when he hath committed his life to
               the life which is after the revivification, Divine grace bestoweth itself upon him,
               and he becometh capable of divine revelations. For the impurity of the world is a
               dark covering before the face of the soul, and it preventeth it from discerning
               spiritual wisdom.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="559">
            <p>Brother: Is he who loveth money able to believe the promises?</p>
            <p>Old Man: No. If he believeth, wherefore doth he possess [riches]? Perhaps our hope is
               [set] upon gold, or perhaps the hand of the Lord is too small to redeem [us]? The
               body of our Lord is given unto us for [our] happiness, and His blood is the drink of
               our redemption, and He withholdeth from us the loaves of bread and the apparel which
               groweth old. He who loveth money is divided in his mind concerning God, and he
               prepareth for himself pleasures before God giveth them unto him; and though he
               rejoiceth in the promises in [his] word, he maketh them to be a lie by his deed. True
               indeed is the word of our Lord which He spake, <quote>It is as difficult for the rich man
               to enter the kingdom of heaven as it is for a camel to go through the hole of the
               needle</quote>; it is impossible to possess in one dwelling both God and mammon. Monks
               should, then, not belong unto the things which are seen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="560">
            <p>Brother: Who is indeed the man of excellence?</p>
            <p>Old Man: He who crieth out always that he is a sinner, and asketh mercy from on high,
               whose word is laden with the feeling of discernment, and his senses with the
               watchfulness of deeds, and who, being silent, yet speaketh, and who, though speaking,
               holdeth his peace, and whose actions are wholly good fruits for the life of time, and
               the revelation of Christ.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="561">
            <p>Brother: What is the way of life?</p>
            <p>Old Man: The going forth of a man from this world on his entrance into another. But
               if a man forsaketh his childhood of humility and cometh to the old age of this world
               in his love, he revealeth the way of life. To go forth truly from this world is to be
               remote from it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="562">
            <p>Brother: And what shall I do in respect of the world which troubleth me?</p>
            <p>Old Man: This world troubleth thee because its care is in thy mind, and the love of
               it is in thy body, and its pleasures are in thy heart; forsake the world and it will
               depart from thee, and root up from thyself all its branches, and behold, the war
               thereof will die down in thee. For as long as thy body seeketh its gratifications,
               and its lust is of this world, thou art not capable of life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="563">
            <p>Brother: What is pure prayer?</p>
            <p>Old Man: Pure prayer is little in speech and great in deeds, for if it were not so
               work would be more excellent than supplication.… For if it be not so why do we ask
               and yet not receive, seeing that the mercy of God aboundeth? The method of penitents
               is, however, something different, as is also the labour of the humble, for the
               penitents are hirelings, and the humble are sons.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="564">
            <p>Brother: From what is the love of money produced?</p>
            <p>Old Man: From desire, for unless a man desireth he doth not possess. When a man
               desireth he possesseth, and when he possesseth he hath fulfilled his desire; and when
               he hath fulfilled his desire, he becometh greedy; and when he hath become greedy he
               committeth fraud, and when he hath committed fraud his possessions have become many.
               When his possessions are many his love diminisheth, and when his love hath diminished
               the remembrance of God is removed from his heart. And when the remembrance of God
               hath been removed from his heart, the mind becometh darkened, and his understanding
               is blinded; and when his understanding hath become blinded the power of discernment
               is darkened, and when the power of discernment hath become dark, the soul loseth its
               sight. And when the soul hath lost its sight good is rooted out therefrom, and
               wickedness entereth in, and sin taketh up its rule; and when sin hath taken up its
               rule the thought of God is blotted out, and the passions of the body are stirred up,
               and they seek to satisfy their needs. And having taken that which they sought for, it
               is necessary for much money to be collected, and when money is multiplied, the
               gratification of the body is fulfilled, and it eateth and drinketh, and committeth
               adultery and fornication, and it lieth and worketh fraud and oppression, and it
               transgresseth the covenant, and destroyeth the Law, and treateth the promises with
               contempt, and the lust for the things which are seen is fulfilled. Let money be an
               abominable thing in our sight, and let us not love it; but if we perform the lust of
               the flesh it is an absolute necessity to love money; for money belongeth to the flesh
               and not to the spirit, even as saith the Apostle, <quote>The flesh hurteth the spirit, and
               the spirit the flesh, and both are opponents each of the other</quote> (Galatians 5:17).</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="565">
            <p>Brother: What is the kind of prayer which is not acceptable before God?</p>
            <p>Old Man: The destruction of enemies, and asking for evil things [to come upon] those
               who do harm to us, and the health of the body, and a multitude of possessions, and
               abundance of offspring—prayers for these things are not acceptable before God. But if
               God beareth with us whilst we are sinners and commit offences against Him, how much
               more is it right that we should bear with each other? It is not right for us to ask
               for the things which belong to the body, for the wisdom of God provideth all
               things.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="566">
            <p>Brother: What is purity of soul?</p>
            <p>Old Man: Remoteness from anger and from the error of the remembrance of evil things,
               and being weaned from the bitter nature, and reconciliation with our enemies, and
               peace which is beyond troubling, and simplicity of love which is above this world;
               with these things is the inner man cleansed, and he putteth on Christ and is
               redeemed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="567">
            <p>Brother: What is envy?</p>
            <p>Old Man: Hatred towards the virtues of other folk, and wickedness towards the good,
               and a bitter mind towards the innocent, and anger against those who are prosperous in
               this world, and the cloaking of the upright conduct of those who repent, and vexation
               with the peace of the lovers of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="568">
            <p>Brother: How ought we to pray before God?</p>
            <p>Old Man: For the return of sinners, and the finding of the lost, and the bringing
               near of those who are afar off, and friendliness towards those who wrong us, and love
               towards those who persecute us, and a sorrowful care for those who provoke to wrath;
               if a man doeth these things verily there is repentance in his mind, and sinners will
               often live, and their soul[s] be redeemed in life. For the prayer which our Lord
               delivered unto us for the need of the body is a word which covereth the whole
               community, and was not uttered solely for those who are strangers to the world, and
               who hold in contempt the pleasures of the body. For he in whose dwelling the kingdom
               of God and the righteousness thereof are found lacketh nothing, even when he asketh
               [not].</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="569">
            <p>Brother: What is remoteness from the world?</p>
            <p>Old Man: The thought (or mind) which overcometh the love or the body; for if the body
               be not trampled upon by the feeling of patient endurance a man cannot conquer in his
               strife.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="570">
            <p>Brother: Is the soul of a man, which is held fast in the lust of the things which are
               seen, fair in the sight of God?</p>
            <p>Old Man: Who is able to live chastely when the body is making demands upon him? Or,
               in what soul is found the love of our Lord which bestoweth itself upon the things
               which are seen and which are corruptible? A servant cannot serve two masters, and the
               soul cannot please God with spiritual excellence so long as the memories of the
               things which are corruptible are in its mind, for the mind of the flesh cannot please
               our Lord; and except the world die in the heart humility cannot dwell therein, and
               except the body be deprived of its lusts, the soul cannot be cleansed from
               thoughts.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="571">
            <p>Brother: Why is the mind disturbed at meeting women?</p>
            <p>Old Man: Because they make use of the lust of nature. For, when the sight hath fallen
               upon the construction for the production of children and the gratification of the
               body, that old poison layeth hold upon it, and the law of the desire is confounded;
               now desire conquereth nature, not by the stirring up of the passions, but by the
               will, [and] by the fulfilling of works of humility, which, by the might of our Lord,
               conquer everything by their love, and by the patient endurance of the merit of
               Christ.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="572">
            <p>Brother: Who is the mighty man, he who is remote from the world, or he who dwelleth
               therein?</p>
            <p>Old Man: The mighty man conquereth in every place, whether he be in the world or
               without. Nevertheless, the fathers departed to the wilderness, the place which is
               preserved from the uproar of those who are afraid that as long as they dwell in the
               body the passions which give trouble will cleave to them. Now, for those who have
               ended the great strife of their conflict in the world Divine grace hath worked with
               its power, and it still worketh for the remembrance and benefit of the community, and
               truly great is the crown of those whose spiritual ship hath not sunk to the bottom of
               the tossed and troubled sea of this world, and hath not ceased its course heavenwards
               by the straight road which is full of fear.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="573">
            <p>Brother: Is it helpful to the soul to make oneself a stranger?</p>
            <p>Old Man: With perfect thanksgiving it doth help, provided that the soul beareth
               chastely afflictions, and rejoiceth in our Lord who giveth pleasure; but if it doth
               not, its good seed is made of no effect because it doth not give fruit beloved of
               God, and if it endureth and uttereth blessing it hath a reward, but if it lack these
               things it becometh a mere wandering of the mind, and a sight which is without profit.
               The best thing of all is the quietness of the mind which is akin to God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="574">
            <p>Brother: Since all the creatures of God are holy, why do the fathers make the sign of
               the blessed Cross over the things which they eat?</p>
            <p>Old Man: It is true that all the creatures of God were pure [when they came from] Him
               that created them, but because sin gained dominion everything became polluted; but
               the advent of our Lord came, and sin was abrogated and righteousness had its rule,
               and everything was made holy, whether it was in the heavens or on the earth. But
               because the blessed fathers knew the wiles of Satan, and that they would certainly
               bring upon them that which would do them harm by means of such things as are employed
               as food, they signed what they ate with the holy sign of the Great Cross so that they
               might slay all the craftiness of the Calumniator.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="575">
            <p>One of the fathers said, <quote>On one occasion I was lying down at night, and I thirsted
               for water to drink; now there was near me one of the holy men who lived in a holy
               manner, and he saw that I took up the vessel to drink without having made over it the
               [sign of] the Cross. And he said unto me, <quote>Wait, master, wait</quote>; and he made the sign
               of the Cross over it, and straightway the Calumniator fell from the vessel in the
               form of a flash of fire, and both he and I saw it. And we wondered at the great might
               of our Redeemer, and at the marvellous symbol of His merit.</quote></p>
            <p>A variant [reads]:—One of the fathers said, <quote>I was lying down one night, and I
               thirsted for water to drink. And there was with me a certain widow who lived a chaste
               life, both when she was with her husband, and afterwards, and she said unto me,
               <quote>Wait, master, wait,</quote> and she made the sign of the holy Cross over the vessel of
               water, and straightway there fell from it the Calumniator in the form of a flash of
               fire, and both she and I saw him. And we wondered at the might of the Redeemer, and
               at the marvellous symbol of His merit.</quote></p>
            <p>These things were indeed told to us by the blessed mouth which is remote from
               falsehood; therefore it is required of us necessarily to do this [i.e., make the sign
               of the Cross] for the protection of our life. Now the Enemy used to wage war openly
               against that widow who did these things, even as I have learned from the chosen ones
               of our Lord, and one of the holymen who heard [this] from her own mouth spake
               thus:—The blessed woman said as follows:—One day I went to the house of God, and
               Satan drew nigh, and said unto me, <quote>Why dost thou pray like a man, and say, Glory be
               to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghost?</quote> And I said unto him, <quote>How then
               shall I pray?</quote> Then Satan said unto me, <quote>Thou shouldst pray in this wise, and say,
               Glory be to thee, Mary, mother of Christ.</quote> Then I answered and said unto him, <quote>There
               is dust in thine eyes, Satan. Why should I forsake the Lord and worship a
               handmaiden?</quote> And he disappeared from me.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="576">
            <p>And the blessed man said unto me also:—The same old woman said in my presence:—And
               again I went to the church according to [my] custom, and I entered in and prayed, and
               then the Enemy came and made blind my eyes, and I could not see, and I called one of
               the women, and she carried me to my house. And after three days he departed from
               before my eyes, and he began to go in front of me; then I said unto him, <quote>There is a
               thing which thou must do for me. Go thou to where thou didst first seize upon me.</quote>
               And we went to the church, I and he. And I left him where he had seized me, and went
               away a short distance, and turning round I looked for him, and I saw him standing
               like a shadow; then I went a little further, and I turned round again, and I [still]
               saw him. And I shut the door of the church and went out, and then I opened it again
               and went in, and I saw him still standing there, and he ceased to practise his wiles
               upon me. Such were the great things which happened to the blessed old woman. For the
               monk must not boast himself over the man who is in the world, for in it are mighty
               men; and if such things as these are to be found in Eve, how much more ought they to
               be found in the Adam which hath been redeemed by [the second] Adam?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="577">
            <p>One of the fathers said, <quote>Whilst I was sleeping one night, the Enemy came and smote
               me, and said unto me, <quote>Go to the world and work righteousness; why dost thou shut
               thyself up like a beast in a cave?</quote> And knowing the wickedness of the Enemy, who
               regarded me with an evil eye, I made the sign of the Cross, and he fled from me.
               Then, having waited a few days, he came and smote me on the neck in a bantering
               fashion, saying, <quote>Now that thou hast become a righteous man, go to the world that I
               may not destroy thee</quote>; and when I prayed and made the sign of the Cross over my face
               he departed from me. And after a short time he came again, and he took up a seat upon
               my neck, and then I bade my soul to be of good cheer, and stood up, and made the sign
               of the Cross, the symbol of merit, before him, and he disappeared again, for he was
               not able to stand before me.</quote> Now these things took place and happened in this wise
               in very truth, and we may therefore know and understand the conduct wherein God
               rejoiceth, and there is, even as this [story sheweth], no reason for fearing the
               devils and all the evil spirits. Whosoever holdeth in contempt humility, and
               penitence of the mind, and the subjugation of the body, and remoteness from the care
               for the things which are seen, falleth into the inclination of the world, and
               despiseth the good riches of the fear of God, and his hope for the inheritance of
               holy men is cut off, and for the delights of heaven which neither pass away nor are
               dissolved. May we, through the grace and mercy of Christ, be held to be worthy of
               these things! Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
