<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Appendix</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_2/Appendix">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_2/Appendix </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Appendix</head>
         <p>Questions of the Brethren, and Answers of the Fathers, which are exceedingly fair and
            beautiful</p>
         <div type="saying" n="604">
            <p>The brethren said:—There were two brethren who were the sons of a merchant, and their
               father died, and they divided their inheritance between themselves, and unto each one
               there came five thousand dînârs. And one of the brethren divided his inheritance
               among the churches, and the monasteries, and the poor, and he himself became a monk,
               and he chose for himself a life of continual silence, and fasting, and prayer; now
               the other brother built a monastery for himself, and gathered brethren to him, and he
               took care of the strangers, and the poor, and the sick, whom he received and
               relieved. When the two brothers were dead there was questioning among the brethren
               about them, and they went to Abbâ Pambô and asked him, <quote>Which manner of life
                  and conduct was the more excellent and exalted?</quote> And having learned from
               God, he said unto them, <quote>They are both perfect, and in my sight they appear to
                  be of equal merit.</quote> Explain to us now the old man’s words, for how can the
               man who is destitute, and the man who hath possessions be equal [in merit]? The old
               man said, <quote>Since the whole conduct of these brethren was to God, and since
                  whatsoever they did they did it for God, with an upright aim, and since the aim of
                  each was the same, they appeared to be in the old man’s opinion of equal merit
                  before God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="605">
            <p>The brethren asked Abbâ Nastîr, <quote>What rule of life and conduct should a man
                  follow?</quote></p>
            <p>The old man said, <quote>All rules of conduct are not alike. Abraham was a lover of
                  strangers, David was a humble man, Elijah loved silence, and God accepted the work
                  of all of them. Whatsoever work is of God, if thy soul desireth it, that do, and
                  God be with thee.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="606">
            <p>The brethren said:—Abbâ Pamô said, <quote>If there be three monks in one place, and
                  one of them live in silence [it is] well, and if another be sick and he give
                  thanks in his weakness, and if another minister to men and relieve them, all three
                  of them are in the same service.</quote> Reveal to us now the mind of this holy
               man.</p>
            <p>And Abbâ Pambô said, <quote>If a man dwell in silence for God’s sake, and not for the
                  sake of vainglory, or any other human thing; and if another, who is sick, give
                  thanks to God for his sickness, and he endure him that ministereth unto him with
                  longsuffering, he becometh like unto him that is in silence; and if he who
                  ministereth unto men doeth it not for a reward of this world, but for God’s sake,
                  and if he constraineth himself in everything, and doeth the will of those who are
                  ministered unto by him in love and gladness, he thus becometh like unto him who
                  shutteth himself up in silence, and like unto him that is sick, and in this way
                  the work of all three is of equal merit. For Abbâ Joseph and Abbâ Poemen divided
                  the perfect ascetic life into three classes, and therefore Abbâ Nastîr said to
                  that brother, <quote>If thou conduct thyself according to any one of the three thou
                  shalt be perfect.</quote> And this is well known from that which Abbâ Anthony said, <quote>Many
                  have afflicted themselves with labours and tribulations, and because they had not
                  in them the power of discernment, they did not know the way of truth.</quote> And again
                  he said, <quote>One man might live in a cell for a hundred years, and yet not know how
                  to dwell therein [rightly] for one day, because he humbleth not himself, and
                  accounteth not himself a sinner, and a feeble man, and ignorant, but he justifieth
                  himself, and blameth others; nevertheless it is right that we should know that,
                  even though some are sick, and others relieve the wants of men and minister unto
                  them with an upright aim, those who lead a life of silence lead a superior life,
                  and follow a line of conduct which is more excellent than all the rules of life
                  which are followed among brethren. And this life is superior in the same way that
                  the Spirit of God is more exalted than the holy angels, according to what we have
                  learned from the history of the holy men Abbâ Arsenius and Abbâ Moses the
                  Ethiopian. For when one of the brethren went to the blessed Arsenius [to enquire
                  of him] concerning the love of a silent life of contemplation, he neither set a
                  table for him nor gave him refreshment; then he went to the blessed Abbâ Moses and
                  he both welcomed him and gave him refreshment. And when one of the great fathers
                  heard [this], he entreated our Lord to reveal to him this matter, saying, <quote>How is
                  it that one fleeth for Thy Name</quote>s sake, and another welcometh and giveth
                  refreshment for Thy Name’s sake?</quote> And there appeared unto him on the river
               two ships, in one of which were Abbâ Arsenius, and the Spirit of God Who was
               travelling along in silence, and in the other was Abbâ Moses, who was travelling with
               holy angels that were feeding him upon honey, with the comb thereof. And by this the
               fathers understood that the life of silent contemplation was as greatly exalted above
               alms and ministrations as was the conduct of Matthew the Evangelist above that of
               Zacchaeus the tax-gatherer.’</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="607">
            <p>The brethren said: The brethren asked Abbâ Pambô, saying, <quote>Supposing that a man
                  who liveth in the world hath a wife and children, and supposing that he giveth
                  much alms, and setteth free slaves, and redeemeth those in captivity, and visiteth
                  the sick, and relieveth those who are afflicted, and fulfilleth all the things
                  which are proper for him [to fulfil], is not such a man equal in labour to one of
                  the three classes of monks, that is, to the man that dwelleth in silence, or him
                  that is sick, or him that ministereth unto the poor?</quote></p>
            <p>And the old man said, <quote>Not altogether.</quote></p>
            <p>And the brethren said, <quote>Wherefore?</quote></p>
            <p>And the old man said, <quote>Because, although the man who is in the world leadeth a
                  life of righteousness, his whole conduct is outside the body, but all the labour
                  of the monks is inside the body, that is, fasting, and prayer, and vigil, and
                  hunger, and thirst, and the constraint of the will at every moment, and wars, both
                  secret and manifest. And it is well known and manifest that the men, who are in
                  the world and who are exceedingly excellent in their conduct, are not equal to the
                  monks in their labours; for our Lord Jesus Christ surnamed the monks <quote>sons of
                  light,</quote> and those who are in the world <quote>sons of the world.</quote> Now the monks with
                  their members, and with their thoughts, and with their bodies, and with their
                  conduct serve God perfectly with stern labours and afflictions, and they offer
                  themselves up to God as a living, and rational, and holy sacrifice, with rational
                  and spiritual service, and they are crucified unto the world, and the world is
                  crucified unto them, according to the word of our Lord, Who said, <quote>Whosoever
                  wisheth to come after Me, let him take up his cross, and follow Me,</quote> that is to
                  say, Let him not fulfil his own will, but let him do My will only, and bear
                  tribulations of all kinds. And monks shall leave father, and mother, and brothers,
                  and sisters, and kinsfolk, and country, and in return for these they shall receive
                  a hundredfold, and shall inherit everlasting life. And to the men who are in the
                  world, He said, <quote>Acquire for yourselves friends of the mammon of unrighteousness,
                  so that when it hath come to an end they may receive you into their everlasting
                  habitations.</quote> For as men who are in the world receive monks into their houses, so
                  shall the monks receive those who have lived in the world into the kingdom of
                  heaven; and by this our Lord shewed that all the good things of God and His
                  kingdom belong to the monks who, from their youth even to their old age, have
                  laboured to God in the excellent works of the ascetic and monastic life. But it is
                  right that we should know to what degree the soul is superior to the body. The
                  life which is led by the monks in silent contemplation, and the works thereof, are
                  as much superior to the life which is led by righteous men in the world, as the
                  life and conduct of the angels are superior to those of men. And the life and
                  conduct of the monks are superior to those of men who are in the world, because
                  the latter please God because of their love for men, whilst the monks do so
                  because of their love for God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="608">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Into how many orders have the fathers arranged the monastic
                  life?</quote> And the old man said, <quote>Into three orders.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="609">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What are they?</quote> And the old man said, <quote>The
                  perfect, those who are half perfect, and the beginners.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="610">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Whence canst thou prove to us that this is so?</quote> The
               old man said: <quote>From the words of our Lord in the Gospel. For he said, <quote>The
                  sower went forth to sow. And some [seeds] fell on the roadside, and others fell on
                  the rock, and others among thorns</quote> (St. Matthew 13:3 ff.) Now these three [kinds
                  of] seed are those who are in the world. And as concerning the other seed of which
                  He spake, saying that it fell on good ground, and gave fruit, some thirtyfold, and
                  some sixtyfold, and some a hundredfold, these are the grades of monks, for the
                  seed which yielded fruit thirtyfold is the beginners, and that which yielded
                  sixtyfold is the half-perfect, and that which yielded one hundredfold is the
                  perfect.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="611">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>And supposing a man in the world conducteth himself in a
                  wholly perfect manner, and according to what is right, is not his labour equal
                  unto that of a beginner?</quote> The old man said, <quote>No.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="612">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why [not]?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Although the
                  monk is little and is a beginner, he is still more excellent than the man in the
                  world who keepeth every just [demand] of righteousness.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="613">
            <p><quote>Why did Abbâ Anthony say unto Paule, his disciple, <quote>Go and dwell in silence
                  that thou mayest receive the temptations of devils?</quote></quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>Because the perfection of the monk ariseth from spiritual conduct, and
                  spiritual conduct is acquired by the conduct of the heart, and purity of heart
                  ariseth from the conduct of the mind, and the conduct of the mind from prayer
                  which is unceasing, and from strife with devils; but unceasing prayer, and the
                  contendings with devils, both in the thoughts and in visions, have no opportunity
                  for existence without silence and solitariness.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="614">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is the meaning of that which Paphnutius and James the
                  Lame said to Mâr Evagrius, <quote>Every lapse which taketh place through the tongue, or
                  through lust, or through an action, or through the whole body, is in proportion to
                  the measure of pride which a man possesseth</quote>? Now what is the lapse which cometh
                  through lust? And what is the lapse which cometh through an action? And what is
                  the lapse which cometh through the whole body? Enlighten us about these [various]
                  kinds of lapses.</quote> The old man said, <quote>The lapse through lust is the
                  fall which taketh place inwardly through pride, even as the blessed Macarius said,
                  <quote>Thou shalt not be lifted up in thy heart and in thy mind through the knowledge of
                  the Scriptures, lest thou fall into a spirit of blasphemy in thy mind.</quote> And the
                  lapse through the tongue resembleth that into which one of the monks once fell
                  through his pride, and he reviled the holy man Evagrius and the fathers who were
                  in the desert of Scete. And the lapse through an action resembleth that into which
                  another monk fell when he became lascivious and abominable; and the lapse through
                  the whole body resembleth that when, through his pride, one of the brethren was
                  abandoned to the hands of thieves, and they burned him with fire.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="615">
            <p>The brethren said:—Palladius said, <quote>Once the blessed man Diocles said, <quote>The
                  mind which falleth from God is either delivered over to the devil of wrath, or to
                  the devil of fornication.</quote> And I said unto him, <quote>How is it possible for the human
                  mind to be with God uninterruptedly?</quote> And he said, <quote>In whatsoever work of the fear
                  of God the soul [is engaged], provided that the soul hath due care, its mind is
                  with God.</quote> What is the meaning of the action of which the old man
               spake?</quote></p>
            <p>The old man said, <quote>He calleth [a man’s] care concerning God’s promises <quote>action
                  of the fear of God,</quote> wishing to say thus:—If thou art unable to bind thy thought
                  continually in various ways to God, though thou thinkest about His Majesty, and
                  His power, and His grace, and thou prayest to Him without ceasing and without
                  wandering [in thy prayer, thy mind cannot be with Him]; but if thou reducest thine
                  understanding by means of the constant labour of prayer and by the thought which
                  is on God, and more particularly through the war with devils that [accompanieth]
                  this work, bring down thy mind by degrees from the thought which is about God, and
                  from prayer, and fetter it with the thought which is lower than this, and meditate
                  on the promises of God, and think upon His commandments and the correction of
                  thyself. And set not free thy mind from spiritual care, and do not make it wander
                  and think the thought of passibility, but fetter thy mind to some thought of
                  excellence, which will make it gain profit. And when it hath rested somewhat, then
                  raise it up on high, and make it to labour in the thought which is of God, and in
                  pure prayer which hath no wandering therein. For as the growth of the capacity of
                  those who are as yet in the grade of bodily prayer and the reading [of the
                  Scriptures] still existeth, even when they are exhausted by standing up, and by
                  the singing of the Psalms, and they rest their bodies for a little by sitting down
                  and by meditation upon the reading, and when they have rested their bodies and
                  their mind hath become enlightened through the reading, they stand up for service
                  and prayer, so also it is right for those who have arrived at a correct conduct of
                  the mind, and who think continually about God, and who pray to Him without
                  wandering, when they are exhausted by this severe labour, to bring down their
                  minds from time to time, and to relieve it by means of thought concerning some
                  profitable subject which is less exalted than the thought about God. And this
                  thought must take the place to them of reading, and they must meditate upon God’s
                  promises and commandments, and upon their straightness which is in God; and if
                  some abominable thought knock [at the door of their minds] they must quickly make
                  their minds to enter into prayer and into the thought which is upon God. And if
                  there stir in their heart a thought of passion, as soon as they have refreshed
                  themselves by means of thinking about some profitable subject, they must make
                  their mind to enter into the height of prayer, and they must pray without ceasing,
                  and meditate upon God. And from this we know that when the soul meditateth with
                  understanding upon some profitable subject, or upon some profitable action, its
                  mind is with God, even as the blessed man Diocles said. Similarly, whensoever a
                  monk thinketh about the passions of sin, or about deeds connected with the world,
                  his mind is with Satan.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="616">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why is it that the Divine Light did not shine in the hearts
                  of all the monks until a long time after they had been cleansed by labours and
                  contests? And why is it that the light of grace did shine upon some men before
                  they went forth from the world and came to the ascetic life, as it did in the
                  heart of Abraham Kindônâyâ through the Divine revelation on the day of his feast,
                  and straightway he left his feast, and went forth from the world?</quote> The old
               man said, <quote>Whensoever this light riseth in its order in the hearts of men,
                  according to what the fathers say, it cometh in this wise. First of all Divine
                  Grace maketh a man hot with the love of God, and he hateth all the glories and
                  honours of this world; and next he cometh in a state of poverty to this rule of
                  life, and Divine Grace itself first giveth him the love of labours, and it maketh
                  the things which are hard easy to him. And it protecteth him from the fierce
                  attacks of the war of devils, so that they may not, whensoever they wish and will,
                  assault him, but only according to his strength, and his capacity, and as is
                  convenient for his growth. And thus after many labours and contests, his heart is
                  purified with abundant humility, and he shineth with the light of grace, and he is
                  held to be worthy to see Christ in a revelation of light. And the fathers also
                  said, that in proportion as the monk himself travelleth along the path of ascetic
                  excellences to meet our Lord by means of labours and contests, so doth our Lord
                  advance to meet him with light until they meet each other, and then the monk
                  remaineth in our Lord by means of labours, and our Lord remaineth in him by means
                  of his light, even as Abbâ Isaiah said in his interpretation of that which our
                  Lord said, <quote>Remain in Me and I in you.</quote> Thus thou seest, O my brother, that He
                  wisheth us to remain in him first of all by the labours of righteousness, and then
                  He will remain Himself in us in purity and in light. And the words, <quote>The monk
                  travelleth along the path of ascetic excellences until he seeth Him and is
                  illumined by Him,</quote> explain the verse, <quote>My soul thirsteth for Thee, the Living
                  God,</quote></quote> et cetera.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="617">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why is it that though the holy fathers incite us
                  continually to the labours of excellence, and to the contending against passions
                  and devils, Abbâ Isidore restrained Abbâ Moses the Ethiopian from works, and from
                  contests with devils, saying, <quote>Rest thee, Moses, and quarrel not with the devils,
                  and seek not to make attacks upon them, for there is a measure [i.e., moderation]
                  in everything</quote>; doth this apply also to works and to the labours of the ascetic
                  life?</quote></p>
            <p>The old man said, <quote>Because at the beginning Abbâ Moses was ignorant of the rule
                  of the ascetic life, and because he was healthy of body, he worked overmuch, and
                  he thought that he would be able to prevail mightily against devils by the
                  multitude of his works alone, and that he would be able to vanquish them.
                  Therefore, because the devils perceived his object, they attacked him more
                  severely with frequent wars, both secretly and openly, but Abbâ Isidore, wishing
                  to teach him the truth, and to make him to acquire humility, said unto him,
                  <quote>Without the power of the Spirit which our Lord gave us in baptism for the
                  fulfilling of His commandments, the which is confirmed in us each day by the
                  taking of His Body and Blood, we cannot be purified from the passions, and we
                  cannot vanquish devils, and we cannot perform the works of spiritual excellence</quote>;
                  thereupon Abbâ Moses learned these things, and his thoughts were humbled, and he
                  partook of the Holy Mysteries, and the devils were conquered, and they reduced
                  their war against him, and from that time forward he lived in rest, and knowledge,
                  and peace. Many monks have imagined that their passions would be healed, and that
                  they would acquire soundness of soul merely by their labours and strenuousness,
                  and therefore they were abandoned by grace, and fell from the truth. For as he who
                  is sick in his body cannot be healed without the physician and medicines, however
                  much he may watch and fast during the time he is taking the medicine, so he who is
                  sick in his soul through the passions of sin, without Christ, the Physician of
                  souls, and without the partaking of His Body and Blood, and the power which is
                  hidden in His commandments, and the humility which is like unto His, cannot be
                  healed of his passions, and cannot receive a perfect cure. Therefore, whosoever
                  fighteth against the passions and the devils by the commandments of our Lord is
                  healed of the sickness of the passions, and acquireth health of soul, and is
                  delivered from the crafts of the devils.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="618">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>With what object did those two monks say to Abbâ Macarius,
                  <quote>If thou art not able to become a monk like us, sit in thy cell, and weep for thy
                  sins, and thus thou shalt be like us?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Because
                  they knew that, if a man was able to be a solitary in his body, and a dweller in
                  silent contemplation, and a worker both in his soul and in his body, who made
                  himself humble and who wept each day for his sins, and who cut off from himself
                  all memories of every kind of passion and anxious thought, and who meditated only
                  upon God and upon his own correct behaviour, such a man was a monk (or solitary)
                  in very truth, even as the blessed Evagrius said, ‘The monk who is remote from the
                  world is he who hath cut off from himself all the motions of his passions, and
                  hath fastened unto God all the mind of his soul.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="619">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why is it that certain ot the Fathers were called
                  Mĕshannayânê [i.e., men who transferred themselves from one place to another],
                  since they were recluses, and never departed from their cells?</quote> The old man
               said, <quote>Because after much silent contemplation, and unceasing prayer, and
                  watching of the mind, they were worthy to depart from the earth in their minds,
                  and to ascend unto heaven to Christ the King. And they did not do this on
                  occasions only, but continually, for whensoever they wished, or whensoever they
                  sang the Psalms, or prayed, or meditated upon God, straightway their mind was
                  exalted to heaven, and stood before our Lord. But there were other [kinds of]
                  <quote>Mĕshannayânê,</quote> that is to say, those who lived with wild beasts in the deserts,
                  such as Abbâ Bessarion, and others who were like unto him.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="620">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is [the meaning] of the fact that when one of the
                  monks saw a brother in the mountain he fled from him, and was unable to bear the
                  smell of the children of men?</quote> The old man said, <quote>The monk fled
                  because he saw that the brother was carrying silver. And when the brother saw that
                  the monk fled, he cast off his garments and pursued him. And when the monk saw
                  that he had cast off his garments, he waited for him, and welcomed him gladly,
                  saying, <quote>Since thou hast cast off the matter which is of this world I have waited
                  for thee. I was not able to bear [the sight thereof] because I myself am naked.</quote> I
                  looked beyond my rule of life and saw that he was carrying a burden upon his
                  shoulder like a man who was in the world.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="621">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why did the monk not permit that brother who came to him to
                  dwell in the cave by his side, but did say unto him, <quote>Thou art not able to bear up
                  against the attack of devils?</quote></quote> The old man said, <quote>Because he knew
                  his manner of life and works, and also that he possessed not the labours and the
                  strenuousness which were sufficient to make him strong to resist the fierce
                  assault of the savage nature of the devils which make war against the monks. For
                  according to the labour of every man, and according to his striving, and his rule
                  of life and strenuousness, and according as he is able to bear, so much the
                  greater are the ferocity, and the wickedness, and the bitterness, and the
                  craftiness of the devils who make war against him. Similarly, when one of the
                  brethren entreated Abbâ Apellen to allow him to live with him in the desert, he
                  said unto him, <quote>Thou art not able to bear the temptation of the devils.</quote> Finally,
                  when the brother urged him [to let him do so], he commanded him to dwell in a cave
                  by his side. And the devils came against him in the night and sought to strangle
                  him, until Abbâ Apellen came, and surrounded the cave with the sign of the Cross,
                  after which the brother was able to live in the cave. For not all monks are able
                  to fight against the devils, but only such as are perfect and humble.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="622">
            <p>Why is it that the two Romans who went to Abbâ Macarius, did not, during the whole
               period of three years which they lived [near him] come to him and ask him, or any
               other aged man, questions about the thoughts? The old man said, <quote>Because the
                  elder brother was exceedingly wise, and perfect and humble. Had he gone to Abbâ
                  Macarius, or to one of the other old men, his perfection would have been revealed,
                  and he would have [received] praise throughout Scete from the Fathers, who would
                  have wondered, saying, <quote>How is it that a young man hath become perfect in three
                  years</quote>? It is, however, not right for us to make ourselves like unto these two
                  brethren, and to neglect the doctrine of the old men. As for the two brethren, the
                  elder was perfect, and the younger was humble, and learned from him.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="623">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>The history of the triumphs of Bessarion saith that during
                  all the days of his life he dwelt in waste places, and in the desert and in the
                  mountains, and among the rocks.</quote> Once having come to a certain monastery,
               he stood up by the door like a wandering beggar, and then sat down weeping and crying
               out, even as one who had been rescued from a storm. And when the brethren entreated
               him to go in and rest with them, he said, <quote>Before I find the possessions of my house
               which I have lost I cannot endure being under a roof; for thieves fell upon me on the
               sea, and a storm reared itself up against me, and I have been robbed of the riches
               which I once possessed, and from being a man of high estate I am become of no
               account.</quote> Now what were the riches which [he inherited] from his parents and lost?
               And what does this [story] mean? Who are parents? What does he refer to by the words
               <quote>sea, and storms, and waves</quote>? Who were the thieves? Are these words spoken of himself
               or of the other persons? The old man said, <quote>These things are said of all the
                  monks who are still striving and contending against passions and devils, and who
                  are lacking at the present time purity of heart, and fruits of the spirit, and
                  visions of our Lord, and they are not spoken of men who are perfect as he was. The
                  word <quote>sea</quote> he applieth to the sea of the mind whereon the monk saileth with works
                  of spiritual excellence, wherefrom he entereth the haven of impassibility, even as
                  the blessed Macarius saith, <quote>He who wisheth to cleave the sea of the mind, maketh
                  himself longsuffering.</quote> And he calleth temptations <quote>storms,</quote> and the passions
                  <quote>waves,</quote> and the <quote>thieves</quote> are devils, and his <quote>parents</quote> are the Father, and the
                  Son, and the Holy Ghost, One God, in Whose image and likeness we are made, even as
                  our Creator said, <quote>Come, let us make man in our image and likeness,</quote> and also as
                  our Lord said, <quote>Be ye like unto your Father, Who is in heaven.</quote> And He calleth the
                  spiritual excellences, which contain likenesses of the similitude of our Father,
                  Who is in heaven, and which make us heirs of God, and sons of the inheritance of
                  Jesus Christ, by the name of <quote>riches and possessions of his parents,</quote> and these
                  are faith, and hope, and the love of God and man, and joy, and rest, and peace,
                  and graciousness, and pleasantness, and lowliness, and humility, and
                  longsuffering, and patient endurance, and integrity, and simplicity, and purity,
                  and mercy, and cleanness of heart, and the holy light of the mind, and pure
                  prayer, and the divine light which riseth on the heart at the hour of prayer, and
                  spiritual prayer, and Divine knowledge, and the visions and revelations of our
                  Lord. These are the possessions of the soul, some of which it acquireth naturally,
                  and some by Divine Grace; now those which it acquireth naturally are they which
                  the Creator sowed in its nature at the beginning of its creation, and those which
                  it acquireth by Divine Grace are they which are bestowed upon it by the baptism in
                  Christ. And these possessions are lost to a man through pleasures, and honours,
                  and lusts, and benefits, but they are found and acquired, and the soul waxeth rich
                  in them, through tribulations, and revilings, and oppression, and hardships. Now
                  although Abbâ Bessarion, and men who were as perfect as he was, possessed these
                  things, other men lack them and are strangers unto them. [And as regards the
                  words] <quote>He once came to a certain monastery, and sat down outside the door like a
                  wandering beggar,</quote> [they mean that] he saw clearly with the secret eye of the mind
                  that the greater number of the monks were destitute of this spiritual possession,
                  and of the spiritual excellences and gifts which have been already mentioned. And
                  being incited there, to by the law of affection and of brotherly love, he cried
                  out and wept on their behalf, as if it had been on his own, and he made
                  supplication to the loving-kindness of God that He would make them worthy of the
                  riches of His love, and of the possession of His Grace.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="624">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What are the nine spiritual excellences which that holy man
                  possessed, and what did he lack?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Although they
                  are not written down I think that they were as follows: 1. Voluntary poverty. 2.
                  Abstinence, 3. Constant evening fasting. 4. Vigil. 5. The recital of the whole
                  Book of the Psalms seven times during the night and day. 6. The reading of the
                  Holy Books between times. 7. Lowliness. 8. Humility. 9. Love of man. These are the
                  nine spiritual excellences which he possessed, and by means of them he vanquished
                  all passions. By poverty he overcame the love of money. By abstinence he conquered
                  unbridled appetite and gluttony. By fasting he overcame the passion of the love of
                  the belly. By vigil he vanquished sleep. By the recital of the Psalms he did away
                  idleness. By reading he kept away the converse of evil. By lowliness he dispelled
                  wrath and anger. By humility he overcame vainglory and pride. By love of man he
                  conquered hatred, and spite, and enmity. Now the spiritual excellence which he
                  lacked, and which is the tenth, was the constant fervour of the love of God, which
                  is in our Lord Jesus Christ, and this can [only] be gathered together, and
                  stablished and acquired by the secret prayer of the mind, which is unceasing and
                  wandereth not, and by the strict and constant suppression of the thoughts of the
                  passions, and the incitements of devils, when they first begin to bestir
                  themselves in the heart. And because among all the works of ascetic excellence
                  there is none more difficult [to do] than this, for, even as the blessed Macarius
                  said, <quote>All the fightings and fierce, and crafty, and evil temptations of the
                  devils are set in array against it,</quote> the holy man is not able easily to become
                  perfect in the love of Christ, which is acquired by the concentration of the mind
                  and by deep thought about God. Therefore the blessed Evagrius said, <quote>If thou canst
                  overcome the wandering of the thoughts, it is the end of all ends; and if thou
                  canst make deep thought about God have dominion in thee, thou canst overcome all
                  passions, and thou shalt be worthy of the perfection of the love of Christ.</quote> By
                  the love of man and by the other virtues a monk may, by the help of God, vanquish
                  all the passions; but by the love of Christ he shall conquer the evil passion of
                  the love of the soul, which is the first of all the passions, and which embraceth
                  them all, even as Saint Evagrius said, <quote>The first of all the passions is the
                  thought of the love of the soul, and after it come the following eight.</quote> And again
                  he said, <quote>Conquer the strife of the love of the soul which is in thy bosom, by
                  that which is towards God.</quote> For until the monk is worthy of this love, he is
                  unable to acquire exact consolation from the remainder of the labours of the other
                  spiritual excellences, even though it be that he obtaineth assistance from them,
                  as Abbâ Isaiah said, <quote>Although the children of Leah were a help to Jacob, yet he
                  loved Joseph most of all, and when Joseph was born, he wished to leave Laban and
                  go to his parents,</quote> that is to say, When a monk hath become worthy, and hath
                  acquired the perfect love of Christ, which is stablished by silent contemplation,
                  and the power to pray without ceasing, and his soul is at all times rejoicing and
                  exulting with gladness, he will not be content to remain in this life; but each
                  and every day he will be desiring eagerly and longing to depart from the body, and
                  to be with our Lord in Paradise, which is the habitation of the spirits of just
                  men who have become perfect, and the holy country which is exalted above the
                  passions, and devils, and the striving of those who cultivate the virtues until
                  the revelation of our Lord Jesus, Who loveth to make perfect a man with the
                  never-ending happiness of His love in a glorious kingdom.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="625">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Explain to us the course of life and labour of the old man
                  [who made] baskets, [and dropped] small stones in them.</quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>The course of life of that old man was one which was of the mind, and it
                  was stern, and excellent, and it swiftly brought the monk unto purity of heart.
                  And as concerning that which he said, <quote>I set two baskets, one on my right hand and
                  one on my left,</quote> etc. it doth not [mean] that he sat the whole day with his
                  baskets round him, but that his two baskets were set in two places. And he himself
                  was occupied with service and prayer, and with his toil, and for every thought,
                  good or bad, which entered his mind he cast a pebble [into the baskets], that is
                  to say, the labour is very severe for the man for a certain time at the beginning,
                  because the devils are envious at the purity of heart which is acquired by him,
                  and therefore they afflicted this old man also for a long time with the multitude
                  of evil thoughts which were stirring in him, even as he said, <quote>Many days I have
                  eaten nothing, because the good thoughts did not outnumber the bad ones.</quote> Now he
                  used to afflict his body with the labour of much fasting, so that he might do away
                  the evil thoughts, because it is not the soul only which feeleth the labours of
                  the body, its counterpart through its union with it, but also those devils which
                  wage war against the soul, and they feel the labours of the body more than doth
                  the soul. For immediately the devils see the monk afflicting his body with
                  labours, they become afraid, and stagger about, because they are more tormented by
                  the labours than is the man who is engaged in them. Therefore the blessed
                  Evagrius, when the demon of fornication assailed him, stripped off his tunic and
                  stood the whole night long, in the season of winter, under the open sky, and by
                  these means he made the demon to suffer pain, and he fled from him. And again,
                  when the demon of blasphemy attacked him, he stood naked under the open sky, in
                  the season of winter, for forty days. And because the thought of gluttony stirred
                  in the heart of Abbâ Zeno, and made him to eat a cucumber by stealth, he crucified
                  his soul in the sun, during the season of summer for five days. In this wise the
                  holy men were afflicting themselves with labours and tribulations, and when the
                  devils were stirring up in them the thoughts of sin, the demons were afflicted and
                  tortured far more than they thereby. Now the demons were afflicted and tormented
                  by the labours of the patient endurance of the monks not only in their minds but
                  in their persons, through the operation of the holy angels, and by the command of
                  God, even as, on one occasion, one of the devils was tortured the whole night in
                  the cell of those two brethren who were brothers naturally, when he wished to
                  separate them from each other. For when the younger brother lighted a lamp the
                  devil threw down the candlestick, and extinguished the light, whereupon the
                  [elder] brother smote him [on] the cheek; and the other brother expressed his
                  contrition, and said, <quote>My brother, have patience, and I will light the lamp
                  [again].</quote> And when God saw the patient endurance and humility of the young man, He
                  commanded His angel, and he fettered the devil the whole night long in their cell;
                  and the devil was tormented therein until the morning because of that [blow on]
                  the cheek which he made the one brother to suffer from the other through his
                  wicked agency; and that wicked devil was fettered and tortured the whole night
                  long. And the devils are tortured not only when we afflict our bodies with
                  labours, in order that we may not consent to the will of devils, but also when
                  they stir up in us evil thoughts; if we constrain ourselves a little, and cast
                  them from us, at the same time calling our Lord to our assistance, straightway the
                  holy angels which cleave unto us will constrain the demons, and will drive them
                  away from us, and we shall be full of light, and of fervour, and of gladness. Even
                  as one of the demons said to Abbâ Pachomius, A certain monk, against whom I wage
                  war, is very strenuous, and whensoever I draw nigh unto him to sow evil thoughts
                  in him, he betaketh himself to prayer, and I, though burning with fire, have to
                  depart from his presence blazing (?) even like iron which hath been thoroughly
                  well [heated] in the fire.’ Now monks are, at the beginning [of their career]
                  afflicted for a long time, not only by the stirring up of the evil thoughts
                  themselves, but also by their tarrying in the heart; but after a known time a man
                  receiveth strength from our Lord, through their tarrying, and also after a known
                  time their motion is restrained, and then the monk also hath rest from strivings,
                  and he is held to be worthy of purity of heart. For at the beginning of the
                  strivings the devils stir up evil thoughts in the heart mightily; sometimes,
                  however, these are destroyed through prayer at the very beginning of their
                  movement, and sometimes they remain. And afterwards the mind becometh strong
                  against them, and doth not permit them to tarry altogether in the heart, but it is
                  as yet unable to restrain their violent movement, and the [tribulation which they
                  cause], even as one of the old men said, <quote>I carried on a strife for twenty years
                  in order that an evil thought might not enter my heart, and until the ninth hour I
                  used to see Satan with his bow drawn to shoot an arrow into my heart. And when he
                  found no opportunity of doing this, he would become dejected and go away ashamed
                  each day.</quote> Now the old man [of whom we first spake] held fast to his rule in
                  respect of the baskets, and though he was afflicted for a long time by the motion
                  of evil thoughts, and sometimes even by their tarrying in his heart, finally he
                  received power over their tarrying only, for their rising up remained for a
                  considerable time. And having laboured in striving for twenty years against the
                  motion of the thoughts, finally he became strong [enough to resist them], and he
                  overcame them. And the devils fled from him, and he arrived at a state of purity,
                  and at the haven of impassibility, and he was held to be worthy of
                  revelations.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="626">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>If the holy men themselves afflict themselves with labours
                  of tribulation because of the tarrying of the evil thoughts which bestir
                  themselves in them, and if they sin against God though not consenting to them, why
                  should we toil against the motion of the devils? For behold, even as the blessed
                  Evagrius said, <quote>Whether they fight against us or not the matter is not in our
                  hands.</quote></quote> The old man said, <quote>The perfection of the monks ariseth from
                  a spiritual rule of life, and a spiritual rule of life cometh from purity of
                  heart, and purity of heart from divine vision; <quote>Blessed are those who are pure in
                  heart, for they shall see God.</quote> When, therefore, a monk laboureth, and afflicteth
                  himself because of the motion of evil thoughts, in order to prevent their
                  remaining for a long time in his heart, and when after a considerable time his
                  heart becometh pure, there remaineth disgust only therein, and it vexeth the mind
                  of the monk, and preventeth his ascent to God, and cutteth off his journeying to
                  Him, and doth not allow him to enjoy the vision of glory. Now when a monk worketh
                  for a considerable time because of the motion of evil thoughts [in him], God hath
                  compassion upon his trouble, and not only doth his heart become cleansed, and his
                  soul pure from every thought of evil, but he is also held to be worthy of the
                  sight of our Lord in a revelation of light, and henceforth, the devils never again
                  dare to stir up evil thoughts in the heart of him that hath been esteemed worthy
                  of this great thing. And should it happen that they dare so to do, they suffer
                  pain and burn even as he suffereth who is hot, and who kicketh away with his feet
                  the piercing goads of iron which glow with heat in the fire. During the interval
                  between the beginning of the strife against evil thoughts and [the attainment of]
                  purity of heart, the devils sometimes vex the monk, and sometimes are vexed by
                  him, even as the blessed Evagrius said, <quote>If those who go down to the conflict
                  afflict [others], they are themselves afflicted</quote>; so the devils afflict us, and
                  they are also afflicted by us. They afflict us when we receive their evil
                  thoughts, and they are afflicted by us when we, by means of prayer and wrath, hide
                  (i.e., suppress) their thoughts. When, then, we labour and afflict ourselves for a
                  considerable time in order that their thoughts may not tarry in us, we also
                  afflict ourselves with labours and prayer so that they may not vex and hinder us
                  by [their] violent motion, and afterwards power is given unto us by our Lord to
                  lift ourselves up upon the necks of our enemies, and thenceforward our heart
                  resteth and is at peace, not only from the perception of their thoughts, but from
                  all the violence of their motion. And the peace and rest of God rule over our
                  souls, and we see that there remaineth only the war which is manifest of the
                  visions of devils until the time of death merely to terrify us, so that we may not
                  be exalted [unduly] and destroy ourselves. And should it happen that the devils
                  stir up thoughts in the heart of him that hath been made perfect, straightway they
                  become extinguished, even as fire is extinguished when water falleth
                  thereon.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="627">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why do the devils fear the labours of the monks, even as
                  the Fathers say, <quote>If thou wishest the devils to be afraid of thee, despise
                  lusts</quote>?</quote> The old man said, <quote>They are afraid because of three things,
                  1. First. Because our Lord treated with contempt three kinds of passions, wherein
                  are included and contained all the various classes of passions, and these are
                  they: The love of the belly, the love of money, and vainglory. By means of these
                  the Calumniator fought against our Redeemer, and through His constancy in the
                  wilderness, and silent contemplation, and fasting, and prayer, He overcame Satan;
                  therefore all the monks who travel in His footsteps, and who by means of fasting,
                  and prayer, and silent contemplation, hideaway all the thoughts of sin, and who
                  perform their labours in righteousness, our Lord maketh to conquer by His
                  strength, and He vanquisheth the devils who are their enemies. And as the demons
                  fear and tremble, not only by reason of the Crucifixion of Christ, but even at the
                  sign of the Cross, wheresoever it be made apparent, whether it be depicted upon a
                  garment, or whether it be made in the air, so also do the devils fear and tremble,
                  not only by reason of the labours of our Lord and His constancy in the wilderness,
                  but also at the existence of the monks in the wilderness, and at their silent
                  contemplation, and their fasting, and their prayers, and their patient persistence
                  in the performance of difficult labours, which take place for Christ’s sake.
                  Therefore on one occasion Abbâ Macarius said unto Palladius, <quote>Speak to the devils
                  which war against thee with disgust, and sluggishness, and despair: if I had no
                  labours of spiritual excellence, nevertheless for the sake of Christ I would guard
                  these walls and His Name would be sufficient for the redemption of my life</quote>. 2.
                  Secondly. The war and contest which the devils [wage] against the monks possess
                  both rule and system, and they are neither irregular nor unsystematic. And as when
                  the devils stir up the monks by means of evil thoughts of sin, and the monks
                  accept them, and consent to them, and let themselves be incited to commit sin
                  thereby, straightway their souls become dark, and remote from God, and sorely
                  afflicted, and ashamed, and guilty, and weak and miserable, so when their souls
                  accept not these thoughts, and they do not consent to them, and do not allow
                  themselves to be incited to sin thereby, but drive them away and cast them out as
                  soon as ever they begin to have motion [in them], and call upon our Lord to help
                  them, straightway all the former things which come against the monks, inasmuch as
                  they do not acquiesce in their incitings, are hurled upon the demons with greatly
                  intensified force, and they become ashamed, and tremble, and are destroyed, even
                  as the blessed Mark said, <quote>As he who breaketh into a house which is not his own
                  taketh to flight with fear and trembling as soon as he heareth the voice of the
                  master of the house, so also doth Satan,</quote> etc. 3. Thirdly. Because without labours
                  and humility we who are rational beings are unable to please God, and because
                  without them neither men nor angels can enjoy His love and His blessings,
                  therefore also the demons and devils, which live wholly in a state of pride and
                  laxity, [cannot enjoy them].</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="628">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why is it that although the Fathers gave the admonition,
                  <quote>Whensoever a demon appeareth unto a man in any form whatsoever, let that man make
                  the sign of the Cross, and pray, and that similitude will disappear,</quote> we see that
                  on several occasions the devils still remain, and not in appearance only, but also
                  in terrors, which remain for a long time, and in many cases in blows and
                  stripes?</quote> The old man said, <quote>The holy Fathers gave the admonition
                  because it would apply in the majority of cases. For since our Redeemer was
                  crucified for us, and since He exposed to disgrace the Rulers and Dominions, which
                  are evil demons, and put them to shame openly by His Person, even as it is
                  written, from that time onwards, whensoever they have made themselves visible to
                  the adorers of Christ in divers form [to do them] harm, as soon as a man hath made
                  mention of the Name of Christ, and hath signed himself with the sign of the Cross,
                  the devils have fled straightway, and their forms have disappeared. And this
                  happeneth not only in the case of holy men, and perfect men, but also in respect
                  of ordinary men who possess shortcomings.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="629">
            <p>The brothers said, <quote>Why was the blessed Martînyânâ, after all the great ascetic
                  practices which he had acquired, and the gifts of the spirit which he had
                  received, and after he had burned his fingers for the sake of the harlot, still
                  afraid of the war of fornication, and why, having gone and dwelt in the island in
                  the sea for thirty years, did he not stay [for] a season with that woman whom he
                  had brought up from the sea, but cast himself in the sea being afraid of the
                  contest?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Because the whole strength of the demon
                  of fornication was discharged upon him, and he was, therefore, properly afraid.
                  For those who have not with them this war in all its fierceness imagine that they
                  have overcome it, but let them not boast themselves, and let them know the truth,
                  that is to say, they have not vanquished the demon of fornication, and it is only
                  that he hath not waged war against them with all his strength, because he hath not
                  been permitted so to do, and he hath not been permitted to do so because of their
                  feebleness and laxity. For the war of fornication which cometh upon a man only
                  attacketh him in the degree which he is able to bear. For, behold, the great and
                  famous fathers who endured this war in all its severity for a long time were
                  always in a state of fear and trepidation, as was also Abbâ Arsenius, who was a
                  man eighty years old; and when the noble lady came to him and said, <quote>Remember me
                  in thy prayers,</quote> he did not hesitate to say, <quote>I will pray to God that He may blot
                  the remembrance of thee out of my heart.</quote> And by means of this which he spake, he
                  put to shame the demon of fornication, and shewed how great was the hatred for
                  this unclean passion that warreth against the holy men which he
               possessed.</quote></p>
            <p>[The story of Martînyânâ and the harlot is as follows:—There was a certain monk who
               dwelt in the desert, and whose name was Martînyânâ, and he laboured in great works,
               and God wrought by his hands many mighty deeds, and he was applauded by all men. Now
               when Satan, the Evil One, saw that he was greatly applauded he became bitterly angry,
               and he wished to distract and to withdraw him from his rule of life and ascetic
               labours. One day Satan saw that many folk were glorifying him, and he went and dwelt
               in a certain harlot, and he sent her to the blessed man in order to make him fall. So
               the harlot took her attire, and placed it in a bag, and went to the holy man, and
               when she arrived at his abode it was evening; and she knocked at the door and said,
                  <quote>O Saint Martînyânâ, open the door to me, so that the wild beasts may not
                  eat me.</quote> Now the holy man thought that she was a phantom, and he rose up
               and prayed, and since meanwhile she ceased not to cry out, he rose up from his
               prayer, and opened the door to her, and said to her, <quote>Whence comest thou to me,
                  O devil?</quote> And she said, <quote>[My] companions have forsaken me on the
                  road, and I wandered about in the desert, and have arrived hither</quote>; and he
               left her [there], and went into the inner cell, and shut the door thereof between
               himself and her. And after the old man had laid down to sleep the harlot arrayed
               herself in her attire, and put on her ornaments, and then sat down; and when the
               morning had come, the old man went forth from his cell, and seeing her dressed he
               said to her, <quote>Whence art thou? What is thy business?</quote> And she said,
                  <quote>I am a daughter of people of high degree, and my parents are dead, and they
                  have left me great wealth. I heard that thou wast a great man, and I have come to
                  thee, and I beg thee to come to my house and take me to wife, and we will live on
                  thy excellence.</quote> Then the old man said unto her, <quote>How can I forsake
                  my labour and my rule of life, and take thee to wife, and fall from my
                  covenant?</quote> And she said unto him, <quote>What sin is there in it? Did not
                  Adam and all the Fathers take wives, and Noah, and Abraham, from whose seed Christ
                  hath risen?</quote> Now by repeating these and suchlike things, she wellnigh
               succeeded in leading the holy man away captive, and he said unto her, <quote>O woman,
                  tarry a little so that I may see, lest peradventure some one may come and see
                  us.</quote> And having gone up to the roof to look, he woke up in his mind, and he
               made a flame of fire and stood up in it, and stayed in the fire until he burnt his
               toes; and when the harlot saw this, she fell down at his feet and wept, saying,
                  <quote>I have sinned against God and thee,</quote> and she revealed unto him the
               whole truth, [saying], <quote>I repent.</quote> And the holy man sent her to a
               nunnery, and he remained in his cell until his feet were healed of the burning of the
               fire. And after he was healed of his sickness, he rose up and went and dwelt in an
               island in the sea, where there were neither women nor men.]</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="630">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is the meaning of that which one of the old men said,
                  <quote>If thou seest the wings ot ravens flying about thou wilt also see the prayer of
                  him that is oppressed in mind being exalted?</quote></quote> The old man said, <quote>As
                  the ravens do not in the course of their flight mount upwards to the height of
                  heaven like the eagle, but fly close to the surface of the ground and wheel about
                  [seeking] for their unclean food, so is the mind of the man who is not fervent in
                  the love of God, and who is continually in a state ot sluggishness and dejection,
                  for when he standeth up for service or for prayer, his thought will not be exalted
                  to the height of the love of Christ, but his mind will wander after evil
                  passions.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="631">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>An old man said, <quote>If thou seest a young man who, in his
                  desire, ascendeth unto heaven, take hold of his foot and sweep him hence, for in
                  this way thou wilt help him</quote>; what is the meaning of the words, <quote>Who in his desire
                  ascendeth unto heaven?</quote></quote> The old man said, <quote>This resembleth that
                  which Isaiah spake, <quote>If the mind seeketh to ascend to the Cross before the
                  feelings cease from feebleness, the wrath of God shall come upon him because he
                  hath begun to do something which is beyond his capacity, without having first of
                  all cured his feelings.</quote> Now certain of the beginners in the ascetic life are so
                  silly and bold as to dare to undertake things which are far above their capacity
                  and their strength; they do not wish to learn, and they will not be persuaded by
                  the commands of their Fathers, but, without having lived the proper period of time
                  in the coenobium, they dare to enter the cell, even as it is written concerning
                  one of the brethren in the Book of Paradise, for immediately he had received the
                  garb of the monk, he went and shut himself up as a solitary recluse, saying, <quote>I am
                  a monk of the desert</quote>; and the Fathers went and brought him out into the monastery
                  [again]. There are others, too, who seek to shut themselves up for a week at a
                  time, and it in no wise helpeth them; and there are others, the children of this
                  world, who at the beginning of their careers imitate the exalted rule of life of
                  the Fathers, and who imagine that they can imitate the rule of the mind, that is
                  to say, of the spirit, when as yet they have not fulfilled the rule of the body.
                  Therefore their lives and works are not open to the Fathers, and they will not
                  receive correction, but they live according to their own desire, and they are
                  delivered over into the hands of the devils who make a mock of them.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="632">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>One of the brethren asked Abbâ Poemen, saying, <quote>My body is
                  feeble, and I cannot lead an ascetic life.</quote> Abbâ Poemen said unto him, <quote>Canst thou
                  lead the ascetic life in thy thought, and not permit it to go with deceit to thy
                  neighbour?</quote> Tell us how the feeble man was able to lead the ascetic life in his
                  thoughts.</quote> The old man said, <quote>This question belongeth closely, both
                  in order and meaning, to that which a certain brother asked Abbâ Poemen, saying,
                  <quote>My body is feeble, but my thoughts are not.</quote> Now in the former case he spake
                  having regard to those who were afraid that through pains and sickness they would
                  become negligent of the labours of spiritual excellence, and, in a different
                  manner, that they might fall into pains and sickness by way of punishment; in the
                  latter case he spake having regard to those who had toiled for a very long time in
                  the labours of self-denial, and who had finally become enfeebled, either through
                  old age, or through pains and sicknesses, and who were ceasing from ascetic
                  labours. Now this is what Abbâ Poemen [meant] when he said, <quote>If thou art not now
                  able, by reason of thy weakness, to toil in the labours of the body as thou didst
                  formerly, toil in the labours of the soul, that is to say, the ruling of the
                  thoughts, which is the ruling of the mind; if thou art unable to fast from meats,
                  fast from evil thoughts; and if thou art no longer able, through the weakness of
                  the body, to stand up and to recite as many Psalms as formerly, make thy mind to
                  stand up before our Lord, and pray before Him vigilantly with the prayer which is
                  secret and pure, and be tranquil, and humble, and pleasant, and good, and
                  forgiving, and merciful; and endure thy sickness and weakness with praise, and
                  make no man to be sorry by thy tongue; and judge not, and blame not, and condemn
                  not thy brother in thy heart. Now these excellences may be cultivated in the soul
                  with the labours of the mind, and not those of the body, and they are not impeded
                  by the weakness of the body.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="633">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why is it that the monks are <quote>obliged to go round about
                  begging for the meat and raiment of which they have need, like those who are in
                  the world, although our Lord promised them, saying, ‘Seek ye first the kingdom of
                  God and its righteousness, and that of which ye have need shall be given to
                  you?</quote></quote> (St. Matthew 6:33). The old man said, <quote>This [saying] is a
                  proof of the wisdom and grace of God towards those who are in the world, for, in
                  the majority of cases, the righteousness of the children of this world consisteth
                  of alms and compassion; but the children of light are righteous men and monks who,
                  in their persons, and in their members, and in their thoughts, serve our Lord. And
                  God hath made the monks to have need of the children of this world because of His
                  love, so that they may care each for the other, and may pray each for the other,
                  that is to say, the children of the world must care for the monks, and the monks
                  must pray in love for them. And as the children of the world make the monks
                  associates with them in the corporeal things of the world, the monks must make the
                  children of the world to be associates with them in the things of heaven, for our
                  Lord spake to the children of the world, saying, <quote>Make ye to yourselves friends of
                  this mammon of iniquity, so that when they have become perfect they may receive
                  you into their tabernacles which are for ever</quote></quote> (St. Luke 16:9).</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="634">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is the difference between [the words], <quote>I will dwell
                  in you,</quote> and <quote>I will walk in you,</quote> which God spake concerning the righteous? And
                  what is the meaning of <quote>dwelling,</quote> and <quote>walking</quote>?</quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>God dwelleth in the saints through the constant remembrance with which they
                  remember Him, as they marvel at Him, and His works; but He walketh in them by
                  means of His visions and revelations [which He sendeth] upon them as they marvel
                  at His majesty, and rejoice continually in His love.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="635">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>With how many, and with what names is the meditation upon
                  God called?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Its names are six, and they are as
                  follows:—1. Hope in God. 2. The state of being bound to our Lord. 3. Continuance
                  with God. 4. Persistence in all the good works of God. 5. Holding fast to God. 6.
                  Dependence upon God. Hope in God [meaneth], fix ye your gaze upon Him, and hope in
                  Him, that is to say, meditate ye upon Him. Being tied to our Lord [meaneth] that
                  we should be bound to our Lord, and should fast and pray, until the old man cometh
                  to an end, both without and within. Continuance with God is the state of being
                  gratified through Him. Persistence [meaneth] that we should possess persistence in
                  the Lord in all the good works of God. Holding fast to God [meaneth], <quote>Cut off
                  from thyself all cares which are not of Him, and let thy mind fasten its gaze upon
                  God only.</quote> Dependence upon God meaneth], <quote>Hang thyself upon God,</quote> to Whom be glory
                  (or praise)! Amen.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="636">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>An old man was asked a question by one of the brethren, who
                  spake thus:—<quote>If I am in a state of admiration of God, and in purity of soul, and
                  the time of prayer arriveth, ought I to come to prayer or not?</quote></quote> And the
               old man said, <quote> <quote>What man who possesseth riches will make himself poor?</quote>
                  Explain to us the meaning of the words of the holy man.</quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>The holy man calleth <quote>admiration of God and purity [of soul]</quote> that to which
                  the blessed Mark gave the name <quote>meditation upon God</quote> and atmosphere of freedom.’
                  There are some brethren whose hearts become pure after labours and great
                  strivings, and they become worthy of pure prayer, and their hearts also become
                  illumined from time to time by the light of Divine Grace, and they attain to the
                  meditation which is on God, and to the spiritual understandings which are superior
                  to custom. The Fathers would not permit the men who attained to this capacity,
                  when they were standing in the purity of soul of this nature, and in the
                  atmosphere which was free from trouble, and when the beater struck the board, and
                  the season for prayer arrived, to leave this enjoyable meditation, and to stand up
                  and sing the Psalms, but they [allowed] them to remain therein until it had come
                  to an end. For a man to sing the Psalms and to perform the service could always be
                  found, but such meditation and such purity of the understanding, and the
                  atmosphere of freedom could not at all times be acquired, and a man is neither
                  able nor hath the power to attain to this state whensoever he pleaseth, for it is
                  a gift from heaven which is given by our Lord from time to time to him that is
                  worthy thereof. For this reason one of the Fathers gave the following
                  commandment:—If a man enjoyeth such meditation whilst he be standing up at the
                  service, let him not interrupt it until it cometh to an end, for such meditation
                  filleth the place of the service of the Psalms. See then that thou drivest not
                  away from thee the gift of God, and let thy subservience (or submission) to the
                  same stand firm; but it is right to know that certain brethren have not as yet
                  attained to meditation of this kind. They have thought that these words were
                  spoken for every man and for men of every kind of capacity, and although their
                  minds have been illumined somewhat by the Psalms and prayers, they have relaxed
                  the fulfilment of the canon of their service, wherein are placed their
                  consolation, and their wages, and their profit, and have occupied themselves [with
                  the meditation], but on several occasions they have been interrupted in the
                  meditation which hath come to them by the devils. It is, therefore, not right for
                  the brethren who are beginners in the ascetic life to do this, but they should
                  commit their life and works and meditation wholly to God, and if it should happen
                  that this meditation cometh to them, let them reveal the matter to one of the old
                  men who is acquainted with such things, so that the demons may not lead them
                  astray and work their destruction.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="637">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>By what means did the Fathers sing the Psalms of the Holy
                  Spirit without wandering [of mind]?</quote> The old man said, <quote>First of all
                  they accustomed themselves whensoever they stood up to sing the service in their
                  cells to labour with great care to collect their minds from wandering, and to
                  understand the meaning of the Psalms, and they took care never to let one word (or
                  verse) escape them without their knowing the meaning thereof, not as a mere matter
                  of history, like the interpreters, and not after the manner of the translator,
                  like Basil and John [Chrysostom], but spiritually, according to the interpretation
                  of the Fathers, that is to say, they applied all the Psalms to their own lives and
                  works, and to their passions, and to their spiritual life, and to the wars which
                  the devils waged against them. Each man did thus according to his capacity,
                  whether he was engaged in a rule of life for the training of the body, or of the
                  soul, or of the spirit, even as it is written, <quote>Blessed are the people who know
                  Thy praises, O Lord,</quote> that is to say, blessed is the monk who, whilst glorifying
                  Thee with praise, collecteth his mind from wandering, and understandeth clearly
                  the knowledge and meaning of the Psalms of the spirit, even as it is written,
                  <quote>Sing ye unto God with praise, sing ye unto our King.</quote> When then a man singeth the
                  service in this manner, and payeth attention to the meaning of the verse, he
                  acquireth daily the faculty of singing a song mingled with the meditation of God
                  and with the gaze [which is fixed] upon Him. And after the time in which he hath
                  arrived at the spiritual rule of life, immediately a monk hath begun to sing the
                  Psalms, though one or two sections of them become too great for him, he is
                  permitted to sing them with understanding and with the meditation which is on God,
                  and he refraineth from the customary Psalms, and he singeth a song which is
                  superior [to that of] body and flesh, and which is like unto that of angels, even
                  as the Fathers say.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="638">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>By means of what thoughts of excellence may the children of
                  this world not be offended by the monks, when they see or hear concerning the
                  stumblings (or lapses) which come upon them through the frailty of [their] nature,
                  and from the wars of the devils?</quote> The old man said, <quote>When they
                  consider and look upon the monks as frail men, who are clothed with a body which
                  is full of passions, and who although they are monks are striving to imitate the
                  life and deeds of angels, yet owing to the weakness of their bodies, and the
                  inclination of their souls, and the need which cleaveth unto them, and the
                  strivings of the devils against them, the children of the world will see that it
                  is quite impossible that the monks should not be snared, involuntarily, by certain
                  weaknesses. For behold, some of the perfect men [mentioned] in the Old and New
                  Testaments were caught in snares against their will, through the frailty of their
                  nature and the war of the devils, as, for example, the blessed and perfect men
                  Moses, and Aaron, and David, and Samson, and Hezekiah, and Peter and
               Paul.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="639">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why do the monks who have led a life of hard labour become
                  in their old age silly, and simple, and act in a foolish way like children and
                  drunken men?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Because all the ascetic excellences
                  which God hath placed in the nature of their souls, and which appear in them from
                  their youth up, perish through the relaxing of the will, and through the love of
                  the body, and the war of the devils, and finally through labours and contendings.
                  Sometimes they receive them from our Lord as gifts, even as it is written, <quote>Except
                  ye turn, and become as little children, ye shall not enter the kingdom of God,</quote>
                  even as our Lord said.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="640">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What should be the beginning of the fight against sin of
                  the man who hath cast all impediments out of his soul, and who hath entered the
                  arena, and where should he begin the contest?</quote> The old man said, <quote>It
                  is well known unto every man that in all the contests against sin and its lusts
                  the labour of fasting is the first thing [to undertake], and it is so especially
                  in the case of him that fighteth against the sin which is within him; and the sign
                  of the enmity against sin and its lusts becometh apparent in those who go down to
                  this invisible conflict when they begin to fast. And next cometh the rising up in
                  the night, and whosoever loveth the occupation of fasting all the days of his life
                  is a friend of chastity. For as the pleasure of the belly, and the laxity caused
                  by the sleep which inciteth to a polluted bed, are the head and chief of all the
                  sins which are in the world, and all the abominations thereof, so fasting, and
                  strict vigil in the fear of God, with the crucifying of the body throughout the
                  night against the pleasures of sleep, are the foundation of the holy path of God,
                  and of all the spiritual excellences. For fasting is the strengthener of all
                  spiritual excellences, it is the beginning and end of the strife, and it is the
                  foremost of all virtues; and as the enjoyment of the light cleaveth closely to the
                  eyes which are healthy, so doth the desire for prayer cleave closely to the
                  fasting [which is observed] with discernment. For as soon as a man hath begun to
                  fast, he desireth greatly to converse with God in his mind. The body which is
                  fasting cannot continue to lie on [its] bed the whole night, for fasting naturally
                  inciteth to wakefulness towards God, not only by day, but also by night; for the
                  empty body is not fatigued overmuch by its conflict with sleep, even though it be
                  weak in the senses thereof, for its mind is towards God in supplication, and it is
                  better for it to cease from labour through weakness than from the weights of
                  meats. As long as the seals of fasting lie upon the mouth of man, his thoughts
                  meditate upon repentance, and his heart maketh prayers to arise; and mildness
                  lieth upon his countenance, and abominable motions are remote from him, and
                  rejoicing never, in the smallest degree, appeareth in his forehead, for he is a
                  foe of lusts and of unprofitable converse. The man who fasted regularly and with
                  understanding, and whom abominable lust brought into subjection hath never been
                  seen, for fasting is the abode of all spiritual excellences, and he who holdeth it
                  in contempt disturbeth them all. Now, the first commandment which God laid down
                  for our nature at the beginning gave [Adam] warning concerning the eating of food,
                  and the head of our race fell through eating, therefore, at the point where the
                  first corruption took place [in asceticism], must begin the building of the fear
                  of God, when they lay down the first course for the observance of the law. And
                  moreover when our Lord shewed Himself at the Jordan He also began at this point,
                  for after He was baptized the Spirit took Him out into the wilderness, and He
                  fasted for forty days and forty nights; and all those who travel in His footsteps
                  lay the beginning of their strife on this foundation. For who shall treat with
                  contempt, or hold lightly the armour which hath been forged by God? If He Who laid
                  down the law fasted, who is there among those who would keep the law that hath not
                  need thereof? Immediately this armour appeareth on a man straightway terror
                  falleth upon the thoughts of the chief of the rebellion, that is, Satan; and his
                  power is shattered at the sight of the arms which our Captain of the host hath
                  placed in our hands, for as soon as he seeth the might of this armour on a man he
                  knoweth at once that he is ready for the contest. What armour is there which is as
                  strong or which giveth such boldness in the fight against evil spirits as hunger
                  for the sake of Christ? For in proportion as a man is harried and brought low in
                  his body, at the time when the phalanx of Satan surroundeth him, doth his heart
                  support itself with confidence, and he who treateth this with contempt is lax and
                  is a coward in respect of other spiritual triumphs, because he hath not upon him
                  the armour whereby the divine athletes have gained the victory. And at the very
                  beginning the sign of weakness appeareth in him, and he himself giveth the
                  opportunity of defeat to his adversary, and since he goeth naked into the strife
                  it is evident that he will emerge therefrom without victory, because he hath cast
                  away from him the strength which would stir up in him the divine zeal; for his
                  members are not clothed with the flame of hunger, that is to say, fasting. As
                  merchants cannot without labour and trouble save up riches, so the righteous man
                  without anguish and labour for the sake of righteousness cannot expect the crown
                  and the reward.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="641">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>If a man attaineth unto purity of heart what is the sign
                  thereof? And when will he know himself if the heart is coming to purity?</quote>
               The old man said, When he seeth that all men are fair, and when no man appeareth to
               him to be unclean or polluted; whosoever is thus indeed standeth in purity. And if
               this be not the case, how can he fulfil the word of the Apostle which saith, <quote>When a
               man standeth wholly in purity, he will think that every man is better than he in
               heart and in truth,</quote> unless it be that he attaineth to the state of him of whom it is
               said, <quote>He whose eyes are pure seeth not wickedness.</quote>”</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="642">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is purity? And to what length doth its limit
                  extend?</quote> The old man said, <quote>In my opinion purity consisteth in
                  oblivion of the various kinds of knowledge which are beyond nature, and which
                  nature hath discovered in the world; and the limit thereof is that a man should be
                  wholly free from them, so that he may arrive at the state of natural simplicity
                  and integrity which he possessed at first, and which somewhat resembleth that of a
                  child, except in the case of small matters.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="643">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Is it possible for a man to attain to this state?</quote>
               The old man said, <quote>Yea. Behold, one of the old men attained to this state to
                  such a degree that he was in the habit of asking his disciple continually if he
                  had eaten or not. And on one occasion one of the saints, who was a a very old man,
                  became too innocent and simple, and attained to such a state of simplicity and
                  purity that he did not even know how to keep watch upon himself so that he might
                  partake of the Mysteries, or whether he had done so or not, until at length his
                  disciples kept him in his cell, and took him that he might partake of the
                  Mysteries, just as if he had been a child. Now although he was in this state as
                  regards the things of this world, he was perfect in his soul.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="644">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What are the [subjects of] meditation and conversation
                  which it is meet for a man to have whilst he is living the life of the recluse and
                  passing his time in silent contemplation, so that his understanding may not occupy
                  itself with casual thoughts?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Dost thou ask
                  concerning meditation, what shall a man have wherewith to put to death the world
                  in his cell? Hath the man whose soul is strenuous and watchful any need [to ask]
                  the question as to what labour he shall occupy himself with when he is alone? What
                  is there for the monk to occupy himself with except weeping? If, then, the monk be
                  unoccupied with weeping, and he be able to pay attention to [any] other thought,
                  what is the meditation which hath died out of him? And if we come to silent
                  meditation, we can also be constant in weeping, and therefore let us beseech our
                  Lord most earnestly with the mind that He may grant this unto us.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="645">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Since, then, a man is not sufficient for the constant
                  exercise of this faculty, because of the frailty (or sickness) of his bodily
                  nature, it is right that he should have something else besides this which shall be
                  useful for the consolation of his mind, so that the passions may not attack him
                  through the idleness of the understanding.</quote> The old man said, <quote>The
                  passions cannot attack the soul of the monk, whose heart hath been cut off from
                  the world by living a solitary ascetic life, unless he hath been negligent of the
                  things which it is proper for him to do; and this is so especially if he hath,
                  besides the employment [of reading] the Scriptures, the helpful thoughts of the
                  man who is occupied with spiritual excellence. And living alone and in silence
                  will help this [result] greatly, and he will receive in his mind the hope of the
                  world which is to come, and the glory which is laid up for the saints.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="646">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>One of the old men said, <quote>I have toiled for twenty years
                  that I might see all men together (i.e., alike).</quote> How can a man attain to this
                  measure, and when, and by what means? Give us a demonstration concerning this
                  matter.</quote> The old man said, <quote>It is only the perfect men who attain to
                  this measure, and according to what the Fathers say, without contemplation in
                  silence, and prayer, and great conflicts, and humility, no man can attain thereto.
                  And there is a similarity to this demonstration in the case of natural parents,
                  for as they regard all their children in the same way, and as they love them all
                  equally, and pity and spare all of them alike, even though there be among them
                  great and small, and healthy and sick, and righteous and sinners, and good-looking
                  and bad-looking, so the strenuous Fathers after the labours and the contests which
                  they have passed through during long periods of time spent in silent and solitary
                  retirement, regard all men, both the righteous and the sinners, in the same way,
                  and they love them all alike and without distinction. And as God maketh the shadow
                  to fall upon all men, both upon the righteous and upon sinners, even though he
                  loveth the righteous for their righteousness, yet He sheweth most compassion upon
                  the sinners. And the coming of our Lord was for the sake of sinners, for [saith
                  He], <quote>I did not come to call the righteous,</quote> &amp;.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="647">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why was it, when the brother, according to the body, of one
                  of the Fathers who was living the life of a recluse, sent to him, when he was
                  about to die, to come and see him, that he would not do so, and that the one
                  brother died without seeing the other? And what is the meaning of the words which
                  he spake, <quote>If I go forth and see him my heart will not be pure before
                  God</quote>?</quote> The old man said, <quote>The holy man was living secluded in a cell,
                  in a habitation of the brethren, and his brother according to the body was also
                  living, like the other brethren in another cell, and when the latter became sick
                  unto death, he wished to see his brother before he died. Now to the holy man,
                  since he was keeping silence in respect of all the other brethren, it did not
                  appear to be right to go forth to his brother according to the body, and not to go
                  forth afterwards to his spiritual brethren, that is to say, to those who dwelt in
                  the monastery with him. Had he gone forth to his brother according to the body at
                  the season of his death, and had not gone forth to his brethren in the spirit, he
                  would not have found freedom of speech with God at the season of prayer, but his
                  mind would have passed judgement upon him, and his mind would have been darkened,
                  as if he had held in contempt and treated his brethren in the spirit in a
                  dishonourable fashion, and had done more honour to his brother according to the
                  body than to them. This is the meaning of what he said, <quote>I cannot go forth, for if
                  I do, my heart will not be pure before God.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="648">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>The sage said, <quote>Whosoever possesseth not the art of
                  labouring, that is, either the things which belong to the labour of the spirit,
                  whereby he may find consolation from God in his inner man in the spirit, or the
                  things which belong to the art of human labour, cannot tarry long in his cell;
                  whosoever doth not possess one or other of these cannot tarry long in his cell.</quote>
                  Explain to us the words of the old man.</quote> The old man said, <quote>The
                  things which belong to the art of human labour are well known unto every man; but
                  things which belong to labour of the spirit he calleth the following: fasting,
                  vigil, the singing of psalms and hymns, the prayers which are said kneeling down,
                  anguish, weeping, tears, and other labours which are like unto these. And together
                  with these [there must be the recital of] the offices for the seven hours [of the
                  day and night], and the reading of the Holy Scriptures and of the [books of]
                  doctrine of the old men, and these make the monk to acquire patient endurance, and
                  the ability to live the ascetic life alone in a cell, and they produce for him joy
                  and spiritual comfort. If he be a beginner in the ascetic life and strong, and he
                  toileth in labours, he will acquire consolation; and if he be a feeble old man, or
                  sick, he will labour in the labours of the mind, and will find joy. For as all the
                  objects which are of gold are wrought by means of anvil, and a hammer, and a pair
                  of tongs, so by means of the labour of the body in a place of silence and
                  seclusion, and the striving of the mind, are wrought all the fruits of the spirit,
                  which the Apostle said were love, joy, peace, faith, humility, graciousness,
                  pleasantness, long-suffering and patient endurance.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="649">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>On one occasion, when the brethren were sitting down and
                  asking questions about the thoughts, one of them said, <quote>It is not a great matter
                  if a man seeth thoughts afar off.</quote> What did he want to say? Explain to us the
                  words of the old men.</quote> The old man said, <quote>When the brethren drew nigh
                  to the Fathers and asked them questions [wishing] to learn concerning the mode of
                  action and thought in respect of the wars of the devils, the Fathers did not
                  persuade those among them who appeared to possess subtlety of thought, and
                  intelligence, and understanding, and to hate the passions, and to be fervent in
                  the spirit, to cast out from themselves straightway the thoughts of the passions
                  whensoever they stirred in them, and to make them to depart foolishly, but they
                  ordered them to tarry with them, and to examine carefully how they arose, and then
                  to contend against them; for in proportion as they were trained in the knowledge
                  of strivings and contendings against the passions and against devils they would
                  benefit not themselves only, but many other people also. And in this wise acted
                  also Evagrius, that man of understanding, and Abbâ Poemen, and others who were
                  like unto them. Therefore Abbâ Joseph said to Abbâ Poemen, <quote>When the passions rise
                  up in thee, give unto and receive from them, and understand carefully their crafty
                  nature, and train thyself to contend against them.</quote> Now there are certain weak and
                  foolish brethren whom in no way whatsoever doth it benefit to dally with the rise
                  of the thoughts of the passions which are in the heart, on the contrary, it is far
                  better for them, immediately they perceive the motions of the passions, to cast
                  them forth from them by prayer, and with anger and hatred. Therefore, when several
                  of the Fathers were gathered together and were discussing the conflicts of the
                  thoughts, and whether it was right to dally with them because of knowledge
                  [concerning them], or to suppress them by means of prayer through fear [of them],
                  one of the Fathers said, <quote>Even to understand the thoughts afar off is a great and
                  excellent work, but it is a far greater work, and one which maketh a man to
                  acquire practice, for him to understand the thoughts, and to wage war against
                  them. When he hath gained experience of their crafty character, then he will
                  suppress them and make them to disappear by the power of prayer and humility. Now
                  the meaning of this question is this. When a man hath laboured in conflict and
                  contest against the passions for a long time in seclusion, by the grace of our
                  Lord his heart becometh purified, and rest and peace reign in his soul, and he
                  hath relief from tribulation, and he rejoiceth in God at all seasons, and the
                  devils have no power henceforth to stir up evil thoughts in his soul, because his
                  heart is filled with divine thoughts, and the understanding of spiritual things,
                  and he is never without the mind which is in God, and the remembrance of His fear
                  and mercy. And should the demons dare to stir up thoughts in him, they will not
                  [succeed] in rousing those which cause anguish and which bring to naught spiritual
                  excellences, but only those which are of an ordinary nature, and which impede the
                  vision, even as Evagrius said.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="650">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>How is it possible for a man to live in such a way as to be
                  pleasing to God?</quote> The old man said, <quote>It is impossible for a monk to
                  rise to the height of the love of God, unless he first of all regard with
                  affection and love man, the image of God; for this is the end of all the
                  commandments of our Lord Jesus Christ, even as He Himself said, <quote>If ye love Me,
                  keep My commandments.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="651">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>An old man said, <quote>If there rise up in thy mind a thought
                  about the need of the body, and thou castest it out once, and it cometh to thee a
                  second time, and thou castest it out, should it come a third time, pay no regard
                  to it, for it appertaineth to war</quote>; explain to us these words.</quote> The old man
               said, <quote>If whilst thou art in seclusion, and art engaged in spiritual labour,
                  Satan, being envious of thee, and wishing to drive thee out of the cell, or to
                  impede thy spiritual progress, stir up in thee one of the thoughts which goad a
                  man into sin, either to eat before the proper time, or to lie down and sleep, or
                  to visit some one, or to do something else; and if he sheweth thee thy power of
                  discretion [saying], <quote>It is unseemly for thee to do this thing</quote>; or again, should
                  some evil devil constrain thee, and hinder thee, and wishing to make thee to cease
                  from thy labour, should mock and scoff at thee; then stand thou up quickly, and
                  bestir thyself boldly, and bow thy knee before our Lord, and pray, and ask, and
                  entreat for help, and mercy, and protection. For that brother who soaked palm
                  fibres in water, and who sat down to plait ropes and mats, was engaged in a
                  similar war, and a demon roused up in him the thought to go and visit one of the
                  brethren; and he cast the thought from him twice, and thrice. Now finally, because
                  he did not understand that the war was of the Evil One, who sought to stop [his
                  work] and drive him out of his cell, he was overcome by the war, and he left the
                  palm leaves soaking in the water, and ran and hurried out in great haste. At
                  length the matter was revealed unto one of the holy men who was a neighbour of
                  his, and he cried out to him, saying, Captive, Captive,’ and made him to come back
                  to his cell, and afterwards the devils cried out with a loud voice, saying, <quote>Ye
                  have overcome us, O monks.</quote> For the demons are so wicked, and they are so envious
                  of the monks when they remain constantly in seclusion for our Lord’s sake, that on
                  several occasions they have, in an irregular manner, driven them out of their
                  cells, as if for a good object, but their object was not a good one.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="652">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why was it that Abbâ Ammon was not able to overcome the
                  passion of wrath for fourteen years, although he said unto us, that he had
                  entreated God, with anguish and tears, both by day and by night unceasingly, to
                  give him the victory over it?</quote> The old man said, <quote>That passion
                  probably overcame him to an excessive degree through the natural constitution of
                  his body, but it is quite certain that the passions and the devils waged war
                  against him like a mighty man and a warrior. For the devils made war upon the
                  Fathers with intense fierceness and violence, upon each man according to his
                  capacity, and in proportion to their power to triumph, through long-suffering,
                  that is to say, through patient and persistent endurance, the battle against them
                  was protracted.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="653">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Abbâ Dorotheus said, <quote>Our lack of ability to distinguish
                  between matters will permit us to acquire great excellence in the virtues</quote>;
                  explain to us what the old man [intended] to say.</quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>He wished to say as follows:—<quote>Because of our lack of ability to distinguish
                  between matters we do not make progress in the virtues, and our heart is not
                  quickly purified, and we do not ascend to perfection, because we do not labour
                  with the knowledge and power of discernment which it is right [for us to have];
                  but [we progress] painfully, and [only] for the sake of vainglory, and as the
                  result of chance circumstances, and without discretion. And, as it cometh, this
                  resembleth that which the blessed Evagrius spake, saying, <quote>As it is not the
                  material foods themselves which nourish the body, but the power which is in them,
                  so it is not matters themselves which make the soul to grow, but the power of
                  discernment which [cometh] from them.</quote> And he also said, <quote>As the
                  feeding, and health, and growth of the body do not come through the actual
                  materials of our foods, for these are cast out of the body in the draught, but
                  from the hidden power which is in them, so also the nourishment and the growth of
                  the soul take place through the fear of God. And the healthy state thereof which
                  ariseth through impassibility, and the perfection thereof which is in
                  righteousness, do not exist through the labours of the body only, but from the
                  deeds and acts which [are performed] with knowledge, that is to say, with a
                  straight object, and from the action of the mind which hateth passions, and from
                  the prayer which is joined to humility, and from the mind which is in God.</quote>
               </quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="654">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Abbâ Arsenius said unto one of the brethren, <quote>Lead the
                  ascetic life with all the strength that thou hast, and the hidden labour which is
                  within, and which is performed for God</quote>s sake, shall vanquish thine external
                  passions’; to what doth he give the name of <quote>passions</quote>?’ The old man said, <quote>In
                  this case Arsenius calleth the labours of the body <quote>passions.</quote> For labours are
                  also called by the name of <quote>passions,</quote> because they constrain those who toil, and
                  make them feel pain, even as Abbâ Macarius said, Constrain thy soul with pains and
                  labours of every kind in ascetic excellence.’ And this is what Abbâ Arsenius said
                  to that brother, Labour with all thy might in the work of righteousness, and toil
                  with the labours of the mind more than with all the various kinds of work of the
                  body. For the labours of the body only incite and gratify the passions of the
                  body, but the labours of the mind, that is to say, the thought which is in God,
                  and prayer without ceasing, and the suppression of the thought[s] with humility,
                  liberate [a man] from all the passions, and they vanquish devils, and purify the
                  heart, and make perfect love, and make him worthy of the revelations of the
                  spirit.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="655">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is the meaning of that which Abbâ Benjamin said, <quote>Had
                  Moses not been gathering the sheep into the fold he would not have seen Him that
                  was in the bush</quote>?</quote> The old man said, <quote>What he said was this:—As the
                  blessed Moses, who was held worthy of the vision in the bush, first gathered
                  together the sheep which he was tending into one company lest, when going to see
                  that wonderful sight, his mind should be perturbed through anxiety about the sheep
                  which were [wandering] in the desert, so also is it with the monk, for if he
                  wisheth and desireth the purity of heart which looketh upon God in the revelation
                  of light, it is right that first of all he should abandon every earthly
                  possession, and his feelings, and his passions, and he should live in seclusion
                  always, and should collect his mind and free it from all wandering and straying,
                  and should have one object only to gaze upon, that is God. In this manner he will
                  become worthy of purity of heart, and he will enjoy visions and revelations
                  concerning Him.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="656">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Hieronymus said that the blessed Evagrius commanded the
                  brethren who were with him not to drink their fill of water, and said, <quote>There are
                  always demons in the places wherein there is water</quote>; what opinion is this?</quote>
               The old man said, <quote>The blessed Evagrius interpreted these words spiritually, as
                  being suitable to our mode of life, and he said that which our Lord said, <quote>The
                  demongoeth round about in the places wherein there is no water, that he may seek
                  for rest, and he findeth it not</quote>; which saying maketh us to understand that when
                  the unclean devil of fornication wageth war against the monk, if the monk
                  afflicteth himself by eating food sparingly, and especially by drinking water
                  sparingly, Satan will never be able to injure him by means of this passion. And
                  the devil will never be gratified at the fulfilment of this passion by him, for
                  there is nothing which will dry up the arteries, and prevent the accident of the
                  night, and make a monk to possess chaste and quiet thoughts by day, so much as the
                  restraining of the belly by thirst. Some fast the whole day until the evening, and
                  some fast for [several] nights at a time, yet when they break their fast and eat a
                  little food, because they drink much water, they benefit in no wise by their
                  fasting and by the sparing use of food which they practise because of the war of
                  lust. For the drinking of much water filleth the arteries [of the monk] with
                  [excessive] moisture, and Satan findeth an occasion for exciting him by means of
                  thoughts in the daytime, and he trippeth him up by means of dreams by night, and
                  he depriveth him of the light of purity. Therefore, in another place, Abbâ
                  Evagrius admonisheth the monk, saying, <quote>If thou wishest for chastity make little
                  thy food, and restrain thyself in the drinking of water, and then impassibility of
                  heart shall rise upon thee, and thou shalt see in thy prayer a mind which emitteth
                  light like unto a star.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="657">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>In how many ways doth Divine Grace call the brethren unto
                  the life of the solitary ascetic?</quote> The old man said, <quote>In very many
                  and different ways. Sometimes Divine Grace moveth a man suddenly, even as it moved
                  Abbâ Moses, the Ethiopian, and sometimes by the hearing of the Scriptures, as in
                  the cases of the blessed Mâr Anthony and Mâr Simon Stylites, and at others by the
                  doctrine of the word, as in the cases of Serapion, and Abbâ Bessarion, and others
                  who were like unto them. Concerning these three ways whereby Divine Grace calleth
                  to those who would repent, I would say that Divine Grace moveth the conscience of
                  a monk in the manner which is pleasing to God, and that through these even
                  evil-doers have repented and pleased God. And there is, moreover, the departure
                  from this world by the hands of angels, by terrors, and sicknesses, and
                  afflictions, even as that which took place in respect of the blessed Evagrius; and
                  sometimes God Himself calleth from heaven and taketh a man out of the world, as in
                  the cases of Paul, and Abbâ Arsenius.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="658">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Wherefore is it that the beginning of the doctrine of the
                  old men is laid down in the books from the choice (or election) of Abbâ Arsenius,
                  and on [his] coming forth from the world into a monastery, and from a monastery of
                  the brethren into the seclusion which is in a cell?</quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>Because he was called by God to the monastery, and from the monastery to
                  the cell, and because it is certain that these two calls were according to the
                  Will of God, well was it that the beginning of the doctrine of the old men [was
                  derived] from the history of this holy man.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="659">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Explain unto us these two calls of Abbâ Arsenius. What is
                  the meaning of that which was said in the first call, <quote>Flee from the children of
                  men and thou shalt live,</quote> and what is the signification of that which was said at
                  the second call, <quote>Flee, keep silence and live a life of contemplation in silence,
                  for these are the principal things which keep a man from sinning?</quote></quote> The old
               man said, <quote>The meaning of <quote>Flee from the children of men, and thou shalt live,</quote>
                  is this:—If thou wishest to be delivered from the death which is in sin, and to
                  live the perfect life which is in righteousness, leave thy possessions, and
                  family, and country, and depart into exile, that is, to the desert and mountains
                  to the holy men; and cultivate with them My commandments, and thou shalt live a
                  life of grace. And the meaning of <quote>Flee, keep silence, and live a life of
                  contemplation in silence</quote> is this:—Since when thou wast in the world thou wast
                  drawn towards anxieties about the affairs thereof, I have made thee to come out
                  from the world, and I have sent thee to the habitation of monks, so that after a
                  short time of dwelling in the coenobium thou mayest be drawn, first to the
                  cultivation of My commandments openly, and secondly to contemplation in silence.
                  And now that thou art trained in the former sufficiently, thou mayest flee, that
                  is to say, get thee forth from the monastery of the brethren, and enter into thy
                  cell, just as thou didst go forth from the world, and didst enter into the
                  monastery. And the meaning of <quote>Keep silence, and lead a life of contemplation in
                  silence,</quote> is:—Having entered into thy cell to contemplate in silence, thou shalt
                  not give the multitude an opportunity of coming in to thee, and talking to thee
                  unnecessarily, except on matters which relate to spiritual excellence; if thou
                  dost not do this thou wilt benefit by sitting in silent contemplation. For through
                  the sight, and the hearing, and the converse of the multitude who shall come in to
                  thee, the captivity of wandering thoughts will carry thee off, and thy silence and
                  thy contemplation will be disturbed. But do not imagine that the mere fact of
                  having left the brethren in the monastery, or not bringing other men into thy cell
                  to be disturbed by them will be sufficient to make thy mind to be composed, or to
                  enable thee to meditate upon God, and to correct thyself, unless thou dost take
                  good heed not to occupy thy mind with them in any way whatsoever when they are
                  remote from thee. For until a man arriveth at a state of impassibility, and
                  overcometh by striving both the passions and the devils, whensoever a monk
                  remembereth any man in his cell, he remembereth him in connexion with some
                  passion, that is to say, with desire (or lust), or with anger, or with vainglory.
                  And if it should happen that the mind wandereth in respect of ordinary things (or
                  means), unless he cutteth them off from him, his wandering inclineth through
                  absolute necessity towards a remembrance which is allied to some passion. And it
                  is also thus in the case of a neophyte, for whensoever during his contemplation in
                  silence he remembered women he falleth into the lust of fornication; and
                  whensoever he remembereth men, he is either wroth with them in his thoughts, and
                  he maketh accusations against them, and blameth them, and condemneth them, or he
                  demandeth from them vainglory, and he inclineth to passibility. Therefore when
                  Abbâ Macarius was asked, <quote>What is the right way for a brother, who is a neophyte,
                  to live in his cell?</quote> he said, <quote>Let no monk when he is in his cell have any
                  remembrance whatsoever of any man, for he cannot profit in any way in restraining
                  his feelings from the conversation of men, except he take care to withhold his
                  thoughts from secret intercourse with them.</quote> This is the meaning of the words, “
                  <quote>Flee, keep silence, and contemplate in silence.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="660">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is the meaning of the words which one of the old men
                  spake, saying, <quote>He who dwelleth with men, because of the commotion of worldly
                  affairs is unable to see his sins; but if he dwell in the silent repose of the
                  desert he will be able to see God in a pure manner?</quote></quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>The excellences which are cultivated in the world, and to which our Lord,
                  speaking in the Gospel, ascribed blessing, are loving-kindness, peace-making and
                  the other commandments which are like unto them, and it is quite possible for such
                  virtues to be cultivated in the world by certain strenuous persons. But the purity
                  of heart which seeth God, and to which our Lord ascribed blessing, saying,
                  <quote>Blessed are the pure in heart, for they shall see God,</quote> cannot be acquired
                  without dwelling in the desert, and solitary and silent contemplation, and the
                  monk must acquire it in the following way. First of all a man must go forth from
                  the world, and dwell in a monastery, and after his training in a monastery and
                  having gone into his cell, he must die through contemplation in silence, and
                  through the other labours of his body, and through striving against the passions,
                  and through conflict with devils. Then through the tranquillity of mind [which he
                  will acquire] in silent contemplation, he will remember his sins, and when he
                  hateth his passions, and hath petitioned for the remission of his sins, and hath
                  suppressed his thoughts, and hath become constant in pure prayer, and hath
                  cleansed his heart from odious thoughts, then shall he be worthy to see in his
                  heart, even as in a polished mirror, the light of the revelation of our Lord
                  [shine] upon it, even as the Fathers say. Well, then, did that holy man say to
                  those brethren, Visit the sick, reconcile the men of wrath, for he who cultivateth
                  spiritual excellences in the world cannot, by reason of the commotion of the
                  affairs thereof, see his sins; but if he continue in silent contemplation and
                  prayer he shall see God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="661">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is [the meaning of] that which Abbâ Sisoes said to
                  Abbâ Ammon, <quote>Freedom of my thoughts in the desert is sufficient for me?</quote></quote>
               The old man said, <quote>Sisoes was a great and a perfect old man, and he dwelt all
                  the days of his life in the remote desert, and after he had become old, and was
                  exceedingly feeble, the Fathers brought him to the monastery of the brethren, who
                  used to go in and visit him each day, for the sake of some profitable discourse
                  and helpful prayer. And because he was unaccustomed to feel comfortable in the
                  presence of many folks, his mind began to wander about in remembering the
                  brethren, and to meditate upon many things, and he was unable to find that
                  dominant freedom for the continuous, secret prayer of the mind, which is superior
                  to every influence that would make it decline, and is free from every [other]
                  attraction, and he was, therefore, rightly grieved. Now one day, Abbâ Ammon went
                  to visit him, and he saw that he was sorry about his coming from the desert, and
                  he said unto him, <quote>Father, it is not right for thee to be sorrowful because thou
                  hast drawn nigh to the place where the brethren dwell, for thy body hath become
                  feeble, and thou art unable to perform those works wherein thou wert wont to
                  labour in the desert.</quote> Now when Abbâ Sisoes heard these things, he looked at Abbâ
                  Ammon sternly, and he answered him with indignation, saying, <quote>What sayest thou to
                  me, Ammon? Was not the freedom of the thoughts which I had in the desert
                  sufficient to take the place for me of all labours? And as regards thyself also, O
                  Ammon, who art conscious of the life and acts of the freedom of the mind, and who
                  art not subject unto the constraint of wandering and disturbance of the mind, and
                  who art not impeded by old age and infirmity, tell me what thou art able to do in
                  the desert at thy great age? Even if I be unequal to the labours of the body,
                  because I have become infirm through old age, I am better able to perform the
                  labours of the mind than I was in the time of my early manhood. Or, perhaps in thy
                  opinion the clear shining of the mind, which a monk acquireth by a life of
                  contemplation in silence, and the constant intercourse with God, and the prayer
                  which is without ceasing, and the remembrance of Christ, and the constant gazing
                  upon Him, and the exultation of the soul in Him, and the favour of His love, and
                  the affection for His commandments, and the desire for His good things, and the
                  meditation upon His glory, and the thought about His excellence and His majesty,
                  and the admiration of His humility, are matters which are small and contemptible?
                  All these labours of the mind, and many others which are like unto them, neither
                  old age nor infirmity impedes, but they are prevented, and brought low, and, by
                  degrees, are destroyed, by converse with the children of men, and by seeing many
                  people, and by care about worldly affairs.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="662">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>They used to say that when the service in the church was
                  over, Abbâ Macarius was wont to flee to his cell, and that the brethren said, <quote>He
                  hath a devil, but he doeth the work of God.</quote> Now who were those who said that he
                  had a devil? And what was the work of God which he used to do?</quote> The old man
               said, <quote>Those who said that he had a devil were the lazy brethren. Whensoever
                  Satan seeth the monks who are leading a life of spiritual excellence in the
                  monastery, the devils stir up the lazy brethren to wage war against them, by means
                  of abuse, and revilings, and backbiting, and calumny, and by means of the trials
                  which they bring upon them. Now the work of God which Abbâ Sisoes did when he fled
                  [to his cell] was this: Prayer accompanied by weeping and tears, according to the
                  exhortation of Abbâ Isaiah, who said, <quote>When the congregation is dismissed, or when
                  thou risest up after eating, sit not down to talk with any man, either concerning
                  the affairs of the world, or concerning matters of spiritual excellence; but go
                  thou into thy cell, and weep for thy sins, even as Abbâ Macarius the Alexandrian
                  said unto the brethren who were with him, “Brethren, flee.</quote> And the
               brethren said, <quote>Father, how can we flee more than [in coming] to the
                  desert?</quote> and he laid his hand upon his mouth, and said unto them,
                  <quote>Flee ye in this manner</quote>; and straightway every man fled to his cell
               and held his peace.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="663">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Abbâ Anthony said, <quote>As a fish dieth when it is lifted up
                  out of the water, so doth the monk [die] if he remain long outside his cell</quote>;
                  explain these words to us.</quote> The old man said, <quote>Because the
                  remembrance of God is, in our Lord Jesus Christ, the life of the soul, which the
                  Fathers call the <quote>repository of life,</quote> and <quote>the breath of the life of the soul and
                  of the mind,</quote> when the monk tarrieth in the cities, and in the sight and converse
                  of the children of men, he dieth in respect of the breath of life which is in God,
                  that is to say, he forgetteth God, and the love of Christ groweth cold in his
                  heart, the love which he hath acquired by many labours, and he forgetteth his
                  virtues, and he becometh lax in respect of [his] liking for tribulations, and he
                  loveth pleasures, and hath an affection for lusts, and the sincerity of his heart
                  is troubled through the disturbance which entereth into his senses, that is,
                  seeing, and speaking, and hearing, which are indeed the strength of the soul; and
                  it happeneth also that he falleth into great passions, wherefrom may Christ God
                  save us! Amen.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="664">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>The excellent man Hieronymus said in the history of the
                  triumphs of the blessed Isidore, the archimandrite, that he had in his monastery
                  one thousand monks, and that they all lived within the gate of his habitation, and
                  that none of them ever went outside it until the day of his death, except two
                  brethren who only set out therefrom to sell their handiwork, and who brought in
                  only such things as were required for their absolute needs. How is it that in an
                  assembly of our early Fathers, that is, a congregation containing one thousand
                  brethren, two men only were sufficient [to provide for] their ministrations? In
                  our generation if there was a congregation of five and fifty monks, only five
                  would lead a life of ascetic excellence in seclusion, and the [other] fifty would
                  be going out and coming in ceaselessly and without rest to supply them with what
                  they needed.</quote> The old man said, <quote>Concerning the love for labours, and
                  the watch which the early Fathers kept [on themselves], and concerning the love of
                  pleasure, and the laxity of ourselves who belong to a later time, if it be right
                  to tell the truth, we ought to speak most concerning the laxity and ignorance of
                  the governors of monasteries. In former times the brethren who lived lives of
                  contemplation and seclusion and loved spiritual repose were many, and those who
                  went out on to the high roads, and entered the cities, and performed outside
                  labours were few; but in our days, in a congregation which, as ye have said,
                  containeth five and fifty monks, five will lead a life of spiritual repose inside
                  the monastery, and the other fifty will toil ceaselessly in the works which are
                  outside it, and during the whole time they will complain and blame the five who
                  are inside, because they do not go out and serve even as do they. And through the
                  words of these foolish and insolent men all the spiritual excellences which are
                  cultivated in the monastery will perish and come to an end. And according to what
                  I say, if the Fathers set the life of contemplation in silence against the whole
                  of the labour of the ascetic life, and if it be more excellent than it all, who
                  would blame him that loveth spiritual contemplation and repose, and the quiet of
                  the cell?</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="665">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>On one occasion a congregation of monks assembled on the
                  great festival of the Resurrection, and there were gathered together in the
                  monastery all the Fathers, and all the recluses, and other monks, and all the old
                  men in the congregation were asked, Which is the mightiest and most severe war
                  which can come upon monks? And they all agreed that no war is harder or more cruel
                  than that which maketh a man to leave his cell and depart, and that when that war
                  is fought down, all other contests may be easily reduced. Explain to us the
                  meaning of these words.</quote> The old man said, <quote>Constant spiritual repose
                  in a cell hath hope closely bound up in it, but going out there from is united to
                  despair. As long as a man liveth in spiritual repose, and loveth the quiet of the
                  cell, little by little he goeth forward, one step at a time, according to the
                  order of succession; and he hath hope that in our Lord he will vanquish each of
                  the passions, and that through his repose and labours he will acquire spiritual
                  excellences and the grace of Christ. But if the life becometh tedious to him, and
                  he go forth and leave his cell, and wander about, he will neither vanquish the
                  passions, nor acquire spiritual virtues, but he will incline to despair, and to
                  utter destruction. Therefore the Fathers have well said that no war is more cruel
                  than the war of wandering.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="666">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Abbâ Theodore and Abbâ Lûkî passed fifty years in being
                  harassed by their thoughts which urged them vexatiously to change [their] place
                  [of living]; and they said, <quote>When the winter cometh we will change.</quote> And when the
                  winter had come, they said, <quote>We will change in the summer</quote>; and thus they
                  continued to do till the end of their lives. Reveal to us if it were the devils
                  who were urging these famous Fathers to go forth from their cells for a period of
                  fifty years, that is, until their death.</quote> The old man said, <quote>The
                  devils urged the great Fathers to wander and to go forth from their spiritual
                  repose because they well knew the benefit which accrued to them therefrom, and
                  these holy Fathers were urged by the devils also, but did not leave their cells.
                  To-day, however, in this generation, the same devils harass the monks, and drive
                  them out of their cells by this war of departure, and therefore the great Fathers
                  who have felt this war of wandering and of departure have said, <quote>There is no war
                  which is more cruel to the monk than this; may Christ help us and deliver us from
                  it.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="667">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Abbâ Anthony used to say, <quote>He who dwelleth in the desert is
                  free from three wars, that is, from speaking, hearing, and seeing</quote>; explain these
                  words to us.</quote> The old man said, <quote>The old man did not speak [thus]
                  because the strife of him that dwelt in spiritual repose in the desert was less
                  fierce than that of him that wandered about and mingled with men, but that he
                  might show how much more hard and laborious was the war of devils which taketh
                  place in the heart of those who dwell in spiritual repose than that which cometh
                  in the heart of those who dwell with brethren. And because of this the fathers
                  pursued after a life of contemplation in silence, lest when the wars of speaking
                  and seeing and hearing were added unto that which was already in their heart, they
                  would fall by reason of their severity, even as actually happened on one occasion,
                  for a woman came to the monks who were living a life of silent contemplation, and
                  there was added to the war which was already in their hearts the wars of seeing,
                  and hearing, and speaking, and they would have been vanquished by the severity
                  thereof had it not been that the grace of our Lord supported them. That the war
                  which taketh place in the senses of the soul against the monks who live a life of
                  silent contemplation is mightier and fiercer than that which taketh place in the
                  senses of the body, is well known from the words which the blessed Evagrius spake,
                  saying, Against the monks who lead a life of silent contemplation the devils in
                  person wage war, but against those who lead a life of spiritual excellence in a
                  general assembly of brethren, the devils only stir up and incite the lazy
                  brethren; but the war which ariseth from the sight, and the hearing, and the
                  speech is much less fierce that that which is waged against the monks who dwell in
                  silent solitude.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="668">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is the meaning of that which Abbâ Anthony said, <quote>A
                  monk</quote>s cell is the furnace of Babylon, and it is also a pillar of light’?</quote>
               The old man said, <quote>There are two things peculiar to the cell; the one warmeth
                  and setteth on fire, and the other giveth light and rejoicing. To neophytes it is
                  oppressive and troublesome, by reason of the many wars and the dejection which are
                  therein, but it rejoiceth the perfect and maketh them glad, with purity of heart,
                  and impassibility, and revelations of light; and it is even thus with those who
                  begin to live in silent contemplation, for although at the beginning they are for
                  a considerable time afflicted by the wars of the passions, and by devils, they are
                  never forsaken by the help of Divine Grace. For our Lord Himself, the Son of God,
                  Jesus Christ, cometh to them secretly, and he becometh to them a helper and a
                  companion, and after they have overcome both passions and devils, according to
                  systematic order, He maketh them worthy of the happiness which is in His perfect
                  love, and the revelation of His glorious light.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="669">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Abbâ. Moses the Ethiopian was on one occasion reviled by
                  certain men, and the brethren asked him, saying, <quote>Wast not thou troubled in thy
                  heart, O father, when thou wast reviled?</quote> And he said unto them, <quote>Although I was
                  troubled, yet I said nothing.</quote> What is the meaning of the words, <quote>Although I was
                  troubled I spake not</quote>?</quote> The old man said, <quote>The perfection of monks
                  consisteth of two parts, that is to say, of impassibility of the senses of the
                  body, and of impassibility of the senses of the soul. Impassibility of the body
                  taketh place when a man who is reviled restraineth himself for God’s sake and
                  speaketh not, even though he be troubled; but impassibility of the soul taketh
                  place when a man is abused and reviled, and yet is not angry in his heart when he
                  is abused, even like John Colobos. For on one occasion when the brethren were
                  sitting with him, a man passed by and upbraided him, but he was not angry, and his
                  countenance changed not; then the brethren asked him, saying, <quote>Art thou not
                  secretly troubled in thy heart, O father, being reviled in this fashion?</quote> And he
                  answered and said unto them, <quote>I am not troubled inwardly, for inwardly I am just
                  as tranquil as ye see that I am outwardly</quote>; and this is perfect impassibility. Now
                  at that time Abbâ Moses had not arrived at this state of perfection, and he
                  confessed that although outwardly he was undisturbed, yet he was waging a contest
                  in his heart, and he maintained silence and was not angry outwardly; and even this
                  was a spiritual excellence, although it would have been a more perfect thing had
                  he not been angry either inwardly or outwardly. And the blessed Nilus made a
                  comparison of these two measures of excellence in the cases of the blessed men
                  Moses and Aaron. The act of covering the breast and heart with the priestly tunic
                  which Aaron performed when he went into the Holy of Holies represented the state
                  of a man who, though angry in his heart, suppresseth his wrath by striving and
                  prayer; and the state of a man not being angry at all in the heart, because he
                  hath been exalted to perfection by [his] victory over the passions and the devils,
                  Nilus compared to that which is said of the blessed Moses, saying, <quote>Moses took the
                  breast for an offering, because the soul dwelleth in the heart, and the heart I in
                  the breast.</quote> And Solomon said, <quote>Remove anger from thy heart,</quote> and concerning Aaron
                  the Book saith, <quote>He was covering his breast with the ephod and tunic,</quote> and this
                  teacheth us monks that it is meet for us to cover over the wrath which is in the
                  heart with gentle, and humble, and tranquil thoughts, and that we should not allow
                  it to ascend to the opening of our throat, and that the odiousness and abomination
                  thereof shall be revealed by the tongue.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="670">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why is it that, although all the fathers used to admonish
                  the brethren to ask the old men questions continually, and to learn from them, and
                  to reveal to them their thoughts, and to live according to their directions, one
                  of the old men said to one of the brethren, <quote>Go, sit in thy cell, and thy cell
                  shall teach thee everything</quote>?</quote> The old man said, <quote>There is no
                  contradiction in these words of the Fathers, and what the old man said hath an
                  object, the meaning of which is well known. The old man who admonished the brother
                  that he should learn like a beginner was great and famous, and to that brother who
                  asked him the question he spake thus:—In the early days when thou goest to thy
                  cell lay hold upon the habits (or orders) of the neophytes, and live according to
                  them for a considerable period, that is to say, with fasting, and vigil, and
                  reading, and reciting the offices, and all the other things, until at length,
                  after the lapse of time, the life of contemplation in silence shall give thee the
                  order which befitteth thy seclusion, and will add those things which are seemly,
                  and will diminish those which are not. This is the meaning of that which was said
                  by the holy man, <quote>Sit in thy cell, and it shall teach thee
               everything.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="671">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>One of the old men used to say, <quote>A man shall have no care,
                  and he shall contemplate in silence, and shall cover up himself; three meditations
                  shall teach purity.</quote> What is the meaning of these three words?</quote> The old man
               said, <quote> <quote>A man shall have no care</quote> means that he shall not care concerning the
                  shortcomings of others, and that all his anxiety shall be concerning his own
                  shortcomings. And, <quote>He shall contemplate in silence</quote> means that he shall not speak
                  even concerning matters of spiritual excellence if it will trouble any man or
                  condemn him. And <quote>He shall cover up himself</quote> meaneth that he shall not reveal his
                  life and deeds, but as far as possible, he shall be unknown and unhonoured. Now by
                  these things is established the purity of heart which seeth God in a revelation of
                  light.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="672">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>How is it possible for a monk to die every day for the love
                  of Christ, even as the blessed Paul said, <quote>I swear by your boasting, my brethren,
                  that, in our Lord Jesus Christ, I die daily, and the world is dead unto me, and I
                  am crucified unto the world, and the world is crucified unto me, and I live, yet
                  not I, but Christ liveth in me</quote>?</quote> The old man said, <quote>A man [can do
                  this] if he contemplate in silence at all seasons, and perform the other works of
                  the body, I mean fasting, and vigil, and the recital of the books of the Psalms,
                  and prayers, and genuflexions, and groanings, and pain, and weeping, and tears,
                  and sighs, and the reading of the Holy Scriptures. And he must especially take
                  care concerning the works of the mind, that is, the constant remembrance of God,
                  and meditation upon Him and His blessings, and upon His commandments and His
                  threatenings; and his gaze must always be on our Lord, and his prayer must be
                  without ceasing and without wandering, and the odiousness of the passions must be
                  away from the heart, and he must suppress with keenness the thoughts of the devils
                  which arise at their prompting. And he must possess that excellence which is the
                  first and most important of all the spiritual virtues, and of all the labours of
                  the ascetic life of the mind, that is to say, death in respect of all the
                  anxieties and cares of this world. And a monk must have no care, and no anxiety,
                  and he must not think about anything, or seek anything, or desire anything, or
                  lust for anything, except for the time when he will attain to the perfect love of
                  God in our Lord Jesus Christ. And he must fulfil at all times the command of the
                  blessed Paul, and his admonition to us wherein he said, <quote>Love ye your Lord,
                  rejoice in your hope, pray without ceasing, be fervent in spirit, endure your
                  tribulations, be not anxious about anything, cast all your care upon the Lord; and
                  let all your prayers, and all your requests, and all your petitions be made known
                  unto God, to Whom be glory for ever and ever! Amen.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="673">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>How can love be acquired by men of understanding?</quote>
               The old man said, <quote>True and pure love is the way of life, and the haven of
                  promises, and the treasure of faith, and it sheweth [the way of] the kingdom, and
                  it is the expositor of the judgement, and the preacher concerning what is
                  hidden.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="674">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>We do not know the power of the word.</quote> The old man
               said, <quote>If a man doth not love God he will not believe in Him, and His promises
                  are not certain to him, and he feareth not His judgement, and he goeth not after
                  Him; but, because love is not in him, so that he may flee from iniquity, and wait
                  for the life which hath been promised, he is always performing the work of sin.
                  And he doth this because His judgement is raised too far above his eyes. Therefore
                  let us run after love, wherein the holy fathers were rich, for it is able to
                  reward its nature and its God, and this is its praise.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="675">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>In what way doth wisdom live in a man?</quote> The old man
               said, <quote>Now when a man hath gone forth to follow God with a sincere mind, grace
                  taketh up its abode in him, and his life and deeds are strengthened in the Spirit,
                  and he hath taken a hatred to the world, for he perceiveth that new spiritual life
                  which is in the new man, and which is exalted above the impurity of human life,
                  and in his mind he thinketh upon the humility of the life and works which are to
                  come, and which are [more] excellent than those here.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="676">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>By what is love made known?</quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>By the fulfilment of work, and by spiritual meditation and by the knowledge
                  of faith.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="677">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What are works?</quote> The old man said, <quote>The
                  keeping of the commandments of God in the purity of the inner man, together with
                  the [performance of] labours by the outer man.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="678">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Is every man who is destitute of works also destitute of
                  love?</quote> The old man said, <quote>It is impossible for the man who is in God
                  not to love and it is impossible that he who loveth should not work; and it is
                  incredible that he who teacheth and doth not work is indeed a believer, for his
                  tongue is the enemy of his actions, and although he speaketh life, he is in
                  subjection unto death.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="679">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>And is he who is in this state destitute of reward?</quote>
               The old man said, <quote>The man who speaketh the things of the spirit, and who
                  performeth the things of the body is not destitute of reward, and that which he
                  needeth is fulfilled for him, but he is deprived of the crown of light, because he
                  desireth not that the rule of the spirit shall have dominion over him.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="680">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Fasting and prayer: what are they?</quote> The old man
               said, <quote>Fasting is the subjugation of the body, and prayer is converse with God,
                  vigil is the war with Satan, abstinence is the being weaned from meats, standing
                  up is the humility of the primitive man, genuflexion is the bowing down before the
                  Judge, tears are the remembrance of sins, nakedness is our captivity through
                  transagression, and [reciting the] service is constant supplication and the
                  praising of God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="681">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Are these things able to redeem the soul?</quote> The old
               man said, <quote>When the things which are within agree with the things which are
                  without and the humility which is manifest appeareth in the hidden works which are
                  within, in very truth a man is redeemed from the heaviness of the
               body.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="682">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>And what is internal humility?</quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>It is humility of love, peace, concord, purity, restfulness, gentleness,
                  subjection, faith, remoteness from envy, [and it is] the soul which lacketh the
                  fervour of anger, and is remote from the lust of arrogance, and is separated from
                  vainglory, and is filled with patient endurance like the great deep, and whose
                  motion is drawn after the knowledge of the spirit, and before whose eyes is
                  depicted the departure from the body, and the great marvel of the Resurrection,
                  and the call to judgement, which [shall come] after the quickening, and its
                  standing before the awful throne of God, and the being redeemed.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="683">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Is it possible for a man to fast and not to be
                  redeemed?</quote> The old man said, <quote>There is a fasting which is a matter of
                  habit, and another which is of desire, and another which is of constraint, and
                  another which is of the sight, and another which is of vainglory, and another of
                  tribulation, and another of repentance, and another of spiritual love; and
                  although each one of them is the same outside the mind, yet in the word of
                  knowledge they are distinct. Now although the manner of each in respect of the
                  body is the same, yet each should be undertaken with thorough purpose, and a man
                  should journey straightly along the way of love, and should bear his burden with
                  spiritual patience, and he should not rejoice in his honour.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="684">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Who is the true [monk]?</quote> The old man said, <quote>He
                  who maketh his word manifest indeed, and endureth his pain patiently; with such a
                  man new life is found, and the knowledge of the spirit dwelleth in
               him.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="685">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Who is he that liveth purely?</quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>He who is free from the delights of the body, and who rejoiceth in the love
                  of his neighbours in the love of God; for in proportion as need hath rule over the
                  soul is spiritual repose produced [therein].</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="686">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>With what can we vanquish lust?</quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>With the remembrance of the good things of the spirit; for, if the desire
                  for the good things which are to come doth not abrogate the lust for the delights
                  of this world, a man cannot overcome at all. Except the merchant’s ship be laden
                  with manifold hope it will not be able to endure the storms, and will sail on the
                  path of tribulation.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="687">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>In what way doth a man go forth from the world?</quote> The
               old man said, <quote>He doeth this when he forsaketh the gratification of all his
                  lust, and when, so far as it lieth in his power, he runneth to fulfil the
                  commandments; the man who doth not do this will fall.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="688">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Through what did the men of old triumph over
                  nature?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Through the fervour of their love which
                  was above nature, and through the death of the man which is corruptible, and
                  through contempt of arrogance, and through abatement of the belly, and through the
                  fear of the judgement, and through the sure and certain promise; through the
                  desire of these glorious things the Fathers acquired in the soul a spiritual
                  body.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="689">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>How can we vanquish the passions which afflict us, since
                  they are placed in our nature?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Through your death
                  to the world, for except a man burieth himself in the grave of continence the
                  spiritual Adam can never be quickened in him. For when a dead man departeth from
                  this temporary life, he hath no perception of the world, and all his senses are at
                  rest and they are useless. Now if that which appertaineth to thy natural body thou
                  dost forsake naturally, and thou dost not do the same voluntarily in respect of
                  thine own person, thou wilt die; but if thy desire dieth through repentance, [thy]
                  nature will cease from this temporary life in the death of the spirit, even as the
                  natural emotions of the body ceased through its natural end.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="690">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>To what extent is a man held to be worthy of
                  revelations?</quote> The old man said, <quote>To the same extent as he is held to
                  be worthy to cast off sin inwardly and outwardly. For when a man dieth through
                  spiritual slaughter to all the conversation of this temporary life, and when he
                  hath committed his life to the life which is after the quickening, Divine Grace
                  alighteth upon him, and he is held to be worthy of divine revelations; for the
                  impurity of the world is a dark covering to the soul, and it preventeth it from
                  discerning spiritual meanings.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="691">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Can the man who loveth money befaithful to the
                  promises?</quote> The old man said, <quote>If he believeth why doth he possess
                  [anything]? Is our hope fixed upon gold? Or is the hand of the Lord too short to
                  redeem? He gave us the Body of our Lord for happiness, and His holy Blood as a
                  drink unto our redemption; and hath He kept back from us the loaf of bread and the
                  apparel which grow old? He who loveth money hath a doubt in his mind concerning
                  God, and he prepareth [the means of] life before God giveth them unto him; and,
                  although in his words he rejoiceth in the promises, he maketh them to be a lie by
                  his deeds.True is the word of our Lord, Who said, <quote>It is as difficult for a rich
                  man to enter into the kingdom of God, as for a camel to go into the eye of a
                  needle</quote> (St. Matthew 19:24); to possess both God and mammon in one abode is
                  impossible. Now those who follow the ascetic life do not belong to the things
                  which are seen.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="692">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Who is truly the man of ascetic excellence?” The old man said,
               ‘He who at all times crieth out that he is a sinner, and asketh mercy from the Lord,
               whose speech beareth the sense of discretion, whose feelings bear the excellence of
               works, who though silent yet speaketh, and who though speaking yet holdeth his peace,
               and whose acts and deeds bear good fruit to his temporary life and the manifestation
               of Christ.”</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="693">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Which is the way of life?</quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>That whereby a man goeth forth from this world in his entrance into the
                  other; but if a man forsaketh his childhood of humility, and cometh to the old age
                  of this world in his love, he revealeth the way of life. Now the true departure
                  from this world is remoteness therefrom.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="694">
            <p>A brother said, <quote>What shall I do to this world when it troubleth me?</quote>
               The old man said, <quote>The world troubleth thee because the cares thereof are in
                  thy mind, and love therefor is in thy body, and its delights are in thy heart. Let
                  the world depart from thee, and tear out from thee all the roots (or branches)
                  thereof, and lo, the war thereof will cease from thee. For as long as thy body
                  seeketh [its] pleasures, and its lust is of the world, it is impossible for thee
                  to live.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="695">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is pure prayer?</quote> The old man said, <quote>That
                  which is of few words and is abundant in deeds. For if [thy] actions be not more
                  than thy petition, thy prayers are mere words wherein the seed of the hands is
                  not; and if it be not thus, why do we ask and not receive, since the mercy of
                  Grace aboundeth. The manner of the penitent is one thing, and the labour of the
                  humble is another; the penitent are hirelings, but the humble are
               sons.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="696">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>By what is the love of money produced?</quote> The old man
               said, <quote>From lust, for except a man lusteth he will not possess [money], and if
                  he doth not possess [money] he will not lust. When a man lusteth he possesseth
                  [money], and having acquired it he fulfilleth his lust; and having fulfilled his
                  lust, he becometh greedy, and having become greedy he committeth fraud; and having
                  committed fraud his possessions increase, and when his possessions have increased
                  love becometh little in him. And when love hath diminished the remembrance of God
                  is wanting in the heart, and the intelligence becometh darkened, and his power of
                  discernment becometh blinded, and when the power of discernment hath become
                  blinded, the power of distinguishing is darkened, and when the power of
                  distinguishing hath become darkened, the soul goeth blind. And when the soul hath
                  become blind goodness is rooted out therefrom, and wickedness entereth in, and sin
                  hath dominion; and when sin hath obtained dominion the thought of God is blotted
                  out, the passions of the body are roused up, and they seek for the means for
                  working out their needs. And when they have obtained that which they seek it
                  becometh necessary for much money to be gathered together, and when money hath
                  multiplied the pleasure of the body is fulfilled, and a man eateth, and drinketh,
                  and committeth adultery and fornication, and he lieth and acteth fraudulently, and
                  transgresseth the covenant, and he destroyeth the Law, and despiseth the promises,
                  and lust is fulfilled, and God is wroth. For if the lust for the things which are
                  seen be hated in our sight, we shall not love money, but if we perform the lust of
                  the flesh it is necessary to love money, because it belongeth to the flesh and not
                  to the spirit, even as the Apostle said, ‘The flesh hurteth the spirit, and the
                  spirit the flesh, and both are opponents each of other</quote></quote> (Galatians
               5:17).</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="697">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What kind of prayer is that which is not acceptable before
                  God?</quote> The old man said, <quote>[The prayer for the] destruction of enemies.
                  When we ask that evil things [may come] upon those who do harm to us, and for
                  bodily health, and abundance of possessions, and fertility in respect of children,
                  these requests are not acceptable before God. If God beareth with us, who are
                  sinners and who offend Him, how much more is it right that we should bear each
                  with the other? It is, then, not meet that we should ask for the things which
                  concern the body, for the wisdom of God provideth everything
               [necessary].</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="698">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is purity of soul?</quote> The old man said,
                  <quote>Remoteness from anger, and the error of remembrance of evil things, being
                  weaned from a bitter disposition, friendliness towards our enemies, peace which is
                  superior to troubling, and sincere love which is above the world; by means of
                  these the hidden man is purified, and he putteth on Christ, and is
                  redeemed.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="699">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is envy?</quote> The old man said, Hatred towards the
               virtues of others, and wickedness towards the good, and a bitter disposition towards
               the innocent, and anger against those who are prosperous in this world, and the
               concealment of the upright acts and deeds of the penitent, and vexation at the peace
               of the friends of God.”</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="700">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>In what way ought we to pray before God?</quote> The old
               man said, <quote>For the repentance of sinners, and the finding of the lost, and the
                  drawing nigh of those who are afar off, and friendliness towards those who do us
                  harm, and love towards those who persecute us, and sorrowful care for those who
                  provoke God to wrath. And if a man doeth these things truly and with a penitent
                  mind, the sinners will often gain life, and the living soul will be redeemed. Now
                  the prayer which our Lord delivered to us as to the needs of the body, is one
                  which applieth to the whole community, and it was not uttered for the sake of
                  those who are strangers to the world, and with whom the pleasures of the body are
                  held in contempt. He in whose habitation (or life) the kingdom of God and His
                  righteousness are found lacketh nothing, even when he asketh not.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="701">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>What is remoteness from the world?</quote> The old man
               said, <quote>The thought which vanquisheth the love of the body, for if the body be
                  not trodden down by the lust of patient endurance, a man cannot conquer in the
                  fight.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="702">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Can the soul of a man who is held fast in the love of the
                  things which are seen be pleasing unto God?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Who
                  is able to live in chastity when the body is making demands upon him? Or, how can
                  be found the love of our Lord in the soul which hath its abode with the things
                  which are seen and are corruptible? No man can serve two masters, and the soul
                  cannot please God with spiritual excellence so long as the remembrances of
                  corruptible things are in its mind, for the mind of the flesh is not able to
                  please God; except the world dieth out of the heart humility cannot live therein,
                  and except the body be deprived of its lusts, the soul cannot be purified from
                  thoughts.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="703">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Why is the mind disturbed at the meeting with
                  females?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Because they are employed in the
                  fulfilment of the lust of nature. When the gaze falleth upon the structure which
                  [is intended for] the production of children, and for the pleasures of the body,
                  the poison of olden time seizeth upon a man, and the law of his will becometh
                  confused; now the will conquereth nature, not by the stirring up of the passions,
                  but by the fulfilment of works. The humble by the power of our Lord conquer
                  everything by their love through the patient endurance of the merit of our
                  Lord.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="704">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Who is the mightier man? He who is remote from the world,
                  or he who dwelleth therein?</quote> The old man said, <quote>The mighty man,
                  wheresoever he dwelleth, conquereth whether he be in the world or out of it. Now
                  the Fathers departed to the desert place which was free from noise and tumult,
                  because they were afraid that so long as they abode in the body the passions which
                  afflicted them would cleave unto them; but those who have completed the great
                  strife of their contest in the world [have performed] an act of grace the power
                  whereof hath worked, and still worketh, for the help and benefit of the community.
                  And verily their crown shall be a great one, because into the disturbed and
                  troubled sea of the world their spiritual ship, which was on its way to heaven
                  along the straight path which was full of fear, hath not gone down.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="705">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>If a man maketh himself a stranger to the world, is it
                  helpful to his soul?</quote> The old man said, <quote>If it fulfilleth with praise
                  it is helpful, and if it endureth tribulation in chastity, and rejoiceth in our
                  Lord, it is beneficial, but it is not, if it doeth away the good seed and
                  preventethit from producing beloved fruit unto God. If it beareth and is blessed,
                  it hath a reward, but if it lack these things it becometh a wandering to the mind,
                  and a sight which is profitless; but best of all these things is the tranquillity
                  of the mind which is nigh unto God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="706">
            <p>The brethren said, <quote>Since all the creatures which God hath made are holy, why
                  were the Fathers in the habit of making the sign of the blessed Cross over such of
                  them as they ate as food?</quote> The old man said, <quote>Verily, all God’s
                  creatures are pure, through the Grace of Him that created them, yet, because sin
                  obtained dominion, every one of them became polluted; then came the advent of our
                  Lord and abrogated sin, and righteousness obtained dominion, and everything became
                  sanctified, whether it was in the heaven or on the earth. But because the blessed
                  Fathers knew the harmful disposition of Satan, who even by means of such things as
                  are used as food carrieth on a war to our injury, they sealed their foods with the
                  holy sign of the Great Cross, that they might bring to naught all the crafts of
                  the Calumniator. For one of the old men said, <quote>On one occasion, when I was lying
                  down at night, I thirsted for water to drink. And there was near me a holy man who
                  lived chastely, and he saw me take up a vessel of water to drink without having
                  made over it the sign of the Cross. And he said unto me, <quote>Wait, master,
                  wait,</quote> and he made the sign of the Cross over it, and straightway there
               fell from the vessel the Calumniator in the form of a flash of fire; and both he and
               I saw this, and we marvelled at the great power of the Redeemer, and at the wonderful
               sign of Hismerit.</quote> Another version of the story reads:—And one of the Fathers said,
               On one occasion I was lying down at night, and I thirsted for water to drink. And
               there was near me a certain widow, who led a chaste life, both when she was with her
               husband, and afterwards, and she said to me, <quote>Wait, master, wait,</quote> and she made the
               sign of the Holy Cross over the vessel of water, and straightway the Calumniator fell
               from the vessel in the form of a flash of fire; and both she and I saw it, and we
               marvelled at the great power of our Redeemer, and at the wonderful sign of Hismerit.
               These things were indeed spoken by that holy mouth which was remote from falsehood.
               Therefore we must necessarily do this (i.e., make the sign of the Cross over our
               food) for the protection of our life. For against this holy woman who did these
               things, the enemy waged war openly, according to what I have learned from a certain
               saint, a chosen man of God, who heard the matter from her own mouth, and he spake
               thus:—The blessed woman spake unto me, saying, One day I went to the house of God,
               and Satan drew nigh, and said unto me, Why dost thou pray like a man, and say, Glory
               be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghost? And I said unto him, If I am
               not to pray thus, how shall I pray? And the blessed woman said, Satan said unto me,
               Pray thus, and say, Glory be unto thee, O Mary, mother of Christ. Then I answered and
               said unto him, [There are] ashes in thine eyes, O Satan. Why should I forsake the
               Lord and adore the mother? And Satan disappeared. And the blessed man also said unto
               me, This same old woman said unto me:—On another occasion I went to church according
               to custom, and I knelt down and prayed, and then the Enemy came and made blind mine
               eyes, and I could not see, and I called to one of the women, and she led me to my
               house. After three days Satan departed from before mine eyes, and he began to go away
               from before me, and then I said unto him, There is something which I must make thee
               do. Go thou to the place where thou didst seize upon me; and we went to the church,
               both he and I, and I left him where he seized upon me. Then I went away a short
               distance, and when I turned and looked at him I saw that he was standing like a
               shadow; and I went on again, and then turned, and still I saw him. And I shut the
               door of the temple and went forth, and then I opened it again and went in, and I saw
               him still standing [there], and at that time his wiles ceased from me. Such were the
               great things which happened to that blessed old woman. For the monk must not boast
               himself over the man who liveth in the world, for there are mighty men in the world;
               for if such qualities are found in Eve, how much greater ones should be found in the
               Adam which is redeemed by Adam?</quote></p>
            <p><quote>One of the Fathers said unto me, <quote>One night whilst I was sleeping, the Enemy
                  came and smote me, and said unto me, <quote>Get thee into the world and cultivate
                  righteousness, for why dost thou shut thyself up like a beast in caves?</quote>
               And knowing the wickedness of the Enemy, who was looking at me with an evil eye, I
               made the sign of the Cross in his face, and he fled from me. Then he waited a few
               days, and came and smote me on the neck, and said unto me mockingly, <quote>Now thou
                  art a righteous man, rise up, and get thee into the world, that I may not destroy
                  thee</quote>; and having prayed, and made the sign of the Cross over my face, he
               departed from me. And a little while afterwards he came again, and sat upon my neck;
               then I made myself bold, and stood up, and made the sign of the Cross, the emblem of
               merit, before him, and again he disappeared, for he was unable to resist me. For all
               these things took place, and happened in very truth, and we may therefore know and
               understand that there is no rule of life in which God so much rejoiceth, or which is
               so terrible unto the devils, and unto all evil spirits, as the rule of humility, and
               penitence of mind, and the subjection of the body, and remoteness from the things
               which are seen. Whosoever despiseth these things will fall into the mire of the
               world; and whosoever holdeth in contempt the good riches of the fear of God, shall
               have his hope of the inheritance of the saints cut off, and of the delights of
               heaven, which never pass away and never end. May we all be held worthy of these
               through the grace and mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ, the True God, to Whom, with His
               Father, and the Holy Spirit, be glory, now, and always, and for ever and ever!
               Amen.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
