<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3004">To Bishop Constantine of Seleucia</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp> proofreading and metadata added by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#iaimone">Isabelle S.
                  Aimone</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m"> The Sixth Book of the Select Letters
                     of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of
                        Antioch</persName> in the Syriac Version of <persName
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">3-11</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.1">
            <pb n="3"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">To <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/1839"
                  >Constantine</persName> the bishop.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those before episcopacy, from the 2nd book the
               12th letter.</head>
            <p> The contents of your sanctity's former epistle to me are as far from applying to my
               vileness as the heaven is far from the earth, to use the words of the prophet. <note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"> Ps. cii. I I. </note>
               For you thought fit to recite to me the passage of the Song of Songs, I mean, "Thou
               art all fair, my neighbour, and there is no spot [in thee."<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"> Ca. iv. 7. </note>
               ...]. I [am turned] into another man, as it is written<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"> I R. x. 6. </note>
               and prophesy, and that not one of all your words shall fall <pb n="4"/> to the
               ground. For he is faithful who said to you high priests, "Ye shall call my name upon
               the sons of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, and I the <persName>Lord</persName> will
               hallow them."<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"> Nu.
                  vi. 27. </note> However, let these things be so. But know, father ours, that,
               after the holy <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/2428">Asterius</persName>
               the bishop and those with him came here, many various .................... will cast
               those that are deceived into a pit of destruction. But all, so to speak, have the one
               object only, to bring to naught the <emp><foreign language="Latin"
                  >typos</foreign></emp> or formula of satisfaction<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"><emp><foreign
                        language="Greek">πληροφορία.</foreign></emp></note> which seemed good to the
               pious king, which he also sent to <placeName>Flavian</placeName>, the prelate of the
               city of <placeName>Antiochus</placeName>, and either altogether to remove and abolish
               it, or to cut away some of its exactitude, because they do not intend to drink the
               still water, as says Ezekiel, but strive to foul it with their own feet<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"> Eze. xxxiv. 18.
               </note>, in order that the sheep which have learned to hear the voice of the Good
               Shepherd, and to drink "the water of Shiloah that goeth softly,"<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"> Is. viii. 6. </note>
               may not be able to avoid the pollution of the drink. Which <persName
                  ref="https://syriaca.org/person/2529">John</persName> of
                  <placeName>Claudiupolis</placeName> also tried to do when he came here. When he
               received me in the house of the glorious <persName
                  ref="https://syriaca.org/person/2453">Patrick</persName>, the Master of the
                  Soldiers,<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer">
                  <emp><foreign language="Greek">στρατηλάτης.</foreign></emp></note> and conversed
               with me by order of our pious king, he said, "There ought to be introduced into the
               formula of satisfaction<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks"
                  rend="footer"><emp><foreign language="Greek">πληροφορία.</foreign></emp></note>
               <pb n="5"/> this statement, 'We receive the synod at
               <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, not as a definition of faith, but as a rejection of
                  <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/655">Nestorius</persName> and of
                  <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/482">Eutyches</persName>.'<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"
                  ><!--Cf.needs to be italized.--> Cf. Zach. Rh. ix 20<emp><foreign language="latin"
                        >ad fin.</foreign></emp>Evag, iii. 31.</note> Thus both those that are
               pleased with the Synod will not be angry, and you will receive contentment in that
               the doctrines which offend you are rejected." But I said, "This argument is silly,
               and the offspring of a drunken mind. Who is there among right-minded persons who will
               accept and praise us on account of this disturbance and confusion? If the <persName
                  ref="https://syriaca.org/person/482">Synod of Chalcedon</persName> introduced the
               doctrine of <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/655">Nestorius</persName> into
               the churches, though it called <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/655"
                  >Nestorius</persName> 'of small intelligence'<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer">Mansi vii. 113.</note>
               in order to entice and deceive those that are more simple, how can we say that it
               rejected the opinion of <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/655"
                  >Nestorius</persName>? But, if the formula of satisfaction<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"><emp><foreign
                        language="Greek">πληροφορία.</foreign></emp></note> in so many words rejects
               the doctrines of the <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/482">Synod</persName>
               and of the impious Tome of Leo<!--is this a person or place??-->, which are the life
               blood of the abomination of <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/655"
                  >Nestorius</persName>, how can we honestly say that we accept this synod as
               against <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/655">Nestorius</persName>? ...
               rather we shall be tripped up as by ..." "What then? Were not those at
                  <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> rightly moved against <persName
                  ref="https://syriaca.org/person/482">Eutyches</persName>? why, [if] you accept
               them on this point, do you think them fit ... an anathema?" [But] I said, "What I am
               about to say is strange, but nevertheless true. It is especially for this reason that
               we say that they are men that deserve anathema, because they unnecessarily extended
               the <pb n="6"/> heresy of <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/482"
                  >Eutyches</persName>. Owing to the fact that they wished to heal the disorder in
               an unintelligent way by means of an opposite infection, I mean by the evil impiety of
                  <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/655">Nestorius</persName>, thenceforward
               those who were infected with the belief in a phantasy, seeing that they were inviting
               them to man-worship, recoiled from this vicious remedy, and thought themselves all
               the more pious, and carried their own corruption further. But, if they had been cured
               and healed by means of right doctrines, they would perhaps have abandoned their
               infection. [If] we accept those [who] met together [at]
                  <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> as being adversaries [of] the heresy of <persName
                  ref="https://syriaca.org/person/482">Eutyches</persName>, and praise them on the
               ground that they spoke well up to a certain point, and do not rather blame them, it
               is time for us to accept also the <persName>
                  <!--uh...--> Arian</persName> heresy, which contends against the evil opinion of
                  <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/1438">Sabellius</persName>, and agrees
               up to a certain point with the right doctrines of the Church, in that it glorifies
                  <persName>God the unbegotten Father</persName>, and in that it does not confound
               the three substances, but confines them within their own attributes or persons. But
               we do not extol it on this account, nor do we judge it to deserve a partial anathema.
               But, because it calls the <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/2245"
                  >Son</persName> and the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName> creatures, and degrades
               them to a servile position, on this account it is utterly repudiated by the orthodox
               doctors of the Church. This same trick we find practised by the other heresies also.
               By displaying a certain part of the sound faith as a decoy and mixing<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"> This is the meaning
                  needed, though I cannot supply the word. </note> with this the vanity of their <pb
                  n="7"/> own profane words they thus appear plausible to those that are more
               innocent and simple; but we do not, on account of the sound part, hold back and
               shrink from repudiating them, but we anathematize them with all our power." When the
               good and excellent <persName> John</persName> had heard these things, he betook
               himself to another topic.<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks"
                  rend="footer"><emp><foreign language="greek">κεφάλαιον.</foreign></emp>
               </note> He asked me whether <persName>Epiphanius</persName> the bishop,"<note
                  resp="https://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"
                  ><!--Cf.needs to be italized.--> Cf. Zach. Rh. v. 5.</note> who is among the
               saints, performed our ordinations fitly and in accordance with the canon. But I said,
               "Very well and most properly," and "after the pattern of the doctors and stablishers
               of the word of the orthodox faith. For he in his boyhood was brought up in
               monasteries, and practised a virginity modelled on the angelic and unembodied life,
               being a citizen of <placeName>Perga</placeName>: a man of no ignoble city, as it is
                  written<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer">Ac. xxxi.
                  39.</note>, yes, and a man of noble birth also, if these things are not small to
               the citizens of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> above. Having been advanced to the
               bishopric of <placeName>Magydum</placeName> (this also is a city in
                  <placeName>Pamphylia</placeName>) at the time of the
                  <persName>Encyclical</persName> which repudiated the impiety that was confirmed at
               <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, under which <persName resp="http://syriaca.org/person/2130">Timothy</persName>, who
               was sent into exile for piety's sake, returned to
               <placeName resp="http://syriaca.org/place/641"><persName>Alexander<!--the Great--></persName>'s city</placeName>, and received back
               the presidency of the flock of <persName resp="http://syriaca.org/person/1871">Mark</persName> the Evangelist, which before
               was unrighteously tended by wolves and torn, when he saw that the bishops had
               changed, and that they had overthrown the Encyclical by a contrary <pb n="8"/>
               document, and had gone back to the <persName resp="http://syriaca.org/person/>Synod</persName> of
                  <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and its hateful doctrines, he left his throne and
                  <placeName>Pamphylia</placeName>, the land of his fathers, and the blessed man
               came as a fugitive to <placeName><persName>Alexander</persName>'s city</placeName>,
               and embraced communion with the saintly <persName>Timothy</persName>, the champion of
               the right faith, having taken joyfully upon him the spoiling of his goods, and
               knowing that he had in heaven a better and enduring inheritance, as the wise
                  <persName>Paul</persName> says.<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks"
                  rend="footer">He. x. 34.</note> But, when <persName>Timothy</persName> of holy
               memory had finished his course and kept his faith<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer">2 Ti. iv. 7.</note>
               and departed to <persName>God</persName>, the zealots of the orthodox faith were
               again persecuted in <placeName><persName>Alexander</persName>'s city</placeName>, and
               the correct word was perturbed by certain men's mixture. Then therefore the blessed
                  <persName>Epiphanius</persName> withdrew to <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, the
               stranger on the earth, who did not know any city of his own, or rather knew that only
               as his own in which <persName>God</persName> over all is purely worshipped. And,
               having associated with <persName>Peter</persName> of <placeName>Iberia</placeName> of
               holy memory, the <persName>God</persName>-clad man, who was bishop of one of the
               cities in <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, and with the other holy fathers and
               orthodox peoples, he was persuaded by them and ordained priests, not going beyond the
               meaning of the sacred canons (far be it!) The canon that forbids a bishop to perform
               an ordination in provinces<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks"
                  rend="footer"><emp><foreign language="greek">έπαρχίας.</foreign></emp></note> or
               parishes which do not belong to him<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer">Mansi ii. 1313,
                  1317</note> comes into play in cases where he forces himself upon other men's
               countries in a disorderly fashion and without an invita<pb n="9"/>tion from anyone,
               not when he is persuaded to ordain by the bishop of the country or city and by the
               orthodox clergymen, especially in time of persecution. We may find such instances
               also if we study church histories. In the times of the <persName>Arians</persName>,
               when the servants of piety were persecuted and suffered every kind of evil,
                  <persName>Eusebius</persName> the bishop of <placeName>Samosata</placeName> (this
               is one of the cities of <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>) went about the cities and
               deserts and villages, and travelled to countries outside the boundaries, wearing a
               soldier's dress and having his head covered by a hood, and applied his sacred hand
               and confirmed priests for places that were in need; who also put on a crown of
               martyrdom, having his head crushed by a stone by the heterodox, and migrated in
               saintly fashion to <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/2245">Jesus</persName>
               who longed for him, and was admitted to the heavenly mansions. These things are
               clearly stated by <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/781">Theodoret</persName>
               in his church history.<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks"
                  rend="footer">Theod. H.E. v. 4.</note> The great light of the
                  <persName>Cappadocians</persName> also, or rather of the whole world, <persName
                  ref="https://syriaca.org/person/2617">Basil</persName> the bishop, the pillar of
               the church, the 'sure foundation'<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks"
                  rend="footer">2 Ti. ii. 19.</note> (for these words of the apostle fit him more
               than any man, as fine raiment a bride), was raised to the throne of the bishopric,
               receiving ordination to the episcopacy, by bishops outside the boundaries. This
                  <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/511">Gregory</persName> the Theologian
               says in the funeral discourse on <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/2617"
                  >Basil</persName> himself, writing thus: 'He is raised to the high throne of the
               bishopric, not without toil nor without envy and contention on <pb n="10"/> the part
               of the prelates of the country, and of the worst men of the city who ranged
               themselves with these; however, the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName> was bound to
               conquer: yes, and it does conquer, gaining an easy victory. For from outside the
               boundaries it stirs up men to anoint, men distinguished and zealous in the matter of
                  piety.'<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer">Or.
                  xliii. 37.</note> But, if <persName ref="https://syriaca.org/person/2617"
                  >Basil</persName>, the teacher of orthodoxy and rule and law of all church
               discipline, was anointed and received ordination (for this is the anointing of a
               high-priest) from those outside the boundaries, because the people of the country or
                  province<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"
                        ><emp><foreign language="greek">έπαρχία.</foreign></emp></note> were jealous
               of him, on account of the <placeName>Arian</placeName> heresy or for other human
               reasons, which is a very small thing, how can we say that the ordinations that were
               performed among us by a man outside the boundaries, when the transgression of
                  <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and the <placeName>Nestorian</placeName> heresy
               bare rule and prevailed, are not to be approved? and we have such great and wonderful
               instances of holy men and such as these, whose zeal is resembled by ours. But what
               shall we for our part say of the ordinations that are now performed in the churches?
               What canon respecting these is not trampled upon? Are not high-priesthoods now
               everywhere for sale, as we see in the case of civil governorship of cities (the other
               things I pass over, lest by falling into evil speaking or backbiting and saying
               things suited to other men I be thought to be choosing for myself matters that do not
               concern me)?" While I was saying these things, the <pb n="11"/> gentle <persName>
                  <!--lol, which one??--> John</persName> covered his face. But since perhaps, even
               after he has returned to you, he will again circulate the same suggestions (for this
               is the habit of those who cause confusion), I have thought it right to make known to
               your sanctity the details of our honest and lawful discussion of this matter in this
               royal city. As to the state of our affairs, I think the religious presbyter <persName
                  ref="https://syriaca.org/person/2008">Peter</persName> has once already given you
               information by letter upon each several point. Still it is a matter for your saintly
               prayers that the <persName>Lord</persName>, as is said in the Psalms, after we have
               "passed through fire and water" may "bring us out into a place of refreshment."<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer">Ps. lvx. 12.</note>
               But you as watchful shepherds and strict disciples of the chief shepherd <persName
                  ref="https://syriaca.org/persons/2245">Jesus</persName>, who brought us up with
               Him from among the dead by the blood of the everlasting covenant, "stand fast in the
               faith, quit you like men, and be strong. Let all your things be done with"<note
                  resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer">1 Co. xvi. 13.</note>
               orthodoxy or the right opinions. For you have "chosen the good part, which shall not
               be taken away from"<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks" rend="footer"
                  >Lu. x. 42.</note> you. And we believe that the whole lump also will coalesce with
               your holy first fruit<note resp="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks"
                  rend="footer">Ro. xi. 16.</note> and be kneaded: for through your prayers we have
               in all our troubles gained experience of the help of <persName>God</persName>, and
               the comfort of hopes of success has not departed from us. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
            <note resp="#compiler">Letters like this, of the same tenour, were written to the
               patricians also, and to Oecumenius.</note>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
