<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Of Love, And Charity, And Of The Welcoming Of
               Strangers</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_9">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_9 </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 9: Of Love, And Charity, And Of The Welcoming Of Strangers</head>
         <div type="saying" n="393">
            <p>A certain old man used to dwell with a brother in a cell in a friendly manner, and he
               was a man of compassionate disposition; now a famine broke out, and the people began
               to be hungry, and they came to him that they might receive charity, and he gave bread
               unto them all. And when the brother saw that he was giving away large quantities of
               bread, he said unto the old man, <quote>Give me my portion of the bread</quote>; and the old man
               said unto him, Take [it],” and he divided [what there was] and gave him [his share],
               and the brother took it from him for himself. And the old man was compassionate, and
               gave away bread from his portion, and many folk heard [that he was doing this] and
               came unto him, and when God saw the generosity of the old man He blessed his bread;
               but the brother took all his portion and ate it up, and when he saw that his bread
               was finished, and that the portion of the old man was still lasting, he made entreaty
               unto him, saying, <quote>My portion hath come to an end, and this [bread of thine is all]
               that I have; receive me as a partner [therein].</quote> And the old man said unto him,
               <quote>Good,</quote> and he associated him with himself again. And when there was abundance
               [again], the people came to take [bread] from him, and he gave it unto them again.
               Now it came to pass that they lacked bread, and the brother went and found that bread
               was wanting, and a poor man came for some, and the old man said unto the brother, <quote>Go
               in and give him some,</quote> and the brother said, <quote>There is none</quote>; for he was filled with
               bread. The old man said, <quote>Go in and search [for some],</quote> and <pb n="88"/>having gone in he found
               that the place wherein they used to set [the bread] was filled with loaves to the
               very top, and he took [some] and gave to the poor man, and he was afraid. Thus that
               brother knew the excellence and the faith of the old man, and he gave thanks unto
               God, and glorified Him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="394">
            <p>Two brethren went to the market to sell their wares, and whilst one of them had gone
               to perform the service, he who was left by himself fell into fornication; and the
               other brother came and said unto him, <quote>My brother, let us go to the cell,</quote> but he
               said unto him, <quote>I cannot go, for I have fallen into fornication.</quote> Now whilst he was
               seeking to do better, the brother began to swear to him, saying, <quote>I also, when I was
               away from thee, fell in the same manner, nevertheless, come, and let us repent
               together, and it may happen that God will pardon us.</quote> And when they came to their
               cells they informed the old men about the temptation which had come to them, and
               whatsoever the old men told them to do the two brothers did, and the one brother
               repented with the other, just as if he had sinned with him. Now God saw the labour of
               his love, and in a few days He sent a revelation unto one of the old men concerning
               the matter, saying, <quote>For the sake of the love of that brother who did not sin,
               forgive thou him that did commit sin.</quote> This is what is meant by the words, <quote>A man
               should lay down his soul for his friend.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="395">
            <p>And they also say that there was a certain self-denying and ascetic brother who
               wished to go to the city to sell his handiwork, and to buy the things which he
               needed; and he called a brother, and said unto him, <quote>Come with me, and let us go and
               return together.</quote> And when they had gone as far as the gate of the city, the man of
               abstinence said unto his companion, <quote>Sit down here, O my brother, and wait for me
               while I go in and perform my business; and I will return speedily.</quote> And having gone
               into the city, and wandered round about in the streets, a certain rich woman tried
               her blandishments upon him, and he stripped off his monk’s garb and took her to wife.
               Then he sent a message to his companion, saying, <quote>Arise, get thee to thy cell, for I
               can never see thee again</quote>; now the man who had been sent to him with this message
               related unto him the whole matter, even as it had happened, and he said to the
               messenger, <quote>God forbid that such things should be spoken about my holy brethren, and
               God forbid that I should depart from this place until my brother cometh, according to
               his word to me.</quote> And having tarried there a long time, and ceasing not from weeping
               and praying either by night or by day, the report of him was heard throughout the
               city, and the clergy, and the monks, and the governors of the <pb n="89"/>city entreated him to
               depart to his monastery, but he would not hearken unto their supplication, and he
               said, <quote>I cannot transgress my brother’s command, and I cannot leave this place until
               we go back together to the monastery.</quote> So he stayed there for seven years, being
               burned by heat in the summer, and dried up by the cold and ice in the winter, and
               with hunger, and thirst, and weeping and watching, he made supplication on behalf of
               his brother. Then at length one day his former companion himself came unto him,
               dressed in costly garments, and said unto him, <quote>O So-and-so, I am he who was with
               thee the monk So-and-so, arise, get thee gone to thy monastery</quote>; and the brother
               looked at him and said, Thou art not, for he was a monk, and thou art a man in the
               world.” Then God looked upon the trouble of that brother, and at the end of the seven
               years the woman died, and the brother who [had married her] repented, and again put
               on the garb of the monk, and went out to his companion; and when he saw him, he rose
               up, and embraced him and kissed him, and he took him with gladness, and they went
               forth to the monastery. Then that brother renewed his former ascetic works, and he
               was worthy of the highest grade of perfection. Thus by the patience of one man the
               other lived, and the saying, <quote>A brother is helped by his brother, even as a city is
               helped by its fortress,</quote> was fulfilled.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="396">
            <p>On one occasion two old men came to an old man, whose custom was not to eat every
               day; and when he saw them he rejoiced, and said, <quote>Fasting hath its reward, and he who
               eateth for the sake of love fulfilleth two commandments, for he setteth aside his own
               desire and he fulfilleth the commandment, and refresheth the brethren.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="397">
            <p>They used to tell the story of a certain brother who fell into sin, and he came unto
               Abbâ <persName>Lôt</persName>, and he was perplexed and confused, and was going in and coming out, and was
               unable to rest. And Abbâ <persName>Lôt</persName> said unto him, <quote>What is the matter with thee, O my
               brother?</quote> and he said, <quote>I have committed a great sin, and I am unable to confess it
               before the fathers.</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Confess it unto me, and I will bear
               it</quote>; and then the brother said unto him, <quote>I have fallen into fornication, and I
               thought thou hadst discovered the matter.</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>Be of good
               courage, for there remaineth repentance; get thee gone and sit in thy habitation, and
               fast for two weeks, and I will bear with thee one half of thy sin</quote>; and at the end of
               three weeks it was revealed unto the old man that God had accepted the repentance of
               that brother, and he remained with the old man, and was subject unto him until the
               day of his death.</p>
            <pb n="90"/>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="398">
            <p>Certain of the fathers came to <persName>Joseph</persName> to ask him a question about welcoming the
               strangers who came to them, that is to say, whether it was fitting for a man to
               forsake his work, and to be with them in the ordinary way or not; and before they
               asked him, he said unto his disciple, <quote>Lay to heart that which I am about to do this
               day, and wait.</quote> Then the old man placed two pillows, one on his right hand, and the
               other on his left, and he said unto the fathers, <quote>Sit ye down</quote>; and he went into his
               cell, and put on the apparel of beggars, and went forth to them; and again, he took
               this off, and put on the beautiful apparel of the monks, and he went forth again, and
               passed among them; and he went in again and took this off, and having put on his own
               clothes, he sat down in their midst, and they marvelled at the doings of the old man.
               Then he said unto them, <quote>Have ye understood what I did?</quote> and they said unto him,
               <quote>Yes.</quote> He said unto them, <quote>What is it?</quote> And they said unto him, <quote>Thou didst put on
               first of all the apparel of beggars</quote>; he said unto them, <quote>Peradventure I have been
               changed by that disgraceful apparel?</quote> and they said unto him, <quote>No.</quote> The old man said
               unto them, <quote>Since I have not myself been changed by all these changes of raiment, for
               the first change brought no loss upon me and the second did not change me, so are we
               in duty bound to welcome the brethren, according to the command of the Gospel, which
               saith, <quote>Give to Caesar the things of Caesar, and to God the things of God</quote> (St.
               Matthew 22:21). Therefore, whensoever strange brethren arrive we must welcome them
               gladly, for it is when we are alone that it is necessary for us to suffer.</quote> Now when
               the fathers heard [these words] they marvelled that he had spoken unto them that
               which was in their hearts before they asked him, and they glorified God, and departed
               with rejoicing; and they received his word as if it had [come] from God, and they
               accepted what he had said, and did it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="399">
            <p>They used to speak about an old man, who was from Syria, and who used to dwell on the
               road of the desert of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and whose work was as follows:—At whatever time a monk
               came to him he would welcome him. And it came to pass that on one occasion a man came
               from the desert and asked him to allow him to rest, but he would not permit him to do
               so, and said unto him, <quote>I am fasting.</quote> Then the blessed man was grieved and said unto
               him, <quote>Is this thy labour, that thou wilt not perform thy brother’s desire? I beseech
               thee to come, and let us pray, and let us follow after him with whom this tree, which
               is here with us, shall bow.</quote> Then the man from the desert knelt down, and nothing
               happened, but when he who received strangers knelt down, that tree inclined its head
               at <pb n="91"/>the same time, and seeing this he profited, and they glorified God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="400">
            <p>On one occasion Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName> came to a certain place to eat with the brethren, and
               there was there a brother concerning whom evil reports were abroad, for it had
               happened that a woman had come and entered his cell. And when all the people who were
               living in that place heard [of this], they were troubled, and they gathered together
               to expel that brother from his cell, and learning that the blessed Bishop <persName>Ammon</persName> was
               there, they came and entreated him to go with them. Now when the brother knew [this],
               he took the woman and hid her under an earthenware vessel. And much people having
               assembled, and Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName>, understanding what that brother had done, for the sake of
               God hid the matter. And he went in and sat upon the earthenware vessel, and commanded
               that the cell of the brother should be searched, but although they examined the place
               they found no one there. Then Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName> answered and said, <quote>What is this that ye
               have done? May God forgive you</quote>; and he prayed and said, <quote>Let all the people go
               forth,</quote> and finally he took the brother by the hand, and said unto him, <quote>Take heed to
               thy soul, O my brother,</quote> and having said this he departed, and he refused to make
               public the matter of the brother.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="401">
            <p>There were two brethren who lived in the wilderness, and they were neighbours, and
               one of them used to hide whatsoever he gained from his work, whether it was bread or
               whether it was oboli, and place it with his companion’s goods; now the other brother
               did not know this, but he wondered how it was that his goods increased so much. One
               day, however, he suddenly caught him doing this, and he strove with him, saying, <quote>By
               means of thy corporeal things thou hast robbed me of my spiritual goods</quote>; and he
               demanded that he should make a covenant with him never to act in this manner again,
               and then he left him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="402">
            <p>On one occasion Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> went to visit a certain monk, and he found him to be
               ill, and he asked him if he wanted anything to eat, for he had nothing whatsoever in
               his cell, and the monk said unto him, <quote>I want some honeycakes</quote>; and when the
               wonderful old man heard [this] he set out for <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and he did not regard this
               journey as a trouble, although [the city] was sixty miles away from them, and he
               brought the honeycakes to give to the sick monk. And this he did himself, and did not
               tell anyone else to bring them, and the old man thus made manifest the solicitude
               which he felt for the monks.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="403">
            <p>They used to tell the story of an old man who lived in <placeName>Scete</placeName>; now he had fallen sick,
               and wished to eat a little fine <pb n="92"/>bread. And when a certain brother heard [this], he
               took his cloak and placed in it some dry bread, and he went to <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and changed it
               [for fine bread] and brought [it] to the old man, and the old man looked upon him and
               wondered. But the old man refused to eat it, saying, <quote>This is the bread of blood, O
               my brother,</quote> and the old men entreated him to eat lest the offering of the brother
               should be in vain, and having pressed him the old man was persuaded and he ate the
               bread.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="404">
            <p>The blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> never deemed it right to do that which was convenient for himself
               to the same extent as that which was profitable for his neighbour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="405">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>I have never desired any work which doeth good to myself and
               harm to my neighbour, and I have the hope that what is of benefit to my brother will
               be labour that is beneficial to me, and that it will be a thing that will invite a
               reward for me.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="406">
            <p>A certain brother from the Great Monastery was accused of fornication, and he rose up
               and came to Father <persName>Anthony</persName>; and there came brethren after him from that monastery to
               inform him about the matter and to take him away, and they began to accuse him,
               saying, <quote>Thus and thus hast thou done,</quote> and the brother made excuses, and said, <quote>I
               never acted in this manner.</quote> Now Abbâ <persName>Paphnutius</persName> happened to be there, and he spake a
               word unto them, saying, <quote>I saw a man in the river with the mud up to his knees, and
               some men came to give him help and to drag him out, and they made him to sink up to
               his neck.</quote> And when Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> heard [him say this], he spake concerning Abbâ
               <persName>Paphnutius</persName>, saying, <quote>Behold, indeed, a man who is able to make quiet and to redeem
               souls!</quote> And the eyes of those brethren were opened, by the word of the old men, and
               they took that brother, and he departed with them to their monastery.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="407">
            <p>They used to say about Abbâ <persName>Theodore</persName> that when he was a young man he dwelt in the
               desert, and that he went to make his bread in the same place as the monks made
               theirs; and he found a certain brother who wished to make bread, but he had no one to
               do the work for him, and he was unable to do it for himself. Then Abbâ <persName>Theodore</persName> left
               his own bread and made that of the brother, and a second brother came and he made his
               also, and a third brother came, and he did likewise; and finally when he had
               satisfied them, he made bread for himself.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="408">
            <p>A brother asked an old man, saying, <quote>There were two brethren, and one of them led a
               life of silent contemplation in his cell, and used to fast six days at a time, and to
               devote himself to great labour, and his companion used to minister <pb n="93"/>to the sick; which
               of them will receive the [greater reward for] his service?</quote> The old man saith, <quote>If he
               who fasted were to raise himself up upon the works which are profitable, he would not
               find himself equal before God with him that visited the sick.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="409">
            <p>There was a certain head of a monastery in a house of monks in the desert, and it
               happened that the brother who ministered unto him had a desire to leave the
               monastery, and he departed and dwelt in another monastery; now the old man was
               unwilling to let him go, and on this account he was always going to him to visit him,
               and he entreated him to return to his monastery, and the brother refused to do so.
               And for three whole years the old man used to go to the brother and entreat him to
               return, and finally he was constrained, and he departed with him. One day the old man
               told him to go out and bring in some fuel for the fire, and whilst he was gathering
               the firewood, by the agency of <persName>Satan</persName>, a stick stuck in his eye and it was put out;
               and when the old man heard of this he was greatly grieved, and being full of sorrow
               he began to speak to him words of good cheer. And the brother answered, and said, <quote>Be
               not afflicted, O father, for I was the cause of this myself, for this hath happened
               to me through all the toil and labour which I brought upon thee when thou usedst to
               go and come to me.</quote> And after a little time, when the brother had recovered from the
               sickness caused by the injury to his eye, the old man said unto him, <quote>Go out and
               bring in some palm leaves from the ground,</quote> for this was the work which the monks who
               dwelt there had to do; and whilst the brother was cutting them, once again, as it
               were by the agency of <persName>Satan</persName>, a stick sprang up in the air, and smote the man in the
               other eye, and it was put out, and he came to the monastery in grief, and he was
               perforce idle and useless because he was unable to do any work. Thus the old man was
               deprived [of a servant], and he had no one with him, because each of the brethren
               dwelt in his own cell. And after a short time the day of his departure, which he had
               known beforehand, drew nigh, and he sent and called all the brethren and said unto
               them, <quote>The day of my departure hath drawn nigh. Watch ye yourselves, and take good
               heed to the service of your lives (or life’s work), and treat not lightly your
               ascetic labours.</quote> And each one of them began to say to him sorrowfully, <quote>Father, why
               art thou leaving us?</quote> and the old man held his peace. Then he sent and brought the
               blind man, and revealed to him concerning his departure, and the blind man wept and
               said unto him, <quote>Wherefore leavest thou me, the blind man?</quote> The old man saith unto
               him, <quote>Pray that I may have openness of face with God, and that I may find mercy
               before Him, and <pb n="94"/>I have hope through His help, that on the First Day of the Week thou
               wilt be able to perform the service with thy companions</quote>; and straightway the old man
               died. And, according to his word, a few days later he appeared unto that brother, and
               his eyes were opened, and he became an Abbâ and a head of monks. Now these things
               were related unto us by those who were acquainted with the period wherein the old man
               lived.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="410">
            <p>A certain man of abstinence saw a man who had a devil, and who was unable to fast,
               and he was exceedingly sorry for him; and by reason of the love for <persName>Christ</persName> with which
               he was filled, and because he not only took care for himself, but for his companion
               also, he prayed and entreated God that the devil might come to him, and that the man
               might be released from him. Now God looked upon his prayer and upon his good will,
               and saw that the holy man was carrying a great load on behalf of that demoniac, and
               since that brother began to prolong his fasting and prayer, and to practise
               continually self-denial, in a few days that evil spirit departed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="411">
            <p>They used to say concerning Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> that when he was pressed by any man to go
               with him to eat at an unusual time, he would go, with the tears streaming from his
               eyes, so that he might not resist the wish of that brother and cause him annoyance;
               for he would forgo his own will, and he would humble himself and go.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="412">
            <p>There was an old man in the Cells whose name was <persName>Apollo</persName>, and when one of the brethren
               came to call him to work, he would go joyfully, saying, <quote>I go to-day with the King
               <persName>Christ</persName> to work on my own behalf, for this is the reward of this labour.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="413">
            <p>On one occasion <persName>Abraham</persName>, the disciple of Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName>, was tempted by <persName>Satan</persName>, and the
               old man saw him fall down, and straightway he spread out his hands towards heaven,
               and said to God, <quote>My Lord, I will not let Thee go until Thou hast healed him,</quote> and
               straightway <persName>Abraham</persName> was healed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="414">
            <p>A certain monk was sitting by the monastery, and whilst he was occupied in great
               labours, it happened that strangers came to the monastery, and they forced him to eat
               with them contrary to his usual custom, and afterwards the brethren said unto him,
               <quote>Father, wast thou not just now afflicted?</quote> And he said unto them, <quote>My affliction is
               to break my will.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="415">
            <p>On one occasion three old men went to Abbâ <persName>Akîlâ</persName>, and on one of them [rested] some
               small suspicion of evil; and one of them said unto him, <quote>Father, make me a net,</quote> and
               he replied, <quote>I will not make thee a net.</quote> Then another said unto him, <quote>Do [us] an act
               of grace, and make us a net, so that we <pb n="95"/>may be able to keep thee in remembrance in
               our monastery</quote>; and <persName>Akîlâ</persName> said again, <quote>I am not at leisure [to do so].</quote> Then the
               third brother, on whom [rested] the suspicion of evil, also said unto him, <quote>Father,
               make me a net which I can possess [direct] from thy hands</quote>; and <persName>Akîlâ</persName> answered
               straightway, and said unto this man, <quote>I will make one for thee.</quote> And afterwards the
               [other] two brethren said unto him privately, <quote>[Consider] how much we entreated thee,
               and yet thou wouldst not be persuaded to make [a net] for us, and thou didst say to
               this man, <quote>I will make thee one immediately!</quote></quote> The old man said unto them, <quote>I told
               you that I would not make one, and ye were not grieved, because I had not the
               leisure; but if I had not made one for this man, he would have said, <quote>It was because
               the old man had heard about my sins that he was unwilling to make a net for me.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="416">
            <p>On one occasion three brethren went to harvest, and the three of them undertook to
               reap the harvest [in certain fields] together for a certain sum of money; but one of
               them fell sick on the first day, and was unable to work, and he went back and lay
               down in his cell. Then one of the two brethren who remained said unto his companion,
               <quote>Behold, O my brother, thou seest that our brother hath fallen sick, let us exert
               ourselves a little, thou and I, and let us believe that by his prayers we shall be
               sufficiently strong to do his share of the work of harvest for him.</quote> Then when the
               harvest was ended, and they came to receive their hire, they called the [sick]
               brother, and said unto him, <quote>Come, brother, and take also the hire of thy
               harvesting</quote>; and he said, <quote>What hire can there be for me since I have not been
               harvesting?</quote> And they said unto him, <quote>Through thy prayers the harvest hath been
               reaped; come now, and take [thy] hire.</quote> Then the contention between them waxed
               strong, for the [sick] brother contended that he ought not to receive [any wages],
               and they said, <quote>We will not leave thee until thou dost.</quote> So they went, that they
               might be heard by a certain great old man, and that brother answered and said, <quote>O
               father, three of us went to harvest, but I fell sick on the first day, and went and
               lay down in my cell, and although I did not work even one day these brethren urge me,
               saying, <quote>Come and take the hire for which thou didst not work.</quote></quote> Then the two
               brethren said, <quote>Three of us went to the harvest, and we took certain fields [to reap]
               together, and if we had been thirty we should have succeeded in reaping them with
               great labour; but through the prayers of this our brother the two of us reaped them
               quickly, and we said to him, <quote>Come, take thy hire, because, through thy prayers, God
               helped us, and we reaped quickly,</quote> but he <pb n="96"/>would not take [it].</quote> Then the old man said
               unto the brethren who were with him, <quote>Beat the board, and let all the brethren be
               gathered together,</quote> and when they were assembled he said unto them, <quote>Come, O ye
               brethren, and hear this day a righteous judgement,</quote> and he related before them the
               whole matter, and they decided that the brother was to receive his hire, and that he
               might do whatsoever he wished [therewith]. And the brother went away weeping and
               distressed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="417">
            <p>On one occasion a certain demoniac came to <placeName>Scete</placeName>, and having passed a long time there
               without being healed, he complained about the matter to one of the old men, who made
               the sign of the Cross over him, and healed him. But the devil was angry, and said
               unto the old man, <quote>Now that thou hast cast me out I will come upon thee</quote>; and the old
               man said unto him, <quote>Come gladly, and I shall rejoice.</quote> And the old man passed twelve
               years with the devil inside him, vexing him, now he used to eat twelve dates each
               day, and after these years that devil leaped out of him, and departed from him. Now
               when the old man saw that he was taking to flight, he said unto him, <quote>To whom dost
               thou flee? Continue [with me] longer</quote>; and the devil answered and said unto him, <quote>By
               Jupiter, God hath made thee useless, O old man; God alone is equal to thy
               strength.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="418">
            <p>The old man <persName>Theodore</persName> asked Abbâ <persName>Pambô</persName>, saying, <quote>Tell me a word</quote>; and with much labour
               he said unto him, <quote><persName>Theodore</persName>, get thee gone, and let thy mercy be poured out on every
               man, for [thy] loving-kindness hath found freedom of speech (or boldness) before
               God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="419">
            <p>A certain brother went to buy some linen from a widow, and as she was selling it to
               him, she sighed; the brother said unto her, <quote>What aileth thee?</quote> and the widow said
               unto him, <quote>God hath sent thee this day that my orphans may be fed.</quote> Now when that
               brother heard [these words] he was distressed, and he took secretly from the linen
               which was his, and threw it on to the widow’s side of the scales until he fulfilled
               an act of charity towards her.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="420">
            <p>A certain brother came to Abbâ <persName>’Ôr</persName>, and said unto him, <quote>Come with me to the village,
               and buy me a little wheat of which I am in need</quote>; now the old man was greatly
               troubled at this, because he was not accustomed to go to the village, nevertheless,
               being afraid [of transgressing] the commandment, he rose up and went with him. And
               when they arrived at the village the old man saw a man passing by, and he called him
               and said unto him, <quote>Do an act of kindness, and take this brother and satisfy his
               need,</quote> and in this way he was able to flee to the mountain.</p>
            <pb n="97"/>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="421">
            <p>On one occasion <persName>Adlêp</persName>, Bishop of <placeName>Neapolis</placeName>, went to visit Abbâ. <persName>Sisoes</persName>, and when he
               wished to depart the old man made him and the brethren who were with him to eat in
               the morning; now the days were the first days of the fast. And when they had made
               ready the table to eat, behold, certain men from the plough knocked at the door, and
               the old man said unto his disciple, <quote>Open to them, and put some of the boiled food in
               a dish, and set it before them to eat, for they have just come from labour.</quote> The
               Bishop said, <quote>Let it alone, or perhaps they will say that Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> eateth at this
               time.</quote> And the old man looked at the youth and said unto him, <quote>Go, and give them the
               food</quote>; and when the strangers saw the boiled food they said unto him, <quote>Have ye
               strangers with you? Peradventure Abbâ is also eating with them?</quote> And the disciple
               said unto them, <quote>Yes.</quote> Then they cried out and spake words of condemnation to the
               company, saying, <quote>May God forgive you, for ye have made the old man to eat at this
               time of the day. Perhaps ye are unaware that ye are causing him much vexation
               thereat?</quote> And when the Bishop heard these things he expressed contrition, and said
               unto him, <quote>Forgive me, I have behaved after the manner of a man, but thou hast acted
               like God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="422">
            <p>They used to say that, [on one occasion] when Abbâ <persName>Agathon</persName> came to the city to sell
               his handiwork, he found a stranger lying sick in the market, and he had no man to
               care for him, and the old man stayed with him; and he hired a room in the town and
               remained therein working with his hands, now [what he received therefor] he spent on
               the rent of the room and on the needs of the sick man, for a period of four months,
               and when the sick man was made whole the old man departed to his own cell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="423">
            <p>And an old man used to say, <quote>It is a defect in a man if, when he is reviled by his
               brother, or when any evil cometh to him from him, he cannot strengthen his love
               before he meeteth him.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="424">
            <p>A brother was, on one occasion, sent from <placeName>Scete</placeName> by his Abbâ on a camel to <placeName>Egypt</placeName> to
               fetch palm leaves for [making] baskets, and having gone down and brought the camel,
               another brother met him and said unto him, <quote>Had I known that thou wast coming up I
               should have begged thee to bring a camel for me also</quote>; and when the brother came and
               told his Abbâ what had been said unto him by his companion, his Abbâ said unto him,
               <quote>Take the camel and lead it to that brother, and say unto him, <quote>We have taken
               counsel, and we have given up the intention of bringing up palm leaves at present,
               but do thou take [the camel] and bring some up <pb n="98"/>for thyself.</quote></quote> Now the brother did not
               wish to accept the camel, but [his companion] entreated him [to do so], saying, <quote>If
               thou dost not take him we shall waste what we have paid in hire for him.</quote> So the
               brother took the camel and brought up his palm leaves. And after he had gone up to
               <placeName>Egypt</placeName> that brother took the camel a second time, and he came back that he himself
               might go up; and the brother said unto him, <quote>Where takest thou the camel?</quote> and he
               said unto him, <quote>To <placeName>Scete</placeName>, so that we also may bring up our palm leaves</quote>; and that
               brother repented and was very sorry, and he expressed contrition and said, <quote>Forgive
               me, my brethren, for your great charity hath taken away my hire.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="425">
            <p>One of the brethren said, <quote>Whilst we were sitting and talking about love, Abbâ <persName>Joseph</persName>
               said, <quote>Do we know what love is?</quote> And he said that Abbâ <persName>Agathon</persName> had a little knife,
               and that a certain brother came to him and said, <quote>Father, the little knife which thou
               hast is pretty</quote>; and Abbâ <persName>Agathon</persName> did not let him depart until he had taken it.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="426">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Agathon</persName> used to say, <quote>If I could find an Arian to whom I could give my body and
               take his in its place, I would do so, because this would be perfect love.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="427">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Muthues</persName>, saying, <quote>What shall I do if a brother come unto me, and
               it be a time of fast or the morning, and I am in tribulation?</quote> The old man said unto
               him, <quote>If thou art afflicted, and dost eat with the brother thou doest well; but if
               thou dost not look at the man, and dost eat, this is a matter of thy will only.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="428">
            <p>Mother <persName>Sarah</persName> used to say, <quote>It is a good thing for a man to give alms, even though he
               do so for the approbation of the children of men, for from this he will come to do it
               for God’s sake.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="429">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, saying, <quote>If I find a place wherein there is pleasure for
               the brethren, dost thou wish me to dwell there?</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Where
               thou wilt not do harm to thy brother, there dwell.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="430">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> used to say that whenever <persName>Isidore</persName>, the priest of <placeName>Scete</placeName>, used to address
               the brethren in the church, he spake the following words only: <quote>My brethren, it is
               written, Forgive thy brother that thou also mayest be accounted worthy of
               forgiveness</quote> (St. Luke 6:37; St. Matthew 6:14).</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="431">
            <p>They used to say that at the beginning Abbâ <persName>Zeno</persName> refused to take anything from any
               man, and that those who brought him things used to go away sorrowfully because he
               would not be persuaded to accept them from them. And other men used to come and ask
               him to give them gifts as of a great old man, and they also went away sorrowfully
               because he re<pb n="99"/>fused to do so. Then the old man said within himself, <quote>Those who bring
               go away in sorrow, and those who beg also go away grieving because they have received
               nothing; I will, therefore, act as follows: If any man bringeth me anything I will
               take it, and if any man asketh me for anything I will give it</quote>; and he did so, and
               pleased every one.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="432">
            <p>The disciple of Abbâ <persName>Theodore</persName> said, <quote>A certain man on one occasion came to sell
               onions, and he filled a basin with some of them and gave them to us; and the old man
               said to me, <quote>Fill [the basin] with wheat and give it to him.</quote> Now there were two
               baskets of wheat there, one full of clean wheat, and the other was full of wheat
               which was dirty, and I filled the basin with the dirty wheat and gave it to him. Then
               the old man looked at me in wrath and anger, and in my fear I fell down, and broke
               the basin; and the old man said unto me, <quote>Arise, thou art not akin to me, but I know
               well what I said unto thee.</quote> And the old man went in and filled his garment with
               clean wheat, and gave it to the man with the onions, together with his onions.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="433">
            <p>A certain monk used to dwell by the side of a coenobium, and he was occupied in great
               ascetic labours, and led a life of hard work, and strangers came to the coenobium,
               and forced him to eat before his time; and afterwards the brethren said unto him,
               <quote>Art thou not now afflicted, father?</quote> He said unto them, <quote>Although I am afflicted I
               have cut off my desire.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="434">
            <p>A certain old man used to say, <quote>It is right for a man to take up the burden for those
               who are akin (or near) to him, whatsoever it may be, and, so to speak, to put his own
               soul in the place of that of his neighbour, and to become, if it were possible, a
               double man; and he must suffer, and weep, and mourn with him, and finally the matter
               must be accounted by him as if he himself had put on the actual body of his
               neighbour, and as if he had acquired his countenance and soul, and he must suffer for
               him as he would for himself. For thus is it written:—<quote>We are all one body,</quote> and this
               [passage] also affordeth information concerning the holy and mysterious kiss.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="435">
            <p>An old man said that the father had a custom of going to the cells of the new
               brethren, who wished to live by themselves, to visit them, lest one of them might be
               tempted and injured in his mind by the devils, and if they found any man who had been
               harmed they would bring him to the church, and would place a wash-basin full of water
               [in the midst], and when prayer had been made on behalf of him that had been brought
               there, all the brethren would wash themselves and <pb n="100"/>then pour some of the water upon
               him, and immediately that brother was cleansed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="436">
            <p>A brother asked an old man, saying, <quote>If I find a brother concerning whom I have heard
               [that he hath committed] some offence, I never rest until I have brought him into my
               cell; but if I see a man who leadeth a good life I bring him unto myself gladly.</quote> The
               old man said unto him, <quote>Do that which is good twice over unto the former man, for he
               is sick, and he needeth help.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="437">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>Defeat cometh to a man if, when he is reviled and treated
               with contempt by his brother, he doth not shew him evenness of heart before he
               repenteth and asketh him to forgive him.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="438">
            <p>There was a monk, and away on the mountain, which was about ten miles distant from
               him, was another monk; and the first monk had some bread in his cell, and he
               meditated in his mind and determined to invite the other monk to come and partake of
               his bread. And again he thought in his mind, saying, <quote>Since the bread is with me I
               shall give my brother the labour [of walking] ten miles [if I invite him to come
               here], but it will be more helpful [to him] if I take one half of the bread which I
               possess, and carry it to him</quote>; so he took the bread to carry it to the cell of the
               other brother. Now as he was journeying along, he tripped up, and fell, and injured
               one of his fingers, and as the blood was running down he began to cry because of the
               pain; and there appeared unto him suddenly an angel who said unto him, <quote>Why weepest
               thou?</quote> And the monk said unto him, <quote>I have hurt my finger, and it paineth me</quote>; and
               the angel said unto him, <quote>Dost thou weep because of this? Weep not, for the number of
               every step which thou takest for our Lord’s sake is written down, and is estimated at
               a great reward (or hire) before Him, and the report of the labour of such things
               goeth up to Him. And that thou mayest be certain that such is the case, behold, in
               thy presence I will take some of this blood and carry [it] to our Lord</quote>; and
               immediately the monk was healed, and with rejoicing and thanksgiving to God he set
               out again on his journey to go to his companion. And having come to him and given him
               the bread, he related unto him concerning the love for man which is found in the good
               Lord, the Creator of the universe, and then went back to his cell. Now after one day
               he took the other half of the bread and went to carry it to another monk. And it
               happened that he also was found to be burning with anxiety to emulate works of this
               kind, and he wanted to do even as the other monk had done; and having set out to go
               and carry the bread of the first monk, they hap<pb n="101"/>pened to meet each other on the way.
               Then the first monk who had done good to the other monk began to say unto him, <quote>I
               possessed a certain treasure, and thou wishest to rob me [of it]</quote>; and the other monk
               said unto him, <quote>Where is it written that the strait and narrow door is sufficient for
               thyself alone? Let us, even us, go in with thee.</quote> Then straightway, whilst they were
               holding converse, the angel of the Lord appeared, and said unto them, <quote>Your
               contending hath ascended unto the Lord even as a sweet smell.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="439">
            <p>On one occasion, a certain excellent man, who feared God in his life and works, and
               who was living in the world, went to Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, and some of the brethren, who were
               also with the old man, were asking him questions [wishing] to hear a word from him.
               Then Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said to the man who was in the world, <quote>Speak a word to the
               brethren</quote>; but he entreated him, saying, <quote>Forgive me, father, but I came to learn.</quote>
               And the old man pressed him [to speak], and, as the force of his urging increased, he
               said, <quote>I am a man living in the world, and I sell vegetables, and because I do not
               know how to speak from a book, listen ye to a parable. There was a certain man who
               had three friends, and he said to the first, <quote>since I desire to see the Emperor come
               with me</quote>; and the friend said unto him, <quote>I will come with thee half the way.</quote> And the
               man said to the second friend, <quote>Come, go with me to the Emperor</quote>s presence’; and the
               friend said unto him, <quote>I will come with thee as far as his palace, but I cannot go
               with thee inside</quote>; and the man said the same unto his third friend, who answered and
               said, <quote>I will come with thee, and I will go inside the palace with thee, and I will
               even stand up before the Emperor and speak on thy behalf.</quote></quote> Then the brethren
               questioned him, wishing to learn from him the strength of the riddle (or dark
               saying), and he answered and said unto them, <quote>The first friend is abstinence, which
               leadeth as far as one half of the way; and the second friend is purity and holiness,
               which lead to heaven; and the third friend is loving-kindness, which stablisheth a
               man before God, and speaketh on his behalf with great boldness.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="440">
            <p>A brother went to visit a certain monk, and when he went forth from him, he said unto
               him, <quote>Forgive me, father, for having made thee to desist from thy rule</quote>; and the monk
               said unto him, <quote>My rule is to refresh thee, and to send thee away in peace.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="441">
            <p>On one occasion a command was given to the brethren who were in <placeName>Scete</placeName>, and it was
               said unto them, <quote>Fast ye this week, and celebrate the Passover.</quote> And it happened that
               some brethren came from <placeName>Egypt</placeName> to Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName>, and whilst <pb n="102"/>he was boiling for them a
               little food, his neighbours saw the smoke [of his fire] rising up, and they said to
               the clergy, <quote>Behold, <persName>Moses</persName> hath broken the command, and hath boiled some food in his
               cell</quote>; and they said unto them, <quote>Hold ye your peace, and when he cometh to us we will
               speak to him.</quote> Now when the Sabbath arrived, the clergy, having regard to his great
               ascetic labours, said unto him before the whole assembly, <quote>O Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName>, though thou
               dost break the command of men, thou stablishest [that of God].</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="442">
            <p>They used to tell the story of a certain brother who, when he was throwing away the
               handles of his baskets, heard his neighbour say, <quote>What shall I do? For the festival
               draweth nigh, and I have no handles to put on my baskets</quote>; and the brother went
               straightway and picked up the handles of his baskets, and brought them to his
               companion, saying, <quote>Behold I have these, of which I have no need, take them and put
               them on thy baskets</quote>; and he left his own work and completed that of his
               companion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="443">
            <p>Certain of the old men went to Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, and said unto him, <quote>Dost thou wish us if
               we see brethren sleeping in the congregation, to smite them so that they may wake
               up?</quote> And he said unto them, <quote>If I see my brother sleeping, I place his head upon my
               knees, and I give him a place to rest upon</quote>; then an old man said unto him, <quote>And what
               dost thou say unto God?</quote> Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said unto him, <quote>I say unto Him thus: Thou
               Thyself hast said, ‘First of all pluck the beam out of thine own eye, and then thou
               wilt be able to see to take the mote out of the eye of thy brother</quote> (St. Matthew
               7:3).</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
