<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Of [The Fathers Who] Wrought Wonderful Works</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_13">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_13 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 13: Of [The Fathers Who] Wrought Wonderful Works</head>
         <div type="saying" n="614">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> said: When we were in <placeName>Scete</placeName>, with Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName>, seven of us went up to
               reap with him, and behold, a certain widow followed after us gleaning, and she ceased
               not to weep. And the old man cried to the lord of the estate, and said unto him,
               <quote>What is the matter with the old woman who weepeth continually?</quote> He said unto him,
               <quote>Her husband took a deposit of money from a man and he died suddenly without saying
               with whom he had placed it, and the owner of the deposit wisheth to take her and her
               children as slaves.</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Tell her to come to us at the place
               where we rest at the season of noon,</quote> and it was told to her. And at the season of
               noon the woman came to them, and the old man said unto her, <quote>Woman, why dost thou
               weep continually?</quote> And she said, <quote>My husband is dead. He had taken a deposit from a
               certain man, and he died suddenly without telling us where he had laid it up.</quote> The
               old man said unto her, <quote>Come [and] and show me where ye have laid him</quote>; and he took
               the brethren with him, and went with her, and having arrived at the place where the
               man was laid, the old man said unto her, <quote>Get thee now to thy house.</quote> And after [she
               had departed] and he had made an end of his prayer, the old man cried out to the dead
               man and said, <quote>O Such-an-one, where hast thou laid up the deposit which belongeth to
               the stranger?</quote> Then the dead man answered straightway, and said, <quote>It is hidden in my
               house beneath the leg of the bed</quote>; and the old man said unto him, <quote>Sleep now until
               the Resurrection.</quote> Now when the brethren saw what had been done, they all fell down
               at his feet in fear; and the old man said unto them, <quote>This hath not happened because
               of me, O my brethren, <pb n="141"/>nor is the matter a great one, but God hath wrought this thing
               for the sake of the widow and the orphans; but what is great is that God desireth a
               soul which is pure and sinless.</quote> And when they had come they told the widow that the
               deposit was laid up in such and such a place, and then the old woman brought it up,
               and gave it to its owner, and set free her children from slavery. And every one who
               heard [of this] gave thanks unto God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="615">
            <p>When Abbâ <persName>Miles (or Manilius)</persName> was passing through a certain place he saw a man
               holding a monk by force as if he had committed murder, and the old man drew nigh and
               questioned the brother, and when he learned that he was being wrongfully accused, he
               said unto those who had seized him, <quote>Tell me where is the man who hath been
               murdered</quote>; and they shewed him. Then the old man drew nigh to the murdered man, and
               said unto all who were standing [there], <quote>Let us pray</quote>; and when he had spread out
               his hands in prayer before God, the dead man rose up. And the old man said unto him
               before every man, <quote>Tell us who it was that slew thee</quote>; and he answered and said, <quote>I
               went into the church and gave some money to the elder, and it was he who rose up and
               killed me, and he carried me out and threw me in the habitation of this monk. I
               entreat you that the goods which I have given to him may be taken back and given to
               my children.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="616">
            <p>On one occasion a certain man in the world went to Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> in the mountain of
               Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>, and he had his son with him, and as they were going along the road his
               son died; now the man was in no wise disturbed, but he took him up in faith and
               brought him to the old man, and he came with his son, and fell down before him with
               his son upon his knees as if he was entreating him to bless them; and the father of
               the boy went out and left his son [lying] dead at the feet of the old man. Now the
               old man did not know that the boy was dead, but he thought that he was making
               supplication and entreaty to him; and he answered and said unto him, <quote>Arise, and go
               forth,</quote> and straightway without any delay whatsoever, the youth rose up and went out
               to his father, who, when he saw him, marvelled; and his father took him and went in
               and did homage to the old man, and informed him about the matter. Now when the old
               man heard this he was troubled, for he did not wish this thing to happen because of
               the praise of men; and his disciple commanded them not to tell the story before any
               man until the day of his death.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="617">
            <p>One of the fathers used to relate that Abbâ <persName>Paule</persName>, who dwelt in <placeName>Thebes</placeName>, would take
               snakes, and scorpions, and horned snakes in his hands, and kill them. And the
               brethren made <pb n="142"/>apologies to him, and said, <quote>Father, tell us through what labour thou
               hast received this gift.</quote> And he said unto them, <quote>Forgive me, O my fathers, if ye
               possess purity of heart, every living thing will be subject unto you as it was unto
               <persName>Adam</persName> before he transgressed the commandment of God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="618">
            <p>On one occasion one of the old men of <placeName>Thebes</placeName> came to <placeName>Mount Sinai</placeName>, and having departed
               from there, one of the brethren met him on the way, and with a groan he said unto the
               old man, <quote>We are distressed, O father, through the want of rain.</quote> And the old man
               said unto him, <quote>Why do ye not pray and ask God for some?</quote> And the brother said unto
               him, <quote>We have prayed and made earnest supplication, and the rain hath not come.</quote> The
               old man said unto them, <quote>Then ye did not pray with all your hearts; do ye wish to
               know that the matter is thus?</quote> And after [this] the old man stood up in prayer, and
               he spread out his hands to heaven, and straightway, without any delay whatsoever, the
               rain came; and the brother saw, and feared, and he fell down and did homage to him.
               Now the old man took to flight, but the brother made known everything which had
               happened, and when [the brethren] heard [thereof] they all glorified God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="619">
            <p>They used to say that, when on one occasion, Abbâ <persName>Moses of <placeName>Scete</placeName></persName> was going into
               <placeName>Patârâ</placeName>, he grew weary through the length of the road, and he was afraid and said,
               <quote>How can I bring water for myself into this place?</quote> And a voice was heard by him,
               saying, <quote>Go on, and fear not.</quote> Now one day a large number of the fathers came to him,
               and he had there only one vessel of water, and having boiled some lentiles the water
               came to an end; at this the old man was troubled, and went out and in, and prayed to
               God, and afterwards a great cloud came and poured down upon them much rain, and it
               filled all the vessels which he had with water. Then afterwards the fathers said unto
               him, <quote>Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName>, tell us why thou didst come in and out</quote>; and he said unto them, <quote>I
               entered into judgement with God, who brought me hither because there was want of
               water, and because I had no water for His servants to drink; therefore I came in and
               out.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="620">
            <p>The old man <persName>Joseph</persName> used to say: <quote>I went on one occasion to Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> and found many
               old men with him, and behold, a certain man had brought a youth who was a kinsman of
               Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, and whose face had been turned backwards through the operation of the
               Evil One; and when his father saw the multitude of the old men who were coming to
               Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, he took him and brought him outside the door of the monastery, and sat
               down there and wept. Now when one of the old men had ended his business, and was
               <pb n="143"/>going forth [from the building], he saw him, and said unto him, <quote>Why weepest thou, O
               man?</quote> The father of the youth said unto him, <quote>I am of the family of Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>. A
               trial hath come upon this youth, but we are afraid to take him to him, for he
               refuseth to see us, and now, if he learneth that I am here, he will send and drive me
               away; but when I knew that ye were coming here, I ventured to come also.</quote> And he cast
               the youth down on the ground at his feet, and wept, saying, <quote>If thou wilt, have mercy
               on me, and take this youth inside, and pray over him</quote>; and the old man took him and
               carried him in with him to Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>. Now the old man acted wisely in the matter,
               and he did not take the youth at once to Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, but beginning with the last of
               the brethren who was there, he brought the youth to each and every one of them,
               saying, <quote>Make the sign of the Cross upon this youth</quote>; and having brought him alike to
               all the brethren and to all the old men who were there, finally he brought him to
               Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, but the blessed man refused to touch him. Thereupon a contention arose,
               and they all entreated him, saying, <quote>Father, do thou even as we all have done</quote>; then
               Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> sighed, and he rose up and prayed, and said, <quote>O God, heal that which Thou
               hast fashioned so that it may not be destroyed by the Enemy,</quote> and he finished his
               prayer, and made the sign of the Cross over him, and straightway the face of the
               youth was made straight, and he was healed. And Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> gave him to his father
               made whole, so he took him and departed with rejoicing.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="621">
            <p>They used to say that the face of Abbâ <persName>Pambô</persName> was like lightning, even as <persName>Moses</persName>
               received the glory of the likeness of <persName>Adam</persName>, and that his face shone, and that he was
               like a king who sitteth upon his throne; and thus was it also with Abbâ <persName>Silvanus</persName> and
               with Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="622">
            <p>They used to say about one of the old men that as he was in the light during the day,
               so also was he [in the light] in his cell by night, and that he used to work with his
               hands and read in the night time just as he did during the day.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="623">
            <p>One of the old men sent his disciple to draw water, now the well was a very long way
               off from their cell, and that brother forgot to take the rope with him; and being
               distressed [thereat] he bowed himself in prayer, and he prayed and cried out, saying,
               <quote>O well, my father [saith], <quote>Fill this vessel for me with water, and without delay</quote></quote>;
               and the water came up, and the brother filled [the vessel], and as soon as he had
               done so the water descended to its place.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="624">
            <p>On one occasion Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> came to the well to draw <pb n="144"/>water, and he saw Abbâ <persName>Zechariah</persName>
               praying to the stream, and the Spirit of God was resting upon him like a dove.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="625">
            <p>On one occasion one of the brethren went to the cell of Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> in <placeName>Scete</placeName>, and
               he looked through the window, and saw the old man standing up, and all his body was
               like fire; now that brother was worthy to see this sight. And having knocked at the
               door the old man came out to him; and seeing that the brother was marvelling at the
               sight which he had seen, he said unto him, <quote>Hast thou been knocking a long time?
               Peradventure thou hast seen something?</quote> and he said unto him, <quote>No; [I have not].</quote> And
               Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> spake with him and dismissed him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="626">
            <p>They used to say that a certain old man said, <quote>Verily, as he who worketh gold, and as
               he who maketh beautiful work, cleanly and at peace, so thou also by thy beautiful
               thoughts must inherit the kingdom of God; but I who have passed the whole period of
               my life in the desert have not been able to overtake thee.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="627">
            <p>They used to say about a certain great old man, who lived in <placeName>Pûrpîrînê</placeName>, that when he
               lifted up his eyes to heaven he could see whatsoever was therein, and that if he
               gazed into the earth, he could see into the depths, and whatsoever was in them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="628">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>John</persName>, who was cast out by the <persName>Marcionites</persName>, used to say:—On one occasion we went
               from <placeName>Syria</placeName> to Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, and when we wished him to speak to us about hardness of
               heart [we found that] the old man did not know Greek, and there was no interpreter
               with leisure [to interpret there]. And the old man saw that we were troubled at this,
               and he began to talk to us in the Greek tongue, and at the beginning of his speech he
               said, <quote>Water is by nature soft, and stone is hard, nevertheless if thou suspendest a
               vessel full of water above a stone, and wilt pour it out upon it drop by drop, it
               will wear away the stone. In the same way the Word of God is soft, and our heart is
               hard, but if it heareth continually the Word of God, the heart will be opened, and
               will turn to the fear of God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="629">
            <p>A certain monk lived in the desert, and there was another brother who lived in a cell
               by his side, and when he visited him from time to time he used to see him praying and
               entreating our Lord that the wild animals might be at peace with him. And after the
               prayer a panther which was suckling her young was found by him, and that brother went
               down upon his knees and sucked with them. And on another occasion the blessed man saw
               that brother praying and beseeching God to make fire to be at peace with him; and he
               lit a fire, and knelt <pb n="145"/>down in the middle of it, and prayed. And that old man used to
               say, <quote>If thou wishest to become a monk, bring thyself into subjection that thou
               mayest be in the congregation of the community, and mayest enter the monastery; but
               if thou canst not cast away from thee care concerning [all kinds of] occupations and
               affairs, thou canst never dwell in the congregation. All the power thou hast is over
               a bottle of water.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="630">
            <p>And there are also wonderful things which the blessed <persName>Bessarion</persName> performed. He made
               the waters of the sea sweet, and <persName>Saul</persName> his disciple drank [of them]; he crossed over
               the water of the river; he prevented the sun from setting in the heavens; and the
               rooting up of the temples of the idols was revealed unto him. As they were going to
               <persName>John the Theban</persName> his disciple became thirsty, and <persName>Bessarion</persName> prayed, and water bubbled
               up, and he gave him to drink; and he healed also the young man who was a paralytic,
               so that he ran to his father; and he cast out a devil from a young man who was always
               asleep, and whom his parents besought him to wake up. I have, however, written down
               all these things in the history of the holy man <persName>Bessarion</persName>, wherein it is written that
               he was sitting at the door of the monastery and weeping bitterly.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
