<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Of Humility And Of Bow A Man Should Think Lightly Of
               Himself, And Should Esteem Himself The Interior Of Every Man</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_10">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_10 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 10: Of Humility And Of Bow A Man Should Think Lightly Of Himself, And Should
            Esteem Himself The Interior Of Every Man</head>
         <div type="saying" n="444">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Isaac</persName>, the priest of the Cells, used to say: When I was a young man I used to
               dwell with Abbâ <persName>Chronius</persName>, and he never at any time told me to do any work; now he was
               an old man and he trembled, but he would stand up and give water with his hands to
               me, and to all of us alike. And with Abbâ <persName>Theodore of <placeName>Parmê</placeName></persName> it was the same, for he
               never told me to do any work whatsoever, but he would make ready the table with his
               own hands, and would say, <quote>Brother, come [and] eat.</quote> And I said unto him, <quote>Father, I
               came <pb n="103"/>that I might assist thee, and how is that thou dost not tell me to do
               something?</quote> But the old man in all this held his peace. And I went up and informed
               the old men, and they came to him, and said unto him, <quote>Father, this brother came unto
               thy holiness that he might be assisted [by thee], and why dost thou not tell him to
               do something?</quote> Then the old man said unto them, <quote>Am I the head of a monastery that I
               should give him a command? I shall say unto him nothing except that [I] wish him to
               do that which he seeth me do.</quote> And from that time I was always before him in doing
               that which the old man was going to do; now whatsoever he did, he did in silence, and
               in this manner he made me to know and taught me to work in silence also.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="445">
            <p>There was a certain <persName>Egyptian monk</persName> in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> under the reign of <persName>Theodosius the
               Less</persName>, and he used to dwell in a little cell, and when the Emperor went forth [on one
               occasion] to take his pleasure, he came by himself to the monk; now the following of
               men who were with him waited for him at a distance. And the Emperor took off his
               crown from his head, and hid it, and he knocked at the door of the monk, and when he
               opened to him he knew that it was the Emperor, but he [feigned] forgetfulness and
               would not recognize him, and he welcomed him as one of his own rank in life, and he
               prayed and sat down. Then the Emperor began to question him, saying, <quote>How are the
               fathers who are in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>?</quote> And the monk said unto him, <quote>They all pray for thy
               health.</quote> And the Emperor examined his cell, and saw nothing there except a small
               basket wherein was bread, and the monk said to him, <quote>Eat,</quote> and he dipped the bread in
               water, and poured oil on it, and salt, and he gave it to the Emperor, who ate it; and
               he gave him some water, and he drank. Then the Emperor said unto him, <quote>Knowest thou
               who I am?</quote> And the monk said unto him, <quote>God knoweth who thou art.</quote> And the Emperor
               said unto him, <quote>I am <persName>Theodosius</persName>, the Emperor,</quote> and straightway the monk paid homage
               unto him. Then the Emperor said unto him, <quote>Blessed art thou in that thou hast none of
               the cares of this world; verily I was born to kingship and before this day I have
               never been satisfied with bread and water, and they have pleased me greatly</quote>; and the
               Emperor began to pay honour to him. And straightway that monk fled to <placeName>Egypt</placeName> with all
               the speed that was possible.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="446">
            <p>A certain brother came to Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName>, the <persName>Egypt</persName>ian, and said unto him, <quote>Father,
               speak to me a word whereby I may live.</quote> Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> saith unto him, <quote>Get thee to
               the cemetery and revile the dead</quote>; and he went and reviled them, and stoned them with
               stones, and he came and informed the old man [that he had done so]. And the old man
               said unto him, <quote>Did they say nothing unto thee?</quote> and the brother said unto him, <quote>No.</quote>
               And again the old man said unto him, <quote>Go to-morrow and praise them, and call them,
               <quote>Apostles, <pb n="104"/>Saints, and Righteous Men</quote></quote>; and he came to the old man, and said, <quote>I have
               praised them.</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>And did they return thee no answer?</quote>
               and he said <quote>No.</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>Thou seest how thou hast praised
               them, and that they said nothing to thee, and that although thou didst revile them
               they returned thee no answer. And thus let it be with thyself. If thou wishest to
               live, become dead, so that thou mayest care neither for the reviling of men nor for
               [their] praise, for the dead care for nothing; in this wise thou wilt be able to
               live.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="447">
            <p>One of the fathers used to relate that he had an old man in a cell, who performed
               many ascetic labours, and who clothed himself in a palm-leaf mat; and this old man
               went to Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName>, who, seeing that he wore a palm-leaf mat only, said unto him,
               <quote>This will profit thee nothing.</quote> And the old man asked him, saying, <quote>Three thoughts
               vex me. Shall I go to the desert, or shall I go forth into exile, or shall I shut
               myself up in a cell, and receive no man, and eat once every two days?</quote> Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName>
               said unto him, <quote>Thou art not able to do any one of these things, but go, sit in thy
               cell, and eat a very little food each day, and let there be in thine heart always the
               word[s] of the publican, <quote>God be merciful to me a sinner,</quote> and thus thou shalt be
               able to live</quote> (St. Luke 18:13).</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="448">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Daniel</persName> used to relate a story, saying:—There was with us in <placeName>Babylon</placeName> of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> the
               daughter of a man who was the captain of a company of soldiers, and she was possessed
               of a devil, and her father took her to many places, but she could not find healing.
               Now her father had a friend who was a monk, and he said unto him, <quote>No man is able to
               cure her except those monks of whom I spake unto thee, but even if we entreat them to
               do this they will not agree to it, because they flee from the love of the approbation
               [of men]. Nevertheless, when they come to sell [their] baskets, ye shall pretend that
               ye wish to buy some, and when they come to sell and to take the price of the baskets
               from thy house, we will say unto them, <quote>Put up a prayer, and this maiden shall be
               healed</quote></quote>; and the man did so. And they came as it were to buy baskets, and they found
               the disciple of these holy men sitting down and selling [them], and they took him and
               the baskets, and carried him to their houses, and then they set another man in his
               place, and commanded him when the monks came to bring them to them. Now when their
               disciple entered the house, the maiden who was possessed of a devil went forth and
               smote him on the cheek, but that brother fulfilled the commandment and turned to her
               the other cheek, and straightway that devil, who was unable to bear the <pb n="105"/>blow of the
               commandment of <persName>Christ</persName> which was fulfilled, cried out with a loud voice, and departed.
               And when the monks came [the people in the house] related unto them the reason for
               what had happened, and they glorified God, and said, <quote>It is customary for the
               boasting of the Evil One to fall before the humility of the commandments of
               <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="449">
            <p>On one occasion Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName> went to Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>, and he lost the way, and sat down
               for a little and fell asleep; and he rose up from his slumber, and prayed unto God,
               and said, <quote>I beseech Thee, O Lord God, not to destroy that which Thou hast
               fashioned.</quote> Then he lifted up his eyes, and, behold, there was the form of a man’s
               hand above him in the heavens, and it shewed him the way until he came and stood
               above the cave of Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>; and when he had gone into the cave to the old man,
               Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> prophesied unto him, saying, <quote>Thou shalt increase in the fear of God.</quote>
               Then he took him outside the cave, and showing him a stone, said, <quote>Curse this stone,
               and smite it,</quote> and he did so, and Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> said unto him, <quote>It is thus that thou
               shalt arrive at this state, for thou shalt bear heaviness, and great abuse</quote>; and this
               actually happened to Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName>. Now, through his abundant goodness Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName> knew
               not wickedness. And after he had become a Bishop, through his spiritual excellence
               they brought unto him a virgin who had conceived, and they said unto him, <quote>So-and-so
               hath done this deed; let them receive correction</quote>; but he made the sign of the Cross
               over her belly, and ordered them to give her six pair of linen cloths, and he said,
               <quote>Peradventure when she bringeth forth either she or the child will die, [and if
               either dieth] let them be buried.</quote> Then those who were with him said unto him, <quote>What
               is this that thou hast done? Give the command that they receive correction.</quote> And he
               said unto them, <quote>See, O my brethren, she is nigh unto death, and what can I do?</quote> Then
               he dismissed her. And the old man never ventured to judge anyone, for he was full of
               loving-kindness and endless goodness to all the children of men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="450">
            <p>They used to say that [on one occasion] when Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> the Great fell ill in
               <placeName>Scete</placeName>, a priest went and brought him to the church, and he spread a palm-leaf mat for
               him, and [placed] a small pillow under his head; and one of the old men came to visit
               him and saw that he was lying upon a mat and that he had a pillow under his head, and
               he was offended and said, <quote>And this is <persName>Arsenius</persName> lying upon such things!</quote> Then the
               priest took the old man aside privately, and said unto him, <quote>What labour didst thou
               do in thy village?</quote> and the old man said unto him, <quote>I was a shepherd.</quote> And the priest
               said unto him, <quote>What manner of life didst thou lead in the world?</quote> and he said unto
               him, <quote>A life of toil, and sore want.</quote> And when the old man had described all the
               tribulation which he had endured in the world, the priest said unto <pb n="106"/>him, <quote>And here
               what manner of life dost thou lead?</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>In my cell I
               have everything comfortable, and I have more than I want</quote>; and the priest said unto
               him, <quote>Consider [the position of] Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> when he was in the world! He was the
               father of kings, and a thousand slaves, girt about with gold-embroidered vests, and
               with chains and ornaments round their necks, and clothed in silk, stood before him;
               and he had the most costly couches and cushions [to lie upon]. But thou wast a
               shepherd, and the comforts which thou didst never enjoy in the world thou hast here;
               but this man <persName>Arsenius</persName> hath not here the comforts which he enjoyed in the world, and
               now thou art at thine ease whilst he is troubled.</quote> Then the mind of the old man was
               opened, and he expressed contrition and said, <quote>Father, forgive me; I have sinned.
               Verily this is the way of truth. He hath come to a state of humility, whilst I have
               attained to ease.</quote> And the old man having profited went his way.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="451">
            <p>They used to say that on one occasion Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> was passing along the road when
               <persName>Satan</persName> met him, and the Devil wished to cut him down with the scythe which he held in
               his hand, but he was unable to do so, and he said unto him, <quote><persName>Macarius</persName>, I am dragged
               along by thee with great force, but I cannot overcome thee. Now, behold, everything
               which thou doest I can do also. Thou fastest, and I never eat at all. Thou watchest,
               and I never go to sleep, and there is one thing only wherein thou dost conquer me.</quote>
               Then <persName>Macarius</persName> said unto him, <quote>And what is that?</quote> And <persName>Satan</persName> said, <quote>It is thy humility,
               for it is because of this that I cannot vanquish thee</quote>; then <persName>Macarius</persName> spread out his
               hands in prayer, and the Devil was no more seen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="452">
            <p>On one occasion a devil took a knife and stood over Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> wishing to cut off
               his leg, and when he was unable to do so on account of the humility [of the old man],
               he answered and said unto him, <quote>Everything which ye possess we possess also, and it
               is only in humility that ye are superior to us, and [it is only by means of it] that
               ye conquer us.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="453">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> said, <quote>I saw all the snares of the Enemy laid out upon the ground, and I
               groaned and said, <quote>Who can escape from these?</quote></quote> And the devils said unto me,
               ‘Humility <quote>maketh a man to escape from these, for we cannot attain unto it.’</quote></p>
            <pb n="107"/>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="454">
            <p>An old man said, <quote>Whensoever a man is praised it is meet for him to think upon his
               sins, and he should consider, saying, <quote>I am unworthy of the things which are said
               about me.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="455">
            <p>The blessed <persName>Macarius</persName> behaved towards all the brethren without any wicked suspicion,
               and certain people said unto him, <quote>Why dost thou act in this manner?</quote> And he said,
               <quote>Behold, for twelve years I have been supplicating my Lord to give me this gift, and
               would you advise me to relinquish it? If it happen that one of the brethren commit a
               sin before the eyes of him who possesseth no wickedness, and he know that it is an
               evil thing, it is not right that he should bear some of the pain of him that hath
               fallen.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="456">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> used to say, <quote>No monk should condemn any man in anything, and no monk
               should reward a man with [evil for] evil, and no monk should be a man of anger.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="457">
            <p>An old man asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, saying, <quote>Some brethren dwell with me; dost thou wish me
               to give them commandments?</quote> And he said unto him, <quote>No, but thou thyself must first do
               work, and if they wish to live, they will observe [it] and do [it].</quote> The old man said
               unto him, <quote>Ought they also to wish me to govern them?</quote> And Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said unto him,
               <quote>No, be unto them an example, and not a lawgiver.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="458">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said, <quote>If a brother come unto thee, and thou be not benefited by his
               coming in [to thee], enquire in thine heart, and learn what thought thou hadst [in
               thy mind] before the entrance of that brother, and then thou wilt learn whence cometh
               the source of injury; if thou wilt do this with humility and knowledge, behold, thou
               wilt live without blame with thy brother, and thou wilt bear thine own shortcomings.
               If a man maketh his habitation with knowledge it will not fall, for God is before it,
               and, as it appeareth to me, from this habitation a man may acquire the fear of
               God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="459">
            <p>A brother asked an old man, saying, <quote>By what means may a man go forward? and the old
               man said unto him, The greatness of a man consisteth of humility, for in proportion
               as a man descendeth to humility, he becometh exalted to greatness.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="460">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>John</persName> used to say, <quote>We relinquish a light burden when we condemn ourselves, but
               we take upon ourselves a heavy burden when we [attempt to] make ourselves
               righteous.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="461">
            <p>On one occasion Abbâ <persName>Theophilus</persName> went to the <placeName>Nitrian Mountain</placeName> to visit the fathers,
               and the priest of the Mountain came to him; and Abbâ <persName>Theophilus</persName> said to him, now he
               was <persName>Theophilus</persName> the Bishop of Alexandria, <quote>What thing of excellence hast thou found on
               this road?</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>I make accusations against myself, and I
               blame <pb n="108"/>myself at all times</quote>; and Abbâ <persName>Theophilus</persName> said unto him, <quote>Verily this is the
               way of truth.</quote></p>
            <p>A variant reads: <quote>On one occasion the Archbishop <persName>Theophilus</persName> went to the mountain of
               Nitria, and a certain Abbâ of the monks who was in the mountain came unto him; Abbâ
               <persName>Theophilus</persName> said unto him, “What more do the monks find in this way [than in any
               other]?</quote> The old man said unto him, They condemn themselves continually, and they do
               not judge their neighbours”; and Abbâ <persName>Theophilus</persName> said, <quote>There is no way but
               this.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="462">
            <p>On one occasion they brought a man possessed of a devil to one of the old men of
               <placeName>Thebes</placeName>, and entreated him to cast the devil out, but the old man was unwilling [to do
               so]; but since they urged him strongly he was persuaded, and he had mercy on the man,
               and he said to the devil, <quote>Get thee out from that which God hath fashioned.</quote> Then the
               devil answered and said, <quote>I am going out, but I would ask thee to tell me one thing:
               What is the meaning of that which is written in the Gospel, Who are the goats and who
               are the sheep?</quote> The old man answered and said, <quote>I myself am [one of] the goats, but
               God knoweth who the sheep are</quote>; and when the devil heard this, he cried out with a
               loud voice, saying, <quote>Behold, I go forth because of thy humility,</quote> and straightway he
               left the man and departed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="463">
            <p>They used to say that on one occasion a few early, white figs came to <placeName>Scete</placeName>, but
               because they were nothing [of importance] they did not send any to Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName>, not
               wishing to insult him; and when the old man heard of this he did not come to the
               congregation, saying, <quote>Ye separated me from the blessed gift which God sent to the
               brethren because I was unworthy to partake of it.</quote> And when the old man heard [this]
               they profited [greatly] by his humility, and the priest went and carried some of the
               figs to him, and brought him to the congregation with great joy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="464">
            <p>A certain Abbâ asked Abbâ <persName>Muthues</persName>, saying, <quote>If I go to a place to dwell, how wouldst
               thou have me conduct myself?</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>If thou wishest to dwell in
               a certain place, [do so,] but do not let go forth concerning thyself any fame for
               praiseworthy acts, [or say,] <quote>I do not eat,</quote> or, <quote>I do not drink,</quote> for such things
               only produce empty fame; and thou wilt find at length that thou wilt profit from
               many, for men will go where they can find qualities of this kind.</quote> Then the brother
               said unto him, <quote>What shall I do?</quote> and the old man said unto him, Wheresoever thou
               dwellest conduct thyself in a simple manner like every one else, and what thou seest
               those who fear God do, [I mean] those in whom thou <pb n="109"/>hast confidence, that do also, and
               thou shalt be at ease. For to be as all other men are is true humility, and the men
               who see that thou art like unto all other men will regard thee as they regard every
               one else, and thou wilt not be troubled.”</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="465">
            <p>A certain brother went on one occasion from <placeName>Egypt</placeName> to <placeName>Syria</placeName> to visit Abbâ <persName>Zeno</persName>, and
               the <persName>Egypt</persName>ians began to make accusations against his thoughts before the old man. And
               when Abbâ <persName>Zeno</persName> heard this, he marvelled and said, <quote>The <persName>Egypt</persName>ians always hide the
               spiritual excellences which they possess, but they describe the shortcomings which
               they do not possess; on the other hand, the <persName>Syrians</persName> and the <persName>Greeks</persName> declare that they
               possess the virtues which they have not, and they hide the shortcomings which they do
               possess.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="466">
            <p>They used to talk about a certain old man who fasted for seventy weeks, and who only
               ate each Saturday; and he asked God that a word from the Book might be given unto
               him, but it was not given. Then he said within himself, <quote>Behold, I have laboured in
               all these things, and I have omitted nothing; I will arise and go to my brother and
               question him [about it].</quote> And when he had shut the door to depart, the angel of the
               Lord appeared, and said unto him, <quote>The seventy weeks wherein thou didst fast have not
               come nigh unto God, but, inasmuch as thou hast humbled thyself to go to thy brother,
               I have been sent to make known unto thee a word, and to give thee rest</quote>; thereupon he
               made the word known unto him, and gave him rest, and departed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="467">
            <p>A brother asked an old man, saying, <quote>What shall I do? For the love of praise is
               killing me.</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Thou doest well, for behold, thou hast made
               the heavens and the earth.</quote> Then the brother was sorry because of what the old man
               had said unto him, and he expressed contrition, and said, <quote>Father, forgive me, but I
               have done nothing of the kind</quote>; the old man said unto him, <quote>If now He Who did make
               them came into this world in humility, why dost thou who art mud boast thyself?</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="468">
            <p>One of the old men said, <quote>Be not humble in thy words only, but also in thy
               deeds.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="469">
            <p>On one occasion a certain governor came to see Abbâ <persName>Sîmôn</persName>, and when the old man heard
               of his coming from those who came to make it known to him beforehand, he straightway
               girded up his loins, and went up a palm tree to clean it. And when those who came
               cried out to him, saying, <quote>Old man, tell us where the monk is,</quote> he said unto them,
               <quote>He is not here</quote>; so they departed from that place.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="470">
            <p>One of the fathers from <placeName>Parmê</placeName> told a story of how, on one occasion when he had
               returned to Abbâ <persName>Theodore</persName>, he found him wearing a ragged shirt, and his breast was
               naked and bare, and his outer garment was dragged round in front of him. And, behold,
               a certain Count came to see him, and when his followers knocked at the door, and
               called the old man, he went out to meet him quite carelessly; and I took a small
               piece of coarse cloth and threw it over his shoulders that his breast might be
               covered, but the old man took it in his hand and waved it, and threw it away. And
               when the Count went I said to him, <quote>Father, what is this that thou hast done? For a
               nobleman came unto thee to be helped, and to gain profit, and behold, he hath perhaps
               gone away offended.</quote> And the old man said unto me, <quote>Get thee gone, Abbâ. We are still
               subject unto men. We have done the deed, and he is gone; but whether he wisheth to be
               benefited, or whether he wisheth to be offended is his affair. As for me, as far as I
               am able I shall always meet men of this kind in this way.</quote> And he commanded his
               disciple, saying, <quote>If any man cometh and wisheth to see me, say not to him anything
               after the manner of men, but if I am eating, tell him that I am eating, and if I am
               asleep, tell him that I am asleep.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="471">
            <p>A certain woman who was afflicted in her lungs with the disease called cancer, heard
               concerning <persName>Longinus</persName> and wished to see him; now he used to dwell in [the monastery of]
               <placeName>Hantôn</placeName> in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>. And whilst the woman was seeking and wishing for him, it
               happened that the blessed man was gathering sticks on the sea-shore, and when the
               woman found him, she said unto him, <quote>Father, where dwelleth the man of God, Abbâ
               <persName>Longinus</persName>?</quote> Now she did not know that he himself was <persName>Longinus</persName>. And he said unto her,
               <quote>What dost thou want with that lying hypocrite? Do not go to him, for he is a liar.
               What is it that causeth thee pain?</quote> Then the woman shewed him the place, and the old
               man made the sign of the Cross over it, and he dismissed her, saying, <quote>Go, and may
               our Lord heal thee, for <persName>Longinus</persName> is unable to do thee any good whatsoever.</quote> And the
               woman went away believing in the word, and she was healed straightway; and afterwards
               when she was telling folks the story, she said, <quote>I have learned by the marks which
               were on the old man that he himself was Abbâ <persName>Longinus</persName>.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="472">
            <p>On one occasion a certain governor arranged to see Abbâ <persName>Sîmôn</persName>, and the clergy told
               him beforehand, saying, <quote>Father, make thyself ready, for a certain governor hath
               heard of thy life and works, and he wisheth to come and be blessed by thee</quote>; and the
               old man said unto them, <quote>I am ready.</quote> Then the old man went in and took in his hand
               some bread and cheese, and went out to the door and sat down there, and <pb n="111"/>he changed
               about from place to place eating; and when the governor came with his company, and
               saw him sitting and eating, they despised him, saying, <quote>So this is the monk of whom I
               have heard!</quote> And they left him and departed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="473">
            <p>An old man was asked, <quote>How is it that there are men who say, <quote>We have seen a vision
               of angels?</quote></quote> and the old man said, <quote>Blessed is he who seeth his sins
               continually.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="474">
            <p>They used to say that when any man came to Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> he used to send him to Abbâ
               <persName>Job</persName>, his brother, saying to him, <quote>He is older than I am</quote>; and <persName>Job</persName> used to say to
               those who came, <quote>Go unto my brother <persName>Poemen</persName>, for he possesseth the grace of these
               gifts.</quote> Now if Abbâ <persName>Joseph</persName> was sitting with him Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> would not speak before
               him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="475">
            <p>When a certain brother went to the festival he asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, <quote>What wouldst thou
               have me to do?</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Be thou a friend unto him that leadeth
               thee away by force, and sell thy work graciously.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="476">
            <p>A brother asked an old man, <quote>What is the work of exile?</quote> And the old man said unto
               him, <quote>I knew a brother who went forth into exile, and he went in to lodge in a
               church, and it happened that the brethren were about to eat some of the sacramental
               bread; and when they sat down this man sat down with them. Now when some of the other
               monks saw him, they said, <quote>Who hath brought this man in [to eat] with us?</quote> And one of
               them said [unto him], <quote>Arise, and get thee outside,</quote> and straightway he rose up and
               went forth as the brother had told him; but the others being sorry about this matter
               went out and brought him in. And after these things a certain man asked him, <quote>What
               was in thy mind when thou didst go out and come in again?</quote> He said unto them, <quote>I
               thought in my mind that I was like a dog which when he is driven out goeth out, and
               when he is called cometh in.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="477">
            <p>They used to say that when Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> was one of the clergy he wore a long outer
               garment, and that the Bishop said unto him, <quote>Behold, thou art wholly white, O Abbâ
               <persName>Moses</persName>.</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Is the <persName>Pâpâ</persName> within or without?</quote> And again,
               wishing to try him, the Bishop said unto the clergy, <quote>When Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> goeth into the
               sacrarium drive him out, and go after him and hear what he saith.</quote> Now when he went
               into the sacrarium they rebuked him and drove him out, saying, <quote>Get outside, O
               <persName>Ethiopian</persName></quote>; and having gone forth he began to say to himself, <quote>They have treated thee
               rightly, O thou whose skin is dark and black; thou shalt not go back as if thou wert
               a [white] man.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="478">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>Do not despise or think <pb n="112"/>lightly of him that standeth before
               thee, for thou knowest not whether the Spirit of God is in thee or in him, though
               thou callest him who standeth before thee him that ministereth unto thee.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="479">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>John</persName> the Less used to say, <quote>Humility and the fear of God are more excellent than
               all the [other] virtues.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="480">
            <p>They used to say that a certain old man, who had young men living with him, told them
               on one occasion to do something, and when they did it not he said nothing further to
               them about it, but rose up himself in their sight and did what he had told them to do
               without anger, and without labour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="481">
            <p>Another old man used to say, <quote>Humility is not without salt, but it is salted with
               salt.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="482">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>I would rather learn than teach.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="483">
            <p>And he also used to say, <quote>Do not learn before the time, so that thou mayest not have
               little admonition all thy time.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="484">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Agathon</persName> said, <quote>If a man of wrath were to raise the dead, he would not be
               accepted by any man.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="485">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Timothy</persName>, saying, <quote>I myself can see that my memorial is ever
               before God</quote>; and the old man said unto him, <quote>It would not be any great thing for thy
               thought (or mind) to be with God, but it would be a great thing for a man to see his
               soul beneath all creation.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="486">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Theodore</persName> used to say, <quote>There is no spiritual excellence greater than that of a
               man who despiseth not his companion.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="487">
            <p>An old man was asked, <quote>By what means doth the soul receive humility?</quote> And he said,
               <quote>By searching into it, and by remembering the evil things which have been done by
               it.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="488">
            <p>One of the old men said, <quote>I asked Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName>, saying, <quote>Tell me a word,</quote> and he said,
               <quote>It is right for a monk to humble himself lower than the idols</quote>; and I went to my
               cell, and took counsel with myself, and meditated for an hour, saying, ‘What do the
               words “lower than the idols</quote> mean?’ Then I returned and went to the old man, and said
               unto him, ‘What do the words <quote>lower than the idols</quote> mean?’ And he said unto me, ‘It
               is written concerning the idols, <quote>They have a mouth and speak not, and they have eyes
               and see not, and they have ears and hear not</quote>; even thus is it right for a monk to
               be.’ And because idols are an abomination, a man must hold himself to be abominable
               in his own sight.”</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="489">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Sisoes of <placeName>Thebaïs</placeName></persName>, saying, <quote>Speak a word to me,</quote> and <persName>Sisoes</persName> said
               unto him, <quote>What have I to <pb n="113"/>say unto thee? I read the New Testament, and I reflect on
               the Old Testament.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="490">
            <p>That same brother went to Abbâ <persName>Sisoes of <placeName>Pâtârâ</placeName></persName>, and told him the word which Abbâ
               <persName>Sisoes of the <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName></persName> had spoken, and Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> said unto him, <quote>I lie down to sleep
               in my sins, and I rise up in my sins.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="491">
            <p>There was a certain monk who lost himself in the desert, and he said to himself, <quote>I
               have kept myself rightly, and I possess all the virtues,</quote> and he prayed to God and
               said, <quote>If I be lacking in anything, shew Thou me how I may perform it.</quote> And God,
               wishing to humble his mind, said unto him, <quote>Go to such and such a head of a
               monastery, and whatsoever he telleth thee to do that do.</quote> And God sent a revelation
               to the head of the monastery, and said unto him, <quote>Behold, such and such a monk will
               come unto thee, and say thou unto him, <quote>Take a whip in thy hands, and go forth and
               pasture swine.</quote></quote> And the monk went forth immediately, even as the head of the
               monastery told him, and pastured swine, and when those who had known him formerly,
               and those who had heard about him, saw him pasturing swine, they said, <quote>Ye see the
               great monk about whom we have heard, behold, his heart hath gone mad, and a devil
               hath seized him, and he is [now] pasturing swine.</quote> Then God, when He saw his
               humility, and that he was hearing and bearing the reproach of men, set him free so
               that he might go back where he had been formerly.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="492">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>If a man hath laid some work upon a brother to do, he must
               perform that command in the fear of God and in humility; for he who for God’s sake
               layeth [some work] upon a brother maketh the brother to submit himself thereto, and
               [the one brother] must do what [the other brother] hath laid upon him. But if a man
               wisheth to give commands to a brother, not in the fear of God, but on his own
               authority, wishing to be unto him a master and a governor, God, Who seeth the hidden
               things of his heart, will not allow him to be obedient unto him and to do [that]
               work, for the work that is for God’s sake is evident, and that which is of the man’s
               own authority is well known. For that which is for God’s sake cometh with humility
               and entreaty, whilst the works which are of man’s own authority are with wrath and
               trouble, and they come from the Evil One.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="493">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Isidore</persName>, <quote>Why is it that the devils fear thee so greatly? The
               old man said, “Because from the time that I became a monk I have laboured hard not to
               allow anger to enter into my throat; that is why they fear me.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="494">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>On one occasion I went to <pb n="114"/>the fair to sell with [other]
               brethren a few things, and I saw anger drawing nigh unto me, and I left the things
               and fled straightway.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="495">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>John</persName> the Less used to say, <quote>On one occasion when I was going up on the <placeName>Scete</placeName>
               road with some palm leaves I heard a camel speaking words to me, and he was about to
               make me angry, but I straightway left the palm leaves and fled.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="496">
            <p>The same old man when he was in the harvest [field] heard a brother speaking to his
               companion in anger, saying, <quote>Come hither,</quote> and straightway he left the harvest and
               fled.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="497">
            <p>A brother asked an old man, <quote>Why is it, when I am performing my little services of
               prayer and praise, that I sometimes see in myself that there is nothing lacking in my
               heart, and that I do not wish it?</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>How then can a man
               appear to love God?</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="498">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>John</persName> the Less said unto the brethren who were with him, <quote>Although we be little
               folk in the eyes of men, let us consider how we may be held in honour before
               God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="499">
            <p>They used to say that Abbâ <persName>Patrâ</persName> and Abbâ <persName>Ampîkôs</persName> were close and affectionate
               friends, and that when the old men were eating in the church, and they were urging
               them to come to the table of the fathers, it was only with hard work that Abbâ <persName>Patrâ</persName>
               would go by himself; and after he had eaten, Abbâ <persName>Ampîkôs</persName> said unto him, <quote>How didst
               thou dare to go to the table of the old men?</quote> Abbâ <persName>Patrâ</persName> said unto him, <quote>If I had sat
               with you the brethren would have honoured me as an old man, and they would have
               required it of me to be the first to say the blessing, and I might have thought in my
               mind that I was greater than you all. But since I went to the fathers I am the least
               of you all, and I am abased, and I think in my thoughts that I am nothing.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="500">
            <p>On one occasion a brother committed sin in the church, and the priest drove him out
               therefrom, and there was there a man of discretion whose name was <persName>Bessarion</persName>, and he
               also arose and went out of the church, and said, <quote>If ye have judged that this man who
               hath committed only one offence is not fit to worship God, how very much less fit am
               I, who have committed many sins, to do so?</quote> And the old man said, <quote> <quote>Woe be unto him
               that is without more than unto him that is within,</quote> that is to say, <quote>Woe be unto him
               that is [within him that is without!</quote>] Now this is what I would say, When a man in
               the world findeth a cause [of complaint] against a man who liveth a life of silent
               contemplation, or who hath departed from the world, this is a [cause of] judgement
               and of a fall unto him who giveth him reason [for complaint]. Take the greatest
               possible care then, O monk, not to commit sin, lest <pb n="115"/>thou disgrace God, Who dwelleth
               in thee, and drive Him out from thy soul.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="501">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Pîôr</persName> worked hard to be able to overcome the disposition to say <quote>Thou</quote> to any of
               the brethren.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="502">
            <p>The disciple of Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> used to say, <quote>When the old man was about to die, he
               commanded us, saying, <quote>Do not let it be a care unto you to make a commemoration for
               me, but offer up the Offering only; for, he used to say, if during my life-time I
               have done anything which is worthy of commemoration, I shall most certainly find [a
               memorial of it].</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="503">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName> said, <quote>A man may pass one hundred years in his cell, and not know rightly
               how a monk should live in his cell, or even how to live secluded for one day.</quote> And he
               used to say, <quote>The proper way and manner for a monk to live is to condemn himself
               continually.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="504">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> used to say, <quote>If a man will only condemn himself he will be able to
               endure and continue wheresoever he dwelleth.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="505">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> used to say, <quote>We live in the troubles and trials which come upon us
               because we do not take to ourselves the humble names which the Scriptures have given
               us; and because we do not consider how our Lord <persName>Jesus</persName> relieved the Canaanitish woman
               (St. Matthew 15:22) who took to herself abominable names, moreover, we do not
               consider how, when <persName>Abigail</persName> said unto <persName>David</persName>, <quote>On me be the sin</quote> (1 Samuel 25:24), he
               was entreated by her and loved her. <persName>Abigail</persName> must be taken as [representing] the
               person of the soul, and <persName>David</persName> as the Godhead; if then, the soul will condemn itself
               before God, He will love it, and will give it the delight of rest.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="506">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>In all thy trials blame no man; blame thyself only, saying,
               <quote>These things have happened to me because of my sins.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="507">
            <p>On one occasion Abbâ <persName>John</persName> was called to the church, and the brethren surrounded him
               and asked him questions about their thoughts; and one of the old men said unto him,
               <quote><persName>John</persName> is like unto a whore who adorneth herself that she may multiply lovers for
               herself; thus art thou.</quote> And Abbâ <persName>John</persName> sighed and said, <quote>Father, thou hast spoken the
               truth.</quote> Afterwards a certain man told him that he loved him, [and said], <quote>Art thou
               not disturbed within?</quote> He said unto him, <quote>No. But as I am without, even so am I
               within.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="508">
            <p>One of the old men used to say about Abbâ <persName>John</persName>, that he lived in such a way that,
               through the humility which he possessed, he held all <placeName>Scete</placeName> suspended on his
               finger.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="509">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>John of the <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName></persName> used to say that, before all <pb n="116"/>else, it was right for a monk
               to acquire humility, for this was the first commandment of our blessed Redeemer, Who
               said, <quote>Blessed are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the kingdom of God</quote> (St. Matthew
               5:3).</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="510">
            <p><persName>John Kolob</persName> used to say, <quote>Humility is the door which leadeth into the kingdom, and our
               fathers, through many revilings, have gone into the city of God rejoicing.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="511">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>It is good for a man to say, <quote>Forgive me,</quote> and then to make
               an offering of something; for this suiteth the monkish garb.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="512">
            <p>The same old man also said, <quote>A dog is better than I am, for he hath love, and he
               cometh not to judgement.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="513">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Eupraxius</persName> used to say, <quote>The tree of life which riseth in the heights is
               humility.</quote> He also said, <quote>Make thyself like unto the publican; and be not made guilty
               with the <persName>Pharisee</persName>; choose for thyself the meekness of <persName>Moses</persName>, so that thine heart,
               which is as hard as steel, thou mayest change into a fountain of water.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="514">
            <p>One of the old men said, <quote>I would rather have defeat with humility than conquest with
               boasting.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="515">
            <p>An old man said, <quote>When the thought of pride goeth up in thee, and thou becomest
               arrogant, examine thy conscience [and see] if thou hast kept all the commandments,
               and if thou lovest thine enemies, and if thou lovest the approbation of thine enemy,
               and if thou art grieved when he is afflicted, and if thou art considered by thyself
               to be an unprofitable servant, and a sinner greater than any other man. And even if
               thou hast performed rightly all the demands of ascetic excellence, thou shalt not be
               proud, for thou must know that the thought of pride abrogateth and maketh
               unprofitable all the virtues.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="516">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>He who is held in greater honour or is more praised than he
               deserveth suffereth great loss; but the man who receiveth neither honour nor praise
               from men shall be praised above all.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="517">
            <p>A brother asked an old man, saying, <quote>Is it a good thing for us to repent many times?</quote>
               The old man said unto him, <quote>We see that when <persName>Joshua</persName>, the son of <persName>Nun</persName>, lay upon his
               face the Lord spake with him</quote> (Joshua 5:14).</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="518">
            <p>An old man was asked, <quote>Why do the devils fight against us in the way they do?</quote> And he
               said, <quote>Because we throw away from us our armour, that is to say, obedience, humility,
               and abstinence.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="519">
            <p>The old men used to say, <quote>Whensoever we have no war to wage then especially it is
               meet that we should abase ourselves, for God, because He knoweth our feebleness,
               <pb n="117"/>giveth us His protection for nothing, but if we boast ourselves, He removeth it from
               us and we perish.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="520">
            <p>A brother asked an old man, saying, <quote>What is the perfection of a monk?</quote> The old man
               saith unto him, <quote>Humility, for when once a man hath arrived at humility, he can reach
               forward to the goal.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="521">
            <p>The old man said, <quote>If a man can say unto his brother, <quote>Forgive me,</quote> and can humble
               himself, this belongeth to the perfection of the monk.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="522">
            <p>One of the old men said, <quote>When a man saith unto his companion, <quote>Forgive me,</quote> and at
               the same time humbleth himself, the devils are consumed.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="523">
            <p>A certain brother was offended at his brother, and when the latter heard thereof he
               went to him to express his contrition, but he would not open the door; then he who
               had offended his brother went to another old man and related the matter unto him, and
               the old man answered and said, <quote>Observe lest in thine own mind thou art justifying
               thyself, and art condemning thy brother, as if he were the offender, for it may be
               that because of this he would not be persuaded to open unto thee. Nevertheless, do
               thou what I am going to tell thee. For although he hath offended thee, go thou, and
               hold firmly [to the belief] that thou hast offended against him, and may God put it
               into thy brother’s mind to be reconciled to thee.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="524">
            <p>And the old man related unto him a story which explained the matter, saying, <quote>There
               were two men who were living in the world, and were fearers of God, and they were
               both of the same mind, and they went forth and became monks; and when they heard in a
               plain manner the word of the Gospel which saith, <quote>There are eunuchs who have made
               themselves eunuchs for the sake of the kingdom of heaven</quote> (St. Matthew 19:12), they
               arrived at the hottest point of their love, and they made themselves eunuchs for the
               sake of the kingdom of heaven. Now when the Bishopheard [of this] he set them aside
               and excommunicated them. Then those men, wishing to show that they had done what was
               good, said unto one another, <quote>We have made ourselves eunuchs for the sake of the
               kingdom of heaven, and this Bishop driveth us out! Let us go and make a complaint
               against him to the head of our monasteries, that is, to the <persName>Bishop of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName></persName></quote>; and
               when they had gone to him they related unto him the whole matter. Then the Bishop
               said unto them, <quote>And I also set you aside and excommunicate you</quote>; and being greatly
               grieved at this remark also they went to the <persName>Bishop of <placeName>Antioch</placeName></persName>, and related the
               matter unto him, and he also drove them away with the same words. <pb n="118"/>Then the two
               brethren said unto each other, <quote>Let us go to the <persName>Patriarch of <placeName>Rome</placeName></persName>, and he will
               avenge us and will take vengeance on all these [Bishops].</quote> And having gone to the
               great <persName>Patriarch and Bishop of <placeName>Rome</placeName></persName>, and made him to know their matter, and what the
               <persName>Bishop and Patriarch [of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>]</persName> had said unto them, they said at length, <quote>We have
               come unto thee because thou art the head of them all.</quote> Then the <persName>Bishop of <placeName>Rome</placeName></persName> also
               said unto them, <quote>I also excommunicate you and excommunicate ye shall be.</quote> Then, not
               knowing what to do, they said to each other, <quote>All these men accept the persons each
               of the other, and each honoureth the other, because they are accustomed to assemble
               together at the Synods, but let us go to the holy man of God, <persName>Epiphanius</persName>, Bishop of
               <placeName>Cyprus</placeName>, because he is indeed a Bishop, and he doth not accept the person of any man.</quote>
               Now when they drew nigh unto the city, it was revealed unto <placeName>Epiphanius</placeName> concerning
               them, and he sent [a man] to meet them, and to say unto them, <quote>Ye shall not come into
               the city.</quote> And when they came to themselves they repented, and said, <quote>In very truth
               we have sinned; with what can we justify ourselves? For, even supposing that the
               Bishop and the Patriarchs have excommunicated us in an unseemly manner, peradventure
               this man is a prophet besides, for behold, God hath revealed unto him concerning us
               beforehand; let us then condemn ourselves in respect of everything which we have
               done.</quote> Then when God, Who knoweth that which is in the hearts [of men] saw that they
               had in very truth condemned themselves, He worked upon the mind of <placeName>Epiphanius</placeName> so
               that, of his own accord, he sent and brought them, and associated them in communion
               with him. And he also wrote concerning them to the Bishop of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, saying,
               <quote>Receive thy sons, for they have repented in truth.</quote></quote></p>
            <p>And the old man said, <quote>This is the healing of a man, and God desireth that a man
               should lay the offence of his companion upon himself.</quote> And when that brother heard
               [this story] he acted according to the word[s] of the old man, and he went and
               knocked at the door of that brother, who, immediately he perceived and knew from
               inside [that it was he], expressed his contrition to him whilst he was as yet inside,
               and then straightway opened the door; and they made friends together, each with each,
               with all their souls, and the two of them were in great peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="525">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> used to say, <quote>As the earth falleth not, because it is fixed from below,
               even so he who abaseth himself shall never fall.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="526">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> asked Abbâ <persName>’Ôr</persName>, and said unto him, <quote>Tell <pb n="119"/>me a word of excellence</quote>; and he
               said unto him, <quote>Dost thou think me true, and dost thou believe my promise?</quote> And Abbâ
               <persName>Sisoes</persName> said unto him, <quote>Yes.</quote> Abbâ <persName>’Ôr</persName> said unto him, <quote>Go, and whatsoever ye have seen
               me do, that also do thyself</quote>; and Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> said unto him, <quote>What do I see in thee,
               O my father?</quote> And Abbâ <persName>’Or</persName> answered and said unto him, <quote>My mind is more abased than
               that of the least of all the children of men.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="527">
            <p>On one occasion seven brethren came to Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> and they entreated him, saying,
               <quote>What is the work of monks?</quote> And the old man answered and said, <quote>When I came to dwell
               in this place I went to two old men, and I asked them this same question. And they
               answered and said unto me, <quote>Dost thou believe in us?</quote> and I said, <quote>Yes.</quote> Then they
               said unto me, <quote>Go, and whatsoever thou hast seen us do, that also do thyself.</quote></quote> And
               the brethren asked him subsequently, saying, <quote>Tell us, father, what was their work?</quote>
               Then the old man said unto them, <quote>The one acquired great humility, and the other
               obedience.</quote> And they said unto him next, <quote>Tell us what is thy work?</quote> and the old man
               said unto them, <quote>According to my will, and according to my mind; it is a great thing
               for a man not to bind himself with any matter</quote>; and having profited they departed in
               gladness, giving praise unto God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="528">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, saying, <quote>What shall I do with the weight of weariness
               which holdeth me?</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>Both large and small boats are
               provided with thick ropes for towing, and if there be blowing a wind which is not
               favourable to the course of the ship, they throw them round their breasts and pull
               them along [from] dry land; and quietly and little by little they let the ship go on
               her way until God sendeth a wind which is suitable for bearing her along
               whithersoever they wish her to go. But if they learn that a storm hath begun to rise,
               they make haste and drive a stake in the ground, and tie up the ship lest she should
               drift away. Now the stake is that a man should condemn himself.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="529">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, <quote>How is it possible for a man to avoid speaking evilly
               to his neighbour?</quote> The old man answered and said unto him, <quote>We and our brethren
               possess two images. Whensoever then a man condemneth himself, his brother appeareth
               unto him beautiful and excellent; but whensoever a man appeareth beautiful to
               himself, his brother will be found to be, in his sight, hateful and abominable.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="530">
            <p>Another old man said also, <quote>Humility is not insipidity, but it is seasoned, as it
               were, with salt.</quote></p>
            <pb n="120"/>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="531">
            <p>He also used to say, <quote>For a man to despise himself is a strong wall.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="532">
            <p>He also used to say, <quote>Him who hath become despised for our Lord’s sake, will our Lord
               make wise.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="533">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>Take heed, with all thy might, that thou doest nothing which
               meriteth blame, and desire not to adorn thyself.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="534">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>If humility descendeth to <placeName>Sheol</placeName> it is exalted unto the
               heavens; and although pride goeth up to the heavens it shall be brought down to
               <placeName>Sheol</placeName>.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="535">
            <p>There were two brethren in <placeName>Scete</placeName>, and he who was younger than his fellow was the
               older in the monastic garb, and one of the fathers having come to visit them, they
               brought out a vessel of water and wanted to wash him. And the man who was the younger
               in respect of years drew nigh to wash the old man, but the old man laid hold upon his
               hands, and prevented him, and then he drew near him that was the elder [in respect of
               years] to wash him. And the brethren who were standing near him said unto him, <quote>The
               younger brother, O father, is the older in respect of the monastic garb</quote>; then the
               old man said unto them, <quote>I take the priority in the monastic garb of the younger man
               and place it upon him that is the elder.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="536">
            <p>There was a certain brother in a monastery, and he used to take the whole weight of
               the brethren upon himself, and seeking to be held in contempt in the sight of every
               man, he used to make accusations against himself, even to the committing of
               fornication, and he used to say, <quote>I have committed it.</quote> Now the brethren who did not
               understand his life and works used to murmur against him, saying, <quote>How very many are
               the wickednesses which this man doeth here, and because of them he doth not even
               work.</quote> Then their Abbâ, because he knew his works, and because he knew also that he
               was taking the affairs of every man upon himself, and that he did not do these
               things, spake unto the brethren, saying, <quote>I will undertake that he will make one mat
               in a week, in humility, [which is more than all] your work [which is done] with
               boasting, and if ye wish to know whether the matter be so [or not], bring hither all
               your work, and bring hither also the mat of that brother, and light a fire and throw
               therein all your work</quote>; [and when they had done so] everything was consumed except
               the mat of that brother. Now when the brethren saw this, they feared, and expressed
               their contrition, and from that time they held him to be an Abbâ.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="537">
            <p>They used to say that Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> never gave his mind to the Lord, and that his
               knowledge was superior to that of [any] one of the old men.</p>
            <pb n="121"/>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="538">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName> asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> concerning the impure thoughts that were born of a man,
               and [concerning] vain lusts; and Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said unto him, <quote>Shall the axe boast
               itself against him that wieldeth it?</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="539">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Betimius</persName> asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, saying, <quote>If a man be angry with me, and I express my
               contrition, and he will not accept it, what am I to do?</quote> the old man said unto him,
               <quote>Take with thee two of thy friends, and express thy contrition [in their presence].</quote>
               And the old man <persName>Betimius</persName> said unto him, And if he will not be persuaded [to accept
               it] then? And Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> answered and said, <quote>Take with thee five others</quote>; and Abbâ
               <persName>Betimius</persName> answered and said, <quote>And if he will not be persuaded by these?</quote> Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>
               saith, <quote>Then take with thee a priest</quote>; and Abbâ <persName>Betimius</persName> said, <quote>And if he will not be
               persuaded [then]?</quote> Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said unto him, <quote>Without anger and without excitement
               pray unto God that He may put into his mind [the desire for peace], and straightway
               thou shalt have no further care.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="540">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>Tell me, brother, if thou hast acquired the seal of work,
               which is humility?</quote> A holy man who saw another sinning wept bitterly, saying, <quote>This
               man may sin to-day, but how many times shall I sin to-morrow? In whatsoever way a man
               may sin before thee, do not condemn him, but think in thy mind that thou art a
               greater sinner than he, even though he be a man in the world, and [remember] besides
               that he is sinning greatly against God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="541">
            <p>Certain brethren went to visit Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, and whilst they were sitting with him,
               they praised a certain brother, saying, <quote>He hateth evil things.</quote> Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said
               unto him that spake unto him, <quote>What is the hatred of evil things?</quote> Now the brother
               was astonished, and he found nothing to say; and he rose up and threw himself before
               the old man, saying: <quote>Do thou tell me what is “the hatred of evil things.</quote> And the
               old man said unto him, The hatred of evil things is for a man to hate his own sins,
               and to justify those of his neighbour.”</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="542">
            <p>A certain brother committed an offence in <placeName>Scete</placeName>, the camp of the monks, and when a
               congregation was assembled on this matter, they sent after Abbâ. <persName>Moses</persName>, but he
               refused to come; then they sent the priest of the church to him, saying, <quote>Come, for
               all the people are expecting thee,</quote> and he rose up and came. And he took a basket
               with a hole in it and filled it with sand, and carried it upon his shoulders, and
               those who went out to meet him said unto him, <quote>What meaneth this, O father?</quote> And he
               said unto them, <quote>[The sands are] my sins which are running down behind me and I
               cannot see them, and I, even I, have come this day to judge shortcomings <pb n="122"/>which are
               not mine.</quote> And when they heard [this] they set free that brother and said nothing
               [further] to him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="543">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> entreated Abbâ <persName>Zechariah</persName>, saying, <quote>Speak a word of consolation unto the
               brethren,</quote> and <quote><persName>Zechariah</persName> took his cloak, and laid it beneath his feet, saying,
               Except a man let himself be trodden upon thus he cannot be a monk.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="544">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Alônîs</persName>, saying, <quote>What is the meaning of a man despising
               himself?</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>It meaneth that thou must set thyself below all
               the beasts, for thou must remember that they will not be judged.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="545">
            <p>And the same old man said also, <quote>If a man accustom himself to be a teacher, this act
               belongeth to labour.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="546">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, saying, <quote>What is the right manner for me to live in my
               cell?</quote> Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said unto him, <quote>How a man should live in his cell is known to men,
               that is to say, he must work with his hands, and eat once [daily], and hold his peace
               always, and meditate on the Holy Scriptures; but for a man to gain profit inwardly
               (or secretly), he must bear the condemnation of himself whithersoever he goeth, and
               he must not neglect the times of service and of secret labour. And if it happen that
               thou hast made the time unprofitable, when thou goest into the congregation of
               service complete thy service without troubling thyself; by the fulfilment of these
               things, grasp to thyself an upright congregation, so that thou mayest draw nigh
               thereto, but keep thyself remote from the assemblies of evil things.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="547">
            <p>On one occasion when Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> was in his cell the devils rose up against him and
               vexed him; and those who used to minister to him came to him, and as they stood
               outside his cell they heard him crying out to God, saying, <quote>O God, forsake me not. I
               have never done before Thee anything which is good, but grant, O Lord, according to
               Thy grace, that I may begin in the way.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="548">
            <p>Now, when he was about to die <persName>Alexander</persName> and <persName>Zoilus</persName>, his brethren and disciples, were
               greatly disturbed, and he said unto them, <quote>Why are ye troubled? The hour hath not yet
               come.</quote> They said unto him, <quote>We are not troubled about thee, father.</quote> And he said unto
               them, <quote>When the hour hath come I will tell you, for it will be for me to rise up
               against you before the throne of <persName>Christ</persName> if ye give my bones to any man.</quote> Then they
               said unto him, <quote>What shall we do then? For we do not know how to bury [thee].</quote> The
               old man said unto them, <quote>Do ye not know how to throw a cord round my legs and to
               carry me outside the mountain?</quote></p>
            <pb n="123"/>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="549">
            <p>And his word at all times was this, <quote><persName>Arsenius</persName>, because thou didst go forth</quote>; and he
               used to repeat this saying, <quote>That I have spoken I have many times repented; that I
               held my peace I have never repented.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="550">
            <p>On one occasion the governor of the country seized one of the inhabitants of his
               village, and the people entreated the old man to go and bring out him that had been
               seized; and the old man said unto them, <quote>Leave me for three days, and afterwards I
               will go.</quote> Then Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> prayed to the Lord, and said, <quote>Lord, if thou dost not
               grant me this act of grace the people will not allow me to live in this place</quote>; and
               the old man went to entreat the governor, and the governor said unto him, <quote>Yea,
               father, thou makest entreaty for a thief.</quote> And the old man rejoiced that he did not
               receive from Him this act of grace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="551">
            <p>On one occasion certain old men went to visit Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>, and Abbâ <persName>Joseph</persName> was with
               them, and the old man wishing to try them spake a word from the Book, and began to
               question the youngest of them, saying, <quote>What is the meaning of this word?</quote> And each
               of them said, <quote>I have never yet understood it,</quote> and last of all Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> said
               unto Abbâ <persName>Joseph</persName>, <quote>And what dost thou say that this word meaneth?</quote> Abbâ <persName>Joseph</persName> saith,
               <quote>I do not know.</quote> And Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> said unto him, <quote>In truth, Abbâ <persName>Joseph</persName>, thou hast
               found the way to say, <quote>I do not know.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="552">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Muthues</persName> said, <quote>In proportion as a man draweth nigh unto God, it is meet that he
               should regard himself as a sinner, for the Prophet <persName>Isaiah</persName> (chap. 6:5), who saw the
               Lord, calleth himself wretched and unclean.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="553">
            <p>The old man used to say, <quote>Who sold <persName>Joseph</persName>?</quote> They said unto him, <quote>His brethren,</quote> and
               the old man said unto them, <quote>No, it was humility that sold him. For he never said, <quote>I
               am your brother,</quote> and he never answered them, but held his peace. He sold himself by
               his humility, and this humility made him governor over the land of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="554">
            <p>A brother came to Abbâ <persName>Muthues</persName>, and said unto him, <quote>How is it that those who are in
               <placeName>Scete</placeName> do more than that which is written in the Book, for they love their enemies
               more than themselves?</quote> <persName>Muthues</persName> said unto them, <quote>I do not yet love even the man who
               loveth me more than I love myself.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="555">
            <p>There was a certain old man in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> before those who belonged to the company of Abbâ
               <persName>Poemen</persName> came there, and he possessed knowledge and great honour; and when those of the
               following of Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> went up from <placeName>Scete</placeName>, every man left [that old man] and came
               to Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> and those who <pb n="124"/>were with him, and the old man was filled with envy, and
               he cursed the followers of Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> because of this. Now Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> heard of it,
               and he was vexed about it, and he said unto the brethren who were with him, <quote>What
               shall we do for this old man? For the men who have forsaken him have cast us into
               vexation, and they have left that holy old man and turned their looks upon us, who
               are nothing. How then can we satisfy this old man?</quote> Then he said unto the brethren
               who were with him, <quote>Make ye some bread and boil a little food, and we will go to him,
               and will take with us also a vessel of wine, and we will eat with him, and perhaps by
               these means we shall be able to pacify him</quote>; and they took the food and went to him.
               And when they had knocked at the door his disciple looked out and asked them, <quote>Who
               are ye?</quote> And they said unto him, <quote>Tell the Abbâ that it is <persName>Poemen</persName>, and he wisheth to
               be blessed by him</quote>; and when his disciple had told him this, the old man said, <quote>Send
               them away,</quote> and he said, <quote>I have not leisure [to receive them].</quote> Then the disciple
               told them these things, but they stayed there lovingly, saying, <quote>We will not go away
               unless we are held to be worthy of the blessing of the old man.</quote> Now, when the old
               man saw their humility and patient persistence, he repented, and opened the door to
               them, and when they were eating together, he said unto them, <quote>Verily, the things
               which I have heard were in you are not in you, but indeed what I see in you is a
               hundredfold [greater than what I expected]</quote>; and he became unto them a friend from
               that day.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="556">
            <p>On a certain occasion when Abbâ <persName>John</persName> was sitting before the church, the brethren
               surrounded him, and asked him about their thoughts, and when one of the old men saw
               him, he said unto him, <quote>Thy repentance is full of sorceries.</quote> Abbâ <persName>John</persName> said unto
               him, <quote>It is even so, and this thou sayest having only seen what is without, but if
               thou couldst see what is within what wouldst thou say?</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="557">
            <p><persName>Muthues</persName> repeated the following:—<quote>When I was a young man I used to say to myself,
               <quote>Perhaps thou wilt do something good</quote>; but now that I am an old man I see that I have
               not done even one good work.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="558">
            <p>He used to say concerning Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> that, if the brethren drew nigh unto him in
               fear, as to a great and holy old man, he would not answer them a word, but if one of
               the brethren treated him with familiar contempt, [saying], <quote>Father, if thou wert a
               camel wouldst thou not steal the natron and sell it, and would not the driver beat
               thee?</quote> he would answer him. And if any man spake unto him in anger, or with words
               similar to these, he would answer any question which was put to him.</p>
            <pb n="125"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
