<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Of Patient Endurance</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_6">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_6 </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 6: Of Patient Endurance</head>
         <div type="saying" n="183">
            <p>On one occasion certain brethren went to Abbâ <persName>Agathon</persName>, because they had heard that he
               took the greatest possible care that his mind should not be disturbed by anything,
               and they sought to try him, and to see if his mind would rise [to any matter]; and
               they said unto him, <quote>Art thou indeed <persName>Agathon</persName>? We have heard that thou art a
               whoremonger and a boastful man.</quote> And <persName>Agathon</persName> said unto them, <quote>Yea, I am.</quote> And again
               they said unto him, <quote><persName>Agathon</persName>, thou art a garrulous and talkative old man</quote>; and he
               said unto them, <quote>Indeed I am.</quote> And again they said unto him, <quote><persName>Agathon</persName>, thou art a
               heretic</quote>; and he said unto them, <quote>I am not a heretic.</quote> Then they said unto him, <quote>Tell
               us now why in answer to all these things which we have said to thee thou hast
               replied, <quote>Yea,</quote> and that thou hast endured them all with the exception of the
               accusation of being a heretic.</quote> Abbâ <persName>Agathon</persName> said unto them, <quote>The earlier things I
               accounted as profitable to my soul, but heresy meaneth separation from God, and I do
               not wish to be separated from God.</quote> And when the brethren heard [these words] they
               marvelled at his solicitude, and went away rejoicing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="184">
            <p>A certain father used to tell the story of a father who had a book wherein were the
               New Testament and the Old Testament, and the price thereof was more than eighteen
               darics, and he laid up the book in a hole in the wall; and there came a certain
               stranger and stayed there, and he coveted the book greatly, and stole it, and
               departed, but the old man did not go after him, although he knew that he had taken
               it. And the brother went to a neighbouring village and wished to sell the book, and
               he asked as its price sixteen darics, and the man who wanted to buy it said unto him,
               <quote>Give it to me, that I may shew it [to a friend],</quote> and he took it and carried it to
               the old man who had lost it. Then the old man said unto him, <quote>How much doth he ask
               for it?</quote> And when he heard how much he said to him, <quote>It is well</quote> (or <quote>it is a good
               price</quote>). Then the man went and said unto the brother who wished to sell the <pb n="40"/>book,
               <quote>Behold, I have shewn it to Father So-and-so, and he hath told me that thy price is
               dear.</quote> And the brother answered and said unto him, <quote>I did not tell thee anything to
               the contrary,</quote> and the would-be buyer said, <quote>No, thou didst not.</quote> Said the brother,
               <quote>I will not then sell thee the book,</quote> and straightway he repented, and came to the
               old man and made excuses to him, and offered him the book, but the old man refused to
               accept it. And the brother entreated him, saying, <quote>Allow me [to restore it to thee],
               O father, for if thou dost not accept it I cannot obtain life</quote>; so the old man was
               entreated, and he took it, and that brother remained with him until his death, and
               through the patient endurance of the old man he gained life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="185">
            <p>On one occasion certain philosophers came to the desert to try the monks. And there
               was living there a man who led a life of fair works, and they said unto him, <quote>Come
               thou hither,</quote> and his anger rose and he reviled them. Now there passed by a certain
               great monk who was a Libyan, and they said unto him, <quote>O thou monk who hast grown
               greyheaded in iniquity, come hither</quote>; and he went to them readily, and they smote him
               on one cheek, whereupon he turned the other to them. And when they saw this they rose
               up straightway and worshipped him, and they said, <quote>Verily this is a monk</quote>; then they
               set him in their midst, and asked him, saying, <quote>What things do ye who are living in
               the desert do more than we? Ye fast, and we also fast; ye lead pure lives, and we
               also lead pure lives; whatsoever ye do we also do; what do ye who live in the desert
               do more than we?</quote> The Libyan said unto them, <quote>We keep watch over our minds</quote>; and the
               philosophers said unto him, <quote>We are unable to keep watch over our minds.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="186">
            <p>They say that Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> the Egyptian on one occasion went up from <placeName>Scete</placeName> to the
               <placeName>Nitrian mountain</placeName>, and as he drew nigh unto a certain place, he said unto his
               disciple, <quote>Pass on a little in front of me</quote>; and when he had done so there met him a
               certain heathen priest, who was running along and carrying some wood about the time
               of noon. And that brother cried out to him and said, <quote>O minister unto devils, whither
               runnest thou?</quote> And the priest turned round and smote him with many severe blows, and
               he left him with but very little breath remaining in him, and he took up his wood and
               went on his way; and when he had gone on a little further the blessed <persName>Macarius</persName> met
               him on his journey, and said unto him, <quote>Mayest thou be helped, O man of labours?</quote> And
               the priest was astonished, and came to him and said, <quote>What fair thing hast thou seen
               in me that thou shouldst salute me [in this gracious <pb n="41"/>fashion]?</quote> And the old man said
               unto him, <quote>I see that thou toilest, and that thou dost not know that thou art toiling
               for naught</quote>; then he said unto the old man, <quote>At thy salutation I also was very sorry,
               and I learned that thou didst belong to the Great God. But a wicked monk met me just
               before thou didst, and he cursed me, and I smote him even unto death.</quote> And the old
               man knew that it was his disciple [of whom he spake], and the priest laid hold upon
               the feet of <persName>Macarius</persName>, and said unto him, <quote>I will not let thee [go] until thou makest
               me a monk</quote>; and they came to the place where the brother was lying, and they carried
               him and brought him to the church of the mountain. Now when the fathers saw the
               heathen priest with him, they marvelled that he had been converted from the error
               which he had held; and <persName>Macarius</persName> took him and made him a monk, and through him many of
               the heathen became Christians. And Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> said, <quote> <quote>An evil word maketh wicked
               even those who are good, and a good word maketh good even those who are wicked,</quote> as
               it is written.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="187">
            <p>On one occasion thieves came to the cell of an old man, and said unto him, <quote>We have
               come to take away everything which thou hast in thy cell</quote>; and he said unto them, <quote>My
               sons, take whatsoever ye please</quote>; and they took everything which they saw in his cell
               and departed. Now they forgot [to take] a wallet which was hanging there, and the old
               man took it and ran after them, and entreated them, saying, <quote>My sons, take this
               wallet which ye have left behind in your cell.</quote> And when the thieves saw this they
               marvelled at the good disposition of the old man, and they gave back everything which
               they had taken from his cell, and they repented, and said to each other, <quote>Verily,
               this man is a man of God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="188">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> the monk loved money so little that, on one occasion when thieves came
               to his cell by night, and took out whatsoever they could find in it, as soon as he
               perceived what they were doing, he helped them in their work and also to carry [their
               plunder] out of the desert.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="189">
            <p>They say that once when Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> was absent a thief entered his cell, and that
               when he returned and found a thief therein loading upon a camel everything which he
               had in his cell, he also went in and took some of the things and laid them on the
               camel; and when the thief had loaded the camel, he began to beat it in order to make
               it rise up, but it would not move. Now when Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> saw that the beast would
               not stand up, he took a basket which was remaining, and brought it out and laid it on
               the camel, and said, <quote>The camel wisheth to carry off this also, O brother, and
               because of this <pb n="42"/>it would not stand up.</quote> Then the old man cried out to the camel,
               <quote>Stand up,</quote> and straightway, because of the old man’s words, it stood up; but when it
               had gone forward for a little it lay down again, and it would not rise up until the
               thief had emptied the whole of its load.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="190">
            <p>And another of the fathers when he was being plundered said unto the thieves, <quote>Make
               haste, and be quick, before the brethren come.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="191">
            <p>On one occasion when some men of iniquity, and doers of wickedness, and thieves, rose
               up against him on the eve of the day of the congregation, an old man said unto the
               brethren, <quote>Let them do their work, and let us do ours.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="192">
            <p>And when certain evil-doers rose up against one of the brethren in his cell, he
               brought forth a basin and entreated them to wash their feet, and the thieves were
               ashamed and repented.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="193">
            <p>And another brother who was travelling on a journey, and did not know the road, asked
               a man to shew him the way and to direct him; now the man whom he had asked was an
               evil-doer, and he led the brother out of his road into a waste place, and he made him
               to arrive at the river <placeName>Nile</placeName>, which he commanded the brother to cross over. And when
               he began to cross over, behold a crocodile was swiftly pursuing the man who was a
               thief, but the servant of God, not being unmindful of him, cried out to him, and made
               known to him concerning the fierce attack which the animal was about to make. Then,
               the thief having been delivered from death, gave thanks to that brother, and
               marvelled at his affection, and protected him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="194">
            <p>The blessed <persName>Pîôr</persName> was on one occasion working for a man in the fields in the summer
               time, and he was weary, and reminded the lord of his hire about his wages, and when
               he delayed [in paying him] Abbâ <persName>Pîôr</persName> returned to his monastery. And on another
               occasion, when the time of harvest had arrived, Abbâ <persName>Pîôr</persName> went to the same man, and
               reaped his crops with a good will, and he returned to his monastery, the man having
               given him nothing. And again in the third year Abbâ <persName>Pîôr</persName> came and helped him to
               harvest his crops, and when he had made an end of the work of harvest according to
               custom, and yet received nothing, he departed again to his monastery. Meanwhile the
               man, who was worthy of blessing, laboured according to his custom in the life and
               works of spiritual excellence, and rejoiced that he had been defrauded of his hire.
               And <persName>Christ</persName> worked upon the lord of his hire in his house, and he took the wages of
               the blessed man, and went round about among the monasteries seeking for him, and
               when, after the greatest difficulty, he had found him, he fell at his feet and
               <pb n="43"/>entreated him to receive his hire. But when the holy man refused the wages and said,
               <quote>Perhaps thou hast need of them, and as for me God will give me my hire,</quote> the man
               increased his supplications unto him, and finally the holy man permitted him to give
               the money to the church.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="195">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>We do not advance because we do not know our capacity, and
               we have not sufficient patience in the work which we begin, and we wish to possess
               spiritual excellences without working for them, and we go from place to place, and
               expect to find some spot where <persName>Satan</persName> is not, and when we see the temptation of <persName>Satan</persName>
               in that place whereunto we have been called, he who knoweth what the war is will
               remain in God. For the kingdom of heaven is within you.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="196">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>If it should happen that a sickness of the body overtake
               thee, let it not be grievous unto thee, for if thy Lord wisheth thee to be sick in
               the body, who art thou that thou shouldst be in despair? Doth He not take care for
               thee in everything? Couldst thou live without Him? Be patient, and entreat thou Him
               to give thee such things as are helpful, and which are according to His will; and
               besides this eat thou His food of grace with long-suffering.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="197">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> used to say, <quote>The certain sign that a monk is a monk is made known by
               trials (or temptations).</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="198">
            <p>A certain brother was estranged from a fellow monk, and he came to Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> the
               Theban, and said unto him, <quote>I am estranged from a fellow monk, and I wish to take
               vengeance for myself</quote>; and the old man said, <quote>Let us pray.</quote> And whilst he was
               praying, he said in his prayer, <quote>O God, henceforward we have no need of Thee to take
               care of us, for we will take vengeance for ourselves</quote>; and when the brother heard
               these words he fell down at the feet of the old man straightway, and said unto him,
               <quote>Henceforward I will not enter into judgement with that brother. Forgive me, O
               Father.</quote> And thus Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> healed that brother.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="199">
            <p>They say that Abbâ <persName>John</persName> the Less, the Theban, the disciple of Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName>, ministered
               unto the Abbâ in his sickness for twelve years, and he sat by him when the old man
               was in a state of exhaustion, and he persevered and endured so patiently, even whilst
               he was performing great labours, that the old man never once said unto him, <quote>Rest, my
               son; rest, my son!</quote> And when the old man was about to die, and the other old men were
               sitting before him, Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName> took his hand, and said unto him, <quote>Live, my son,
               live!</quote> Then he committed <pb n="44"/>him to the old men and said unto them, <quote>This is an angel,
               and not a man.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="200">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Paulê</persName> and <persName>Tîmâth</persName> his brother dwelt in <placeName>Scete</placeName>, and there was contention between
               them frequently; and Abbâ <persName>Paulê</persName> said, <quote>How long are we to remain thus?</quote> Abbâ <persName>Tîmâth</persName>
               said unto him, <quote>When I come upon thee bear with me; and when thou comest upon me I
               will bear with thee.</quote> And from that time they were at peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="201">
            <p>Certain brethren asked Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> a question, and said unto him, <quote>If we are going
               along a road, and he who is conducting us forgetteth the way, is it necessary for us
               to tell him?</quote> And Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> said unto them, <quote>No.</quote> Then a brother said unto him,
               <quote>Are we then to let him lead us astray?</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>What then?
               Thou hast a stick, canst thou not take it and smite him? Now I knew twelve brethren
               who were travelling along the road, and in the night time he who was leading them
               lost the way, and all the brethren knew that he had done so; and every one of them
               struggled with his thoughts, [and decided] not to tell him. And when the day had come
               he who had been leading them learned that he had wandered off the road, and he made
               excuses and said unto them, <quote>Forgive me because I lost the way</quote>; and they all said,
               <quote>We all of us knew it, brother, but we held our peace.</quote> And when he heard this he
               marvelled, saying, <quote>The brethren would endure even unto death and would utter never a
               word</quote>; and he glorified God. Now the distance which they had wandered from the road
               was twelve miles.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="202">
            <p>Certain brethren came unto Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>, and said unto him, <quote>Speak unto us a word
               whereby we may live</quote>; and the old man said unto them, <quote>Behold, ye have heard the
               Scriptures, and they are sufficient for you,</quote> and the brethren said, <quote>We wish to hear
               [a word] from thee also, O father.</quote> Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> said unto them, <quote>It is said in the
               Gospel, <quote>If a man smite thee on the [one] cheek, turn to him the other also</quote></quote> (St.
               Luke 6:29); and they said unto him, <quote>We cannot do this.</quote> Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> said unto them,
               <quote>If ye cannot turn the other cheek, continue [to be smitten] on the one cheek</quote>; and
               they said to him, <quote>And this we cannot do.</quote> The old man said unto them, <quote>If ye cannot
               do even this, do not pay back blows in return for the smiting which ye have
               received</quote>; and they said, <quote>We cannot even do this.</quote> Then the old man said unto his
               disciples, <quote>Make then for the brethren a little boiled food, for they are ill</quote>; and
               he said to them, <quote>If ye cannot do this, and ye are unable to do the other things,
               prayers are necessary forthwith.</quote></p>
            <pb n="45"/>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="203">
            <p>They used to say that Mother <persName>Sarâ</persName>, who dwelt above the river and was sixty years old,
               had never looked out [from her abode] and seen the river.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="204">
            <p>A certain old man dwelt in the desert at a distance of ten miles from the monastery,
               wherefrom he had always to draw water, and on one occasion the matter became very
               wearisome to him, and he said, <quote>What is the necessity for me to labour so much? I
               will come and will take up my abode by the side of this stream.</quote> And having said
               this, he turned behind him and he saw a man coming after him, and he was counting his
               footsteps, and he asked him, saying, <quote>Who art thou?</quote> And he answered and said unto
               him, <quote>I am an angel of the Lord, and I have been sent to count thy footsteps, and to
               give thee thy reward</quote>; and having heard this the old man was consoled greatly, and he
               went five miles further from the place wherein he was, and took up his abode
               there.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="205">
            <p>They say that three thieves went into the cell of Abbâ <persName>Theodore</persName>, and that two of them
               laid hold upon him whilst the third carried off the things which he had in his cell;
               and having taken out even the books which he had there, they were going to carry away
               his cloak, when he said unto them, <quote>Leave me this</quote>; and as they refused to do so, he
               moved his arms and hands and hurled the two men who were holding him from him, and
               when they saw this they were afraid. Then the old man said unto them, <quote>Fear ye not,
               but divide what ye have taken into four parts, and take three of them, and leave me
               one.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="206">
            <p>They used to say that the cave in <placeName>Patârâ</placeName> which belonged to Abbâ <persName>Chaeremon</persName> who was in
               <placeName>Scete</placeName>, was forty miles distant from the church, and twelve miles further from a
               spring of water. And he used to bring to the church, with the labour of his hands,
               two pitchers of water, one for each day, and when he was tired he would set one down
               by the roadside and go back afterwards and fetch it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="207">
            <p>They used to say that the cell of the blessed <persName>Arsenius</persName> also was two and thirty miles
               from the church, but he never went anywhere and others brought him whatsoever he
               required.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="208">
            <p>The blessed <persName>Arsenius</persName> never changed the water [wherein he soaked] the leaves which he
               twisted into ropes except once a year, but he used to add frequently to it, for he
               twisted palm leaves and sewed them together until the sixth hour [daily]. And the
               fathers entreated him, saying, <quote>Tell us why thou dost not change the water of the
               leaves, for it is very foul</quote>; then the old man answered, and said, <quote>It is right that
               I should endure this foul smell in return for the odours of the sweet scents, and
               oils, and delightful odours, which I enjoyed when I was in the world.</quote></p>
            <pb n="46"/>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="209">
            <p>It is related of a certain old man that if he heard a brother speak evilly to him he
               would labour very hard to make something which would please the brother who had
               spoken to him, and that if that brother did not live with him, the old man would send
               whatsoever he had made to the place where he was.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="210">
            <p>A certain old man used to say, <quote>It is a disgrace for a monk to enter into judgement
               with the man who hath done him an injury.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="211">
            <p>A brother asked a certain old man, saying, <quote>Tell me one thing, whereby, if I keep it,
               I shall live.</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>If thou canst endure being reviled and
               cursed, this command is the greatest of all the commandments.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="212">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, saying, <quote>What shall I do to my heart which flaggeth and
               is frightened if a little toil, and tribulation overtake me, or if temptation come
               upon me?</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Therefore we should wonder and admire the
               righteous man <persName>Joseph</persName> who, being only a very young man—that is to say, seventeen years
               of age—was sold into slavery into the land of <persName>Egypt</persName>, the land of the worshippers of
               idols, and he endured temptations, and God made him glorious to the end.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="213">
            <p>And he said also, <quote>We may consider also the blessed <persName>Job</persName>, who never became slothful,
               for he persevered in his trust in his God, and his enemies were not able to shake him
               from his hope.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="214">
            <p>On one occasion the brethren who were in <placeName>Scete</placeName> were cleaning and dressing palm
               leaves, and there was among them a man who had become ill through his excessive
               spiritual labours, and he was coughing, and bringing up clots of phlegm and spittle;
               and as he spat, involuntarily, some of the spittle fell upon a certain brother. Then
               the mind of that brother on whom the spittle had fallen said unto him, <quote>Tell that
               brother not to spit upon thee</quote>; but straightway he licked up the spittle, and he
               turned and said to his mind, <quote>Thou hast not licked up the spittle, therefore do not
               tell him not to spit upon thee.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="215">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> used to say that <persName>John Colob</persName>, who made entreaty unto God, and [his]
               passions were removed from him, and he was set free from anxious care, went and said
               unto a famous old man, <quote>I perceive that my soul is at rest, and that it hath neither
               war nor strife [to trouble it].</quote> Then the old man said unto him, <quote>Go and entreat God
               to let war and strife come unto thee again, for it is through war and strife that the
               soul advanceth in spiritual excellence.</quote> And afterwards, whensoever war stood up
               before him, he did not pray, <quote>O Lord, remove striving from me,</quote> but he made
               supplication unto <pb n="47"/>God, saying, <quote>O Lord, give me patience to endure the strife.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="216">
            <p>There was a certain man who had within himself love and affection for the
               brotherhood, and who never had in his mind any evil thought whatsoever; and a certain
               brother stole some things and brought [them] and deposited them with him, and the man
               did not consider or perceive by what means the brother had obtained them. Now some
               days later the matter was discovered, and it was pointed out to the owner of the
               things that they had been deposited with the old man, who made excuses to them,
               saying, <quote>Forgive ye me, for I repent.</quote> And after a few days the brother who had
               stolen the things came to him, and he began to demand [them from] the old man, and
               said unto him, <quote>Thou thyself didst take the things</quote>; and the old man made excuses to
               him, saying, <quote>Forgive me</quote>; and the old man brought out all the work of his hands, and
               gave it to him, and the brother took it and departed. Now the disposition of the old
               man was such that, if one of the brethren committed a fault, and denied it, he would
               make excuses for him, saying, <quote>It was I who did this thing</quote>; thus meek and humble was
               the holy man, and he never wronged any man even by the least word.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="217">
            <p>A certain brother lived by himself, and he was disturbed in his mind, and went and
               revealed the matter to Abbâ <persName>Theodore</persName> of Parmê. And the old man said unto him, <quote>Go and
               humble thy mind, and submit thyself to live with the brethren</quote>; and he went and did
               as the old man had told him, and took up his abode with other men. And he went back
               to the the old man, and said unto him, <quote>Father, I am not content to dwell with other
               men</quote>; then the old man said unto him, <quote>If thou art not content to live either by
               thyself or with others, why didst thou come out to be a monk? Is it not necessary for
               thee to endure trials? Tell me, how long hast thou lived this life?</quote> And the brother
               said unto him, <quote>Eight years.</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Verily I have led the life
               I lead now for seventy years, and not one pleasure hath come in my way [the whole
               time], and yet thou wishest to find pleasure (or rest) in eight years!</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="218">
            <p>A certain brother, who had vanquished <persName>Satan</persName> in everything, subsequently had his eyes
               blinded by <persName>Satan</persName> so that he could not see, yet this blessed man did not pray for
               himself, and that he might be able to see, but he only prayed that he might be able
               to endure patiently his trial; and through his constancy his eyes were opened.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="219">
            <p>A monk was smitten by a man on the leg and was severely injured, but the holy man was
               neither angry nor wroth <pb n="48"/>with him that had smitten him, [but he nursed the place
               wherein he had been wounded, and made excuses to the man who had struck him].</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="220">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> used to say, <quote>When an unbaked [or moist] brick is laid in the
               foundations of a building by the river-side, it will not support it, but if it be
               burnt in the furnace it will support the building like a stone. And thus it is with
               the man who possesseth a carnal mind, and who doth not become hot and burn with heat,
               even as did <persName>Joseph</persName> with the word of God, for when he cometh to have dominion he will
               be found to be wanting. For very many of those upon whom trials have come have
               straightway been swept away and have fallen. It is therefore a good thing for a man
               to know the gravity of dominion, and to be required to bear trials, which are like
               the onset of many mighty waters, so that he may remain firm and unmoved.</quote> And of this
               holy man <persName>Joseph</persName>—if a man wisheth to have the story told—<persName>Arsenius</persName> used to say that <quote>He
               was not a being of earth at all—so much was he tempted. And [consider] the country
               [of <persName>Egypt</persName>] wherein formerly there was not even a trace of the fear of God! But the
               God of his fathers was with him, and He delivered him out of all his tribulations,
               and <persName>Joseph</persName> is now with his fathers in the kingdom of heaven; and let us also make
               supplication with all our might that we too may in the same manner be able to flee
               from and escape from the righteous judgement of God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="221">
            <p>They say that there was with Abbâ <persName>Isidore</persName>, the priest of <placeName>Scete</placeName>, a certain brother who
               was infirm in his mind, and he was a man who used abusive language and possessed very
               little intelligence, and Abbâ <persName>Isidore</persName> wished to turn him out from his abode; and when
               that brother came to the door of the monastery, the old man said once again, <quote>Bring
               him to me,</quote> and he rebuked him, saying, <quote>Brother, be silent, lest through thy little
               intelligence and thine impatience thou provoke our Lord to anger</quote>; and thus by his
               longsuffering Abbâ <persName>Isidore</persName> quieted that brother.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="222">
            <p>A lover of ascetic labours saw a man carrying a dead person on a bier, and he said
               unto him, <quote>Dost thou carry a dead man? Go and carry the living.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="223">
            <p>They say that there was a certain monk who, whenever he found a man reviling and
               cursing him, used to run towards him with all his power, saying, <quote>These [words] are
               the causes of spiritual excellence in those who are strenuous, for those who ascribe
               blessing to a man disturb the soul, as it is written, <quote>Those who ascribe blessing to
               you lead astray your soul.</quote></quote></p>
            <pb n="49"/>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="224">
            <p>Certain old men came unto an old man who dwelt in the desert that they might reveal
               unto him their thoughts, and might profit by his knowledge, and they found some young
               men outside his cell who were pasturing sheep, and they were saying unto one another
               words which were unseemly. And the old men said unto the old man, <quote>Father, how is it
               that thou dost not command these young men not to curse?</quote> And the old man said unto
               them, <quote>My brethren, believe me, I have many times wished to command them [not to do
               so], but I have rebuked myself, saying, <quote>If thou canst not endure this little thing,
               how couldst thou bear some severe trial if it were to come upon thee?</quote> I have
               therefore never said anything to them, so that the matter might be a cause of
               remembering that I have to endure the things which are to come.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="225">
            <p>A certain brother ministered unto one of the fathers who was sick, now his disease
               was decline of the body, and he used to bring up foetid pus; and the mind of the
               brother said unto him, <quote>Flee from him, for thou canst not endure this foetid smell.</quote>
               Then the brother took an earthen vessel and put into it some of the water in which
               the old man had washed, and when he was thirsty he used to drink some of it; and his
               mind began to say unto him, <quote>Flee not, but drink not of this filthy water.</quote> But that
               brother laboured on greatly in respect of the water in which the sick man had washed,
               and although his soul shrank from that filthiness, he persevered in drinking it; and
               God saw his labour and tribulation, and He changed the filthy washing water which was
               in the earthen vessel into clean water, and He healed that old man.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="226">
            <p>One of the monks wished to go out from his monastery and to wander about so that he
               might have a little relaxation and enjoyment, and when they saw him, an old man said
               unto him, <quote>Seek not gratification in this world, O my son, but work rather and
               persevere therein in the invincible power of the Holy Trinity.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="227">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> used to say, <quote>Secret withdrawal [from work] maketh dark the mind, but for
               a man to endure and to persevere in his works maketh light the mind in our Lord, and
               it strengtheneth and fortifieth the soul.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="228">
            <p>And he used to say also, <quote>Bear disgrace and affliction in the Name of <persName>Jesus</persName> with
               humility and a troubled heart; and shew before Him thy feebleness, and He will become
               unto thee might.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="229">
            <p>Certain people praised one of the brethren before the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, and when that
               brother came to the blessed man the old man put him to the test, and he found that he
               could not bear contempt and contumely. And the old man said unto <pb n="50"/>him, <quote>Thou art like
               unto a palace the front of which is decorated and beautiful, but the back whereof
               hath been broken into by thieves and plundered.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="230">
            <p>A brother asked an old man a question, saying, <quote>What shall I do?</quote> And the old man
               said unto him, <quote>Go and learn to love putting restraint upon thyself in
               everything.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="231">
            <p>One of the old men said concerning <persName>Lazarus</persName>, the poor man, <quote>We cannot find that
               <persName>Lazarus</persName> ever did one excellent thing except that he never murmured against the rich
               man as being one who had never shewn him an act of mercy; but he bore his infirmity
               with the giving of thanks, and because of this God took him to Himself.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="232">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> used to say, <quote>If contumely be accounted by thee as an honour, and blame
               as praise, and poverty as wealth, thou wilt not die.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="233">
            <p>A certain brother asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, saying, <quote>What mean the words, <quote>If a man be angry
               with his brother without a cause?</quote></quote> (St. Matthew 5:22.) The old man said unto him,
               <quote>If thy brother make use of oppression, and wrong, and fraud in respect of thee, and
               thou art angry with him [because of them], thou art angry with him without a cause.
               And if he tear out thy right eye, or cut off thy right hand, and thou art angry with
               him, thou art angry with him without a cause; but if a man wisheth to separate thee
               or to put thee away from God, then to be angry and wroth with him is a good
               thing.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="234">
            <p>There were two men in the desert who were brethren in the flesh, and a devil came to
               separate them from each other; and one day the younger brother lit a lamp and set it
               upon a candlestick, but, by the agency of the Evil One, he overturned the candlestick
               and extinguished the lamp. Then the elder brother was angry and smote him, and the
               younger brother made excuses to him, saying, <quote>Have a little patience with me, and I
               will light the lamp again.</quote> Now when God saw his patient endurance, He punished that
               devil until the morning, and the devil came and told the prince of devils what had
               happened; and there was with the prince of devils a certain priest of idols, and
               straightway this man left everything, and he went and became a monk. And at the very
               beginning he laid hold upon humility, saying, <quote>Humility is able to bring to naught
               all the power of the Adversary, even as I have heard from the devils, who said,
               <quote>Whensoever we stir up the monks, they turn to humility, and they make excuses one to
               the other, and thus they do away all our power.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="235">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said, <quote>Abbâ <persName>Isidore</persName>, the priest of the church, on one occasion spake to
               the people, saying, My <pb n="51"/>brethren, when ye are working in a certain place it is not
               strength to depart therefrom because of the labour; and as for myself, I wrap myself
               up in my cloak and I go to the place where labour is, and labour becometh unto me a
               pleasure.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="236">
            <p><persName>Paesius</persName>, the brother of Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, had an affection for the people who were outside
               his monastery, and Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> did not wish this to be, and he rose up and fled to
               Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName>, and said unto him, <quote>My brother <persName>Paesius</persName> hath made a promise of love to
               certain folk, and I am not pleased thereat.</quote> Abbâ Ammon said unto him, <quote><persName>Poemen</persName>, thou
               art still alive. Go, and sit in thy cell, and meditate in thy mind, saying, <quote>Behold,
               there is a year for thee in the grave.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="237">
            <p>There were two monks who lived in one place, and an old man came to them, and wishing
               to put them to the test, he took a stick, and began to beat to pieces the garden
               herbs of one of them; and when one monk saw him doing this, he hid himself. And when
               only one root was left, the other brother said unto him, <quote>Father, if it please thee,
               leave me this root that I may boil it and we may eat together.</quote> Then the old man made
               excuses to that brother, and said unto him, <quote>The Spirit of God hath rested upon thee,
               O my brother.</quote></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
