<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Of The Acceptance Of Repentance, And Of How It Is Right
               For Us To Repent In Truth</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_12">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_12 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 12: Of The Acceptance Of Repentance, And Of How It Is Right For Us To Repent
            In Truth</head>
         <div type="saying" n="598">
            <p><persName>TWO brethren</persName> were in restraint to the lust of fornication, and they went and took to
               themselves <persName>wives</persName>. At length, however, they repented, and said to each other, <quote>What
               have we gained by leaving the labour of angels, and coming to this [state of]
               impurity, since after the present life we shall be delivered over to fire and
               everlasting torture? Let us return to the desert and repent.</quote> And they went forth
               straightway, and came to the desert to the fathers, and they entreated them to offer
               up supplications on their behalf; now the outward appearance of both was the same,
               and they shut themselves up for one year, and they made supplications to God, and
               entreated Him to pardon them, and to each of the two brethren a like quantity of
               bread and water was given. Now after their period of repentance was fulfilled, they
               went forth from their seclusion; and the old men saw that the countenance of one was
               changed, and that it was exceedingly sad, whilst that of the other brother was
               cheerful and glad, and the fathers marvelled why, seeing that the two men had been
               partaking of the same amount of food, and had endured the same restraint, the face of
               one was so different from that of the other. And they asked him of the sad face,
               saying, <quote>What didst thou think about in thy cell?</quote> And he said, <quote>On the evil things
               which I have committed, and I think about the torture which is to come, and by reason
               of my fear my flesh cleaveth to my bones.</quote> And they asked him whose appearance was
               cheerful, saying, <quote>Do thou also tell us what thou didst think about in thy cell.</quote> And
               he said, <quote>I gave thanks unto God, Who hath delivered me from the impurity of this
               world, and from everlasting punishment, and Who hath <pb n="136"/>brought me to this labour of
               angels, and with such things I remembered God and rejoiced.</quote> Then the old men said,
               The repentance of each is equal before God.”</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="599">
            <p>An old man was asked by one who toiled, <quote>Is the repentance of sinners accepted by
               God?</quote> And the old man, after he had taught him with many words, said unto him, <quote>Tell
               me, O my beloved one: if thy cloak were to be torn in rags, wouldst thou throw it
               away?</quote> And he said unto him, <quote>No, but I would sew up the rents, and then I could use
               it again.</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>If thou wouldst shew pity upon thy garment
               which hath no feeling, shall not God shew pity on that which He hath fashioned, and
               which is His work?</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="600">
            <p>A certain brother fell into temptation, and through tribulation relinquished the garb
               of monkhood; and he wished to begin to renew his ascetic life, but he saw the great
               difficulty of the matter, and he drew back, and said, <quote>When shall I ever find myself
               in the same condition as I was formerly?</quote> And through fear he did not begin his work,
               and he went and made the matter known to an old man, and the old man said, <quote>The
               matter is thus: There was a certain man who possessed an estate, and he held it to be
               of no account and did not cultivate it, and it became full of tangled undergrowth and
               thorns. Now one day he remembered it, and he sent his son, and said unto him, <quote>Go,
               clean the estate.</quote> And when he had gone and seen the abundance of the undergrowth he
               was afraid, and said to himself, <quote>When shall I be able to clean away all this
               undergrowth?</quote> And he threw himself upon a bed, and lay down, and went to sleep, and
               thus he did every day. Then his father went forth and found that he was asleep, and
               that he had done nothing; and he said unto him, <quote>How is it, my son, that no work
               whatsoever hath been done by thee?</quote> And he said to his father, <quote>When I came to work
               and saw the abundance of the undergrowth, I was afraid and said, When shall I be able
               to clean all this away?</quote> And his father said unto him, My son, work according to the
               measure of thy sleep each day, and it shall be sufficient for thee’; and when he
               heard [this] the young man plucked up courage, and did thus, and in a short time he
               cleansed the estate. Thus also thou shalt not be afraid, but begin the work of thy
               rules, and God, by His Grace, will establish thee [among those in] the first rank.</quote>
               Now when the brother had done thus he was helped.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="601">
            <p>A brother asked one of the old men, and said, <quote>If a monk stumble and fall into sin,
               are many labours necessary for him, and if he doeth them will he be able to stand in
               the <pb n="137"/>grade wherein he was formerly? He who goeth forth from the world, and beginneth
               the cultivation of spiritual excellence, will find it easy to advance, for he who is
               occupied in labours, if it be that he is reduced from the grade wherein he stood by
               his stumbling, will be afflicted and grieved in his mind.</quote> Then the old man answered
               and said unto him, <quote>A monk is like unto a house which hath fallen down, and if he be
               awake in his mind (or thought), and if he be zealous and anxious to build that which
               was fallen down, he will find ample material which will be of use in his building
               among the remains of that which fell down before [he began to build]; for he will
               find the foundation stones, and the old stones from the walls, and other things,
               which were employed in the old building, and out of these, if he be so disposed, he
               will be able to make his building to rear itself up better than the man who hath not
               yet dug the places for the foundations and laid the foundation stones, and who doth
               not possess the materials which are to be employed in the building, and who only
               beginneth to build with the hope that he will be able to finish. And thus is it with
               him that falleth from the practice of rules and works of the monkish life into
               temptation, for if he turn back, and repent, he will possess ample material from
               [his] former works of the ascetic life which he possesseth [to begin his building
               afresh], I mean to say, the training and the service of the work of the hands, which
               is the foundation [thereof]. Whosoever then hath gone forth from the world, and
               beginneth the cultivation of ascetic excellence, when he hath done these things he
               will still be found standing in the front rank of the solitary (or monkish)
               life.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="602">
            <p>One of the old men told the following story, saying:—There was a certain monk who
               dwelt in the desert, and he lived a life of strict and severe rule, and he was famous
               among men, and he could even cast out devils and heal the sick. And it came to pass
               that, through the agency of <persName>Satan</persName>, the passion of fornication was stirred up against
               him, and because he was not sufficiently humble to reveal his war unto the old men
               who were before him, in a few days’ time he fell into fornication with a woman who
               used to come to him continually for assistance. Now having fallen, he despaired about
               himself, and he rose up to go to the world, and he was sad and grieved concerning his
               fall; and he meditated, saying, <quote>I will go into the desert which is further away, and
               I shall not see any man, and I shall not be seen of any, and there I will die like
               the wild animals.</quote> And when he had gone, and he was wandering about in the desert and
               in the mountains, <pb n="138"/>he used to cry out by night and by day, saying, <quote>Woe is me! woe is
               me!</quote> And he ceased not to weep and to groan. Now there was in that desert a certain
               solitary old man who dwelt in a cleft in the rock, and when he heard the sound of the
               weeping and lamentation, his mercy for him revealed itself, and he went forth and met
               him, and they saluted each other. And the old man answered and said unto him, <quote>Why
               weepest thou in this fashion?</quote> And the young man said, <quote>Because I have angered God,
               and because I have fallen into fornication.</quote> Then was the old man astonished, and he
               said, <quote>O how greatly did I fear and tremble at thy lugubrious voice. For I thought
               that thou hadst been entrusted with the governorship of the brethren, and that thou
               hadst governed unjustly, or that thou hadst squandered in an unseemly manner the work
               of the community. For the harlot repented, and for the unbeliever there is a
               foundation, and the thief is a son of the kingdom, but <persName>Ananias</persName> and <persName>Sapphira</persName> were
               slain because they stole the money of the community of the brethren, and thus is
               slain the soul of every one who with fraud or carelessness squanders the possessions
               of the religious houses. But be thou of good courage, O brother, and go back again to
               thy cell, and make thine entreaty to God as thou repentest, and He will stablish thee
               in thy former grade.</quote> Then the monk went back to his place, and he shut himself in,
               and never again undertook to talk with any man, except him that handed in to him his
               food through the little window of his cell, and there he remained until the end of
               his life, and he attained to a most exalted state of perfection.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="603">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Ammon of <placeName>Rîtheaôn</placeName></persName> asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> about the impure thoughts which are produced
               in a man, and the vain lusts; and Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said unto him, <quote>It belongeth to <persName>Satan</persName>
               to sow them, but it is our affair not to welcome them.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="604">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName>, saying, <quote>Behold, there were two men, the one was a monk,
               and the other a son of the world; now the monk used to determine in the evening to
               cast away from him in the morning the garb of the monk, and the son of the world used
               to make up his mind that on the morrow he would take the garb of monkhood. Now it
               happened that both men died on the same night; how will they be regarded, and which
               determination will be reckoned to them?</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>He who was a
               monk died a monk, and he who was a child of the world died as such, for as they were
               found [to be] so were they taken.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="605">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName>, saying, <quote>What shall I do, father? For I have fallen.</quote>
               The old man said unto him, <quote>Rise up</quote>; and the brother said unto him, <quote>I did rise up,
               but <pb n="139"/>I fell again.</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Rise up again</quote>; and the brother said
               unto him, <quote>I did rise up again, many times, and I fell [again].</quote> The old man said
               unto him, <quote>Rise up again</quote>; and the brother said unto him, <quote>Until when?</quote> The old man
               said unto him, <quote>Until thou advancest, either in good deeds or in falling; for in the
               road wherein a man advanceth he goeth, whether it be to death or to life.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="606">
            <p>It happened on one occasion that a brother in the monastery of Abbâ <persName>Hatîl (or Helît)</persName>
               was tempted, [and he fell,] and having been expelled from that place he went to the
               mountain, to Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>, and having remained with him for a long time, Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>
               sent him back to the monastery from which he had gone forth. Now when the sons of the
               monastery saw him, they cast him out, and he returned to Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>, and said unto
               him, <quote>Father, they have refused to receive me</quote>; and Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> sent them a message,
               saying, <quote>A storm rose up against a ship on the sea, and destroyed the freight which
               she carried, but with the greatest difficulty she was saved [and brought] to land.
               Now what do ye wish to do? Do ye wish to drown him that hath been saved?</quote> And when
               those monks [heard the words of] Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>, they sent to the brother, and welcomed
               him with gladness.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="607">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> used to say, <quote>There are many who fall and who rise up to an attitude of
               rectitude, but there are some who fall from good deeds to polluted things; better is
               he who falleth and riseth up than he who standeth and then falleth.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="608">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said, <quote>If a man sinneth, and he saith, <quote>I have not sinned,</quote> and thou
               chidest him, thou cuttest off his will; but if thou sayest unto him, <quote>Be not sorry
               about this, but guard thyself from sinning again,</quote> by these means thou wakest his
               soul to repentance.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="609">
            <p>He also said, <quote>I prefer a man who hath sinned, and done wickedly, and repented, to
               the man who hath not sinned and hath not manifested repentance; for the former
               possesseth a humble mind, and the latter esteemeth himself in his thoughts a just
               man.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="610">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Sarmâtâ</persName> used to say, <quote>I prefer a man who hath sinned, and who knoweth how to
               acknowledge his sins, to him that doeth righteousness, and who saith, <quote>I do what is
               fair.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="611">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Theodore of <placeName>Parmê</placeName></persName> used to say, <quote>The man who is in [a state of] repentance is not
               bound by the Law.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="612">
            <p>They used to say that the thoughts of a certain old man used to say unto him, <quote>Let
               to-day go by, and repent to-morrow</quote>; but he would say, <quote>Nay, not so, for I will
               repent to-day, and to-morrow shall be as God willeth.</quote></p>
            <pb n="140"/>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="613">
            <p>There was at one time among the brethren a certain man who at the beginning of his
               [ascetic] career took good heed unto his soul, but when a short time had elapsed, he
               began to treat the salvation of his life with contempt; and his Abbâ ordered him to
               strip off the garb of the monks, and to put on the apparel of men who are in the
               world, and to depart from among the brethren. Then the man fell down at his feet, and
               entreated him, saying, <quote>If thou wilt forgive me this once only, thou wilt gain me
               henceforward, for I repent of these things which I have done through negligence.</quote> And
               having multiplied and prolonged his entreaties, and made many promises that he would
               in the future mend his ways, he was held worthy of forgiveness; and he struggled with
               all the power of his soul to such purpose as to become a pattern to great and
               small.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
