<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Of Fasting And Abstinence And Of Other [Similar]
               Labours</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_2">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_2 </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 2: Of Fasting And Abstinence And Of Other [Similar] Labours</head>
         <div type="saying" n="63">
            <p>They used to say about Abbâ <persName>Paphnutius</persName> that he would not readily drink wine, and that
               on one occasion he came by chance upon a band of thieves, and found them drinking;
               and the captain of the thieves recognized him, and knew that he never drank wine; and
               he looked closely at him [and saw that] he was a man of great ascetic works. And the
               captain filled a cup with wine and, taking a sword in his hand, he said unto the old
               man, <quote>If thou wilt not drink I will slay thee</quote>; and the old man knew that the grace
               of God wished to work on the captain of the thieves through him, and sought to do
               good to him, so he took [the cup] and drank [the wine]. Then the captain made excuse
               to him and said, <quote>Forgive me, father, for having distressed thee</quote>; and the old man
               said unto him, <quote>I believe, by God, that through this cup God will forgive thee thy
               sins.</quote> And the captain of thieves said unto him, <quote>I believe, by God; from this time
               forth I will never vex any man.</quote> Thus, because for God’s sake <persName>Paphnutius</persName> gave up his
               own wish, he was able to do good to all that band of thieves.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="64">
            <p>A certain old man came unto one of the holy men who was a companion of his, and who
               cooked a few lentiles; and one of the two said unto his fellow, <quote>Shall we sing a part
               of the service?</quote> And he sang the whole of the Psalms of David, and his companion
               repeated two books of the Great Prophets, and when it was morning the old man
               departed to his own place, and they forgot all about the food. And the old man went
               another evening and found the food which had been cooked, and he was sorry and said,
               <quote>Oh! how was it that we came to forget that little mess of lentiles, and did not eat
               it?</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="65">
            <p>On one occasion a brother came to Abbâ <persName>Isaiah</persName>, who threw a handful of lentiles into a
               saucepan to boil, but when they had just begun to boil he took them off the fire; and
               the brother said unto him, <quote>Are they not yet cooked, O father?</quote> And the old man said
               unto him, <quote>Is it not sufficient for thee to have seen the fire? For this [alone] is
               great refreshing.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="66">
            <p>A certain old man became very seriously ill, for he suffered from some disease of the
               stomach, and much blood came <pb n="16"/>away from him; and one of the brethren had some dried
               prunes, and because of the severe illness of the old man he cooked a little food, and
               put some of the prunes in it, and brought it to him, and entreated him, saying,
               <quote>Father, do [me] an act of grace, and take a little of this stew, for perhaps it will
               do thee good.</quote> And the old man lifted up his eyes and looked at him, and said, <quote>In
               which of the Scriptures hast thou found this thing? Verily I have wished that God
               would leave me in this illness for the last thirty years, for when I am weak then am
               I strong</quote>; and the old man, although he was grievously sick, would not take even a
               little of the food, and when the brother saw [this] he took it and went back to his
               cell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="67">
            <p>They used to say concerning Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName>, the Egyptian, that if it happened that he
               ate with the brethren, he would make an agreement with himself that if there was wine
               [on the table] and he drank one cup of it, he would drink no water for a whole day;
               now the brethren, wishing him to be refreshed (or pleased), used to give him wine,
               and the old man took it joyfully so that he might torment his body. And when his
               disciple saw this thing, he said unto the brethren, <quote>I entreat you, for our Lord’s
               sake, not to give him wine to drink, for if he drinketh it he will go to his cell and
               afflict himself because thereof</quote>; and when the brethren knew this they did not give
               him any more wine to drink.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="68">
            <p>There was a certain old man who made a vow not to drink any water during the Fast of
               Forty Days; and when he became thirsty (literally, hot) he would wash a potter’s
               vessel, and fill it with water, and hang it up in front of him. Then the brethren
               asked him why and wherefore he acted thus, and he said, <quote>That I may labour the more,
               and receive a reward from God</quote>; now he said this that he might incite them to great
               labours.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="69">
            <p>A brother asked an old man questions about comforts [or pleasures], and the old man
               said unto him, <quote>Eat grass, wear grass, and sleep on grass, and then thy heart will
               become like iron.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="70">
            <p>A certain brother was hungry one morning, and he fought against his inclination and
               determined not to eat until the third hour; and when the third hour had passed, he
               dipped his bread in water, and sat down to eat, but he forced himself to wait until
               the sixth hour arrived, when he said within himself, <quote>Let us wait till the ninth
               hour.</quote> And when the ninth hour had come, he prayed, and saw the working of <persName>Satan</persName>
               rising up before him like smoke, and he suppressed his desire [to eat], and his
               hunger passed away from him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="71">
            <p>A certain brother from the Cells brought some new bread, and he invited all the old
               men who were under vows at <pb n="17"/><placeName>Scete</placeName> to partake of a meal; and when each of them had
               eaten two bread-cakes, they ceased eating. Then the brother, who knew their labours
               of abstinence, and that they did not usually eat, and never satisfied themselves,
               made excuses to them, saying, <quote>Eat ye this day, for our Lord’s sake, until ye are
               satisfied</quote>; and hearing this each ate ten cakes more. All this [sheweth] how much
               they afflicted themselves in not satisfying themselves with any kind of food.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="72">
            <p>On one occasion two old men were going up from <placeName>Scete</placeName> to <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and because of the
               fatigue of the way they sat down on the bank of the river to eat some food, and one
               of them took his bread-cake in his hand and dipped it in the water; and he answered
               and said unto his companion, <quote>Wilt thou not dip thy cake in water, O father?</quote> And his
               companion answered and said unto him, <quote>It is written, When a possession increaseth
               set not thy heart upon it</quote> (Psalm 62:10).</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="73">
            <p>They used to say about Abbâ <persName>Isaac</persName>, the priest of the Cells, that he ate the ashes of
               the censer which was before the altar with his bread.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="74">
            <p>On one occasion there was an offering [made] in the mountain of Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>, and a
               skin of wine was there, and one of the monks took some of it in a small vessel, and
               with a cup in his hand he went and carried it to Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName>. And he mixed him a
               cupful, and he drank it, and he mixed him a second cupful, and he took it and drank
               it, but when he mixed him a third cupful Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> refused to drink it, saying,
               <quote>Stay thy hand, brother, knowest thou not that [the third cup] is of <persName>Satan</persName>?</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="75">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>John</persName> said, <quote>If a king wishes to subdue a city belonging to enemies, he first of
               all keepeth them without bread and water, and the enemy being in this wise harassed
               by hunger becometh subject unto him; and thus it is in respect of the hostile
               passions, for if a man endureth fasting and hunger regularly, his enemies become
               stricken with weakness in the soul.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="76">
            <p>They used to say about Abbâ <persName>Dioscurus</persName> that his bread was made of barley and lentiles,
               and that at the beginning of each year he would set himself some [new] task of
               ascetic excellence, saying, <quote>This year I will not hold converse with (or visit) any
               man,</quote> or, <quote>I will not speak at all,</quote> or, <quote>I will not eat food which hath been
               boiled,</quote> or, <quote>I will not eat fruit,</quote> or, <quote>I will not eat vegetables.</quote> He began each
               year with resolutions of this kind and carried them out, and each year he set himself
               some new task.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="77">
            <p>On one occasion when certain brethren went to the church during the Easter Festival,
               they gave a brother a cup <pb n="18"/>of wine, and when they urged him to drink it, he said to
               them, <quote>Forgive me, O my fathers, but ye did the same thing to me last year, and I
               drank a cup of wine, and I was greatly troubled thereby for a long time.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="78">
            <p>The monks were celebrating a festival in <placeName>Scete</placeName>, and they gave a certain old man a cup
               of wine, and he handed it back, saying, <quote>Take this death away from me</quote>; and when the
               others who were eating with him saw him [do this] they also would not take the
               wine.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="79">
            <p>And again on another occasion certain first-fruits of wine were sent that it might be
               given to the brethren cup by cup, (i.e., a cup each). And one of the brethren went up
               to a roof, that he might escape from drinking, and it parted asunder beneath him, and
               he fell through it; and when the sound came [to the brethren] they went and found him
               lying [on the ground], and they began to think about him, and said, <quote>O lover of
               vainglory, this hath befallen thee rightly.</quote> And an old man laid him out, saying unto
               them, <quote>Forgive ye my son, for he hath done a good work. And, as the Lord liveth, this
               breach shall not be built up in my days, for all the world shall know that because of
               a cup of wine a schism hath taken place in <placeName>Scete</placeName>.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="80">
            <p>It was reported to Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> about a certain brother that he would not drink wine,
               and the old man <persName>Poemen</persName> said, <quote>The nature of wine is not such as to make it useful to
               the dwellers in monasteries.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="81">
            <p>They used to say about Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> the Theban that he never ate bread. During the
               Easter Festival the brethren came to him, and having made excuses they entreated him
               to eat with them; and he answered and said, <quote>I will do one [of two] things; I will
               either eat bread and bread alone, or I will eat of the meats which ye have boiled.</quote>
               And they said unto him, <quote>Then eat bread only.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="82">
            <p>A certain old man said, <quote>Reduce thy knowledge of the things of man, and thy belly
               also, and thou shalt find all [manner of] delights.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="83">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> used to say, <quote>The Spirit of God never entereth into the house wherein
               there are delights and pleasures.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="84">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName>, <quote>What [good do] I do in going to church, for often [the
               devils] recognize me and seize me?</quote> The old man saith unto him, <quote>There is work in the
               matter.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="85">
            <p><persName>Abraham</persName> his disciple thereupon said unto him, <quote>Father, if there happen to be a
               congregation on the Sabbath, or on Sunday, and a brother drink three cups of wine, is
               that too much?</quote> The old man saith unto him, <quote>If <persName>Satan</persName> did not <pb n="19"/>exist three cups would
               not be too much to drink, but since he doth exist three cups are too much.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="86">
            <p>On one occasion some early grapes were sent to Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> because he longed for
               them, and to give a proof of his abstinence, he sent them to another brother who was
               sick, and who craved for grapes; and having received them, he rejoiced over them
               greatly, and then he despised his desire, and sent them on to another brother, as one
               who had no wish for food of any kind, and who held his self-denial in contempt. Now
               when the brother had received the grapes, although he desired greatly to eat them, he
               did the same as the other brother had done, and no man wished to eat them. And after
               they had gone about among many of the brethren, the last one who received them sent
               them to the blessed <persName>Macarius</persName> as a gift of great honour; and when the blessed <persName>Macarius</persName>
               saw the grapes he marvelled at the extent of the self-denial of the brethren, and
               gave thanks unto God, and he did not eat them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="87">
            <p>On one occasion certain monks went down from <placeName>Egypt</placeName> to visit the Fathers, and when
               they saw that they were eating—now it was after prolonged hunger and very much
               fasting, and continual abstinence,—they were greatly offended; and when the elder of
               the coenobium learned [about this] he came to quiet their minds. And he proclaimed in
               the church of the congregation, saying, <quote>Ye shall fast in your customary manner,</quote> and
               honour your ascetic rule of life, so that your voluntary abstinence may not be held
               in contempt.” Now the Egyptian strangers wished to depart, but the monks shut them in
               cells. And when they had fasted the whole of the first day they began to feel faint,
               but notwithstanding this the monks made them to fast two days at a time; now the
               monks who were in <placeName>Scete</placeName> used to fast for a week at a time. And when the day of the
               Sabbath came, the Egyptians sat down to eat with the old men, and when one of the
               Egyptians began to eat hurriedly and voraciously, one of the old men caught hold of
               his hands, saying, <quote>Eat moderately, (or according to rule) like the monks.</quote> Then one
               of the others clutched at the old man’s hand, saying, <quote>Let me eat so that I may not
               die, for behold, I have not eaten a piece of boiled food for a whole week.</quote> And the
               old man said unto him, <quote>If now ye have become so very weak after having fasted but
               one night only, why were ye offended at the brethren who live a life of self-denial
               for long periods of time, and who fulfil their seasons with voluntary abstinence?</quote>
               And straightway those Egyptians made excuses to the old men, and they were edified by
               their patient endurance, and departed rejoicing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="88">
            <p>Once Abbâ <persName>Agathon</persName> had two disciples, and they sepa<pb n="20"/>rated from him, and each of them
               dwelt in a place by himself. One day he asked one of them, and said, <quote>How dost thou
               live in thy cell?</quote> And the disciple answered and said, <quote>I fast until evening, and
               then I eat two bread-cakes</quote>; and Abbâ <persName>Agathon</persName> said unto him, <quote>It is a beautiful way
               of living, but it is very laborious.</quote> Then Abbâ <persName>Agathon</persName> said unto the other disciple,
               <quote>And how dost thou live?</quote> And the disciple answered and said unto him, <quote>I fast two
               days at a time, and after each fast I eat two bread-cakes.</quote> Then the old man said
               unto him, <quote>Thou toilest greatly, and maintainest a twofold strife. For one man eateth
               every day and filleth not his belly, and another fasteth two days at a time and
               taketh whatsoever he needeth; but thou, though thou dost fast two days at a time,
               dost not fill thy belly.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="89">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Abraham</persName> went to Abbâ <persName>Areus</persName>, and as they were sitting down, another brother came
               to Abbâ, and asked him, saying, <quote>Tell me what I shall do to live?</quote> And he said unto
               him, <quote>Go and pass the whole week in plaiting palm leaves and twisting ropes thereof,
               and eat bread and salt once each day in the evening, and then come again to me, and I
               will tell thee [what else to do].</quote> And the brother went away and did as he had told
               him to do, and when Abbâ <persName>Abraham</persName> heard this he wondered. Now when the week was ended
               that brother came again to the old man <persName>Areus</persName>, with whom there happened to be also
               Abbâ <persName>Abraham</persName>. And the old man said unto the brother, <quote>Get thee gone, and pass thou
               the whole week in fasting two days at a time.</quote> And when that brother had gone, Abbâ
               <persName>Abraham</persName> said unto Abbâ <persName>Areus</persName>, <quote>Why dost thou command all the other brethren to bear a
               light burden, but layest aheavy load upon the brother who was here?</quote> Then the old man
               said unto him, <quote>The other brethren as they come, ask, and according as they ask they
               receive and depart; but this brother cometh for God’s sake, that he may hear the word
               of profit, for he is a worker, and whatsoever I say unto him he performeth with care
               and diligence.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="90">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Theodotus</persName> used to say, <quote>Abstinence from bread quieteth the body of the
               monk.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="91">
            <p>A certain old man used to say, <quote>I knew Abbâ <persName>Patermuthis</persName> in the cells, and he did not
               drink wine, but when they took some wine and mixed it with water, and urged him to
               drink [it], he said, <quote>Believe me, O my brethren, I hold it to be a most beautiful
               thing.</quote> And he blamed himself and condemned himself because of the mixing, and at the
               same time he gave thanks unto God and accepted His gracious gift.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="92">
            <p>They used to say about Abbâ <persName>Paphnutius</persName> that he did not drink wine readily, even
               though he was sick.</p>
            <pb n="21"/>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="93">
            <p>Abbâ <persName><persName>Poemen</persName></persName> said, <quote>The soul can be humbled by nothing except thou enfeeble it by the
               eating of [little] bread.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="94">
            <p>They used to say about Abbâ <persName>Sarnâôs</persName> that he laboured exceedingly hard, and that he
               only ate two bread-cakes each day. And when he came to Abbâ Job, who was a man that
               was perfect in the laborious work of active excellence, and who was also a man that
               practised strict self-denial and abstinence, he said unto him, <quote>As long as I live in
               my cell I can observe my rule of life, but if I go outside my cell I make openly
               submission because of the brethren.</quote> Then Abbâ <persName>Sarnâôs</persName> said unto him, <quote>To be able to
               keep hold upon thy rule of life only so long as thou art in thy cell is no great act
               of spiritual excellence, but it would be if thou couldst do so when thou didst go
               forth outside thy cell.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="95">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> used to say, <quote>As smoke driveth away bees, and men take the sweetness of
               their labour, even so also doth ease of the body drive away the fear of God from the
               heart, and it carrieth away all the good [effect] of its labour.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="96">
            <p>On one occasion Abbâ <persName>Sylvanus</persName> and <persName>Zechariah</persName> his disciple were going to a monastery,
               and they prepared a little food to eat before they set out on their journey. And when
               they had gone forth his disciple found water on the way, and he wished to drink, but
               the old man said unto him, <quote><persName>Zechariah</persName>, to-day is a fast day,</quote> but the disciple said,
               <quote>Nay, O father, for behold we have eaten.</quote> Then Abbâ <persName>Sylvanus</persName> said unto him, <quote>The
               food which we ate was obligatory, but let us keep the fast, O my son.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="97">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said, <quote>Every corporeal pleasure is contemptible before the Lord.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="98">
            <p>The disciple of Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> had to say unto him several times, <quote>Rise up and let us
               eat.</quote> And he used to say unto him, <quote>My son, have we not eaten?</quote> And the disciple
               would say unto him, <quote>Nay, father.</quote> Then the old man would say unto him, <quote>If we have
               not eaten, bring the food and let us eat.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="99">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Daniel</persName> used to say, <quote>In proportion as the body groweth, the soul becometh
               enfeebled; and the more the body becometh emaciated, the more the soul groweth.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="100">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Benjamin</persName>, the priest of the Cells, said, <quote>On one occasion we went to a certain
               old man in <placeName>Scete</placeName>, and we wanted to give him a little oil; and he said unto us,
               <quote>Behold, that little vessel of oil which ye brought to me three years ago is still
               lying in the place where ye put it, and it hath remained in the same state as that
               wherein ye brought it.</quote> And when we heard [this] we marvelled at the old man’s manner
               of life.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="101">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Benjamin</persName> also said, <quote>We went to another old <pb n="22"/>man, and he took some food which we
               were going to eat, and threw into it a little oil of radishes. And we said unto him,
               <quote>Father, throw into our food a little sweet oil,</quote> but when he heard these words, he
               made the sign of the Cross over himself, and said, <quote>If there be any other oil besides
               this I know not of it.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="102">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Joseph</persName> asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> what was the proper way in which to fast, and Abbâ
               <persName>Poemen</persName> said unto him, <quote>I prefer the man who eateth every day a very small quantity of
               food, and who doth not satisfy his cravings for food.</quote> And Abbâ <persName>Joseph</persName> said unto him,
               <quote>When thou wast a young man didst thou not fast two days at a time, O father?</quote> Then
               the old man said unto him, <quote>Yea, I did, and three days at a time, and four days at a
               time, and even a week at a time; and the old men, like men of might, have tried all
               these by experience, but they have found that it is beneficial for a man to eat an
               exceedingly small quantity of food each day, and because of this they have delivered
               unto us an easy way to the kingdom.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="103">
            <p>One of the fathers said, <quote>I knew a brother in the Cells who used to fast the whole of
               the Great Sabbath, and when the brethren were assembled in the evening he used to
               flee to his cell in order that he might eat nothing in the church; and he would eat a
               few plantains with salt, and without bread, that he might conceal his
               abstinence.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="104">
            <p>They used to tell about a certain monk who, having gone forth from the world, and
               lived in the coenobium for a number of years, was gracious unto every man in his
               humility, and all the brethren marvelled at his abstinence from meats; then he went
               to the barren desert, and lived there for many years, eating for food wild herbs. And
               afterwards he entreated God to inform him what reward He would give him, and it was
               said unto him by an angel, <quote>Go forth from this desert and get thee along the road,
               and behold a certain shepherd shall meet thee, and according to [what he saith] so
               shalt thou receive.</quote> Now when he had made ready to depart, the shepherd of whom he
               had been told by the angel met him, and saluted him, and having sat down to hold
               converse with each other, the monk saw in the shepherd’s bag some green herbs, and he
               asked him, saying, <quote>What is this?</quote> And the shepherd said unto him, <quote>It is my food.</quote>
               And the monk said unto him, <quote>How long hast thou been feeding thyself on these green
               herbs?</quote> And the shepherd said unto him, <quote>Behold, for the last thirty years, more or
               less, and I have never tasted anything else except these herbs which I have eaten
               once a day, and I drink as much water as my food requireth; and the <pb n="23"/>wages which are
               given to me by the owner of the sheep I give unto the poor.</quote> Now when the monk heard
               these things he fell down at the feet of the shepherd, and said, <quote>I imagined that I
               had laid hold upon abstinence, but thou through thy well-ordered life art worthy of a
               greater reward than I, because I have eaten every kind of green thing immediately it
               came in my way.</quote> Then the shepherd said unto him, <quote>It is not right that rational men
               should make themselves like unto the beasts, but they should eat whatsoever is
               prepared for them at the seasons which are duly ordered and appointed for them, and
               afterwards they should fast from everything until an appointed time.</quote> And the monk
               profited by these words, and he added to his labour and became perfect, and he
               praised God, and marvelled how many were the saints in the world who were not known
               to the children of men.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
