<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Of Flight From Men, And Of Silent Contemplation, And Of
               Dwelling Continually In The Cell, [A Work] Which Was Composed By Bishop <persName>Palladius</persName> For
               The Prefect <persName>Lausus</persName></title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by <persName>Palladius of <placeName>Galatia</placeName></persName>, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_1">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_1 </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 1: Of Flight From Men, And Of Silent Contemplation, And Of Dwelling
            Continually In The Cell, [A Work] Which Was Composed By Bishop <persName>Palladius</persName> For The Prefect
            <persName>Lausus</persName></head>
         <div type="saying" n="1">
            <p>When Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> was in the palace, he prayed to God, and said, <quote>O Lord, direct me
               how to live</quote>; and a voice came to him, saying, <quote><persName>Arsenius</persName>, flee from men, and thou
               shalt live.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="2">
            <p>And when <persName>Arsenius</persName> was living the ascetic life in the monastery, he prayed to God the
               same prayer, and again he heard a voice saying unto him, <quote><persName>Arsenius</persName>, flee, keep
               silence, and lead a life of silent contemplation, for these are the fundamental
               causes which prevent a man from committing sin.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="3">
            <p>A certain man said that there were once three men who loved labours, and they were
               monks. The first one chose to go about and see where there was strife, which he
               turned into peace; the second chose to go about and visit the sick; but the third
               departed to the desert that he might dwell in quietness. Finally the first man, who
               had chosen to still the contentions of men, was unable to make every man to be at
               peace with his neighbour, and his spirit was sad; and he went to the man who had
               chosen to visit the sick, and he found him in affliction because he was not able to
               fulfil the law which he had laid down for himself. Then the two of them went to the
               monk in the desert, and seeing each other they rejoiced, and the two men related to
               the third the tribulations which had befallen them in the world, and entreated him to
               tell them how he had lived in the desert. And he was silent, but after a little he
               said unto them, <quote>Come, let each of us go and fill a vessel of water</quote>; and after they
               had filled the vessel, he said unto them, <quote>Pour out some of the water into a basin,
               and look down to the bottom through it,</quote> and they did so. And he said unto them,
               <quote>What do ye see?</quote> and they said, <quote>We see nothing.</quote> And after the water in the basin
               had ceased to move, he said to them a second time, <quote>Look into the water,</quote> and they
               looked, and he said unto them, <quote>What do ye see?</quote> And they said unto him, <quote>We see our
               own faces distinctly</quote>; and he said unto them, <quote>Thus is it with the man who dwelleth
               with men, for by reason of the disturbance caused by this affair of the world he
               cannot see his sins; but if he live in the peace and quietness of the desert he is
               able to see God clearly.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="4">
            <p>On one occasion Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName> came during the season of winter to Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName>, and he
               saw that the old man was grieved because he had left the desert; and Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName> said
               unto him, <quote>Why art thou distressed, O father? For what wast thou able to do in the
               desert in thine old age?</quote> And the old man <persName>Sisoes</persName> looked at him fiercely, and said,
               <quote>What sayest thou to me, <persName>Ammon</persName>? Are not the mere thoughts of the freedom which is in
               the desert better for us [than living out of it]?</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="5">
            <p>There were two brethren in the desert who were the equals of each other in the
               spiritual life, and they led a life of ascetic self-denial, and performed the exalted
               works which belong to spiritual excellence. And it happened that one of them was
               called to be the head of a habitation of the brethren, but the other remained in the
               desert, where he became a man perfect in self-denial. And he was held by God to be
               worthy of the gift of healing those who were possessed of devils, and he knew
               beforehand the things which were about to happen, and he made whole the sick. Now
               when he who had become the head of a habitation of brethren (i.e., a coenobium, or
               monastery) heard these things, he decided in his mind that his fellow monk must have
               acquired these powers suddenly, and he lived a life of silence and ceased from
               converse with men for three weeks, and he made supplication unto God continually that
               He would shew him how the monk in the desert wrought these mighty works, while he had
               not received even one of the gifts which he had. And an angel appeared and said unto
               him, <quote>He who dwelleth in the desert maketh supplication to God both by night and by
               day, and his pain and anxiety are for our Lord’s sake; but thou hast care for many
               things, and thou hast converse with many, and the consolation and encouragement of
               the children of men must be sufficient for thee.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="6">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> on one occasion went to the brethren in a certain place where there
               were some reeds growing, and the wind blew upon them, and they were shaken. And the
               old man said, <quote>What is this rustling sound?</quote> and they said unto him, <quote>It is that
               caused by the reeds which are being shaken by the wind.</quote> And he said unto them,
               <quote>Verily I say unto you, if the man who dwelleth in silence heareth but the twittering
               of a sparrow, he shall not be able to acquire that repose in his heart which he
               seeketh; how much less then can ye do so with all this rustling of the reeds about
               you?</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="7">
            <p>A certain brother came to Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName>, and said unto him, <quote>My thoughts vex me, and
               say, <quote>Thou canst not fast and thou art not able to labour, therefore visit the sick,
               which is a great commandment.</quote></quote> Then Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName>, after the manner of one who was
               well acquainted with the war of devils, said unto him, <quote>Eat, drink, and sleep, and
               toil not, but on no account go out of thy cell</quote>; for the old man knew that dwelling
               constantly in the cell induceth all the habits of the solitary life. And when the
               brother had done these things for three days he became weary of idleness, and finding
               a few palm leaves on the ground, he took them and began to split them up, and on the
               following day he dipped them in water and began to work (i.e., to weave baskets); and
               when he felt hungry he said, <quote>I will finish one more small piece of work, and then I
               will eat.</quote> And when he was reading in the Book, he said, <quote>I will sing a few Psalms
               and say a few prayers, and then I shall eat without any compunction.</quote> Thus little by
               little, by the agency of God, he advanced in the ascetic life until he reached the
               first rank, and received the power to resist the thoughts and to vanquish them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="8">
            <p>When Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> was dwelling in the mountain of Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>, the man who used to
               minister unto him departed and remained away for a period of ten months and did not
               come [back] to him, and he saw no man. And afterwards, as he was walking in the
               mountains, he saw a man hunting wild animals, and the old man said to him, <quote>Whence
               comest thou? And how long hast thou been here?</quote> And the man said unto him, <quote>Father, I
               have been in this mountain eleven months, and I have seen no man except thyself.</quote>
               Then the old man having heard these things went into his cell, and smote upon his
               face, and said, <quote>Behold, O <persName>Sisoes</persName>, well mayest thou think that thou hast done
               nothing, for thou hast not made thyself even like unto this man who is in the world,
               and is not a monk.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="9">
            <p>I once asked Abbâ <persName>Sarmâtâ</persName> a question, and said unto him, <quote>What shall I do, O my
               father, for I do nothing which the monks do? On the contrary, I am negligent, and I
               eat, and drink, and sleep, and I think many filthy thoughts, and my mind is ever
               disturbed, and I depart from one work to another, and from one group of thoughts to
               another. What shall I do, then? For I am troubled, and my soul is little.</quote> And Abbâ
               <persName>Sarmâtâ</persName> said unto him: <quote>Sit thou in thy cell, and whatsoever thou canst do, that do,
               and trouble not thyself. For I wish thee to do now a little, even as did Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>
               in the mountain, and I believe that by sitting in [thy] cell for the sake of the Name
               of God, thou also wilt be found in the same place as Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="10">
            <p>On one occasion the brethren went up from <placeName>Scete</placeName> to go to Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>, and having
               embarked in a boat to journey to him, they found [there] a certain old man, who was
               also going to visit him, and they were not acquainted with him. And as they were
               sitting in the boat, they spake now and again a word of the Fathers, or a word from
               the Book, or they talked about the work of their hands; and the old man listened unto
               all they said, but held his peace. Then, having crossed the ferry, the old man was
               found to be going also to Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>. And when they had all arrived at the place
               where he was, he said unto them, <quote>Ye found excellent company in this old man</quote>; and to
               the old man himself he said, <quote>Thou didst find excellent brethren to travel with thee,
               O father.</quote> And the old man said, <quote>They are excellent brethren, but they have no door
               to their house, and whosoever wisheth can go into the stable, and untie the ass, and
               go whithersoever he pleaseth on him.</quote> Now this he said because they uttered every
               word which came into their mouths.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="11">
            <p>A certain brother asked Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName>, saying, <quote>Father, how was it that thou didst
               leave <placeName>Scete</placeName> where thou wast with Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName>, and didst come here?</quote> And the old man
               said unto him, <quote>When <placeName>Scete</placeName> began to be filled [with monks] I heard that Abbâ <persName>Antonius</persName>
               had fallen asleep, and I came to the mountain here, and found that this place was
               quiet, and I lived here for a little time.</quote> The brother said unto him, <quote>How long hast
               thou been here?</quote> and the old man said, <quote>Behold, I have been here seventy years this
               day.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="12">
            <p>They used to say concerning Abbâ <persName>Theodore</persName> and Abbâ <persName>Luk</persName> that they passed fifty years
               with disturbed minds, and were troubled the whole time about changing their place [of
               abode]; and they said, <quote>Behold, we will change in the winter</quote>; and when the winter
               arrived, they said, <quote>We will change in the summer</quote>; and thus they did unto the end of
               their lives.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="13">
            <p>A certain father came to Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName>, and he knocked at the door, and the old man
               opened unto him thinking that it was his servant [who had knocked]; and when he saw
               who it was, he cast himself upon his face, and the father entreated him, saying,
               <quote>Stand up, O father, that I may give thee the salutation of peace.</quote> But <persName>Arsenius</persName>
               disputed with him, saying, <quote>I will not stand up until thou hast departed</quote>; and though
               he entreated him to do so often he would not stand up, and the father left him and
               departed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="14">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Battimion</persName> said, <quote>When I went down to <placeName>Scete</placeName> they gave me some apples to take to
               the brethren, and when I had knocked at the door of Abbâ <persName>Abhîlâ</persName>, he said to me when
               he saw me, <quote>If these apples had been of gold I would not have wished thee to knock at
               my door; and moreover, do not knock at the door of any other brother</quote>; so I returned
               and placed the apples in the church and departed.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="15">
            <p>They said concerning Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> that when the church began [to fill] he fled quickly
               to his cell, and, [though] the brethren said, <quote>He hath a devil,</quote> he was performing
               the work of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="16">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Joseph</persName> said to Abbâ <persName>Nestîr</persName>, <quote>What shall I do with my tongue, for I cannot
               conquer it?</quote> Abbâ <persName>Nestîr</persName> said unto him, <quote>If thou talkest wilt thou have relief from
               this [trouble]?</quote> And he said unto him, <quote>Nay.</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>If then
               thou hast no relief when thou talkest, why dost thou talk?</quote> Abbâ <persName>Joseph</persName> said unto
               him, <quote>What shall I do? For I cannot stand against it.</quote> The old man said unto him,
               <quote>Wilt thou have relief then?</quote> and he said unto him, <quote>Nay.</quote> The old man said unto him,
               <quote>If thou canst not gain relief by talking, then hold thy peace.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="17">
            <p>A certain brother went to Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> on the second Sunday in the Fast of Forty Days
               and repeated unto him his thoughts, and sighing over what the old man had told him,
               he said unto him, <quote>I had almost kept myself from coming here to-day</quote>; and the old man
               said, <quote>Why?</quote> Then the brother said, <quote>I said in my mind, Peradventure during the fast
               the door will be closed against thee</quote>; and Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said unto him, <quote>We do not
               learn to shut a door made of wood, but to close the door of the tongue.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="18">
            <p>When a certain brother in <placeName>Scete</placeName> was going to the harvest, he went to Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName>, the
               Black, and said unto him, <quote>Father, tell me what I shall do; shall I go to the
               harvest?</quote> and Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> said unto him, <quote>If I tell thee, wilt thou be persuaded to do
               as I say?</quote> And the brother said unto him, <quote>Yea, I will hearken unto thee.</quote> The old
               man said unto him, <quote>If thou wilt be persuaded by me, rise up, go, and release thyself
               from going to the harvest, and come unto me, and I will tell thee what thou shalt
               do.</quote> The brother therefore departed and obtained his release from his companions, as
               the old man had told him, and then he came to him. And the old man said unto him, <quote>Go
               into thy cell and keep Pentecost, and thou shalt eat dry bread and salt once a day
               [only], and after thou hast done this I will tell thee something else to do later
               on</quote>; and he went and did as the old man had told him, and then came to him again. Now
               when the old man saw that he was one who worked with his hands, he shewed him the
               proper way to live in his cell; and the brother went to his cell, and fell on his
               face upon the ground, and for three whole days and nights he wept before God. And
               after these things, when his thoughts were saying unto him, <quote>Thou art now an exalted
               person, and thou hast become a great man,</quote> he used to contradict them, and set before
               his eyes his former shortcomings, [and say], <quote>Thus were all thine offences.</quote> And
               again, when they used to say to him, <quote>Thou hast performed many things negligently,</quote>
               he would say, <quote>Nevertheless I do small services for God, and He sheweth His mercy
               upon me.</quote> And when by such means as these the spirits had been overcome, they
               appeared unto him in the form of corporeal creatures, and said unto him, <quote>We have
               been vanquished by thee</quote>; and he said unto them, <quote>Why?</quote> and they said unto him, <quote>If
               we humble thee, we are raised up by thee to an exalted position, and if we exalt thee
               we are accounted by thee for humility.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="19">
            <p>There was a certain brother in the monastery who worked hard, and the brethren who
               were in <placeName>Scete</placeName> heard about him, and came to see him, and they entered into the place
               where he used to work; and having received them, and saluted them, he turned round
               and began to work again. And when the brethren saw what he did, they said unto him,
               <quote><persName>John</persName> gave thee the garb of the monk, and made thee a dweller in a monastery, but he
               did not teach thee to receive a blessing (literally, prayer) from the brethren, or to
               give one, or to say to them, <quote>Pray ye,</quote> or, <quote>Sit ye down.</quote></quote> And <persName>John</persName> said unto them,
               <quote>Nay, a sinner is not sufficient for these things.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="20">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> said, <quote>As a fish when it is lifted up out of the water dieth, even so
               doth the monk who tarrieth outside his cell.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="21">
            <p>They tell the story of a certain brother who came to <placeName>Scete</placeName> to see Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName>, and
               who went into the church and entreated the clergy to take him to see him; and the
               clergy said unto him, <quote>Refresh thyself a little, and thou shalt see him.</quote> And the
               brother said unto them, <quote>I will eat nothing before I meet him and see him</quote>; and when
               the clergy heard this they sent a brother with him to shew him Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName>, because
               his cell was some distance away. And when they had arrived there, they knocked at the
               door and went inside, and having saluted him, and prayed, they sat down and held
               their peace; and the brother who was from the church answered and said, <quote>I will
               depart, pray ye for me.</quote> But when the other brother saw that he possessed not freedom
               of speech with the old man, he said unto the brother from the church, <quote>I also will go
               with thee,</quote> and they departed together.</p>
            <p>Then he entreated him, saying, <quote>Take me also to Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> who was a thief,</quote> and when
               they went to him, the old man received them with joy, and having refreshed them
               greatly he dismissed them in peace. And the brother who had brought the visitor to
               Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> said unto him, <quote>Behold, I brought thee to a man from a foreign land, and
               to an Egyptian, which of the two pleaseth thee?</quote> And he answered and said unto him,
               <quote>The Egyptian who hath just received me, and refreshed me.</quote> And when one of the old
               men heard what had happened, he prayed to God, and said, <quote>O Lord, shew me this
               matter; one fleeth from the world for Thy Name’s sake, and another receiveth and is
               gracious for Thy Name’s sake.</quote> And behold, suddenly there appeared unto him on the
               river two great boats, and lo, Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> and the Spirit of God were travelling in
               silence in the one, and Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> and the angels of God were in the other, and they
               were feeding the monk with honey from the comb.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="22">
            <p>A certain brother asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> a question, saying, <quote>If I see something done,
               dost thou wish me to tell it abroad?</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>It is written,
               <quote>Whosoever shall declare a matter incorrectly, it is a disgrace to him and [a subject
               for] mockery.</quote> And if thou art asked, speak; and if thou art not asked, hold thy
               peace.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="23">
            <p>On one occasion there was an assembly in a great church, and all the old men were
               asked in a body, <quote>What striving is the mightiest against the monks?</quote> And they all
               agreed that there was none stronger than that which would make a man leave his cell
               and depart, for when this striving is overcome, all the rest can quite easily be
               brought low.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="24">
            <p>They say concerning Abbâ <persName>Âpôs</persName>, who afterwards became Bishop of <persName>Oxyrhyncus</persName>, that when
               he was a monk he laboured with great toil in the ascetic life, and that he was moved
               every hour by Divine Grace, but that after he became Bishop, though he wished to
               perform the same labours, he was not able to do so. And he cast himself before God,
               and made supplication unto Him, saying, <quote>Peradventure, O my Lord, it is because of
               the Bishopric that Thou hast removed Thy grace from me,</quote> and it was said unto him,
               <quote>It is not so, but formerly thou wast in the desert, and there were no men there, and
               God took care of thee; here, however, thou art in a portion of the world which is
               inhabited, and men care for thee.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="25">
            <p>A certain brother from the Cells soaked some palm leaves in water, and then sat down
               to weave ropes, and his mind said unto him, <quote>Go and visit such and such a brother</quote>;
               and he pondered on the matter, and said, <quote>I will go after a few days.</quote> And again his
               mind said unto him, <quote>Supposing thou shouldst die, what wilt thou do? for thou wouldst
               not see thy brother</quote>; and once again he satisfied his mind by saying, <quote>I will go
               after such and such a time.</quote> Now when the summer had come, he said within himself,
               <quote>To-day is not the right time for going,</quote> and again he said to his mind, <quote>As soon as
               thou hast cut off the end of the palm leaves it will be time for thee to go</quote>; and he
               said to himself, <quote>I will finish these leaves, and then I will go.</quote> And once again his
               mind urged him and said, <quote>The weather is beautiful to-day,</quote> and he rose up
               straightway and left the palm leaves soaking in the water, and he picked up a cloak
               and ran off on his way. Now he had as a neighbour a certain old man who used to see
               visions, and as soon as this man saw the brother running, he cried out, and said unto
               him, <quote>Prisoner, prisoner, come hither</quote>; and when he had gone in the old man said unto
               him, <quote>Go back to thy cell,</quote> and the brother went back, and he related unto him the
               whole story of his war. And having entered his own cell, he offered up repentance
               unto God, and the devils cried out with a loud voice, saying, <quote>Thou hast vanquished
               us, thou hast vanquished us, O monk.</quote> Now he had a palm-leaf mat under him, and it
               was charred as if it had been burned in the fire, and the devils vanished like smoke;
               then straightway the brother perceived their wiles, and he gave thanks unto God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="26">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said: A certain brother asked Abbâ <persName>Sîmôn</persName>, and said, <quote>If I go out from my
               cell, and I find a brother absorbed and immersed in matters unnecessary for
               salvation, shall I associate myself also with him? And supposing also that I should
               find him laughing, and that I also should laugh, when I have gone into my cell again
               shall I not be forgiven my relaxation?</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>What dost
               thou wish? Dost thou mean that having gone out of thy cell and having found a man who
               was laughing, and laughed with him, and having found a man who was talking, and
               talked with him, thou canst go back to thy cell and find thyself as thou wast before
               thou didst go out?</quote> And the brother said unto him, <quote>If not, how then?</quote> Then the old
               man answered and said unto him, <quote>It is right for thee to keep a careful watch both
               within and without.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="27">
            <p>An old man said, <quote>One man is thought to be silent, and yet his heart judgeth and
               condemneth others, and the man who acteth thus speaketh continually; another man
               speaketh from morning till evening, and yet keepeth silence, that is to say, he
               speaketh nothing which is not helpful.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="28">
            <p>There were two excellent brethren in the Cells, and they were held to be worthy to
               see things of mystery, and each one of them saw the might which was sent down by God
               upon his brethren. Now it happened that one of them came on Friday to the coenobium,
               and as he was outside, he saw that some of the brethren were eating from the morning
               [upwards], and he said unto them, <quote>Is it possible that ye eat at this time on Friday?
               And do ye usually hold a congregation at the turn of the day?</quote> And as his brother
               looked upon him, he saw that the might of God was going away from him, and he was
               grieved, for he was accustomed to see it upon him. And when they had come to their
               own cell he said unto him, <quote>What hast thou done, O my brother? Or what thoughts hast
               thou had? For I do not see upon thee as usual the might of God.</quote> And the brother made
               answer and said, <quote>I know not; I do not feel that I have any filthy thoughts in me,
               and I do not perceive in my soul that any evil act hath been committed by me.</quote> His
               brother said unto him, <quote>Peradventure some vain and empty word hath gone forth from
               thy mouth.</quote> Then that brother recalled the matter to his mind, and said, <quote>Yea,
               yesterday I saw certain men outside the coenobium eating, and I said unto them, <quote>Do
               ye eat at this time on Friday?</quote> This then is my sin. But I entreat thee to labour
               with me for two weeks, and thou and I will beg God to forgive me.</quote> And they did even
               as he had said, and after two weeks his brother saw that might which is of the
               goodness of God come upon him as usual.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="29">
            <p>The old men used to say about the blessed Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName>, and Abbâ <persName>Theodore of <placeName>Parmê</placeName></persName>,
               that they possessed in a far greater degree than many monks a hatred of the
               admiration of men; Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> was never pleased at meeting and conversing with a
               man, and Abbâ <persName>Theodore</persName>, even though he was willing to meet a man, was as sharp as a
               sword in his conversation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="30">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> said unto the brethren when the service in the church was ended, <quote>Flee
               ye, O brethren</quote>; and one of the old men said, <quote>Father, whither can we flee farther
               than this desert?</quote> Then <persName>Macarius</persName> laid his hand upon his mouth, saying, <quote>Flee in this
               manner,</quote> and straightway he went to his cell and, shutting the door, sat down.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="31">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said:—Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> asked Abbâ <persName>Zechariah</persName> a question when he was about to
               die, and said unto him, <quote>Father, is it good that we should hold our peace?</quote> And
               <persName>Zechariah</persName> said unto him, <quote>Yea, my son, hold thy peace.</quote> And at the time of his death,
               whilst Abbâ <persName>Isidore</persName> was sitting with him, Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> looked up to heaven, and said,
               <quote>Rejoice and be glad, O my son <persName>Zechariah</persName>, for the gates of heaven have been
               opened.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="32">
            <p>A brother asked an old man, saying, <quote>What is humility?</quote> And the old man answered and
               said unto him, <quote>That thou payest not back evil for evil.</quote> That brother said unto him,
               <quote>And supposing that a man cannot attain to this measure, what must we do?</quote> The old
               man said unto him, <quote>Let us flee and follow after silence.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="33">
            <p>And an old man said, <quote>Lay hold upon silence. Look carefully into and scrutinize the
               manner in which thou trainest thyself, both when thou art lying down, and when thou
               art standing up. Meditate upon the fear of God, and be not afraid of the attack of
               sinners. Consent not to everything. Be swift to hear and slow to believe.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="34">
            <p>An old man said: <quote>The man, who hath learned by experience the sweetness of the
               quietness which is in his cell, doth not flee from meeting his neighbour because he
               is as one who despiseth him, but because of the fruits which he plucketh from
               silence.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="35">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> used to say, <quote>The man who fleeth from the world is like unto ripe grapes,
               but he who dwelleth among the attractions of the children of men is like unto sour
               grapes.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="36">
            <p>An old man said: <quote>Human care and worry and anxiety about the things of the body
               destroy the faculties of knowledge and expression in a man, and leave him like unto a
               piece of dry wood.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="37">
            <p>They used to say about Abbâ <persName>Nastîr</persName> that the old man was like unto the serpent which
               <persName>Moses</persName> made for the healing of the people (Numbers 21:9 ff.), and that he was perfect
               in all spiritual excellences, and that, although he kept silence, he healed every
               man.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="38">
            <p>A certain brother asked an old man a question, and said unto him, <quote>Father, what shall
               I do? For, although my body is in my cell, my thoughts wander about into every place,
               and because of this they vex me greatly, saying, <quote>Thou hast no benefit whatsoever,
               for though thy body is shut up in the cell, thy thoughts wander and are scattered
               abroad.</quote> And they bring me to despair, and counsel me to go back to the world as one
               who has not the ability to acquire the rule of life which is proper for the ascetic
               monk.</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Thou must know, O my son, that this is an attack
               of <persName>Satan</persName>, but go, and continue to abide in thy cell, and go not out of it at any
               time, and pray to God that He may give thee the power to endure patiently, and then
               thy mind shall collect itself in thee. For the matter is like unto that of a she-ass
               which hath a sucking foal. If she be tied up, however much the foal may gambol about
               or wander hither and thither, he will come back to her eventually, either because he
               is hungry, or for other reasons which drive him to her; but if it happen that his
               mother be also roaming about loose, both animals will go to destruction. And thus is
               it in the matter of the monk. If the body remain continually in its cell, the mind
               thereof will certainly come back to it after all its wanderings, for many reasons
               which will come upon it, but if the body as well as the soul wander outside the cell,
               both will become a prey and a thing of joy to the enemy.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="39">
            <p>A certain brother belonging to a habitation of brethren said to Abbâ <persName>Bessarion</persName>, <quote>What
               shall I do?</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Keep silence, and consider thyself to be
               nothing.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="40">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> besought Abbâ <persName>Zechariah</persName>, saying, <quote>Speak a word of consolation to the
               brethren</quote>; and <persName>Zechariah</persName> took his cloak, and placed it under his feet, saying,
               <quote>Except a man die thus he cannot be a monk.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="41">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said, <quote>The rule of the monk is this—to bear at all times his own
               blame.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="42">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said, <quote>If thou holdest thyself in thine own sight to be of no account,
               thou mayest dwell where thou pleasest, and find rest.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="43">
            <p>The same old man used to say, <quote>A man will be always tripped up by that thing which he
               will not cut off from himself.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="44">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Alônîs</persName> said, <quote>If a man will only remember that which is written, <quote>Thou shalt be
               justified by thy words, and shalt be condemned by thy words</quote> (St. Matthew 12:37), he
               would know that it is right to hold his peace.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="45">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said, <quote>If thou wishest to acquire the power to keep silence, think not
               and say not within thyself that thou art doing the works of spiritual excellence, but
               say, <quote>I am not even worthy to speak.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="46">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> said, <quote>He who liveth in the desert is free from three kinds of spiritual
               attacks, that is to say, those which arise through the ears, speech, and sight; he
               hath only one kind to fight, namely, that of the heart.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="47">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Alônîs</persName> said, <quote>Unless a man saith in his heart, <quote>Only God and myself exist in
               this world,</quote> he will not find rest.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="48">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> used to say, <quote>It is well for a man to dwell in his cell, and if he suffer
               with patient endurance he will find blessings of every kind.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="49">
            <p>A certain brother asked Abbâ <persName>Panbô (Pambo)</persName>, <quote>Is it a good thing for a man to praise
               his neighbour?</quote> Saith the old man, <quote>It is a much better thing for a man tohold his
               peace.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="50">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said, <quote>In all the labour which cometh upon a man, his victory is only
               assured when he holdeth his peace.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="51">
            <p>A certain brother said unto an old man, <quote>If a brother bringeth unto me news from the
               outer world, dost thou wish me to tell him not to bring it to me?</quote> The old man said
               unto him, <quote>Nay,</quote> and the brother said unto him, <quote>Why?</quote> The old man said unto him,
               <quote>Because not even we are able to flee from this. For having told our neighbour that
               he must not do this, we ourselves afterwards may be found doing the very same thing.</quote>
               And that brother said unto him, <quote>What then is the right [course of action]?</quote> Then the
               old man said unto him, <quote>If we take upon ourselves to hold our peace, the example
               alone will be sufficient to make our neighbour do the same.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="52">
            <p>The blessed <persName>Theophilus</persName>, Archbishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, once went with a certain judge to
               Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName>, and begged the old man to let him hear some saying from him; and the
               old man held his peace for a little, and then answered him, and said, <quote>If I speak a
               word to you will ye observe it?</quote> And they promised to keep it. The old man said unto
               them, <quote>In whatsoever place ye hear that <persName>Arsenius</persName> is, come not nigh thereunto.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="53">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> said unto Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName>, <quote>Why fleest thou from us?</quote> And the old man
               said unto him, <quote>God knoweth that I love you, but I cannot be both with God and with
               men. The thousands and ten thousands of beings who are above have only one will, but
               men have many wills: I cannot, therefore, leave God and be with men.</quote> And the old man
               was always uttering these words, <quote><persName>Arsenius</persName>, for this thou didst go forth.</quote> And he
               used to say thus: <quote>I have many times repented that I spoke, but that I held my peace
               I have never repented.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="54">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> said, <quote>The cell of a monk is the furnace of <placeName>Babylon</placeName> wherein the Three
               Children found the Son of God, and it is also the pillar of cloud wherefrom God spake
               with <persName>Moses</persName>.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="55">
            <p>On one occasion the Fathers in <placeName>Scete</placeName> were gathered together, and because certain folk
               were wishing to see Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName>, they treated him with contumely, saying, <quote>Why doth
               this Ethiopian come and go in our midst?</quote> But <persName>Moses</persName> hearing this held his peace. And
               when the congregation was dismissed, they said unto him, <quote>Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName>, wast thou not
               afraid?</quote> And he said unto them, <quote>Although I was afraid I uttered not a word.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="56">
            <p>On one occasion certain brethren came unto <persName>John</persName> the Less to tempt him, for they had
               heard that he never permitted his mind to think about any of the affairs of this
               world, and that he never spoke about them. And they said unto him, <quote>Father, we thank
               God because He hath brought down this year rain in abundance, and the palms are
               thriving and are flourishing beautifully, and work for the hands of the brethren is
               abundant.</quote> The old man <persName>John</persName> saith unto them, <quote>Even thus is it with the Holy Spirit of
               God, for when It descendeth upon the hearts of holy men they blossom and bring forth
               the fruit of the fear of God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="57">
            <p>A certain brother came to take some baskets from <persName>John</persName> the Less, and when he had
               knocked at the door, the old man came out to him, and said unto him, <quote>What seekest
               thou?</quote> And the brother said unto him, <quote>Father, I want baskets.</quote> And <persName>John</persName> the Less
               went in to bring them out to him, but he forgot to do so, and sat down, and went on
               plaiting. And the brother knocked at the door again, and when Abbâ <persName>John</persName> went forth to
               answer him, he said unto him, <quote>Wilt thou bring out the baskets to me, Father?</quote> And
               again <persName>John</persName> went in, and sat down, and went on plaiting, and when the brother knocked
               again, <persName>John</persName> went forth and said unto him, <quote>Brother, what seekest thou?</quote> And he said
               unto <persName>John</persName>, <quote>Baskets, Father</quote>; and <persName>John</persName> took his hand and led him inside, saying, <quote>If
               thou wishest for baskets take them and get thee gone, for I am not able [to bring
               them to you].</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="58">
            <p>Some time ago Abbâ <persName>Evagrius</persName> went to <placeName>Scete</placeName> to a certain father and said unto him,
               <quote>Speak some word whereby I may be able to save myself.</quote> The old man saith unto him,
               <quote>If thou wishest to be saved, when thou goest unto any man speak not before he asketh
               thee a question.</quote> Now <persName>Evagrius</persName> was sorry about this sentence, and shewed regret
               because he had asked the question, saying, <quote>Verily I have read many books, and I
               cannot accept instruction of this kind</quote>; and having profited greatly he went forth
               from him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="59">
            <p>On one occasion there was a congregation in the Cells concerning a certain matter,
               and Abbâ <persName>Evagrius</persName> spoke. And a certain elder said unto him, <quote>We know, Abbâ, that
               hadst thou been in thine own country where thou art a bishop and the governor of
               many, [thou wouldst have been right in speaking]; but in this place thou sittest [as]
               a stranger.</quote> Now <persName>Evagrius</persName> was sorry, but he was not offended, and he shook his head,
               and bent his gaze downwards, and he wrote with his finger and said unto them,
               <quote>Verily, it is even as thou sayest, O my fathers; I have spoken once, but I will not
               do it a second time.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="60">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>John</persName>, who was in prison, said that there was a man sitting in his cell who
               always made mention of God, and in this was fulfilled that which is written, <quote>I was
               in prison, and ye came unto Me</quote> (St. Matthew 25:36).</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="61">
            <p>They used to say about Abbâ <persName>Agathon</persName> that for a period of three years he placed a
               stone in his mouth [and kept it there], until he had learned thoroughly how to hold
               his peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="62">
            <p>A certain brother went to Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> in <placeName>Scete</placeName>, and asked him to speak a word; and the
               old man said unto him, <quote>Get thee gone, and sit in thy cell, and thy cell shall teach
               thee everything.</quote></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
