<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Of How It Is Meet For Us To Weep For Our Sins And To
               Mourn For Them Always</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_4">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_4 </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 4: Of How It Is Meet For Us To Weep For Our Sins And To Mourn For Them
            Always</head>
         <div type="saying" n="136">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName>, and said unto him, <quote>Tell me some word whereby I may
               live</quote>; and Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName> said unto him, <quote>Go and make thy mind like unto the minds of
               those evil-doers who are in the prison house, and who ask those who go to them,
               saying, <quote>Where is the governor? When will he come here?</quote> And their minds tremble in
               fearful expectation. Thus also is a monk bound to wait in expectation always, and he
               must admonish himself, saying, <quote>Woe is me! For how can I stand before the throne of
               <persName>Christ</persName>? And how shall I be able to make answer unto Him?</quote> If thou art able to think
               thus always thou wilt be able to live.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="137">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> was once passing through Egypt, and he saw a woman sitting in the
               cemetery and weeping, and he said, <quote>If every kind of instrument of sweet music in the
               world were to come [here] they would not be able to change the grief of this woman’s
               soul [into gladness]; even thus it is meet for a monk to have pain (or grief) within
               himself.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="138">
            <p>Three old men once came to Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> because they had heard that he was a great
               man. And the first one said unto him, <quote>Father, how can I escape from the river of
               fire?</quote> And Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> answered him never a word. Then the second old man said unto
               him, <quote>Father, how can I escape from the gnashing of teeth, and from the worm which
               never dieth?</quote> And Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> answered him never a word. Then the third old man said
               unto him, <quote>Father, what shall I do? For the remembrance of the outer darkness
               troubleth me.</quote> And Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> answered and said unto them, <quote>I never think on any of
               these things, but I believe that God is Merciful, and that He will shew mercy unto
               me</quote>; then the old men went away <pb n="31"/>grieved at the answer which Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> had spoken
               unto them. Now because he did not wish to send them away sorrowful, he brought them
               back, and said unto them, <quote>Blessed are ye, O my brethren, for I have been jealous of
               you</quote>; and they said unto him, <quote>In what matter hast thou been jealous of us?</quote> And he
               said, <quote>The first one of you spake about a river of fire; and the second spake about
               the gnashing of teeth and the worm which dieth not; and the third spake about the
               outer darkness; if remembrances of this kind have dominion over your minds it is
               impossible for you to commit sin. What can I do who am stubborn of heart? For
               hardness of heart will not allow me to perceive even that there a punishment for men
               existeth, and because of this I sin every hour.</quote> And when the old men had heard these
               words, they made excuses to him, and said, <quote>In very truth according to what we have
               heard, even so have we seen.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="139">
            <p>A certain father said that on one occasion when the brethren were eating the food of
               grace, one of them laughed at table; and Abbâ <persName>Sînû</persName> saw him, and burst into tears, and
               said, <quote>What can there be in the heart of this brother who hath laughed? It is meet
               that he should weep because he is eating the food of grace.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="140">
            <p>They say that when Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> was sick the old men who were sitting with him saw
               that he was talking [to some one], and they said unto him, <quote>What seest thou, O
               father?</quote> And he said unto them, <quote>Some people came to take me away, and I entreated
               them to leave me [here] a little longer that I might repent.</quote> Then one of the old men
               said unto him, <quote>What power hast thou in thee now for repentance?</quote> Abbâ <persName>Sisoes</persName> said
               unto them, <quote>If I can do nothing else I can sigh and lament a little over my soul, and
               this will be sufficient for me.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="141">
            <p>Certain brethren went to an old man and, making apologies to him, they said, <quote>Father,
               what shall we do, for Satan is hunting after us?</quote> And he said unto them, <quote>It is right
               for you to be watchful and to weep continually. My own thoughts are always fixed upon
               the place where our Lord was crucified, and I sigh and lament and weep about it
               always;</quote> and thus having received a good example of repentance the brethren departed
               and became chosen vessels.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="142">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Muthues</persName>, saying, <quote>Speak a word to me</quote>; and the old man replied,
               <quote>Cut off from thee contention concerning every matter whatsoever, and weep, and
               mourn, for the time hath come.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="143">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Ammon</persName> said that he saw a young man who laughed, and he said unto him, <quote>Laugh
               not, O brother, for if <pb n="32"/>thou dost, thou wilt drive the fear of God out of thy
               soul.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="144">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Paule</persName> used to say, <quote>I had sunk in the mire up to my neck, and I wept and spake
               before God, saying, <quote>Have mercy on me.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="145">
            <p>They used to say that Abbâ <persName>Theodore</persName> and Abbâ <persName>’Ôr</persName> put on the skins of lambs for
               clothing; and they said to each other, <quote>If God were to visit us now what should we
               do?</quote> and they left [the skins], and departed to their cells weeping.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="146">
            <p>A blessed Archbishop, when he was about to depart from this world, said, <quote>Blessed art
               thou, O <persName>Arsenius</persName>, because thou hast remembered this hour.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="147">
            <p>An old man said, <quote>God dwelleth in the man into whom nothing alien entereth.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="148">
            <p>A brother asked a certain old man, and said unto him, <quote>My soul desireth tears, even
               as I have heard that the old men [desire] them, but they will not come to me, and my
               soul is vexed.</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>The children of <persName>Israel</persName> entered into
               the land of promise [after] forty years; now tears are the land of promise, and since
               thou wouldst enter therein thou must not henceforward be afraid of fighting. For God
               wisheth to bring tribulation upon the soul in this manner in order that it may at all
               times be wishful to enter into that land [of promise].</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="149">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> a question and said unto him, <quote>What shall I do? for my
               thoughts disturb me, and they say unto me, <quote>Thy sins have been forgiven thee,</quote> and
               they make me to pry into the shortcomings of the brethren.</quote> Then Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> spake to
               him about Abbâ <persName>Isidore</persName>, who dwelt in a cell and wept over his soul, and his disciple
               used to dwell in another cell; and the disciple came to the old man, and finding him
               weeping, said unto him, <quote>My father, why weepest thou?</quote> And the old man said unto him,
               <quote>I am weeping for my sins.</quote> Then the disciple said unto him, <quote>And hast thou any sins,
               father?</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>Indeed I have, my son, and if I were
               permitted to see my sins, not three or even four men would suffice to weep with me
               for them.</quote> Then Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> said, <quote>Thus it is with the man who knoweth himself.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="150">
            <p>I have heard that the old men who lived in <placeName>Nitria</placeName> sent to <persName>Macarius</persName> the Great, who was
               living in <persName>Scete</persName>, and entreated him, saying, <quote>In order that all the people may not be
               vexed, we beseech thee, O our father, to come to us so that we may see thee before
               [thou departest] to our Lord. And having gone [to them] they all gathered together to
               him, and the old men begged and entreated him to speak unto the brethren one <pb n="33"/>word of
               profit; and the holy old man wept, and said unto them, Let us weep, O my brethren,
               and let us make our eyes to overflow with tears before we go to the place where the
               tears of our eyeballs will burn up our bodies.</quote> And they all wept, and they fell upon
               their faces, saying, <quote>Father, pray for us.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="151">
            <p>When the blessed <persName>Arsenius</persName> was about to deliver up his spirit the brethren saw him
               weeping, and they said unto him, <quote>Art thou also afraid, O father?</quote> And he said unto
               them, <quote>The dread of this hour hath been with me in very truth from the time when I
               became a monk, and was afraid.</quote> And so he died.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="152">
            <p>And when Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> heard that he was dead, that is to say, that Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName> had
               gone to his rest, he said, <quote>Blessed art thou, O Abbâ <persName>Arsenius</persName>, for thou didst weep
               over thyself in this world. For he who weepeth not for himself in this world must
               weep for ever in the next. He may weep here voluntarily, or there because of the
               punishments [which he will receive], but it is impossible for a man to escape weeping
               either here or there.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="153">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName> and said unto him, <quote>What shall I do in the matter of my
               sins?</quote> And the old man said unto him, <quote>When <persName>Abraham</persName> went into the Land of Promise he
               bought himself a grave, and through the grave he inherited the land.</quote> And the brother
               said unto him, <quote>What is a grave?</quote> Then the old man said unto him, <quote>Weeping and
               mourning are a grave and a place [of burial].</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="154">
            <p>One of the brethren asked Abbâ <persName>Poemen</persName>, saying, <quote>Father, what shall I do in the matter
               of my sins?</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Whosoever wisheth to blot out his offences
               can do so by weeping, and he who wisheth to acquire good works can do so by means of
               weeping; for weeping is the path which the Scriptures have taught us, and the fathers
               have also wept continually, and there is no other path except that of tears.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="155">
            <p>And the same old man (i.e., <persName>Poemen</persName>) said, <quote>There are two things [to remember]: We
               must fear our Lord, and do good unto our neighbour.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="156">
            <p>Abbâ <persName>Noah</persName> asked Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName>, and said unto him, <quote>Speak to me a word</quote>; and the old
               man said, <quote>Flee from the children of men.</quote> <persName>Noah</persName> said unto him, <quote>Father, what doth it
               mean to flee from the children of men?</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>Thou shalt sit in
               thy cell and weep for thy sins.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="157">
            <p>A brother asked an old man, and said unto him, <quote>What shall I do, father?</quote> The old man
               said unto him, <quote>It is right that we should sigh and lament always.</quote> Now it happened
               that one of the old men fell asleep, and that after a long <pb n="34"/>interval he came to
               himself again, and the brethren asked him, saying, <quote>What didst thou see there, O
               father?</quote> and he said unto us with many tears, <quote>I heard there the sound of the weeping
               of many, who were crying out and wailing incessantly, and saying, <quote>Woe is me! Woe is
               me!</quote> And it is meet that we should always be saying the same thing.</quote></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
