<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Of Voluntary Poverty</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_5">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_5 </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 5: Of Voluntary Poverty</head>
         <div type="saying" n="158">
            <p>Abbâ Arsenius once fell sick at Scete, and he was in need of a bowl of pottage; and
               since this was not to be found there, he took the remains of the Eucharist (or food
               of grace), and said, <quote>I give thanks unto Thee, O Christ, that, because of Thy name, I
               am able to receive the food of grace.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="159">
            <p>There was a certain holy man whose name was Philagrius, who lived in Jerusalem, and
               he worked with his hands and toiled [to earn] the food which he needed; and the old
               man rose up to see the work of his hands, and he found a purse containing one
               thousand darics which had dropped from some one [on the road], and he remained in the
               place where he was, saying, <quote>The man who lost this will come back seeking for it.</quote>
               And behold the man did come back, and he was weeping, and the old man took him aside
               and gave him the darics; and their owner laid hold upon him, and wished to give him
               some small sum of money, but the old man refused to accept anything. Then the owner
               of the darics began to cry out and say, <quote>Come ye and see what the man of God hath
               done</quote>; but the old man fled secretly and departed from the city, lest what he had
               done should become known, and men should pay him honour because of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="160">
            <p>They say that Abbâ Serapion the Bishop went on one occasion to one of the brethren,
               and found [in his cell] a hollow in the wall which was filled with books; and the
               brother said unto him, <quote>Speak to me one word whereby I may live.</quote> And the Bishop said
               unto him, <quote>What have I to say to thee? For thou hast taken that which belongeth to
               the orphans and widows and laid it up in a hole in the wall.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="161">
            <p>Abbâ Theodore of Parmê possessed some beautiful books, and he went to Abbâ Macarius
               and said unto him, <quote>Father, I have three books, and I gain profit from them, and the
               brethren borrow them from me, and they also have profit from them; tell me, now, what
               shall I do with them?</quote> And the old man answered and said, <quote>Ascetic labours are
               beautiful, but the greatest of them all is voluntary poverty.</quote> And when Abbâ Theodore
               heard these words he went and sold the books and gave the price of them to the
               poor.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="162">
            <p>They say about a certain monk that when his food came to him he was in the habit of
               taking so much of it as he needed, [but that if it happened that another man was
               brought to him he would not accept any of it], saying, <quote>It is sufficient for me;
               behold my Lord hath fed me.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="163">
            <p>A certain monk used to live in a cave in the desert, and a message was sent unto him
               by his kinsfolk, saying, <quote>Thy father is grievously sick, and is nigh to die,
               therefore come, and inherit his possessions</quote>; and he made answer unto them, saying,
               <quote>I died to the world long before he will die, and a dead man cannot be the heir of a
               living one.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="164">
            <p>An old man was asked by a brother the question, <quote>How shall I live?</quote> Then the old man
               took off his garment, and girded up his loins therewith, and lifted up his hands and
               said, <quote>It is meet for a monk to be as naked in respect of this world’s goods as I am
               of clothing. And in his striving against his thoughts he must stand as upright as a
               vigorous athlete, and when the athlete contendeth he also standeth up naked, and when
               he is anointed with oil he is quite naked, and hath nothing upon him; and he learneth
               from him that traineth him how to contend, and when the enemy cometh against him he
               throweth dust upon him, which is a matter of this world, that he may be able to grasp
               him easily. In thyself, then, O monk, thou must see the athlete, and he who sheweth
               thee how to contend is God, for it is He Who giveth the victory, and Who conquereth
               for us; and those who contend are ourselves, and the striving is [our] opponent, and
               the dust is the affairs of the world. And since thou hast seen the cunning of the
               Adversary, stand thou up and oppose him in thy nakedness, being free from any care
               which belongeth to this world, and thou shalt overcome [him]. For when the mind is
               weighted down with the care of the world it cannot receive the holy word of God.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="165">
            <p>They say concerning Abbâ Arsenius that as, when he lived in the world, his apparel
               was finer than that of anyone else, so, when he lived in Scete, he wore raiment which
               was inferior to that of every one else. And when, at long intervals, he came to
               church, he used to sit behind a pillar so that no one might see his face, and he
               might not see the faces of others; now his face was like that of an angel, and his
               hair was as white as snow, and as abundant as [that of] Jacob. His body was dry by
               reason of his labours, and his beard descended to his belly, but his eyelashes were
               destroyed by weeping; he was tall in stature, but somewhat bowed by old age and he
               ended his days when he was ninety-five years old. He lived in the world, in the
               palace, for forty years, in the days of Theodosius, the great king, who became the
               father of the Emperors Honorius and Arcadius, and he lived in Scete forty years, and
               he lived for ten years in the Troja of Babylon which is opposite the Memphis which is
               in Egypt, and he dwelt for three years in Canopus of Alexandria, and during the two
               remaining years he came to Troja again, where he died. And he finished his career in
               peace and in the fear of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="166">
            <p>On one occasion a certain Bishop came to the Fathers in Scete, and a brother went
               forth to meet him, and having met him, he took him and brought him into his cell; and
               having set before him bread and salt, he said, <quote>Forgive me, O my father, for I have
               nothing else to set before thee.</quote> And the Bishop said unto him, <quote>I wish that when I
               come another year I may not find even bread and salt in thy cell.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="167">
            <p>One of the old men said, <quote>If thou sittest in a place and seest people with abundant
               provisions, look not at them; but if there be a man who is destitute, look at him as
               one who hath no bread, and thou shalt find relief.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="168">
            <p>Abbâ Isaac, the priest of the Cells, used to say that Abbâ Pambô said, <quote>The manner of
               the apparel which a monk ought to wear should be such that if it were cast outside
               the cell for three days no one would carry it away.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="169">
            <p>A certain brother asked one of the old men a question, and said unto him, <quote>Dost thou
               wish me to keep two darics as provision for the needs of the feebleness of the body?</quote>
               And the old man, perceiving his mind and also that he wished to keep them, said unto
               him, <quote>Yea.</quote> Now when the brother had gone to his cell, he became troubled in his
               mind, and he debated in his thoughts, saying, <quote>Did the old man speak truthfully or
               not?</quote> Then he rose up, and went back to the old man, and made excuses to him, and
               said, <quote>For our Lord’s sake, tell me the truth, because my thoughts are troubling me
               about these two darics.</quote> The old man said unto him, <quote>I spake to thee as I did because
               I saw that thy mind was to keep them, but it is not necessary for thee to keep the
               two darics, except only for the need of thy body. But why is thy hope set upon two
               darics? If by chance they were lost would not God take care of thee? Let us then cast
               [our] care upon Him, for it belongeth to Him to take care of us continually.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="170">
            <p>Some of the old men used to tell a story about a gardener who used to work and to
               give away whatsoever he gained thereby in alms, but subsequently his thoughts said to
               him, <quote>Gather together a few oboli, lest when thou hast grown old thou fall into
               want</quote>; so he gathered together some money, and filled a large vessel therewith. And
               it fell out that he became sick, and the disease seized upon his foot, and he spent
               the whole of the money in the vessel on the physicians, and was not in the least
               benefited thereby. At length another physician came unto him and said, <quote>If thou dost
               not cut off thy foot all thy body will putrefy,</quote> and he came to consider the cutting
               off of his foot. And in the night he came to himself, and he groaned, and wept, and
               said, <quote>Remember, O Lord, my former deeds,</quote> and straightway a man appeared behind him,
               and said unto him, <quote>Where are thy oboli?</quote> and the gardener said immediately, <quote>I have
               sinned, forgive me</quote>; and straightway the man approached his leg, and it was made
               whole forthwith, and he rose up, and went to the garden to work. And in the morning
               the physician came to cut off his foot as he had said, and [the servants] told him,
               <quote>He went to this work in the night</quote>; and straightway [the gardener] glorified
               God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="171">
            <p>Abbâ Agathon saw Abbâ Nastîr wearing two shoulder wrappers, and he said unto him, <quote>If
               a poor man were to come, and ask thee for a garment, which of them wouldst thou give
               him?</quote> And Abbâ Nastîr replied, <quote>I would give him the better of them</quote>; and Abbâ
               Agathon said unto him, <quote>And if another poor man came, what wouldst thou give him?</quote>
               Abbâ Nastîr saith unto him, <quote>I would give him the half of that which remained.</quote> And
               Abbâ Agathon said unto him, <quote>Supposing yet another beggar came, what wouldst thou
               give unto him?</quote> And Nastîr said unto him, <quote>I would cut the half which remained into
               two pieces, and give one to him, and with the other I would cover my body.</quote> And Abbâ
               Agathon said unto him, <quote>And supposing yet another beggar were to come?</quote> and Nastîr
               said, <quote>I would give him what was left. For though I do not wish to receive anything
               from any man, yet I would go and sit down in some place until God sent me wherewith
               to cover myself.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="172">
            <p>The blessed woman Eugenia said, <quote>It is right for us to beg, but only we must be with
               Christ. He who is with Christ becometh rich, but he who honoureth the things of the
               body more than the things of the spirit shall fall both from the things which are
               first and the things which are last.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="173">
            <p>One of the old men said, <quote>How can a man teach unto his neighbour that which he
               himself doth not observe?</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="174">
            <p>They say that Abbâ Theodore excelled in the three following things more than any
               other man, and that he attained in their performance a degree which was greater than
               that of many, namely, voluntary poverty, self-abnegation, and flight from the
               children of men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="175">
            <p>Abbâ Poemen used to say, <quote>He who laboureth and keepeth [the result of] his work for
               himself is a twofold grief.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="176">
            <p>Abbâ Isaac used to say to the brethren, <quote>Our fathers and Abbâ Panbô used to wear old
               garments which were much mended and were patched with rags, but at this present ye
               wear very costly apparel; get ye gone from this place, for ye have laid the country
               waste, and I will not give you commandments, for ye will not keep them.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="177">
            <p>On one occasion a brother came to the church of the Cells wearing a small head-cloth
               which came down to his shoulders, and when Abbâ Isaac saw him he followed him, and
               said, <quote>Monks dwell here, but thou art a man in the world, and thou canst not live
               here.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="178">
            <p>A certain man, having made himself remote from the world, and divided his possessions
               among those who were in need, left to himself the remainder of his riches. And when
               the blessed Anthony heard [this] he said unto him, <quote>Dost thou wish to become a monk?
               If thou dost, get thee to such and such a village, and take some meat, and lay it
               upon thy body, and come hither alone</quote>; and having done this the dogs, and the hawks
               and other birds of prey rent and tore his body. And when he returned to the blessed
               man, Saint Anthony asked him whether he had done as he had commanded him, and when
               the man had shewn him his body which was rent and torn, the blessed Anthony said unto
               him, <quote>Even thus are those who wish to go out from the world, and who nevertheless
               leave themselves certain possessions, wherefrom arise for their owners war and
               strife.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="179">
            <p>A brother asked Abbâ Poemen the question, saying, <quote>An inheritance hath been
               bequeathed to me; what shall I do with it?</quote> Abbâ Poemen said unto him, <quote>Go, and after
               three days come unto me, and I will give theecounsel.</quote> And the brother came, and Abbâ
               Poemen said unto him, <quote>What counsel shall I give thee, O brother? If I tell thee to
               give it to the church, they will make feasts with it; and again, if I tell thee to
               give it to thy kinsmen, thou wilt have no reward; but if I tell thee to give it to
               the poor, thou wilt have no [further] care. Therefore go and do with thine
               inheritance what thou pleasest, for I am not able to advise thee rightly.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="180">
            <p>A certain man entreated an old man to accept from him a gift of grace for his wants,
               but he refused to do so because the labour of his hands was sufficient for him; and
               when he who asked him to accept it persisted, saying, <quote>If thou wilt not accept it for
               thine own needs, at least do so for the wants of others,</quote> the old man answered and
               said unto him, <quote>It would be a twofold disgrace [unto me]. First, because I should
               accept something which I do not want, and secondly, because I should be giving away
               with boasting the charity of another.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="181">
            <p>An old man used to say, <quote>It is not right for a man to have any care whatsoever except
               the fear of God, for,</quote> said he, <quote>although I am forced to take care for the needs of
               the body, no thought whatsoever concerning anything riseth in my mind before the time
               when I shall require to make use of it.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="182">
            <p>The same old man used to say, <quote>When thou risest up, in the morning, say, <quote>O body,
               work that thou mayest be fed; O soul, rouse up that thou mayest inherit life.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
