<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Of Obedience Towards God, And Towards Our Fathers And
               Brethren</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_7">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_2/Book_1/Chapter_7 </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 7: Of Obedience Towards God, And Towards Our Fathers And Brethren</head>
         <div type="saying" n="238">
            <p>They say that Abbâ John, the disciple of Abbâ Paulê, possessed great obedience. Now
               in the place where they used to live there was a sepulchre, wherein dwelt a savage
               panther, and Abbâ Paulê saw in it a few little heaps of goods, and he said unto John,
               <quote>Go to the sepulchre and bring me some of the things from there</quote>; and John said unto
               him, <quote>My father, what shall I do with the panther?</quote> And the old man laughed and said
               unto him, <quote>If he cometh against thee, tie him up and bring him here</quote>; so John went
               there at eventide, and the panther came against him, and when he went to lay hold of
               him the animal fled from him. Then John pursued him, saying, <quote>My father told me to
               fetter thee,</quote> and he seized him, and bound him with cords. Meanwhile the old man was
               very much troubled about John, and he was sitting waiting for him anxiously; and
               behold, he came dragging along the panther which was tied with ropes, and the old man
               saw and marvelled. Then the brother said unto him, <quote>Father, behold, I have taken
               prisoner the panther according as thou didst command, and I have brought him here</quote>;
               and the old man, wishing to remove from him the occasion for boasting, smote him, and
               said, <quote>Thou hast brought a wandering dog!</quote> and he untied the animal and let him
               depart.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="239">
            <p>Abbâ Joseph used to say, <quote>There are three things which are held in honour before God:
               first, when a man is sick, and he addeth to his toil, and receiveth it with
               thanksgiving; secondly, when a man maketh all his works to be pure before God, and
               when he hath in them no human consideration; thirdly, when a man submitteth himself
               to authority, and obeyeth his father, and setteth aside his own will. Such a man hath
               one crown the more, but I personally would choose the sickness.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="240">
            <p>They used to say that Abbâ Sylvanus had in Scete a disciple whose name was Mark, and
               that he possessed to a great degree the faculty of obedience; he was a scribe, and
               the old man loved him greatly for his obedience. Now Sylvanus had eleven other
               disciples, and they were vexed because they saw that the old man loved Mark more than
               them, and when the old men who were in Scete heard [of this] they were afflicted
               about it. And one day when they came to him to reprove him about this, Sylvanus took
               them, and went forth, and passing by the cells of the brethren, he knocked at the
               door of each cell, and said, <quote>O brother, come forth, for I have need of thee</quote>; and he
               passed by all their cells, and not one of them obeyed him quickly. But when they went
               to the cell of Mark, he knocked at the door and said, <quote>Brother Mark,</quote> and as soon as
               Mark heard the voice of the old man, he jumped up straightway, and came out, and
               Sylvanus sent him off on some business. Then Sylvanus said unto the old men, <quote>My
               fathers, where are the other brethren?</quote> And they went into Mark’s cell, and looked at
               the quire of the book which he was writing, and they saw that he had begun to write
               [one side of] the Greek letter o (or ω), and that as soon as he heard the voice of
               his master, [he ran out] and did not stay to complete the other side of the letter.
               Now when the old men perceived these things, they answered and said unto Sylvanus,
               <quote>Verily, O old man, we also love the brother whom thou lovest, for God also loveth
               him.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="241">
            <p>On another occasion the mother of Mark came to see him, and she had with her an
               abundant company of members of her household; and an old man went forth to her, and
               she said unto him, <quote>Abbâ, tell my son to come forth and see me</quote>; and the old man went
               in, and said to him, <quote>Go forth and see thy mother.</quote> Then Mark wrapped himself up in
               rags, and blackened his face by standing up in the sooty chimney, and he went forth
               thus fulfilling the behest of his master, and shutting his eyes, he said unto those
               [who were with his mother], <quote>Live ye! Live ye!</quote> but he did not look at them. Now his
               mother did not recognize him, and she sent in again to the old man a message, saying,
               <quote>Send me my son, O father, so that I may see him.</quote> Then the old man said unto Mark,
               <quote>Did I not tell thee to go out and see thy mother?</quote> And he said unto him, <quote>Father, I
               went forth according to thy word, but I beseech thee do not tell me to go forth
               again, lest peradventure I feel myself compelled to disobey thee</quote>; and [the old man]
               spake with her, and quieted her, and sent her away in peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="242">
            <p>And they used to tell about two brethren who lived in a monastery, and who both had
               arrived at a high grade in the ascetic life; the one devoted himself to an austere
               life of self-denial and poverty, and the other was obedient and humble. And being
               angry with each other they wished to know which of the two [kinds of] service was the
               greater, and they went down to the river where there were many crocodiles, and that
               brother who possessed the faculty of obedience went in, and stood up among them, and
               they all worshipped him. Then he cried out to his fellow who was a mourner, and said
               unto him, <quote>Forgive me, O my brother, I have not yet attained to such a high degree of
               faith as thou hast</quote>; and when they returned to the monastery, the head of the
               monastery heard a voice, saying, <quote>The man who obeyeth is better than the man who
               leadeth a life of voluntary poverty.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="243">
            <p>Abbâ Daniel used to say, <quote>On one occasion Abbâ Arsenius called me and said unto me,
               <quote>Make thy father to be gratified, so that when he goeth to our Lord, he may make
               entreaties to Him on behalf of thee, and good shall be unto thee.</quote></quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="244">
            <p>A certain brother was engaged in a war against Satan, and he told the matter to Abbâ
               Herakles; and wishing to strengthen and confirm him the old man told him the
               following story:—There was a certain old man who had a disciple, and he had been very
               obedient unto him for many years, and when the war came upon him, he made a request
               to his master, saying, <quote>I beseech thee to make me a monk.</quote> And his master said unto
               him, <quote>Seek out a place for thyself, and we will build a cell for thee, and thou shalt
               become a monk.</quote> So the disciple went and found a place, which was distant from his
               master about one hundred paces, and he made himself a cell. Then the old man said
               unto that brother, <quote>Whatsoever I say unto thee, that do. When thou art hungry, eat;
               and when thou art thirsty, drink; and sleep, but thou must not go out from thy cell
               until the Sabbath Day, when thou shalt come to me.</quote> Then the old man went back to his
               cell. And the brother did according as the old man told him for two days, but on the
               third day he became dejected, and wearied, and said, <quote>What hath the old man done for
               me, seeing that he hath not commanded me to make prayers?</quote> Then he rose up and sang
               more Psalms than usual, and after the sun had set he ate his food, and he rose up,
               and went, and lay down upon his mat; and he saw, as it were, an Ethiopian who stood
               up and gnashed his teeth at him, and the monk, by reason of his great fear, ran
               quickly to his master, and he knocked hastily at his door, saying, <quote>Father, have
               mercy upon me, and open to me immediately.</quote> Now because the old man knew that he had
               not kept his commandment he refused to open the door to him until the morning, and
               when he opened the door in the morning, he found him [there], and as the brother
               entreated him to be allowed to enter, the old man had compassion upon him and brought
               him in. Then he began to say unto the old man, <quote>I beseech thee, O father, [to believe
               me]. When I went to lie down to go to sleep, I saw a black Ethiopian on my bed.</quote> The
               old man said unto him, <quote>This [happened] because thou didst not keep my words.</quote> Then
               he laid down a rule for him which was suitable to his strength and to the monastic
               life, and dismissed him, and little by little he became an excellent monk.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="245">
            <p>A man who wanted to be a monk came to Abbâ Sisoes the Theban, and the old man asked
               him, if he had any possession whatsoever in the world, and he said, <quote>I have one son</quote>;
               and the old man, wishing to find out if he possessed the faculty of obedience, said
               unto him, <quote>Go, and throw him in the river, and then come, and thou shalt be a monk,</quote>
               and because the man was obedient he went straightway to do it. Now when he had
               departed the old man sent another brother to prevent him from doing this thing, and
               when the man had taken up his son to throw him into the river, the brother said unto
               him, <quote>Thou shalt not cast him in.</quote> Then the man said unto him, <quote>My father told me
               that I was to cast him in,</quote> and the brother replied, <quote>He told me that thou wast not
               to cast him in,</quote> so the man left him, and came [unto the old man], and through his
               obedience he became a chosen monk.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="246">
            <p>The Abbâ who was in Îlîû used to say, <quote>Obedience cometh into existence because of
               obedience; for if a man obeyeth God, God also will obey him.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="saying" n="247">
            <p>On one occasion four brethren came to Abbâ Pambô from Scete, and they were wearing
               skins, and each one of them, whilst his neighbour was absent, recounted [to him] his
               works, [saying], the first one fasteth very often, and the second leadeth a life of
               poverty, and the third possesseth great love, and concerning the fourth the other
               three said, <quote>He hath been in subjection to the old men for twenty-two years.</quote> Then
               Abbâ Pambô said unto them, <quote>I say unto you that the spiritual excellence of this man
               is great. Each of you hath chosen the ascetic virtue which he possesseth according to
               his own wish, but this man hath cut off his own desire, and hath performed the will
               of others; and those who are thus will, if they keep these things to the end, become
               confessors.</quote></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
