<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book" n="9">
            <head>Book 9</head>
            <div type="section" n="9.0">
               <p>Also this ninth Book, concerning the reign of <persName>Justinian</persName>, states how he became
                     Anti-<persName>Caesar</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n218-1"/> on the fifth day of the
                  week in the last week of the fast; and, after he had governed for three months in
                  conjunction with <persName>Justin</persName> his uncle, who died at the end of July, when the year five
                  was now ending,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n218-2"/> this Justinian became
                     emperor,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n218-3"/> in the year eight hundred and
                  thirty-eight of the Greeks, in the three hundred and twenty-seventh Olympiad. And
                  the events which happened during his reign down to the year fifteen,<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n218-4"/> a space of ten years, which is contained
                  in the sections below, are set down in this ninth Book, consisting of twenty-six
                  chapters. Behold! they are set down below, and are as follows:—</p>
               <p>The first chapter of the ninth Book deals with the fighting which went on in the
                  summer of the year five before <placeName>Nisibis</placeName> and <placeName>Thebetha</placeName>, a Persian fortress.</p>
               <p>The second chapter of the Book treats of the battle which was fought in the desert
                  of <placeName>Thannuris</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The third chapter of the Book gives an account of the battle which was fought
                  before the city of <placeName>Dara</placeName> on the frontier.</p>
               <p>The fourth chapter of the Book gives information about the battle which was fought
                  on the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName> in the year nine.</p>
               <p>The fifth chapter tells of <persName>Gadar</persName> the Kadisene, a Persian general, how he was
                  killed; and <persName>Izdegerd</persName>, who was with him, a nephew of the <persName>Ptehasha</persName> of <placeName>Arzanene</placeName>, was
                  taken prisoner.</p>
               <p>The sixth chapter deals with the battle which was fought before <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName> on
                  the frontier, and the large numbers <pb type="page" n="219"/>of Huns who invaded
                  the territory of the Romans in the year ten.</p>
               <p>The seventh chapter explains how in the summer of the year eleven peace was made
                  between the Romans and the Persians by the ambassadors, <persName>Rufinus</persName> and <persName>Hermogenes</persName>,
                  the master of the offices.</p>
               <p>The eighth chapter of the ninth Book treats of the Samaritans who rebelled and set
                  up a tyrant of their own in the country of <placeName>Palestine</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The ninth chapter of the Book, concerning the heresy of <persName>Julian</persName> the Phantasiast,
                  bishop of the city of <placeName>Halicarnassus</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n219-1"/> how
                  it appeared.</p>
               <p>The tenth chapter sets forth the first epistle of <persName>Julian</persName> to <persName>Severus</persName>, with a
                  question about the body of <persName>Christ</persName> our God.</p>
               <p>The eleventh chapter of the Book treats of the answer to the epistle of <persName>Julian</persName>,
                  which the doctor <persName>Severus</persName>, the chief priest, wrote to him.</p>
               <p>The twelfth chapter of the Book imparts information about the second epistle of
                     <persName>Julian</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n219-2"/> which he wrote to Severus.</p>
               <p>The thirteenth chapter tells of the answer made by <persName>Severus</persName> the patriarch to this
                  second epistle of <persName>Julian</persName>.</p>
               <p>The fourteenth chapter of the Book treats of the riot which took place in the
                  royal city, and describes how <persName>Hypatius</persName> and <persName>Pompeius</persName> were put to death, and large
                  numbers of the people were massacred in the circus in the year ten.</p>
               <p>The fifteenth chapter treats of the request contained in the petition which the
                  believing bishops who had been summoned from exile to the royal city presented to
                  King <persName>Justinian</persName> concerning their faith.</p>
               <p>The sixteenth chapter of the ninth Book sets forth the defence made by <persName>Severus</persName> the
                  chief priest in his epistle to King <persName>Justinian</persName>, refusing to come, when summoned by
                  him to the royal city.</p>
               <p>The seventeenth chapter of the ninth Book treats of <persName>Carthage</persName>, the chief city of
                  the country of <placeName>Africa</placeName>, how it was <pb type="page" n="220"/>taken by <persName>Belisarius</persName> the
                  general and a Roman army, and made subject to King <persName>Justinian</persName>.</p>
               <p>The eighteenth chapter of the ninth Book deals with <placeName>Rome</placeName> and <placeName>Naples</placeName> in the country
                  of <placeName>Italy</placeName>, and how they were taken by <persName>Belisarius</persName> the general and a Roman army.</p>
               <p>The nineteenth chapter of the ninth Book again treats of <persName>Severus</persName> the patriarch,
                  who went up<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n220-1"/> to the royal city and
                  appeared before the king, and was received in the palace, and remained there till
                  the end of the month of March in the year fourteen, and then departed.</p>
               <p>The twentieth chapter of the ninth Book treats of the epistle of <persName>Severus</persName> the
                  patriarch to the order of priests and the society of monks in the East, dealing
                  with his expulsion from the royal city.</p>
               <p>The twenty-first [chapter]<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n220-2"/> of the ninth
                  Book sets forth the canonical epistle of union and concord which was sent by
                  <persName>Anthimus</persName>, chief priest of the royal city, to <persName>Severus</persName> the patriarch.</p>
               <p>The twenty-second chapter of the ninth Book treats of the epistle of concord and
                  union canonically sent by Severus in answer to <persName>Anthimus</persName>, chief priest of
                  <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, the royal city.</p>
               <p>The twenty-third chapter of the ninth Book introduces the epistle of concord and
                  union which was canonically sent by <persName>Severus</persName> to <persName>Theodosius</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The twenty-fourth chapter of the ninth Book treats further of the canonical
                  epistle of union and concord which was sent by <persName>Theodosius</persName> the patriarch in answer
                  to <persName>Severus</persName> the doctor.</p>
               <p>The twenty-fifth chapter of the ninth Book gives information about the canonical
                  epistle of concord which was sent by <persName>Anthimus</persName>, chief priest of the royal city, to
                  <persName>Theodosius</persName>, patriarch of the great city of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The twenty-sixth chapter of the ninth Book records<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n220-3"/> the answer to the epistle, which was canonically sent by <pb
                     type="page" n="221"/><persName>Theodosius</persName>, archbishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, to <persName>Anthimus</persName>, chief
                  priest of the royal city, in concord and brotherhood.</p>
               <p>There is inserted also in it, at the end of this ninth Book, the prologue given
                     above,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-1"/> which was composed concisely
                  under heads by the holy Moro, bishop of <placeName>Amida</placeName>, a man deserving of blessed memory,
                  upon the Gospel and the dispensation of <persName>Christ</persName> in the flesh, and also a story
                  which is contained in the eighty-ninth canon, taken from the Gospel of <persName>John</persName> and
                     mentioned<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-2"/> by him alone, about a woman
                  with child by adultery, who was brought to Him by the Jewish doctors.<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-3"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.1">
               <head>Chapter 1</head>
               <head>The first chapter of the ninth Book, treating of the accession of <persName>Justinian</persName>,
                  and of the fighting which went on before <persName>Nisibis</persName> and the fortress of
                  <placeName>Thebetha</placeName></head>
               <p>In the year five,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-4"/> when <persName>Justin</persName> was king, that old man of whom we related
                  above<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-5"/> that he came from the country of <placeName>Illyricum</placeName>, he made his sister's
                  son, who was general,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-6"/> Anti-Caesar,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-7"/> and <persName>Justinian</persName> became
                  Anti-Caesar on the fifth day of the week in the last week of the fast. 
                  And,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-8"/> after he had governed for three months, his uncle died, at the end
                  of July, and he became emperor,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-9"/> in the year eight hundred and thirty-
                  eight of the Greeks,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-10"/> in the three hundred and twenty-seventh Olympiad.
                  And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-11"/> as to his own <placeName>Castra Mauriana</placeName> he gave orders, and a great city was 
                  built, and privileges<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-12"/> were granted to it, and a military force was also
                  stationed in it; and water was brought into it from a distance,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n221-13"/> because
                  its own water was bad.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="222"/>
               <p>And, behold! from the beginning of his reign down to this day he has indeed
                  devoted attention to building, refounding<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n222-1"/> cities in various countries,
                  and repairing walls in various places for the protection of his dominions.</p>
               <p>But, since the Persians and the Romans were at enmity with one another in those
                  times, while <persName>Timus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n222-2"/>(?), the master of the soldiers,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n222-3"/> was duke on
                  the frontier, the army with its officers was mustered round him to fight against
                  <placeName>Nisibis</placeName>; and they fought, but could not take it, and retired thence to the
                  fortress of <placeName>Thebetha</placeName>; and the army came close up to the wall and made a breach in
                  it; and it was the hottest part of the summer. And through some cause or other
                  they were prevented from effecting their purpose, and did not get possession of
                  the fortress, which was about fifteen parasangs from <placeName>Dara</placeName>. And the army was
                  ordered to return to <placeName>Dara</placeName>; and, because they greedily ate honey and the
                  flesh<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n222-4"/> of large numbers of swine, some of the infantry<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n222-5"/> died of
                  thirst on the march and were lost to the army, and others threw themselves into
                  the wells of the desert and were drowned, and the rest were burnt up by the heat
                  on the march, but the cavalry reached <placeName>Dara</placeName>; and so the army was broken up.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.2">
               <head>Chapter 2</head>
               <head>The second chapter of the ninth Book, concerning the battle which was fought in
                  the desert of <placeName>Thannuris</placeName></head>
               <p>During the lifetime of <persName>Justin</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n222-6"/> the king, who had learned that <placeName>Thannuris</placeName>
                  was a convenient place for a city to be built as a place of refuge in the desert,
                  and for a military force to be stationed to protect ʿArab against the marauding
                  bands of <pb type="page" n="223"/><persName>Saracens</persName>, <persName>Thomas</persName> the silentiary, a native of
                  <placeName>Aphphadana</placeName>, had been sent to build such a city. And, when he had made but
                  inconsiderable progress, then the works which had begun to be carried out were
                  destroyed by the Saracens and Kadisenes from <placeName>Singara</placeName> and <placeName>Thebetha</placeName>. Now, because
                  the Romans, as we have stated above, had taken the field and fought against
                  <placeName>Nisibis</placeName> and <placeName>Thebetha</placeName>, therefore afterwards<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n223-1"/> the Persians also similarly
                  came and made an entrenchment(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n223-2"/> in the desert of <placeName>Thannuris</placeName>. And, Duke
                  <persName>Timus</persName>, the master of the soldiers,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n223-3"/> having died, <persName>Belisarius</persName> had succeeded
                  him; and he was not greedy after bribes, and was kind to the peasants, and did not
                  allow the army to injure them. For he was accompanied by <persName>Solomon</persName>, a eunuch from
                  the fortress of <persName>Edribath</persName>(?);<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n223-4"/> and he was an astute man, and well-versed in
                  the affairs of the world; and he had been notary to <persName>Felicissimus</persName> the duke, and had
                  been attached to the other governors; and he had gained cunning through experience
                  of difficulties.</p>
               <p>Accordingly, a Roman army was mustered for the purpose of marching into the desert
                  of <placeName>Thannuris</placeName> against the Persians under the leadership of <persName>Belisarius</persName>,
                  <persName>Cutzes</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n223-5"/> the brother of <persName>Butzes</persName>, <persName>Basil</persName>, <persName>Vincent</persName>, and other commanders, and
                  <persName>Atafar</persName>, the chief of the <persName>Saracens</persName>. And, when the Persians heard of it, they
                  devised a stratagem, and dug several ditches among their trenches,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n223-6"/> and
                  concealed them(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n223-7"/> all round outside by triangular<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n223-8"/> stakes of
                  wood, and left several openings. And, when the Roman army came up, they did not
                  perceive the Persians' deceitful stratagem in time, but the generals entered the
                  Persian entrenchment<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n223-6"/> at full speed, and, falling into the pits, were
                  taken prisoners, and <persName>Cutzes</persName> was killed. And of the Roman army those who were
                  mounted<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n223-9"/> turned back and returned in <pb type="page" n="224"/>flight to
                  <placeName>Dara</placeName> with <persName>Belisarius</persName>; but the infantry, who did not escape, were killed and taken
                  captive. And <persName>Atafar</persName>, the <persName>Saracen</persName> king, during his flight was struck(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n224-1"/>
                  from a short distance off, and perished; and he was a warlike and an able man, and
                  he had had much experience in the use of Roman arms, and in various places had won
                  distinction and renown in war.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.3">
               <head>Chapter 3</head>
               <head>The third chapter of the ninth Book, concerning the battle before <placeName>Dara</placeName></head>
               <p>The Persians were proud and puffed up<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n224-2"/> and boastful; and, indeed, the
                  <rs>Mihran</rs> and the marzbans assembled an army and came against <placeName>Dara</placeName> and encamped at 
                  Ammodis, being fully confident in the expectation of taking the city, because the
                  Roman army had been diminished by their sword. And their cavalry and infantry
                  approached and came up on the south side of the city, intending to encompass it
                  all round for the purpose of blockading it; but a Roman force met them by the help
                  of our Lord, who chastises but does not utterly deliver over unto death. For a
                  certain <persName>Sunica</persName>, a general, who was a Hun,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n224-3"/> and, having taken refuge with
                  the Romans, had been baptized, and <persName>Simuth</persName>(?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n224-4"/> a Roman tribune,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n224-5"/>
                  and their armour-bearers with twenty men each drove the whole Persian army away
                  from the city several times, passing boldly and vigorously from one part of the
                  field to another, and cutting men down right and left with the lance. And they
                  were practised in the use of the sword; and their cry was loud and terrific, and
                  made them appear terrible to the Persians, so <pb type="page" n="225"/>that they
                  fell before them: and two of their leaders were killed, besides no small number of
                  horsemen; while of the faige, who are the Persian infantry, many were cut down and
                  hurled back by the Helurians,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n225-1"/> under <persName>Butzes</persName>, to the east of the city.</p>
               <p>And the Persians, when they saw how great the number of the dead was, acted
                  craftily, and sent to <persName>Nisibis</persName>, asking them to bring as many baggage-animals as
                  possible and come at once to <placeName>Dara</placeName>, and take as much spoil as they could. And, when
                  large numbers came, they laded them with the bodies, of their slain, and then they
                  returned in shame. However, the rest of the Persian force invaded<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n225-2"/> Roman
                  ʿArab, and burned it with fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.4">
               <head>Chapter 4</head>
               <head>The fourth chapter, concerning the battle which was fought on the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName> in
                  the year nine<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n225-3"/></head>
               <p>The Persians, having learned wisdom by experience through the great injury which
                  they had suffered from the attacks of the Romans whenever they approached the city
                  and went out against them, went up into the desert portion of the Roman territory
                  and encamped on the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>; and according to their usual practice they made a
                  trench.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n225-4"/> And <persName>Belisarius</persName> at the head of a Roman<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n225-5"/> force and
                  tribunes<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n225-6"/> came up against them to battle; and they arrived in the last
                  week of the fast. And the Persians were found to be as a little flock, and so they
                  appeared in their eyes: and <persName>Asthebid</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n225-7"/> their commander was afraid of them,
                  and those who were with him; and he sent<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n225-8"/> to the Romans, asking them to
                  respect the feast, <pb type="page" n="226"/><quote>for the sake of the Nazarenes and
                  Jews who are in the army that is with me, and for the sake of yourselves, who are
                  Christians.</quote> And, when <persName>Belisarius</persName> the general<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n226-1"/> had considered this, he was
                  willing to agree; but the commanders murmured greatly, and would not consent to
                  wait and respect the day. And, when they went out to battle on the eve of the
                  first day of the week, the day of unleavened bread, it was a cold day, with the
                  wind in the face of the Romans; and they showed themselves feeble, and turned and
                  fled before the Persian attack; and many fell into the Euphrates and were drowned,
                  and others were killed; but <persName>Belisarius</persName> escaped, while the nephew<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n226-2"/> of
                  <persName>Butzes</persName> was taken prisoner (for he himself was ill at <placeName>Amida</placeName>, and did not go to the
                  battle, but sent his army to <placeName>Abgersatum</placeName> under <persName>Domitziolus</persName>), and went down to
                  Persia, but eventually returned: and how this happened I will relate in this
                  next<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n226-3"/> chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.5">
               <head>Chapter 5</head>
               <head>The fifth chapter of the ninth Book, concerning <persName>Gadar</persName> the Kadisene, a Persian
                  general, how he was killed; and <persName>Izdegerd</persName>, who was with him, and was nephew of
                  <persName>Hormizd</persName>, <persName>Ptehasha</persName> of <placeName>Arzanene</placeName>, was taken prisoner</head>
               <p>The Romans, when <persName>Belisarius</persName> was duke, in the year five,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n226-4"/> having been
                  prevented from building <placeName>Thannuris</placeName> on the frontier, wished to make a city at
                  <placeName>Melebasa</placeName>; wherefore<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n226-5"/> <persName>Gadar</persName> the Kadisene was sent with an army by <persName>Kawad</persName>;
                  and he prevented the Romans from effecting their purpose, and put them to flight
                  in a battle which he fought with them on the hill of <placeName>Melebasa</placeName>. And he was high in
                  the confidence of <persName>Kawad</persName>, <pb type="page" n="227"/>and had been stationed with an
                  army to guard the frontier eastwards from <placeName>Melebasa</placeName> in the country of <placeName>Arzanene</placeName> as
                  far as <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>. And this man uttered many boasts and vain words against the
                  Romans, and blasphemed like <persName>Rab Shakeh</persName>, who was sent by <persName>Sennacherib</persName>. And he
                  brought about seven hundred armed cavalry, and some infantry, who accompanied them
                  for the sake of amassing plunder; and they crossed the <placeName>Tigris</placeName> into the district of
                  <placeName>Attachae</placeName> in the territory of <placeName>Amida</placeName>. And <persName>Bessa</persName> was duke in <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>; and it was
                  summer time in this year nine.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n227-1"/> And with <persName>Gadar</persName> was <persName>Izdegerd</persName>, the
                  nephew<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n227-2"/> of the Ptehasha<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n227-3"/> who, as a neighbour, knew the region of
                  <placeName>Attachae</placeName>. And when <persName>Bessa</persName> heard of it he went out against him with about five
                  hundred horsemen from <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>, which was about four(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n227-4"/> stades
                  distant. And he met him at <placeName>Beth Helte</placeName> and routed his army on the <placeName>Tigris</placeName>, and
                  killed <persName>Gadar</persName>, and took <persName>Izdegerd</persName> prisoner and brought him to <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>. This man
                  after the peace, which was made in the year ten,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n227-5"/> was given in exchange
                  for <persName>Domitziolus</persName>, who returned from <placeName>Persia</placeName>. But <persName>Bessa</persName> the duke after routing <persName>Gadar</persName>
                  and the Persian cavalry, who were guarding the frontier of <placeName>Arzanene</placeName>, entered the
                  country and did much damage there; and he carried off captives and brought them to
                  <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.6">
               <head>Chapter 6</head>
               <head>The sixth chapter informs us in this ninth Book about the fighting which went
                  on before <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>, and about the great host of Huns which invaded the
                  territory of the Romans</head>
               <p>The villages in the country of <placeName>Arzanene</placeName> are the property of the Persian crown, and
                  no small<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n227-6"/> sum is collected as poll-tax <pb type="page" n="228"/>from their
                  inhabitants for the king's treasury and for the office<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-1"/> of <rs>the Ptehasha</rs>, 
                  who is stationed there (he is the king's prefect).<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-2"/> To this country, as
                  related above, <persName>Bessa</persName> the duke did much injury; who took the nephew of <rs>the Ptehasha</rs> 
                  captive, and also kept him prisoner in <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>. And King <persName>Kawad</persName> was much
                  distressed when he heard from <rs>the Ptehasha</rs> about the devastation of the country:  
                  which same Hormizd left no stone unturned,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-3"/> using force and
                  cunning(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-4"/> against <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-5"/> in order to get possession of
                  it, for it acts as an ambush and a place of refuge for a Roman army, enabling it
                  to ravage <persName>Arzanene</persName>. And an army was, so to speak, equipped by the Persian
                  army:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-6"/> <persName>Mihr Girowi</persName> was sent to hire a large number of Huns and bring them
                  to their assistance. And they came and were gathered together against <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>
                  at the beginning of the year ten;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-7"/> and they made a trench<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-8"/> against
                  it, and a <quote>mule</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-9"/> and many mines; and they made assaults upon it, and
                  pressed it hard. And in it was Butzes and a Roman force of no small size, and they
                  drove large numbers of Persians back in battle. But Nonnus also, the bishop of the
                  city, had died.</p>
               <p>Now <persName>Belisarius</persName>, being held culpable by the king on account of the rout which had
                  been inflicted on the Roman army by the Persians at <placeName>Thannuris</placeName> and on the
                  <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>, had been dismissed from his command, and went up to the king; and he
                  was succeeded at <placeName>Dara</placeName> by <persName>Constantine</persName>.</p>
               <p>And a large Roman army was mustered, and <persName>Sittas</persName> was general;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-10"/> and <persName>Bar
                  Gabala</persName>, the Saracen king, was with them. And they reached <placeName>Amida</placeName> in
                  November<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-11"/>(?) of the year ten;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n228-12"/> and <persName>John</persName>, the hermit of
                  <placeName>Anastasia</placeName>, a man of honourable character, who had been elected to the bishopric,
                  accompanied <pb type="page" n="229"/>them. And, when they had gone to <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>
                  and the winter came on (and the country is northerly and cold), the Persians were
                  impeded<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n229-1"/> by rain and mud, and underwent<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n229-2"/> hardships, while they
                  were also afraid of the numbers of the Roman army; and <persName>Kawad</persName> their king also had
                  died while they were there; and they made a compact with the Romans to withdraw
                  from the city.</p>
               <p>And, soon after they had withdrawn and <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName> had been freed from blockade,
                  and the Roman army had returned, the Huns,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n229-3"/> who had been hired by the
                  Persians, arrived. This great people suddenly attacked the territory of the
                  Romans, and massacred and slew many of the tillers of the soil, and burned
                  villages and their churches; and they crossed the Euphrates and advanced as far as
                  <placeName>Antioch</placeName>; and no one stood before them or did them any harm except only the same
                  <persName>Bessa</persName>, the duke of <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>, who fell upon a detachment of them during their
                  retreat and killed them, and captured<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n229-4"/> about five hundred horses and much
                  spoil; and the man became rich. And at the fortress of <persName>Citharizon</persName> the duke there
                  repulsed a party of them, consisting of about four hundred men, and captured their
                  baggage-animals.</p>
               <p>Now<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n229-5"/> after <persName>Kawad Khosru</persName> his son became king. His mother during the
                  lifetime of <persName>Kawad</persName> her husband had been vexed by a demon; and all the magians and
                  sorcerers and enchanters, who had been summoned by <persName>Kawad</persName> her husband, who loved
                  her greatly, did her no good, but, to say the truth, added demons to demons in
                  her. She in the year four,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n229-6"/> in the days of <persName>Liberius</persName> the duke, was sent to
                  the blessed <persName>Moses</persName>, who was a monk close to <placeName>Dara</placeName>, about two parasangs' space
                  distant, and was a famous man. And she was with him a few days, and was cleansed,
                  and returned to her own land, <pb type="page" n="230"/>having received from this
                  holy <persName>Moses</persName> of the monastery called <placeName>Tarmel</placeName> an amulet taken from the bones of <persName>Cyriac</persName>
                  the martyr to protect her, that in it she might find refuge, so that the spirit
                  should not return upon her. And, to do him honour, she, under a certain symbolical
                  form(?),[#230-1] built him a house of prayer in her own country, and he is
                  worshipped there. And, remembering the grace wrought in her through this blessed
                  <persName>Moses</persName> of <placeName>Tarmel</placeName>, she did a service to the land of the Romans in the manner and on
                  the occasion set forth below.</p>
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter" n="9.7">
               <head>Chapter 7</head>
               <head>The seventh chapter of the ninth Book, how peace was made between the Romans
                  and the Persians,and lasted six or seven years, in the days of <persName>Rufinus</persName> and of
                  <persName>Hermogenes</persName>, the master of the offices.</head>
               <p><persName>Justinian</persName> the king, considering the things which had happened in his dominions
                  between the rivers, and the forces which had at various times been destroyed by
                  the Persians, and the tillers of the soil who had been slain and made captive by
                  the Huns, and the land which had been burnt with the villages upon it, was not
                  inclined again to send an army to contend in war with <persName>Khosru</persName>, who became king
                  after <persName>Kawad</persName> his father. And, since this man was friendly to Rufinus, and it was he
                  who had advised his father to make him his successor, he used to make assertion to
                  the king, and encourage him, and to undertake that, if he showed himself before
                  him in his own country, he would for the sake of the <pb type="page" n="231"
                  />peace desired by the king accept what he justly asked of him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n231-1"/> And so
                  this <persName>Rufinus</persName> and <persName>Hermogenes</persName>, the master of the offices, were sent as
                  ambassadors<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n231-2"/> to <placeName>Khosru</placeName> in the year eleven;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n231-3"/> and they had much
                  speech with him. And, because this Rufinus was well known there, in as much as he
                  had been several times sent to <placeName>Kawad</placeName>, and was his friend, and used to give many
                  presents to the magnates of his kingdom, and the queen, the mother of <persName>Khosru</persName>, was
                  friendly to him, because he had advised <persName>Kawad</persName> to make her son king, and she owed
                  gratitude to <persName>Moses</persName> the blessed monk of <placeName>Tarmel</placeName> after God for her healing, she
                  earnestly entreated <persName>Khosru</persName> her son, and on consideration of a sum of gold which he
                  received, which was sent by King <persName>Justinian</persName> according to the message transmitted to
                  him by <persName>Rufinus</persName> and <persName>Hermogenes</persName> his ambassadors, he made peace; and a written treaty
                  was drawn up and ratified. And[#n231–4] the stars in the sky had appeared dancing
                  in a strange manner, and it was the summer of the year eleven.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n231-5"/> And it
                  lasted about six or seven years, until the year three.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n231-6"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.8">
               <head>Chapter 8</head>
               <head>The eighth chapter of the ninth Book, concerning the Samaritans, who rebelled
                  and set up a tyrant of their own in the country of <placeName>Palestine</placeName>.</head>
               <p>The Samaritans in the country of <placeName>Palestine</placeName> who live near the city of <placeName>Neapolis</placeName>, not
                  far from <placeName>Caesarea</placeName>, having heard that <pb type="page" n="232"/>the Persians had from
                  time to time attacked and invaded the Roman territory, and supposing that they had
                  shown themselves weak before them, were emboldened by the thought that they had
                  been sent from <placeName>Khuth</placeName> and <placeName>Babylon</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n232-1"/> and from <persName>ʿAwa</persName> and from <placeName>Hamath</placeName> and from
                  <persName>Sʾfarwayim</persName> by <persName>Shalmanʿasar</persName>, king of <placeName>Assyria</placeName>, and settled in the land of <placeName>Samaria</placeName>;
                  and, having rebelled, they set<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n232-2"/> a tyrant at their head; and they entered
                  <placeName>Neapolis</placeName>, and killed <persName>Mommuno</persName> the bishop there; and they made an insurrection, and
                  wrought havoc in the country, wishing to help the Persians, because it was out of
                  their country that they had been settled in the territory of the Romans; and they
                  burnt many temples of the saints; and they occupied the city and amassed
                  spoil.</p>
               <p>And, when the king heard of this, he sent <persName>Hadrian</persName> the tribune;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n232-3"/> and there
                  were gathered together also the duke of the country, who was with him, and an army
                  of Romans, and the Saracens of <placeName>Arabia</placeName>; and they marched against the Samaritans.
                  And they were cut to pieces by the Romans; and they killed the tyrant, and took
                  the city and restored it to its former normal condition of subjection to their
                  authority. And a bishop was also appointed in it; and a military force was
                  stationed there, to guard it and to keep order among the inhabitants of the
                  country.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.9">
               <head>Chapter 9</head>
               <head>The ninth chapter of the ninth Book, concerning the Phantasiastic Heresy of
                  <persName>Julian</persName> of <placeName>Halicarnassus</placeName>, how it appeared <persName>Julian</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n232-4"/> bishop of the city of
                  <placeName>Halicarnassus</placeName>, withdrew from his see through zeal with the other believing
                  bishops; and he was an old man, and he was zealous in the faith: and in his desire
                  to avoid speaking of two natures he, like <persName>Eutyches</persName> and <pb type="page" n="233"
                  />the monks who have not a right knowledge of the true order of things, fell into
                  the heresy of <persName>Eutyches</persName>. (And he was an acquaintance and a friend of the learned
                  <persName>Severus</persName> the chief priest; and once this same <persName>Julian</persName> on being questioned by someone
                  composed a treatise against the Diphysites, and he produced it(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n233-1"/> at no
                  great length without cause of offence.) However, though that wise
                  combatant<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n233-2"/> <persName>Severus</persName> had heard of it, he had kept this knowledge
                  hidden,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n233-3"/> fearing lest, if he corrected it, house should be divided against
                  house, and he should cause a division in love, which no man had been able to
                  separate, being patiently determined to accept his poverty, which is according to
                  right(?).</head>
               <p>And, when in this way<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n233-4"/> reason was added to reason, as our Lord brought it
                  about, in order, that is, that the learning of <persName>Severus</persName> might be made manifest, the
                  beauty of his true faith, for the benefit of the discerning and of those who love
                  instruction, [he was compelled to expose the matter].<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n233-5"/></p>
               <p>And, to show the nature of the original subject of contention,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n233-6"/> I insert
                  some epistles, which, taken in order, supply information to the reader, in the
                  following chapters of this ninth Book.</p>
            </div> 
            <pb type="page" n="234"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.10">
               <head>Chapter 10</head>
               <head>The tenth chapter, concerning the first epistle of Julian to Severus, with a
                  question about the body of Christ<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n234-1"/></head>
               <p><quote>Certain<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n234-2"/> men have appeared here who say that the body of our Lord was
                  corruptible, making use of testimony from the holy Cyril; in the first place from
                  what he wrote to Succensus, saying, <quote>After the Resurrection it was the body which
                  had suffered, though it no longer supported human infirmities but was
                  incorruptible</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n234-3"/> and from this they wish to prove that before the
                  Resurrection it was corruptible, in as much as it was of our nature, but after the
                  Resurrection it received incorruptibility: and in the second place from what he
                  wrote to <persName>Theodosius</persName> the king, saying, <quote>It is a marvel and a miracle that a body
                  naturally subject to corruption rose without corruption.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n234-4"/></p>
               <p><quote>And they quoted such things as these by way of extracts; but I, who set down the
                  whole passage,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n234-5"/> made it my endeavour to show the opinion held by numerous
                  doctors. But they brought me also his sixty-seventh treatise, which was written by
                  him on the subject of the holy Virgin, the Theotokos, and in it are contained the
                  words, <quote>The body of our Lord was in no way subjected to the sin which belongs to
                  corruption, but was susceptible of death and of true burial, and He destroyed them
                  in it.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n234-6"/> And I indeed considered it to be an error in <pb type="page"
                     n="235"/>writing. And so, in order that the dispute may be solved by our being
                  examined by you, I have also sent what I have written,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n235-1"/> and I am convinced
                  that our fathers agree with it. And write to me at once, that I may know what
                  opinions to hold on these matters, because I do not consider it right that we
                  should again say that that which was not corrupted was susceptible of corruption.
                  And pray that our life may be in unison with the grace of God.</quote></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.11">
               <head>Chapter 11</head>
               <head>The eleventh chapter, the response<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n235-2"/> to this epistle of <persName>Julian</persName>, which
                  <persName>Severus</persName> wrote to him, as follow</head>
               <p><quote>When<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n235-3"/> first I received your piety's epistle, I rejoiced in accordance
                  with my custom at your greeting, with which I was well pleased. Since in it you
                  urge me to read the tome composed by you, which you sent with it, written to those
                  who, you say, think and say concerning the body of our Lord and God, <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>
                  our Saviour, that it was corruptible, and you ask me to write a criticism of it
                  and send it to the love of God that is you, in obedience to you I have readily
                  done this, I, a man who change about from one place to another and have no
                  convenient time even for other things that are required. Still, so far as it was
                  possible for it to be written, I have written it, partly by collecting in my
                  memory passages from the teaching of the fathers, partly also from the few volumes
                  of their works which were here. For I know well that there was a similar question
                  in the royal city also, and by means of the proofs from the fathers drawn up by me
                  the controversy and dispute were brought to an end. And so, since there appeared
                  to me to be something unseemly in the things written by you, <pb type="page"
                     n="236"/>since I find that the doctors of the holy Church, who have been from
                  time to time, have instructed me<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n236-1"/> differently on these matters, I have
                  delayed sending what I have written to your piety (as indeed was right), lest some
                  in ignorance should suppose that the controversy conducted in these words was a
                  strife between us, and, although a discussion such as I knew it was would abound
                  in love, yet some might suppose it to be hostility. Accordingly, let me know at
                  once what your pleasure is upon these things, for I am ready to perform whatever
                  is agreeable to your affection, holding as my warrant the saying of the apostle,
                  who said, <quote>Let everything that is done by you<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n236-2"/> be done in
                  love.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n236-3"/></p>
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter" n="9.12">
               <head>Chapter 12</head>
               <head>The twelfth chapter, the second epistle of <persName>Julian</persName> to <persName>Severus</persName>, written in answer
                  to the preceding,as a response<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n236-4"/> to it</head>
               <p><quote>You<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n236-5"/> write that there appeared to you to be something unseemly in the
                  things which I have written; and you ought to have informed me at once in the
                  epistle, and released me from anxiety. But I believe that in all that I have
                  written I have truly confessed the Incarnation derived from us, and I have exerted
                  myself to prove that the fathers were in accord with one another; for I do not
                  consider it possible for us to believe and hold that which is corruptible and that
                  which is incorruptible to be the same. And, while we confess Him who by His
                  stripes healed all men to be passible, yet we also know Him to be raised and
                  exalted above passions; and, if He was mortal, yet we also confess that He
                  trampled on<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n236-6"/> death, and gave life to mortals through His death.
                  Accordingly you have only caused me anxiety by saying that I have written <pb
                     type="page" n="237"/>something that is unseemly, and not telling me what it is,
                  that I may defend it. But condescend to write and tell me what is stated by the
                  fathers, by <persName>Athanasius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n237-1"/> and <persName>Cyril</persName> and others, for I wish to know your mind
                  also. But<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n237-2"/> I believe that I have followed the intention of the fathers,
                  who are not at variance with themselves or at variance with one another, even as
                  <persName>Paul</persName>, who says that salvation is not by works but by faith, is not at variance
                  with <persName>James</persName>, who says that faith without works is dead. They did not say these
                  things in opposition to one another, but in concord.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n237-3"/></p>
               <p><quote>But pray that we may be enlightened by God, and may not through passion yield to
                  our own wills, while at the same time you cause the word in a brief compass to
                  shine upon us.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>The holy <persName>Cyril</persName> writes, <quote>It is not easy for us to say that corruption can ever
                  take hold of the flesh which was united to the Word</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n237-4"/> and five lines
                  lower down, <quote>It is a wonder and a miracle that a body<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n237-5"/> naturally subject
                  to corruption was raised.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n237-6"/> And what is the idea which he wishes to bring
                  out (for he is not at variance with himself in these things), if he was not in
                  these words thinking of the corruption of universal nature? For He bore our
                  infirmities of His own will and not by compulsion of nature; and He took up our
                  sins in His body on the tree, dying for our sin.</quote></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.13">
               <head>Chapter 13</head>
               <head>The thirteenth chapter, the response<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n237-7"/> to this epistle, addressed to the
                  same <persName>Julian</persName> by <persName>Severus</persName></head>
               <p><quote>It<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n237-8"/> seems to me a very strange thing, when I call to <pb type="page"
                     n="238"/>mind the few words which I wrote, that the love of God that is in you
                  says that you were in great anxiety; since I performed your request for no other
                  reason than to free you from anxiety and disturbance. For, if you had sent me a
                  small question and problem, then I might perhaps have used<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n238-1"/> few words in
                  making answer; but, since it is a tome of many lines and a
                  fully-completed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n238-2"/> work that you have sent me to examine, after considering
                  the things contained in it every day according to my ability, I will make my
                  opinion clear to you.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Now in respect of what is fitting I have found much which I will do readily
                  for<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n238-3"/> your piety; and, to show that I am not speaking falsely, listen to
                  what you wrote, as follows: <quote>In order to bring about an understanding of the
                  matter in dispute, I have sent what I have written; but test it to see whether it
                  is in accord with the Holy Scriptures, because I believe that our fathers were in
                  accord with these. Write and tell me what opinion I am to hold.</quote> Since,
                  therefore,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n238-4"/> you have given me matter for much discussion, how is it that
                  in your second epistle you have required me to treat of many matters in a few
                  lines and in a single utterance, as you say, a thing which needs many words and
                  proofs from the fathers, who spoke under the inspiration of God? For the Holy
                  Scripture says, <quote>It is the Lord that teacheth intelligence and
                  knowledge</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n238-5"/> and again in another place, <quote>The Lord giveth wisdom; and from
                  His presence cometh knowledge and understanding. And He giveth salvation to the
                  righteous.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n238-6"/> For, if your piety and we endeavour in this way to prove with
                  respect to these fathers that they are not in opposition to one another, there is
                  nothing to prevent us from examining the matter carefully and knowing that they
                  have never in anyway shown <pb type="page" n="239"/>themselves to be in opposition
                  either to one another or to themselves.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>For<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-1"/> you rightly and justly<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-2"/> say that the doctors are not in
                  opposition to one another, even as <persName>Paul</persName> is not in opposition to <persName>James</persName> when the one
                  says, <quote>By faith is a man justified without works,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-3"/> while the other wrote,
                  <quote>Faith without works is dead</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-4"/> because <persName>Paul</persName> spoke of faith before
                  baptism, which is the perfection of confession out of a pure heart, when it has
                  not previously displayed good works in the world,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-5"/> but such a man is
                  justified by believing and confessing and being baptized; while <persName>James</persName> referred to
                  faith after baptism, when he said that it is dead without works, if a man does not
                  confirm it by right action.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-6"/> For baptism is the earnest of a good
                  conversation; since even our Lord, who was to us an instructor, after He had
                  hallowed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-7"/> the water and been baptized<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-8"/> by <persName>John</persName> and given
                  us<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-9"/> the institution of baptism, went up to the mountain and underwent a
                  struggle with the tempter and destroyed all his power, thereby guiding us, that we
                  might know that after the divine cleansing we ought to display a contest in deed
                  and to struggle according to law with the adversary, therein displaying our
                  virtues.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>But someone will object, and say, <quote>Behold! <persName>Paul</persName> took <persName>Abraham</persName> as a proof that a
                  man is justified by faith without works, saying, <quote>Therefore they that are in the
                  faith are blessed with the believing <persName>Abraham</persName></quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-10"/> and, <quote>To him that hath
                  not worked but hath believed on Him that can justify sinners his faith is reckoned
                  for righteousness</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-11"/> while <persName>James</persName> proved by the case of <persName>Abraham</persName> that a man
                  is not justified <pb type="page" n="240"/>by faith only, but by works confirmed by
                  faith.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n240-1"/> And how are these not contradictory? for the same<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n240-2"/> <persName>Abraham</persName>
                  is an example of those who have not worked but believed, and of those who have
                  shown faith by works.</quote></quote></p>
               <p><quote>I am ready to explain from the Holy Scriptures. For he who examines the periods
                  of <persName>Abraham</persName>'s life [will see]<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n240-3"/> that he is an instance of both, of the faith
                  which before baptism confesses salvation by believing in <persName>Christ</persName>, and of that after
                  baptism which is joined with works, which is a reproduction<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n240-4"/> of the old
                  circumcision of the flesh, which drives away<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n240-5"/> the denial of uncircumcision
                  and brings to us the adoption as sons by God; wherefore Moses also was ordered to
                  say thus to <persName>Farʿoh</persName>; <quote>And say thou unto <persName>Farʿoh</persName>, <quote>Israel is my son, my
                  firstborn.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n240-6"/> Wherefore <persName>Paul</persName> writes to the Colossians and says, <quote>In whom
                  ye were circumcised with a circumcision not made with hands, in the putting off of
                  the flesh of sins and in the circumcision of <persName>Christ</persName>, and ye were buried with Him
                  in baptism.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n240-7"/> Wherefore he said of<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n240-8"/> <persName>Abraham</persName> also that he was
                  justified by faith without works while he was in uncircumcision, before he was
                  circumcised, thus pointing to confession before baptism without works, writing to
                  the Romans, <quote>To <persName>Abraham</persName> his faith was reckoned for righteousness. How? Not through
                  circumcision, but in uncircumcision.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n240-9"/> And he did not speak falsely; for
                  the words of <persName>Moses</persName> are witness, which say of God that He said to <persName>Abraham</persName>, <quote>Look
                  toward heaven and tell the stars, if thou be able to tell them</quote>; and He said, <quote>So
                  shall thy seed be</quote>: <pb type="page" n="241"/>and Abraham believed God, and it was
                  reckoned to him for righteousness.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-1"/></p>
               <p>"But again our master <persName>James</persName> also took the same <persName>Abraham</persName> as an example in the faith <!-- starting quote for paragraph but no ending quote -->
                  which saves<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-2"/> by works after baptism, he being then circumcised and not in
                  uncircumcision. And we may learn from the Scripture; for he writes thus: <quote>Wilt
                  thou know, O man, that faith without works is dead? For our father <persName>Abraham</persName> was
                  justified by works, when he offered <persName>Isaac</persName> his son as a burnt-sacrifice. Thou seest
                  that faith wrought with his works, and by works was made perfect. And the
                  Scripture was fulfilled which saith, <quote><persName>Abraham</persName> believed God, and it was reckoned to
                  him for righteousness: and He was called his friend.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-3"/> It is<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-4"/>
                  easy again for one who reads the writings of <persName>Moses</persName> to learn from the book of
                  Genesis that <persName>Abraham</persName>, after he was circumcised, offered <persName>Isaac</persName> as a
                  burnt-sacrifice<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-5"/> and fulfilled the commandment and was justified by works,
                  giving us an instance of faith after baptism, which is a spiritual circumcision,
                  justifying a man by works; for it is written, <quote><persName>Abraham</persName> was circumcised, and
                  <persName>Ishmael</persName> his son, and those born in his house, and those bought with his money from
                  strange peoples</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-6"/> and then God, trying <persName>Abraham</persName>, said to him, <quote>Take thy
                  son, whom thou lovest, even <persName>Isaac</persName>, and get thee to the high land; and offer him
                  there as a burnt-sacrifice.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-7"/> Accordingly these words of the apostles and
                  those written in the old law do not seem to be in opposition<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-8"/> to one
                  another, but to be one, and to have been spoken by one spirit concerning faith
                  before<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-9"/> baptism, which justifies the man who presents himself upon a
                  short<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-10"/> confession<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-11"/> only without action,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-12"/> baptism <pb
                     type="page" n="242"/>being full salvation if a man depart from the world
                  forthwith, and another faith, which is after baptism, which requires the proof of
                  good works and also raises the man to the measure of perfection and to high
                  place.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n242-1"/> And so also<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n242-2"/> <persName>James</persName> very properly says of it that faith is
                  made perfect by works; since the wise <persName>Paul</persName> also in another place gives similar
                  teaching respecting faith, saying that it is made perfect through works: for the
                  Galatians,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n242-3"/> after they had been baptized and been reckoned sons of God
                  through the Spirit, were perverted to Judaism and were circumcised, since they
                  vainly supposed that by the circumcision of their flesh they gained something in
                  <persName>Christ</persName> beyond the uncircumcised; and he wrote to reprove them, saying, <quote>In <persName>Jesus</persName>
                  Christ neither circumcision nor uncircumcision availeth anything; but faith which
                  is worked out by love.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n242-4"/> From this also, therefore, it is plain that that
                  kind of faith after baptism is of avail and saves with which work is joined and
                  united in love; and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n242-5"/> what work done in love is <persName>Paul</persName> declares and says,
                  <quote>Love is long-suffering and kind; love is not envious and excited and puffed up,
                  nor is it ashamed; and it seeketh not its own, and is not provoked; and it
                  imputeth no evil; and rejoiceth not in iniquity, but rejoiceth in the truth; and
                  it hopeth all things, and endureth all things. Love doth not quickly
                  fail.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n242-6"/> These things are for the direction of action<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n242-7"/> and labour
                  and toil, that many may be profited and be saved, when united to faith. And who
                  will dare to find fault? for respecting this our Lord also said, '<quote>If ye love Me,
                  keep My commandments.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n242-8"/></p>
               <pb type="page" n="243"/> 
               <p><quote>As, therefore, the Holy Scriptures and our fathers have been consistent in the
                  teaching given to us, so upon this question too they are in accord in teaching
                  those who do not read negligently: wherefore, as it is written, <quote>Everything is
                  known<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n243-1"/> to the understanding, and plain<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n243-2"/> to them that find
                  knowledge</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n243-3"/> which knowledge I have endeavoured to send in a discreet
                  manner to your affection, as is the duty of Christians.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n243-4"/></p>
               <p><quote>But, since I have learned from several quarters that you have published the tome
                  containing your work, which was addressed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n243-5"/> to me, not only in the great
                  city of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> but also in various places, in accordance, as I am persuaded,
                  with <persName>Christ</persName>, even God the Lawgiver, I have in love again sent and written to our
                  brother the presbyter <persName>Thomas</persName> not to publish my work, but to keep it to himself,
                  because I hoped that by the counsel of two persons, as by one mouth and soul, my
                  writings and those of your Holiness might be made known. For after this fashion I
                  once and again examined the teaching of the memorable <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n243-6"/> and
                  <persName>Eleusinus</persName> the bishops, and the books which they composed upon abstruse
                  matters<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n243-7"/> concerning the faith; and I never found in their case any
                  declaration of the relations which we had with one another in love during our
                  discussions, when by the help of our Lord we were alike of one mind. For I never
                  produced either book or treatise in order to gain distinction with men, or to win
                  renown beyond the measure of my feebleness, but in the rectitude of the Gospel in
                  accordance with the teaching and legislation of the apostles. However, it is also
                  unseemly that at such a time as this we should abandon the struggle against the
                  heretics and contend and write against one another, lest the saying of the apostle
                  be <pb type="page" n="244"/>fulfilled against us, who says, <quote>If ye bite and devour
                  one another, take heed that ye be not consumed one of another.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n244-1"/> Such
                  contentions it is the duty of those who love our Lord to shun with all their
                  power, and to love one another, that peace may abound and may visit the <placeName>Israel</placeName> of
                  God. Greet the brotherhood that is with you. The one that is with me salutes you
                  in our Lord.</quote></p>
               <p>When <persName>Julian</persName> received this epistle also from this learned <persName>Severus</persName>, he was very
                  indignant, and was moved with anger; and he wrote, saying that his request had
                  been refused by him for a year<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n244-2"/> and a month, and he had not
                  received<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n244-3"/> the respect due to him, and he had been tricked(?).<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n244-4"/> And
                  then <persName>Severus</persName> again wrote a long treatise abounding in proofs from the true doctors
                  of the holy Church, who say that the body of <persName>Christ</persName> which He received from us was
                  susceptible of innocent passions except sin until the Resurrection.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n244-5"/> And
                  for this reason, in order that it may be known, I have set down the above epistles
                  for the discerning.</p>
               <p>There were many books addressed to <persName>Julian</persName> and <persName>Felicissimus</persName> and <persName>Romanus</persName> and others
                  who shared his opinions, and in them there is also much material for profit in
                  study for those that love instruction. And they became known to the sagacious and
                  intelligent of the true party of the faith concerning the Incarnation of our
                  Saviour, and the simple were preserved and enlightened so as not to become
                  Eutychianists, and especially the monks.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="245"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.14">
               <head>Chapter 14</head>
               <head>The fourteenth chapter of the ninth Book, concerning the riot which happened at
                  <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and how <persName>Hypaptius</persName> and <persName>Pompeius</persName> were killed, and large numbers of
                  the people<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n245-1"/> were massacred in the circus</head>
               <p>In the year ten<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n245-2"/> the slaughter wrought by the many Huns who invaded the
                  territory of the Romans, and harried it, and killed many people who were in the
                  country, and burned, as recorded above, was not enough, but in the royal city also
                  many persons perished there in a riot<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n245-3"/> which broke out. For, when <persName>John</persName> of
                  <placeName>Caesarea</placeName> in <placeName>Cappadocia</placeName> was prefect<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n245-4"/> there, by sedulously inventing pretexts
                  against persons by the use of trickery<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n245-5"/> and cunning, there and in various
                  cities, he amassed a large quantity of gold for the royal treasury from all
                  classes, both magnates and craftsmen; and he was listened to with attention in the
                  palace, and was formidable to everyone, since he stood so high in the confidence
                  of the king that he made false accusations against many persons; and he was
                  surrounded by flatterers<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n245-6"/> and informers.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n245-7"/> And there were present
                  in the royal city no small number of people from every quarter who had complaints
                  against him, and favoured<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n245-8"/> and supported one of the factions.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n245-9"/>
                  Wherefore there were constant outcries<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n245-10"/> against him and against the king;
                  and the factions united and were in accord with one another for several days; and
                  the workshops were shut, and they began to plunder everything that came in their
                  way, and to burn. And the king <pb type="page" n="246"/>was alarmed; and at last
                  the palace was shut. And the parties collected in the circus<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n246-1"/> and raised a
                  great riot; and they kept crying out that <persName>Hypatius</persName> should be king; and, if not,
                  they would burn the city. And <persName>Hypatius</persName> was compelled to come out, and <persName>Pompeius</persName>
                  accompanied him. And they took a necklace belonging to one of the soldiers and set
                  it on his head and enthroned him king, and they cried out at him and praised him.
                  And, when this happened, by the advice of certain persons they set fire to the
                  great church of the city, in order that upon receiving the news of the disaster
                  the assembled people might be scattered; for King <persName>Justinian</persName> was in distress and
                  alarm in the palace. And <persName>Mundus</persName>, a general,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n246-2"/> and his troops were present
                  there; and he and the Scholarians and all the troops who were at hand received
                  orders, and they shut the door of the circus, and they massacred and slew all
                  classes of people who were present there; and there were no means of fleeing and
                  escaping from the massacre. And more than 80,000 persons perished there in this
                  riot. And <persName>Hypatius</persName> and <persName>Pompeius</persName> were at last arrested, and came in before the
                  king. And, when he understood the state of the case, he wished to spare the men's
                  lives; but he was not able to do so, for his consort was enraged, and swore by God
                  and by him, and adjured him also to have the men put to death. And they were sent
                  to the seashore and killed and thrown into the sea.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.15">
               <head>Chapter 15</head>
               <head>The fifteenth chapter, concerning the believing bishops who were recalled from
                  exile to the royal city and presented a supplication<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n246-3"/> to the king
                  concerning their faith, which runs as follows</head>
               <p><quote>Various<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n246-4"/> other men crown your believing head, O victorious king, with a
                  crown of praises—men who take <pb type="page" n="247"/>occasion from the case of
                  other persons to write words about your favours towards them; but we, who have
                  been ourselves judged worthy to experience your virtues, render thanks to you with
                  a crown of laudation, which we weave with splendour. And, while in the desert,
                  and, so to speak, at the end of the world, we have been this long time dwelling in
                  quietness, praying to the good and merciful God during such days as those on
                  behalf of your Majesty and on behalf of our sins: and your tranquillity has
                  inclined towards our vileness and in your believing letters summoned us to come to
                  you. And the thing is a wonder to us that you did not receive this our request
                  with scorn,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n247-1"/> but, with the kindness innate in you, sympathised with us, so
                  as to bring us<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n247-2"/> out of affliction, making the pretext that this or that
                  man had interceded for us.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Now we, since it is our duty to obey when commanded, immediately left the desert,
                  and, journeying quietly along the road in peace without our voice being heard,
                  have come before your feet; and we pray God, the bountiful giver, on our behalf to
                  reward your serenity and the God-loving queen with good gifts from on high, and to
                  bestow peace and tranquillity upon you, and to set every rebellious people as a
                  stool beneath your feet.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>However, now that we have come, we present a supplication to your peacefulnesses
                  containing our true faith, not wishing to hold an argument with any man on any
                  matter that is not profitable, as it is written,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n247-3"/> lest we annoy your ears;
                  for it is very hard for a man to convince persons of a contentious disposition,
                  although he make the truth manifest. And so, as we have said,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n247-4"/> we refuse
                  to engage in a dispute with the contentious, who will not receive instructors; for
                  our master<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n247-5"/> <pb type="page" n="248"/>the apostle said, <quote>We have no such
                  custom, neither the Churches of God.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n248-1"/></p>
               <p><quote>Accordingly, victorious king, we do now also declare the freedom of our faith,
                  although in the desert, when we received your edict at the hands of <persName>Theodotus</persName> the
                  duke, we wrote and declared what we think, and your Majesties gave us a message of
                  truth free from affliction in that you were graciously moved and summoned us to
                  your presence. And, since we have been judged worthy of the mercies of God, we do
                  in this supplication inform your orthodoxies that by the grace of God we have from
                  our earliest infancy received the faith of the apostles, and have been brought up
                  in it and with it, and we think and believe even as our three hundred and eighteen
                  God-inspired holy fathers, who drew up the faith of life and salvation, which was
                  confirmed by our one hundred and fifty holy fathers who once met here, and
                  ratified by the pious bishops who assembled at <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> and rejected the impious
                  <persName>Nestorius</persName>. And so in this faith of the apostles we have been baptized and do
                  baptize, and this saving knowledge is grounded in our hearts, and this same
                  doctrine alone we recognise as a rule in the faith, and beyond it we receive no
                  other; because it is perfect in all points, and it does not grow old nor need
                  renovation.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Now we acknowledge a worshipful and holy Trinity of one nature, power, and
                  honour, which is made known in three persons; for we worship the Father and His
                  only Son, God the Word, Who was begotten of Him eternally beyond all times, and is
                  with Him always without variation, and the Holy Spirit,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n248-2"/> which proceeds
                  from the Father, and is of the nature of the Father and of the Son. One of the
                  persons of this holy Trinity, that is, God the Word, we say by the will of the
                  Father in the last days for the salvation of men took flesh of the Holy Spirit and
                  of the holy Virgin the Theotokos <persName>Mary</persName> in a body endowed with a rational and
                  intellectual soul,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n248-3"/> passible after our nature, and became man, <pb
                     type="page" n="249"/>and was not changed from that which He was. And so we
                  confess that, while<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n249-1"/> in the Godhead He was of the nature of the Father, He
                  was also of our nature in the manhood. Accordingly He Who is the perfect Word, the
                  invariable Son of God, became perfect man, and left nothing wanting for us in
                  respect of our salvation, as the foolish <persName>Apollinaris</persName> said, saying that the
                  Humanisation of God the Word was not perfect, and deprives<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n249-2"/> us, according
                  to his opinion, of things that are of prime importance in our salvation. For, if
                  our intellect was not united with Him, as he absurdly says, then we are not saved,
                  and in the matter of salvation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n249-3"/> have fallen short of that which is of the
                  highest consequence for us. But these things are not as he said; for the perfect
                  God for our sake became perfect man without variation, and God the Word did not
                  leave anything wanting in the Humanisation, as we have said, nor yet was it a
                  phantom of Him, as the impious <persName>Mani</persName> supposes, and the erring <persName>Eutyches</persName>.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And, since <persName>Christ</persName> is truth and does not know how to lie and does not deceive,
                  because He is God, therefore God the Word truly became incarnate, in truth again,
                  and not in semblance, with natural and innocent passions, because of His own will
                  He for our sake among the things which He took upon Himself in the passible flesh
                  of our nature of His own will endured also our death, which He made life for us by
                  a Resurrection befitting God, for he first restored incorruption and immortality
                  to human nature.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And, indeed, as God the Word left nothing wanting and was not phantasmal in the
                  Incarnation and Humanisation, so He did not divide it into two persons and two
                  natures according to the doctrine introduced by <persName>Nestorius</persName> the man-worshipper and
                  those who formerly thought like him, and those who in our day so think.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And the faith contained in your confession refutes the doctrine of these men and
                  contends with it, because in your <pb type="page" n="250"/>earnestness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n250-1"/>
                  you said thus: <quote>God appeared, Who became incarnate. He is in all points like the
                  Father except the individuality of His Father. He became a sharer of our nature,
                  and was called Son of Man. Being one and the same, God and man, He showed Himself
                  to us, and was born as a babe for our sake; and, being God, He for men and for the
                  sake of their salvation became man.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n250-2"/></p> <!-- [Last Update] -->
               <p>"If those who dispute with us adhered to these things in truth and were not
                  content to hold them in appearance only, but rather consented to believe as we do
                  and you do and as our holy God-inspired fathers did, they would have abstained
                  from this stirring of strife. For that Christ was joined by composition, and that
                  God the Word is joined by composition with a body endowed with a rational and
                  intellectual soul the all-wise doctors of the Church have plainly stated.
                  Dionysius, who from the Areopagus and from the darkness and error of heathendom
                  attained to the supreme light of the knowledge of God through our master Paul, in
                  the treatise which he composed about the divine names of the Holy Trinity says,
                  'Praising<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n250-3"/> it as kindly, we say, as is right, that it is kindly,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n250-4"/>
                  because it in truth partook perfectly of our attributes in one of its persons,
                  drawing to itself and raising the lowliness of our manhood, out of which the
                  simple Jesus became joined by composition in a manner that cannot be described;
                  and He who was from eternity and beyond all times took upon Him a temporal
                  existence, and He who was raised and exalted above all orders and natures became
                  in the likeness of our nature without variation and confusion.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n250-5"/> And
                  Athanasius again in the treatise upon the faith named the unity of God the Word
                  with soul-possessing flesh a composition, speaking thus: 'What is the relationship
                  to the unbelief of those who <pb type="page" n="251"/>call it an indwelling
                  instead of an Incarnation,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n251-1"/> and instead of a union and composition a human
                  energy?'"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n251-2"/></p>
               <p>"If, therefore, according to our holy fathers, whom your peacefulnesses have
                  followed, God the Word, who was before simple and not composite, became incarnate
                  of the Virgin, the Theotokos Mary, and united soul-possessing and intellectual
                  flesh to Himself personally and made it His own and was joined with it by
                  composition in the dispensation, it is manifest that according to our fathers we
                  ought to confess one<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n251-3"/> nature of God the Word, who took flesh and became
                  perfectly<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n251-4"/> man. Accordingly God the Word, who was before simple, is not
                  recognised to have become composite in a body, if He is again divided after the
                  union by being called two natures. But, just as an ordinary man, who is made up of
                  various natures, soul and body and so forth, is not divided into two natures
                  because a soul has been joined by composition with a body to make up the one
                  nature and person of a man, so also God the Word, who was personally united and
                  joined by composition with soul-possessing flesh, is not divided into or in two
                  natures because of His union and composition with a body. For according to the
                  words of our fathers, whom the fear of God that is in you has followed, God the
                  Word,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n251-5"/> Who was formerly simple, consented for our sake to be united by
                  composition with soul -possessing and intellectual flesh and without change to
                  become man. Accordingly one nature and person of God the Word, Who took flesh, is
                  glorified, and there is one energy of the Word of God which is made known, which
                  is exalted and glorious and fitting for God, and is also lowly and human. How is
                  it that some are not corrected?"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n251-6"/></p>
               <p>And they are urgent and refuse to accept what Leo wrote in the Tome in opposition
                  to these things, he and those of his opinions; and they produced quotations from
                  him, and from <pb type="page" n="252"/>Nestorius and Theodore and Diodorus and
                  Theodoret and the Synod of Chalcedon,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n252-1"/> who speak of two natures after the
                  Incarnation of God the Word, and two persons; and they provided a copious
                  refutation of these with proofs drawn from the fathers who have at various times
                  held opinions contrary to these and taught one nature and person in the Church,
                  saying that God the Word was in truth humanised without change and became perfect
                  man, and the same remained perfect God, besides things which I forbear to record
                  here on account of their length, and because they were everywhere to be found in
                  works against the Diphysites.</p>
               <p>And at the end of their petition<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n252-2"/> they said thus: "And for this reason we
                  do not accept either the Tome or the definition of Chalcedon, O victorious king,
                  because we keep the canon and law of our fathers who assembled at Ephesus and
                  anathematised and deprived Nestorius and excommunicated any who should presume to
                  compose any other definition of faith besides that of Nicsea, which was correctly
                  and believingly laid down by the Holy Spirit. These we reject and anathematise.
                  And this definition and canon those who assembled at Chalcedon deliberately set at
                  naught and transgressed, as they state in the Acts <ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n252-3"/> of that
                  Synod;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n252-4"/> and they are subject to punishment and blame from our holy fathers
                  in that they have introduced a new definition of faith, which is contrary to the
                  truth of the doctrine of those who from time to time have been after a pure manner
                  doctors of the Church, who, we believe, are now also entreating Christ with us,
                  that you may aid the truth of their faith, honouring the contests undergone by
                  their priesthoods, by which the Church has been exalted and glorified. For thus
                  shall peace reign in your reign by the power of the right hand of God Almighty, to
                  whom we pray on your behalf<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n252-5"/> that without toil or struggle in arms He will
                  set your enemies as a stool beneath your feet."</p>
               <p>And, when the letter of defence for the faith, as given <pb type="page" n="253"
                  />above, had been presented to the king and been read, and many words had been
                  spoken during the no small space of one year and more by the believing bishops who
                  had come thither to the royal city by the king's command, as recorded above, with
                  whom was the learned John the archimandrite, the son of Aphthonia, (and he wrote a
                  record of the discussions), the king would not banish the Synod of Chalcedon from
                  the Church, while he summoned by letter the holy Severus the chief priest, who was
                  hiding in various places. And, since he rejected the king's request and refused to
                  come to him, the believing bishops who were in Constantinople returned each one of
                  them to any place he chose to hide himself, according as he judged convenient for
                  him.</p>
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n253-1"/> then after a time, in the year thirteen,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n253-2"/> after many letters
                  from the king, the holy Severus also came to him and was received, and he was in
                  the palace till March of the year fourteen,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n253-3"/> while the Diphysite bishops
                  everywhere were disturbed and annoyed and also alarmed, and especially Ephraim of
                  Antioch, until in their anxiety they stirred up Agapetus, chief priest of Rome,
                  who shared their opinions, and invited and brought him to the royal city.
                  Moreover, how it came about and what happened will be made known in a chapter
                  which I am going to write below.</p>
               <p>The end of the petition contained in the fifteenth [chapter]<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n253-4"/> concerning
                  the monks who assembled at Constantinople.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n253-5"/></p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="254"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.16">
               <head>Chapter 16</head>
               <head>The sixteenth chapter of the ninth Book treasof the defence, which Severus,
                  when refusing to come to the royal city, wrote in an epistleto the king, as
                  follows</head>
               <p>"The<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n254-1"/> eternal Word of the Father, the Son of God, Who had in the end taken
                  flesh and was not changed, and, moreover, became perfectly man by the Holy Spirit
                  and Mary the holy Virgin, the Theotokos, and in everything was truly made like
                  unto us except sin, fulfilling the teaching of salvation in parables,
                  [sowed]<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n254-2"/> the seed from it in His disciples, that they too and all
                  throughout the whole world who by their means received the word, if anything that
                  was good sprang up from it in the way of righteousness and pious deeds, might
                  ascribe this not to themselves but to the power of that which He sowed in the
                  beginning, as by grace, and, when among valleys and boulders<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n254-3"/> and stone
                  rocks in the wilderness, might with loud and strong voices cry out, making
                  utterance. Similarly, therefore, has your serene Mightiness also sown<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n254-4"/> the
                  seed of kindliness that is in my vileness, and has caused this letter to spring
                  forth from me; not as the offspring of presumption, for how was it possible that
                  in answer to the powerful and strong voice of your Majesty, which reached my ears,
                  an utterance should not be emitted by me? For, when those who bitterly despised my
                  vileness thought that they had everywhere shut the doors in my face without mercy,
                  then indeed, as by an unexpected miracle, you by your letter summon me to
                  yourself, me, a man who am, as it were, driven about and banished by enemies. And
                  this same thing is like God, who to them that were pursued<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n254-5"/> by foemen,
                  when they thought themselves <pb type="page" n="255"/>shut in and caught by them,
                  provided a broad way of safety, worthy of His wisdom and His great might; a way
                  which worked a miracle upon Farʿoh, who had let them go after their long time of
                  subjection, and again<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n255-1"/> pursued after them to bring them into subjection to
                  his hard yoke, and with his horsemen surrounded them in the wilderness of the Sea
                  of Rushes and barred the way, thinking in his heart and saying, 'These men are
                  entangled in the land, for the wilderness hath shut them in.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n255-2"/> But the
                  marvellous God to those who thought themselves hemmed in by warriors made a way of
                  grace over the sea dry, that they might cross it on foot; who commanded Moses to
                  raise his staff over the sea and cause it to be divided. And so in close
                  resemblance to these things you also with your Majesty's wand of peace have
                  divided the sea in the wilderness which hemmed me in; and the way which, it was
                  thought, could not be traversed you have again caused to be traversed by me."</p>
               <p>"And it is a great proof of your gentleness that you unhesitatingly indited your
                  letter to me even with oaths, promising me immunity from injury; in this also
                  after the manner of God, because He too, condescending to the weakness of men,
                  oftentimes sent forth His promises with oaths, as Scripture teaches, and Paul made
                  mention of it, saying, 'When God made promise to Abraham, because He had none
                  greater than Himself by whom He could swear. He sware by Himself and said,
                  "Blessing, I will bless thee; and multiplying, I will multiply thee."'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n255-3"/>
                  But I, the vile one, am bold to say that I was in no need of such
                  security,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n255-4"/> since I trust the word that comes out of your mouth only,
                  believing it to be a perfect safeguard to me, even as the wise Koheleth said,
                  'Observe the mouth of the king, and be not anxious in regard to the word of the
                  oaths of God.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n255-5"/> But I have confidence in the test which springs from the
                  deeds which in truth bear witness more than oaths to your peacefulness as well
                  as<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n255-6"/> to your inclination to the mercies which belong to a gentle <pb
                     type="page" n="256"/>soul. For, as soon as you have taken upon yourself the
                  cares of the kingdom, you release from sorrow all classes of men sentenced to
                  exile, chief priests and magnates and common people, having regard to that which
                  is equally esteemed by all men, the light of the sun,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n256-1"/> and rain, and the
                  temperate air which it brings, and the other things which are required for and
                  conduce to the life of men."</p>
               <p>"But I will not, by drinking from the copiousness of this rich stream of your
                  gentleness, cause myself to err, and be rendered proud; but I have determined to
                  declare what is in my mind. For I am afraid lest, if my meanness be openly seen in
                  the royal city, many persons may be alarmed, and, though I am in truth nothing but
                  merely a vile person bound under this heavy yoke of sins, when they hear of this,
                  many persons may be roused to anger and inflamed by this paltry anxiety, as by a
                  little coal of fire, so as to trouble and annoy even your Mightiness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n256-2"/>
                  owing to your affection towards me: and I think that it will not seem to you
                  fitting nor to others profitable. Now this I say, not as though I had any power
                  against your Majesty's Mightiness, for it is written, 'When a righteous king
                  sitteth upon a throne, no evil riseth up against his eyes,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n256-3"/> but because I
                  am persuaded that, as this power<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n256-4"/> belongs to you by grace from on high, so
                  you are clad in understanding and wisdom, and make it your endeavour to
                  do<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n256-5"/> many things, not by this sword, but by sagacity befitting kingship.
                  And this we are taught by the Scripture, which says, 'A wise king winnoweth and
                  scattereth the wicked.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n256-6"/> And, just as it is easy for those who are
                  winnowed by the wind, which blows away the chaff, to hold aloof from
                  sinners,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n256-7"/> so also is it simple for your serenity, my lord, with the
                  all-considering heart and with <pb type="page" n="257"/>the mercy of a
                  gracious<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n257-1"/> father, to separate those that are under subjection to you from
                  those of the contrary part, in order that the Churches in union may be reckoned
                  worthy of friendship. For I know that it was for this reason also that you judged
                  it right that my feebleness too should come to your feet, because, when also you
                  reckoned this same thing<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n257-2"/>worthy of a letter from you to the pious bishops
                  of the East, who are men that pray for the safety and preservation of your
                  Majesty, they also, after they had written to you what they thought, informed my
                  feebleness of this your will, urging us according to the custom of the Church to
                  help you<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n257-3"/> by prayer on your behalf."</p>
               <p>"Now in your great city of Alexandria nothing has been done by me of the things
                  falsely asserted against me. And it is easy for me to show the folly of the
                  informers;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n257-4"/> for they have slandered me, saying that by means of a large
                  sum of gold which I distributed there, I stirred up riotous contention. And this
                  same thing is known to those who hate me greatly that, though involved in the
                  passions of other sins, I do not seek hastily to amass money; and this by no light
                  reasons, but my life<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n257-5"/> is habitually frugal, insomuch that not even the
                  renowned bishopric drew me away from this habit. For, as it is the approved custom
                  for a priest to perform priestly functions,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n257-6"/> in the same way it is the
                  approved custom for him to be poor: wherefore also the law given by Moses ordained
                  that the chosen tribe of Levi should have no inheritance in the land, but for
                  their necessary food the appropriated oblation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n257-7"/> should be sufficient,
                  being associated in this with <pb type="page" n="258"/>the widows and the needy
                  and the orphans, because they are accustomed to poverty, saying, 'And the Levite
                  shall come (because he hath no part or inheritance with thee), and the stranger
                  and the orphan and the widow, which are in thy villages, and they shall eat and
                  rejoice; that the Lord thy God may bless thee in all thy works which thou
                  doest.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n258-1"/> But, since, as it is written, 'Righteous lips are acceptable to
                  the king, and he loveth upright speech,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n258-2"/> your Mightiness may learn from
                  the governors who have been at any time in Alexandria, and now from their
                  officials,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n258-3"/> whom nothing escapes, whether anything of the kind has been
                  done by me even in word, or has been reported to have been done, as they have
                  falsely and maliciously asserted of me. But about these informers<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n258-4"/> I will
                  not say anything, because it does not escape your knowledge what kind of men they
                  are: but I await a judgment with them, after we have been separated from this
                  world of toil, before the tribunal of Christ, where we shall give an account for
                  idle words and for vain thoughts; and especially shall we bishops, to whom much
                  has been intrusted, be judged, although here we delight in bodily things and dally
                  in them."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n258-5"/></p>
               <p>"But, if some apply the term turbulence to what I wrote to Julian, bishop of
                  Halicarnassus, who has been perverted to the heresy of the Manichees and reckons
                  the voluntary saving passions of Christ, the great God, as a phantasy, I do with
                  ten thousand mouths and tongues confess and do not deny what I wrote, even as no
                  one will hastily order me to deny my faith: for this is the opinion of your
                  orthodoxy also, who more than the affairs of the world care to hold fast the
                  things which belong to the Spirit. And I was not impelled to do this by my own
                  will or my own motion, but I was greatly pressed by him to write, because he
                  thought that I agreed with his doctrine. For, when I had gone through what he sent
                  to me (and I am<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n258-6"/> far away from Alexandria), in the things which <pb
                     type="page" n="259"/>he wrote I found that under the name of incorruptibility
                  he covered, as it were with a sheepskin, the blasphemies<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n259-1"/> of Mani, because
                  there are many things which I will forbear to mention. "This foolish man, who
                  confesses the passions with his lips only, hiding his impiety, wrote thus:
                  'Incorruptibility was always attached to the body of our Lord, which was passible
                  of His own will for the sake of others.' And in brotherly love I wrote and asked
                  him: 'What do you mean by "incorruptible," and "suffered of His own will for the
                  sake of others," and "was attached to the body of our Lord,"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n259-2"/> if without
                  any falsehood you confess it to be by nature passible? For, if by the
                  incorruptibility possessed by it you mean holiness without sin, we all confess
                  this with you, that the holy body from the womb which He united to Himself
                  originally by the Holy Spirit of the pure Virgin, the Theotokos, was conceived and
                  born in the flesh without sin and conversed with us men, because "He did no sin,
                  neither was guile found in His mouth,"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n259-3"/> according to the testimony of the
                  Scriptures. But, if you call impassibility and immortality incorruptibility, and
                  say that the body which suffered in the flesh on our behalf was not one that was
                  capable of suffering with voluntary passions and dying in the flesh, you reduce
                  the saving passions on our behalf to a phantasy; for a thing which does not suffer
                  also does not die, and it is a thing incapable of suffering.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n259-4"/> And upon
                  receiving such remarks as these from me he openly refused to call the holy body of
                  Emmanuel passible in respect of voluntary passions; and therefore he did not
                  hesitate to write thus, without shame and openly: 'We do not call Him of our
                  nature in respect of passions, but in respect of essence.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n259-5"/> Therefore, even
                  if He is impassible, and even if He is incorruptible, yet He is of our nature in
                  respect of nature.'"</p>
               <pb type="page" n="260"/>
               <p>And the rest of the erring fatuity of Julian, which is contained at great length
                  in the epistle, I forbear<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n260-1"/> to record now, matters which are to be found in
                  the many books which this holy Severus composed against Julian.</p>
               <p>But at the end of the epistle he wrote, saying thus: "I therefore entreat you and
                  take hold of your feet, again repeating the request that you will leave my
                  meanness alone, and not again bring me forth among men, because I am enfeebled in
                  my body and in my mind; wherefore also I am weak, since true are the words of
                  Scripture which say, 'The mind falleth among blows(?).'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n260-2"/> And there are now
                  many white hairs on my head, which bear witness to me of death, the departure from
                  this weary life, and it appears to me to be a thing very good and beneficial to
                  sit hidden in a corner and bear in my mind the separation of soul from body,
                  awaiting my grave;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n260-3"/> for 'the earth is the home of everyone that
                  dieth,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n260-4"/> as Job said; because in the case of other animals who live on the
                  earth their hair, does not change, but in the case of this rational animal, man,
                  because he was destined to come to judgment and have his deeds examined in the
                  future world, as soon as he reaches old age, the hair of his head turns white,
                  such appearance making announcement to him and inciting him, as far as those who
                  have delayed are concerned, to prepare his deeds for his departure; and the
                  Scripture also bears testimony to him, saying, 'Lift up thine eyes and look on the
                  fields, for they are white and prepared for harvest';<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n260-5"/> for the separation
                  of the soul from the body is in truth a harvest, and, as with a sickle, He cutteth
                  it away from it, and it is bereft. So I beg that your Mightiness will grant me
                  this simple request,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n260-6"/> that I may dwell hidden where I am, because the <pb
                     type="page" n="261"/>rest of my days in the world I am determined to live in
                  secret, as in a corner; for such is the life of a monk.</p>
               <p>"May Christ, who is God over all, give you dominion over your enemies, with
                  perfect peace and concord among the Churches, that you may be crowned with this
                  also. And, if I am committing any fault or presumption in this my letter of
                  petition, I entreat you to forgive me, as on other points; for it is very becoming
                  in a Christ-loving king to overcome evil with good, as the apostle said,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-1"/>
                  a duty which you display in deed, and are therefore rightly called
                  victorious."</p>
               <p>The signature of Severus to the epistle—</p>
               <p>"May the only Trinity, for that is our God, preserve<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-2"/> your orthodoxy many
                  years, keeping the dominion of the commonwealth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-3"/> of the Romans in peace,
                  and may He bring every nation of Romans and barbarians into subjection to you, and
                  grant to the holy Churches<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-4"/> by your means perfect concord in sound faith;
                  and may He reckon you worthy to receive a crown in the kingdom of heaven."</p>
               <p>Now after this epistle the holy Severus remained till the year thirteen,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-5"/>
                  and then came to the royal city, because he was pressed by letters from the
                  king.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.17">
               <head>Chapter 17</head>
               <head>The seventeenth chapter, concerning Africa, which was conquered by Belisarius
                  the general<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-6"/></head>
               <p>When in the summer of the year eleven<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-7"/> Rufinus and Hermogenes, the master
                  of the offices, had by the help of our Lord made peace between the Romans and the
                  Persians on the terms contained in the written treaty, and the Roman
                  generals<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-6"/> and army in the East had come to the royal city, they received
                  blame from the king and incurred his displeasure, <pb type="page" n="262"/>because
                  they had not acted worthily of the high honour and rank which he had bestowed on
                  them by showing themselves brave and astute<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-1"/> in the struggle against the
                  Persians, and especially Belisarius, because of the loss of the army under his
                  orders, which had been defeated in battle at Thannuris and on the Euphrates; and
                  he made his defence to the king on the ground of the impatience of the army, and
                  the lack of discipline<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-2"/> among the men under him.</p>
               <p>Now there were in Constantinople certain magnates from Africa, who, owing to a
                  quarrel which they had with the prince of the land, had left their country and
                  taken refuge with the king, and they gave him information about the country and
                  incited him, saying that it was very extensive and very peaceful, and that it had
                  no thought<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-3"/> of a war with the Romans, but was engaged in a struggle with
                  the Moors, a people who are settled in the desert and live by robbery and
                  devastation like the Saracens. And they pointed out to the king that this country
                  had been torn and snatched from the Roman Empire since the days of Zirzeric, who
                  took Rome, and also carried off valuable objects of gold and silver and other
                  precious substances, and withdrew to Carthage in Africa, a distinguished<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-4"/>
                  city, which he took and occupied; and he settled there, and stored and placed the
                  treasures in it.</p>
               <p>And so the king made ready an army under Belisarius and Martin and Archelaus the
                  prefect,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-5"/> and many ships carrying<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-6"/> arms and
                  accoutrements(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-7"/> for the army; and they sailed over the sea; and, because
                  God willed this expedition and assisted it, they arrived in a few days and
                  suddenly appeared before the royal city of Carthage. And the prince of the land
                  was not there,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-8"/> <pb type="page" n="263"/>but was engaged in war with the
                  Moors in the desert; but a small force, which was in the city, which came out and
                  met the Romans, was defeated in battle and was vanquished and retreated. And the
                  city was surrendered, and the Romans entered and occupied it. And they collected
                  spoil; and the prince's treasure was kept for the king of the Romans.</p>
               <p>Now the Romans also occupied a few of the cities of the country, because they were
                  betrayed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n263-1"/> to them by certain men who were with them, who betrayed the
                  country and knew it well; and it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n263-2"/> is a spacious land, extending over about
                  fifty days' journey, and contains more than one hundred and thirty cities, and is
                  rich and fertile. But the king and the chief priests of the land and the magnates
                  of the people were Arimenites.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n263-3"/></p>
               <p>Now, when the prince heard it and came with an army, it was found to be small and
                  contemptible before the Romans; and, when he understood that his kinsmen had been
                  taken, and his magnates had surrendered, and his treasure had been carried away,
                  he was weakened, and on condition that his life should be spared he surrendered.
                  And he was taken away in company with Belisarius in the year twelve,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n263-4"/> and
                  was publicly presented to the king in the circus<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n263-5"/> before the
                  people,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n263-6"/> with the treasure<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n263-7"/> and his kinsmen and his magnates. And
                  an ambassador of Khosru, king of the Persians, was there and was present and saw
                  these things. And from that time Africa has been subject to the Romans. And
                  gradually the other cities in the region of Africa were reduced: only the Moors
                  continue their accustomed hostilities there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.18">
               <head>Chapter 18</head>
               <head>The eighteenth chapter of the ninth Book, concerning Rome, which was taken by
                  Belisarius</head>
               <p>Alimeric<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n264-1"/> the tyrant held possession of Rome by rebellion in the days of
                  Zeno and Anastasius; and he was a warlike man and an able, and he added great
                  strength to the country of Italy, and he rebuilt Rome and kept the barbarians out
                  of it. And he had died, and his successors one after another held and governed the
                  country of the Romans in rebellion against the kingdom of Constantinople.</p>
               <p>Now a certain Dominic,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n264-2"/> one of the chief men of the country, had a quarrel
                  with the tyrant, and took refuge with King Justinian, and gave him information
                  about the country. And he was an old man, well read in the Scriptures,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n264-3"/> a
                  Diphysite; and he often engaged in disputation, and I know him. Now the king,
                  having conquered Africa in the manner described above, was eager to conquer Rome
                  also. And, observing that Belisarius had been successful in the war in Africa
                  without doing any injury to the population of the country or diminishing it by
                  bloodshed, but had been content with the necessary demands of tribute, taxes, and
                  subjection, he made ready an army for him and sent him to Rome. And John the chief
                  priest there had died during those days, and Agapetus had succeeded him.</p>
               <p>And, when the army had reached a place called Naples, a celebrated city, not far
                  from Rome, and had taken it, the Senate<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n264-4"/> in Rome and their
                  council,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n264-5"/> together with their chief,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n264-6"/> were disturbed and afraid,
                  because they had already heard how Carthage and the tyrant of that country of
                  Africa had been conquered; and, observing these things, they anticipated <pb
                     type="page" n="265"/>matters by sending a petition, asking for peace, and
                  promising to surrender the city; and later they also sent hostages. And afterwards
                  Belisarius arrived there with the army and was received in the city with the
                  praises of its inhabitants, and he occupied it and did no injury in it. And he was
                  there for a time, while occupying the other cities also and bringing them into
                  subjection to the king, without doing any hurt by slaying or destroying the
                  population. And the king gained renown by these things and rejoiced in the year
                  fourteen.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n265-1"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.19">
               <head>Chapter 19</head>
               <head>The nineteenth chapter, concerning Severus, whoagain went up to Constantinople
                  and appeared before the king</head>
               <p>Now<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n265-2"/> the well-tried Severus, after receiving pressing summonses from the
                  king, at last came to Constantinople in the year fourteen,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n265-3"/> and was
                  received in a friendly manner in the palace by the king, who was disposed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n265-4"/>
                  and incited thereto by Theodora the queen, who was devoted to Severus, and he was
                  honourable and venerable in her eyes. And, Epiphanius, the chief priest of the
                  city, having died, Anthimus had succeeded him; and he was an ascetic man and a
                  practiser of poverty, and a friend of the needy and a believer. He was bishop of
                  Trebizond, and, happening for some reason to be present there, and being a man of
                  virtuous character and known to the king and the magnates for his chastity, he was
                  appointed patriarch; and he would not receive the Synod of Chalcedon into the
                  faith.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="266"/>
               <p>And in Alexandria, after Gaian had been driven out, who was a Julianist, and was
                  there for three months after the death of Timothy, Theodosius became bishop, a man
                  of conspicuous faith and learned and kind and gentle; and he was an acquaintance
                  and a friend of the holy Severus.</p>
               <p>When these three chief priests were joined together in love, and in faith<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n266-1"/>
                  were not divided from one another, Ephraim<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n266-2"/> of Antioch was alarmed and
                  greatly disturbed, and yet more so because<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n266-3"/> Peter of Jerusalem was not of
                  his own inclination a lover of discord<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n266-4"/> or a heretic, although through
                  weakness and lack of energy and vigour he conducted himself according to the
                  times.</p>
               <p>Now<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n266-5"/> it happened that in those days Sergius,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n266-6"/> an archiatros of
                  Rhesaina, went up to Antioch to make a complaint against Asylus,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n266-7"/> the
                  bishop of that city, telling Ephraim the patriarch<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n266-8"/> that he had been
                  injured by him. And this man was a man of eloquence and practised in the reading
                  of many books of the Greeks and in the teaching of Origen, while for some time he
                  had been reading commentaries on the Scriptures by other doctors in Alexandria
                  (and he was skilled in the Syriac tongue, reading and speaking) and books<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n266-9"/>
                  of medicine. And of his own inclination he was a believer, to which evidence is
                  also borne by the prologue and the very apt translation of Dionysius which he
                  made<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n266-10"/> and the treatise composed by him on the faith in the days of the
                  illustrious Peter, the believing bishop. However, as regards his character, this
                  Sergius was very <pb type="page" n="267"/>wanton in the lust of women, and he was
                  incontinent and not chaste, while he was greedy in respect of the love of
                  money.</p>
               <p>Of this man Ephraim made trial, and, finding him to be a man of experience,
                  promised to do for him anything that he asked, if he would go as his emissary to
                  Rome with an epistle to Agapetus, the chief priest there, and return. And he
                  accepted.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n267-1"/> And he was furnished with presents by Ephraim, and received a
                  letter for the man, while he was accompanied by a lad named Eustace, an architect,
                  from Amida,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n267-2"/> who spreads about a strange story about Sergius; but, lest it
                  should do harm to the reader, I do not record it.</p>
               <p>These men also accordingly came to Rome to Agapetus, and they delivered the
                  epistle and were received; and the man was pleased with their epistle, in which he
                  found agreement with his opinions. And he came with them to Constantinople in the
                  month of March in the year fourteen;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n267-3"/> and Severus was there, and Anthimus
                  was chief priest. And the whole city was disturbed at the arrival of
                  Agapetus;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n267-4"/> and the earth with all that is upon it quaked; and the sun
                  began to be darkened by day and the moon by night, while ocean was tumultuous with
                  spray(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n267-5"/> from the 24th of March in this year till the 24th of June in the
                  following year fifteen.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n267-6"/> And Agapetus, when he appeared before the king,
                  had a splendid reception from him, because he spoke the same language<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n267-7"/> and
                  was chief priest of the country of Italy, which had been <pb type="page" n="268"
                  />conquered and brought into subjection to him. And he was instructed in the
                  outward words of Scripture but did not understand its meaning; and he held an
                  ignoble opinion upon the Incarnation of Jesus, our Lord Christ, God the Word, and
                  he would not consent to call the Virgin Mary the Theotokos, and divided the unity
                  into two natures, since he held the priority of the conception of the babe, like
                  those of the school of Diodorus and Nestorius. And he abstained from communion
                  with Anthimus and Severus, and they yet more from communion with him; and one of
                  them he called an adulterer and the other a Eutychianist: and he perverted the
                  love of the king towards them and made him hostile to them; and he drove them from
                  the city.</p>
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n268-1"/> Anthimus and Severus and Theodosius of Alexandria made union with one
                  another<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n268-2"/> in epistles, which we have set down below; and Anthimus and
                  Severus left the city to live each of them in hiding wherever was convenient for
                  him.</p>
               <p>Now Menas became bishop<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n268-3"/> in the royal city after Anthimus. And Sergius the
                  archiatros died suddenly there, and Agapetus died after him in those days by a
                  miracle, his tongue being eaten away and rending him in his lifetime;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n268-4"/> and
                  Silverius became bishop in Rome after him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.20">
               <head>Chapter 20</head>
               <head>The twentieth chapter, the epistle of Severus to the order of priests and monks
                  in the east, treating of his expulsion from the royal city</head>
               <p>"To<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n268-5"/> the God-loving presbyters and deacons and archimandrites<pb
                     type="page" n="269"/>and priors and all the holy order of monks in the East
                  Severus greeting in our Lord."</p>
               <p>"That I have passed outside the city which is ruler among cities and beyond the
                  pursuit of men, some of you, O holy ones, being present, have seen with their own
                  eyes, I who have reckoned it right to indite this short letter on my part and to
                  stir you up to the expression(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n269-1"/> of thanksgiving for what I even reckon
                  as my glory(?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n269-2"/> and to state clearly that the actions of the divine
                  providence towards us<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n269-3"/> are in truth beneficial to us for the preservation
                  of the orthodox faith and the formation of a new will, with which, as one may say,
                  it is right to clothe oneself after the fashion<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n269-4"/> of a new garment, and for
                  shunning every heretical opinion and contention. For Jacob also the patriarch, the
                  great in endurance of labours and in trust in God, when he fled from intercourse
                  with the barbarians in Shʾkhem and from the dangers that surrounded him there,
                  urged those that dwelt with him to the same course to which I have urged you, as
                  he says in Scripture: 'And Jacob said to his household and to all them that were
                  with him. Put away from among you the strange gods, and be clean, and change your
                  garments: and let us arise and go up to Beth El and build there an altar unto God,
                  who answered me in the day of distress and delivered me in the way which I
                  went.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n269-5"/> For he has in truth delivered me from all the expectation of the
                  adversaries, who hate me without a cause, and mocked at me and wagged their heads
                  and said, as in Job, 'His foot hath fallen into a gin, and he hath been caught in
                  a net. Let gins come upon him, and they shall prevail against him, as
                  thirsting<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n269-6"/> for him. His noose is hid in the <pb type="page" n="270"
                  />ground, and the net is over his paths.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n270-1"/> But, as for the wickedness of
                  these men, it is not sated with blood; the Christ-worshipping queen was a
                  sufficient protection for me, and God, who through your prayers directed her to
                  that which is good in His sight, even as He cries in Isaiah the prophet to those
                  that trust in Him, 'Fear not, because I have delivered thee. I have called thee by
                  thy name, because thou art Mine. If thou pass through water, I am with thee, and
                  rivers shall not overflow thee ; and in fire thou shalt not be burned, and flame
                  shall not scorch thee. Because I am the Lord thy God, the Holy One of Israel, that
                  delivereth thee.'"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n270-2"/></p>
               <p>"And He that said these things has not only given me a marvellous deliverance, but
                  has further also added an addition to the portion of the believers, to say truth,
                  to the portion of the Lord and to the possession of His inheritance, Israel, that
                  it may not be as those whom the Scripture blames, saying, 'Ye shall sow your seed
                  in vain.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n270-3"/> For the pious Anthimus, archbishop of the royal city, who
                  received the chief chair, even when he was in possession of it, would not retain
                  it, but in upright fashion and with true judgment and knowledge hated the impiety
                  of these men, and accepted the communion of us and of Pope Theodosius of
                  Alexandria and of all the pastors who belong to our confession. Accordingly they
                  vainly lead men astray who say that they do not receive the Synod of Chalcedon in
                  respect of the definition of faith, but in respect of the rejection of Eutyches
                  and Nestorius, clokes which Flavian also used but did not succeed in leading your
                  zeal astray, and you were not overreached by Satan, and are able to say like Paul,
                  'His devices do not escape us.'"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n270-4"/></p>
               <p>And so on with the rest of the epistle.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="271"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.21">
               <head>Chapter 21</head>
               <head>The twenty-first chapter, the epistle of Anthimus to Severus of Antioch</head>
               <p>"To<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n271-1"/> our pious and holy brother and fellow-minister, the patriarch, my
                  lord Severus, Anthimus greeting in our Lord.</p>
               <p>"Bearing in my mind the utterance of the Lord which says, 'To whomsoever much has
                  been committed, from him shall much be required,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n271-2"/> and the saying<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n271-3"/>
                  of the Psalmist, 'Who shall ascend into the hill of the Lord? and who shall stand
                  in His holy place?'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n271-4"/> and the apostle, who ordains of what sort a man must
                  be who is set apart for God, I have been in no small fear. For, if those great
                  patriarchs called themselves, one 'dust and ashes'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n271-5"/> and another 'a worm
                  and no man,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n271-6"/> what shall I say, the small and contemptible, who have
                  attained to the height of this ministry without being worthy of it? For the
                  disturbance of the holy Churches also agitates my soul greatly; for certain men,
                  being held fast in sins and, as if displaying an appearance of avoiding variation
                  and confusion, which does not exist, wantonly<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n271-7"/> divide God the Word, who is
                  one and indivisible, and became incarnate without variation. And for this reason I
                  am in great sorrow, as it is said in the Psalmist, 'Sorrow hath taken hold upon me
                  because of the sinners that have forsaken Thy law.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n271-8"/> But trust in God
                  gives me joy, and I believe that He will surely perform His promises and will give
                  us all that we mean creatures need, not because we are His friends but because of
                  importunity, and He will make requisition for all His elect; who has also for a
                  long time preserved your Holiness from sins <pb type="page" n="272"/>through your
                  apostolic<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n272-1"/> contests and labours and your spiritual teachings, which by
                  grace have been vouchsafed unto you, as a stone that cannot be moved, as well as
                  us, His holy Churches, to be an invariable foundation of the faith. It is
                  therefore the same God who assigns exaltation to the lowly and greatness to the
                  small and strength to the weak, as the divine apostle says, 'By grace are we all
                  justified.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n272-2"/> And these things, being by divine power made strong in
                  weakness, have by an ineffable judgment brought our weakness also to be ruler in
                  the holy Church in this royal city. Acknowledging therefore His grace, we beg you,
                  pious one, to entreat Christ our God to assist our worthlessness; and, because
                  different men<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n272-3"/> have different marks, the mark of priests is also the
                  preaching of the gospel, for, 'Speak,' He says, 'priests, and, when you go up upon
                  the high mountains, make proclamation.'"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n272-4"/></p>
               <p>"In this first spiritual and love-abounding<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n272-5"/> greeting I communicate with
                  you, O holy one; for, while rejoicing in union and also in conjunction with you
                  and in spiritual ties in accordance with the laws of the Church, I declare that I
                  cleave to the one only definition of faith, that which was laid down by the three
                  hundred and eighteen holy fathers who assembled at Nicaea under the direction of
                  the Holy Spirit, and to this I pray that I may cleave unto the end; which
                  definition was ratified<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n272-6"/> by the Synod of one hundred and fifty holy
                  fathers which assembled in this royal city against the impious fighters against
                  the Spirit; and not only so, but also by the holy Synod which assembled at Ephesus
                  against the impious Nestorius, the leaders of which were the archbishops,
                  memorable for piety and love of God, Celestine of the Romans and Cyril of
                  Alexandria, who in his twelve chapters overthrew Nestorius the man-worshipper. To
                  these chapters I assent together with all his writings and embrace <pb type="page"
                     n="273"/>them as a holy law, while together with these holy teachings of Cyril
                  I receive also the formula of Zeno uniting the Churches, which aims at the
                  consummation of religion for the annulling of the Synod of Chalcedon and the
                  impious Tome of Leo. I confess that God the Word, who was begotten before the ages
                  of God the Father, the only Son, connatural and coeternal with the Father, through
                  whom all things were made and through whom all things were established, the Light
                  of Light, the invariable image and invisible will of the Father, in the last days
                  became incarnate and became perfectly man of the Holy Spirit and of the holy
                  Theotokos and ever-virgin Mary, and united to Himself personally flesh of our
                  nature, having a rational and intellectual soul, and without variation and
                  confusion and sin took our resemblance upon Him. For He remained immutable as God,
                  and even in assuming our attributes He did not at the same time also diminish His
                  own divine properties; and that which was derived from us He made His own by
                  dispensation by a junction<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n273-1"/> consisting in a natural union. For He who was
                  begotten without time and without a body of God the Father, the same submitted to
                  a second<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n273-2"/> birth in a body; and, after He had in an ineffable manner become
                  incarnate of a virgin mother, she that bore Him also continued a virgin even after
                  the birth. Wherefore also we truly confess her to be the Theotokos, and that He
                  who was born of her in the flesh is perfect God and perfect man, the same out of
                  two natures one Son, one Lord, one Christ, and one nature of the incarnate Word;
                  and He became perfectly man, while each one of the natures remained without
                  confusion in its sphere of manifestation, the natures which combined to form an
                  indivisible unity. So also He is very rightly one of the holy and connatural
                  Trinity, before the Incarnation and after the Incarnation, inasmuch as He did not
                  add a number to the Trinity, the number of a quaternity; and He is impassible in
                  that He is of the nature of the <pb type="page" n="274"/>Father, but passible in
                  the flesh in that He is of our nature. For God the Word did not suffer in His own
                  nature, but in flesh<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n274-1"/> of our nature; and He who personally united this to
                  Himself suffers in our likeness. And Gregory the Theologian defined the matter and
                  called Him impassible in the Godhead, passible in the assumption of
                  flesh.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n274-2"/> And He is one and the same in the miracles and also in the
                  passions; and by dispensation He made our passions His own, voluntary and innocent
                  ones, in flesh which was passible and mortal and of our nature, intellectually,
                  and rationally possessed of a soul. And this all the time of the dispensation He
                  allowed to be passible and mortal for the purpose mentioned above with respect to
                  His Humanisation, I mean that He suffered not in semblance but in reality. For in
                  the flesh that was capable of suffering He endured voluntary and natural and
                  innocent passions and the death by the Cross; and by a miracle befitting God, that
                  of the Resurrection, He made and rendered it impassible and immortal and in every
                  way therefore incorruptible, since it came from the union and existence<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n274-3"/>
                  in the womb, which<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n274-4"/> was holy and without sin. While recognising,
                  therefore, the distinction between the elements which have combined<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n274-5"/> to
                  form the unity of nature, I mean the divine and the human nature, we do not
                  separate them from one another; also we do not cut the One and ineffable into or
                  in two natures, nor yet do we confound Him by rejecting the distinction between
                  the Godhead and the manhood, but we confess Him to be one out of two,
                  Emmanuel."</p>
               <p>"And, thus believing and taking my stand upon this belief, as upon a rock, I also
                  anathematise the deviations from the truth which have been made by both sides, and
                  the impious and erring men who went before them as their <pb type="page" n="275"
                  />leaders<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n275-1"/> (I refer to Valentine and Marcion and Arius and Macedonius and
                  Eunomius and Apollinaris and Eutyches), and those also who owing to the union with
                  the Word have vainly and impiously confessed the flesh which was derived from us
                  and was personally united to God the Word to be impassible and immortal, and have
                  introduced a semblance and a phantasy as belonging to the great mystery of the
                  immutable and veritable Humanisation of the Lord; and I anathematise also Paul of
                  Samosata and Photinus and Diodorus and Theodore and Nestorius, and also Theodoret
                  and Andrew and Hibo and Eutherius and Alexander of Hierapolis and Irenæus the
                  twice-married and Cyrus and John[#n275-2 and Bar Tsaumo the Persian and the Synod
                  of Chalcedon and the Tome of Leo and those who say that He is made known and
                  exists in two natures, i.e. our Lord Jesus Christ after the ineffable union, and
                  do not confess that there is one aspect,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n275-3"/> one person and nature of God the
                  Word, who became incarnate and became man. On the basis of these apostolic and
                  divine and blameless doctrines, holy brother ours, I give you the right hand of
                  communion, a communion which I will hold fast till my last breath, while I will
                  not consent to hold communion with any man who thinks differently from this,
                  because Basil says, 'He who<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n275-4"/> communicates without discrimination with the
                  foolish<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n275-5"/> is separated from the freedom<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n275-6"/> of Christ.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n275-7"/> For I
                  know that you also, pious one, hold these things<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n275-8"/> fast, and have<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n275-9"/>
                  for a long time laboured. For who is there who in our times has undergone such a
                  contest, removing from place to place, that his faith may not be shaken? And in
                  you I see the doctors of the Church, because you have duly set the lamp <pb
                     type="page" n="276"/>visibly on a stand, shining, as you do, in deed and word.
                  It will be worthy therefore of your piety in consideration of these things to
                  gladden us by instruction in return for our letter." And the rest, consisting of
                  the greeting of the epistle."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n276-1"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.22">
               <head>Chapter 22</head>
               <head>The twenty-second chapter, the epistle of Severus to Anthimus</head>
               <p>"To<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n276-2"/> our all-pious and all-holy brother and fellow-minister, the patriarch
                  Anthimus, Severus greeting in our Lord Jesus Christ our God."</p>
               <p>"For the letter<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n276-3"/> of your chastity Paul the apostle shall give me a
                  precedent for crying aloud in very opportune time, 'Thanks be unto God for His
                  ineffable gift':<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n276-4"/> for immediately upon your accession to the see of the
                  patriarchal throne of the Church in the royal city you determined in the
                  exaltation of the primatial see for the sake of the right religion to despise that
                  which to others is an occasion for betraying their faith. For in those who wish to
                  follow the divine commandments and, as it is written, to go after the Lord, the
                  wisdom of the Most High places fitting thoughts, in deacons and presbyters and
                  patriarchs according to the order of their priesthood; insomuch that the patriarch
                  Abraham, after he had settled in many and divers countries, came to a certain
                  country and drank copiously from a well that sprang from it, which was named the
                  Well of Oaths, because<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n276-5"/> he made oaths and treaties with the barbarians who
                  lived near the country, and he planted fair and fruitful plantations; and, lest
                  his thoughts should be dissipated in them, he called there upon the name of the
                  Lord, the everlasting God, and, as he said to Him, 'Thy thoughts shall not go
                  after the beauty of things that are seen and forget God in the pleasant delight of
                  the sight, <pb type="page" n="277"/>for He alone is from everlasting, and hath
                  made the things that are seen bright to the eyes and pleasant to the taste': and
                  Scripture goes on to relate thus: 'Abraham planted a piece of land by the Well of
                  Oaths and called there on the name of the Lord, the everlasting God'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n277-1"/> (and
                  some have explained it to be wood-land and some plantation-land). In the same way,
                  therefore, your piety after having settled in other countries has come to the head
                  of the oaths,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n277-2"/> as to a piece of land fair in produce, I mean the see of
                  the royal city, which is rich in the pomp<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n277-3"/> of the world, and drinks from
                  the plentiful abundance of the stream. And, when you perceived that certain men
                  wish to be perverted to a reprobate mind, differing<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n277-4"/> from the pure
                  unadulterated coinage, well tried in the orthodox faith, you did not allow the
                  eyes of your mind to go astray through the beauty of the world and the splendour
                  of its vanities, which pass away; but, after the pattern of the patriarch Abraham,
                  you called there upon the name of the Lord, the everlasting God,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n277-5"/>whose
                  merciful Word became incarnate<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n277-6"/> and became man, that is, in order that the
                  second Adam might in truth die the death that had prevailed over us<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n277-7"/> and
                  overthrow its eternal dominion, a death which it was not possible for impassible
                  and immortal flesh to endure, because that which is impassible and immortal is not
                  capable of suffering and dying. For, if He did not die our death for our sins and
                  destroy this <pb type="page" n="278"/>death in flesh resembling our
                  passions<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n278-1"/> when He rose from the dead, we are strangers and alien to the
                  benefit of the Resurrection. For 'Christ died for our sins,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n278-2"/> cries Paul;
                  and again, 'Since by man came death, by man came also the resurrection of the
                  dead. For, as in Adam all die, so in Christ shall all live';<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n278-3"/> and again,
                  'Since the children partook of flesh and blood,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n278-4"/> He also in like manner
                  partook of the same, that through death He might bring to naught him that had the
                  power of death, that is, Satan, and might deliver them who through fear of death
                  were all their lifetime under subjection to bondage. For He received not of
                  angels, but of the seed of Abraham did He receive. Wherefore it was right that in
                  all things He should be made like unto His brethren.'[#278-5]Now the seed of
                  Abraham was the passible body of our race, which God the Word, the Ruler of All,
                  united to Himself personally from the Holy Virgin, in order that with Him He might
                  raise our race, which had fallen under the power of death, inasmuch as He was the
                  firstfruits of our race. So also, since He is one nature and person, it is
                  manifest that the incarnate Word of God of His own will endured the assay and
                  assault of human<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n278-6"/> and natural and innocent passions. And the signs, even
                  the human ones. He utters in a divine fashion(?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n278-7"/> and performs some of
                  them in a manner befitting God and some in human fashion. And we do not on account
                  of the difference of the energies and the utterances and the miracles<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n278-8"/> and
                  the passions fall into the division of the two natures after the ineffable union
                  and divide these things, the utterances and tokens and energies,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n278-9"/>
                  forasmuch as we know that it is the same who wrought the miracles and who suffered
                  and spoke in a divine manner and after the dispensation."</p>
               <pb type="page" n="279"/>
               <p>"These, to speak briefly, are the foundations on which the faith and confession of
                  Christ rest, and 'to them nothing can be added, and from them nothing can be taken
                  away.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n279-1"/> I<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n279-2"/> use opportunely in connexion with these things the holy
                  words of Koheleth, and with application to those who have swerved from the king's
                  highway and have gone in a crooked way and rejoice in evil perversity,
                  but,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n279-3"/> as the Scripture said, 'in the Spirit which speaks
                  parables,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n279-4"/> according to the law which was before delivered unto the
                  Church by the apostles."</p>
               <p>And again a little lower down in the epistle he says,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n279-5"/> "On these terms I
                  undertake to participate in communion and also in inseparable conjunction with
                  your piety and with those only who hold and also preach these things with you, and
                  those who hold or say anything different I reject as strangers and aliens to our
                  communion; and I avoid the foolishness that is in these men, as also your
                  messenger said, as a thing that makes us alien to the boldness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n279-6"/> of Christ
                  and supplies many with an occasion to sin. But, as one of those men of wisdom in
                  divinity also says, 'By reason of foolishness many have sinned.'"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n279-7"/> For, if
                  so be that we stand upon this watch-tower and place of observation and proclaim
                  this to those who are under our power, we shall hear from them combs of honey,
                  even good words, and the sweetness of them is healing to the soul.</p>
               <p>"Since therefore you have chosen for yourself to contend in a good struggle and
                  have confessed a good confession, cry out like the prophet Habakkuk, 'I will stand
                  upon my watch <pb type="page" n="280"/>and walk upon a rock,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-1"/> and despise
                  them that strive below. And, if so be they place you under curses and anathemas,
                  say to God with David with great fitness, 'They shall curse,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-2"/> and Thou
                  shalt be blessed: let them that rise up against me be ashamed, but Thy
                  bond-servant shall rejoice.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-3"/> For also those who profess a sound faith
                  according to the utterance of the apostle 'are come unto Mount Tsiyon,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-4"/>
                  and unto the city of the living<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-5"/> God, unto Jerusalem in heaven, and to
                  innumerable companies of angels, and to the Church of the firstborn, which are
                  written in heaven.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-6"/> Now, how can a man, shooting from the earth, hit
                  those that are in the Church that is in heaven and mingle with it? For in vain
                  will he toil and without profit will he stretch his bow, even if he dare to shoot
                  upwards; for upon himself will the arrows that are shot come down: for we listen
                  also to one of the wise men, who says thus: 'He that casteth a stone upwards
                  casteth against his own pate';<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-7"/> only if so be we continue unto the end,
                  armed in the breastplate of the right faith and girt about in every place with all
                  kinds of spirits.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-8"/> Now of this conjunction with your piety, which has been
                  brought about for us by this canonical letter, tending both to unity of spirit and
                  to be a bond<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-9"/> of peace, as the apostle said,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-10"/> I will send
                  information to our fellow-minister my lord Theodosius, the holy Pope and
                  archbishop of the great and Christ-loving city of Alexandria, who labours in
                  apostolic fashion, and undergoes a contest and stands in danger on behalf of the
                  true word, and increases the efficacy<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-11"/> of the talents intrusted to him
                  every day by means of industry, and rejoices constantly in the manifestation of
                  them. And do you write to him, <pb type="page" n="281"/>even as you have written
                  to us, and grasp him with the same hands of concord, and write and enter into
                  communication with him by a communicatory letter in accordance with the rules and
                  laws of the holy Church. Wherefore the love of God that is in you should take care
                  to perform your part towards him also, and it shall be to you, according to the
                  prophecy of Isaiah, 'a wall and an outwork';<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n281-1"/> as shall come to pass. And
                  greet your brotherhood. That which is with me greets you in our Lord."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.23">
               <head>Chapter 23</head>
               <head>The twenty-third chapter, the epistle of Severus to Theodosius</head>
               <p>"To<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n281-2"/> our all-pious and all-holy brother and fellow-minister, the chief
                  priest, my lord Theodosius, Severus greeting in our Lord."</p>
               <p>"In the Book of the Judges, which is the Book of the Tribes, he said that the
                  tribe of Judah invited the tribe of Simeon his brother to community of lots,
                  urging him, as to brotherly assistance, in these words: 'And Judah said unto
                  Simeon his brother, Come with me into my lot, and let us fight with the
                  Canaanites; and I likewise will go into thy lot. And Simeon went with
                  him.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n281-3"/> But I invite your person, holy brother, not to the community of war
                  and fighting and to give a helping hand for the sake of lots of inheritance, but
                  rather to the community of peace and concord, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n281-4"/> on account of a gain
                  made by the Church which Christ, even God, purchased with His own blood, a
                  wonderful addition. For the holy Anthimus, the chief priest, who has been judged
                  worthy to tend the Church of the royal city, severing the bonds and snares of the
                  bitterness of the heretics, and repelling now their deceitful arts, now his open
                  attacks,[#n281-5 has embraced our communion, <pb type="page" n="282"/>holding the
                  sound and pure faith. And to my meanness he has sent a letter, containing a
                  covenant of communion upon a perfectly orthodox confession, and he has
                  anathematised by name everyone who is a heretic and an alien; and his mind is not
                  estranged from the commandments and ordinances of the Lord, which our spiritual
                  fathers left as holy laws, upon which<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n282-1"/> we all ought to gaze earnestly and
                  say, like the enduring Job, 'Gazing upon righteousness, I will not turn
                  away.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n282-2"/> So I eagerly and with goodwill welcomed this event which has
                  happened as the gift of God, and I repeated the saying of the divine Scripture,
                  'This day we know that the Lord is with us, that all the peoples of the earth may
                  know that the power of God is mighty.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n282-3"/> For this is written in Joshua the
                  son of Nun."</p>
               <p>"And it would indeed have been right that the<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n282-4"/> holy archbishop Anthimus
                  should first apply to your evangelical<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n282-5"/> throne and offer to you the
                  firstfruits of concord; but the necessity of this time and the distance of the
                  country and the hurry of events changed the due order of things; and because this
                  was done in secret; for as a wise doctor of divine doctrines you know what is
                  written in the record by John the Theologian rather than Evangelist,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n282-6"/> that
                  the disciples were assembled with the doors shut for fear of the Jews, and that
                  the great God and our Saviour, Jesus Christ, while the doors were shut, appeared
                  inside by a miracle, and stood in the midst and said, 'Peace be with
                  you.'"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n282-7"/></p>
               <p>"I have therefore attached to this letter a copy of my own letter of concord and
                  that of the God -loving chief priest, the man above mentioned, which were composed
                  under fear of the Jews, and have sent them to your Holiness. But the religious
                  presbyter and steward, Theopompus,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n282-8"/> also has certainly<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n282-9"/> already
                  given you an account of this proceeding (for he also has communicated with
                  you<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n282-10"/> in this counsel and <pb type="page" n="283"/>action), because I
                  believed that the love of God that is in you would rejoice and exult over it,
                  especially when you met with the canonical letters containing the covenants."</p>
               <p>"But know, O pious brother, beloved by me above all things, that these demands of
                  the Chalcedonians<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n283-1"/> differ in no way whatever from the promised covenant of
                  Nahash the Ammonite, which he wished to make with the Children of Israel, who said
                  to him, 'Make a covenant with us, and we will serve thee'; but he cruelly and
                  barbarously returned answer, 'On this condition will I make a covenant with you,
                  that you pluck out all your right eyes; and I will lay a reproach upon
                  Israel.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n283-2"/> We are therefore in need of much watching and of immutable
                  faith, and of prayers and entreaties that He that keeps Israel will not slumber
                  nor sleep, and that He will turn the reproach upon those that are rich and
                  boastful, and we may not become 'a scorn and a reproach to them that are round
                  about us,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n283-3"/> as David somewhere sings, while falling from divine things,
                  they also confess human things; for no trust is to be placed in unbelievers and
                  enemies of God. But to you, who are understanding in divine things, what is here
                  said is matter of knowledge."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.24">
               <head>Chapter 24</head>
               <head>The twenty-fourth chapter, the epistle of Theodosius to Severus</head>
               <p>"To<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n283-4"/> our all-pious and all-holy brother and fellow-minister, the
                  patriarch, my lord Severus, Theodosius greeting in our Lord."</p>
               <p>"O being beloved by me above all things, rock of Christ, and guardian of the pure
                  faith who cannot be shaken, very excellent is the blessing granted to our time,
                  which has displayed your spiritual constancy to the holy Churches of God. We are
                  also in good hope and are confident that the blameless pattern of your virtue,
                  which we possess, will be preserved <pb type="page" n="284"/>for you.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n284-1"/> But
                  I do not know which of your virtues to admire; for what is there among your
                  qualities which is either defective or which stands in need of superfluous
                  description? If so be I admire the severe manner of your lovely life, the virtue
                  of chastity attracts me to it, and the glorious purity of right faith, which
                  justly demands to be placed before them all, and your life<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n284-2"/> of labours
                  endured for a long time for God's sake, and your flight from place to place, and
                  the fact that in everything you have chosen to suffer, in order that we may not be
                  perverted from the right faith. In the same faith how many times have you under
                  stress of events boldly cried with Paul, 'Who shall separate me from the love of
                  Christ? Shall tribulation or distress or persecution ?'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n284-3"/> But in what
                  category shall we place the exactitude of your teaching, whereby those that err
                  are reproved and deceit is plucked out by the roots, while those that believe are
                  delivered and are planted into the right faith? And it seems to me as if I heard
                  Christ, even God, saying to you what He said to Jeremiah the divine prophet:
                  'Behold! I have put My words in thy mouth. Behold! I have this day set thee over
                  nations and over kingdoms, to root out, and to pull down, and to destroy, and to
                  build, and to plant';<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n284-4"/> and again what He said about Paul: 'He is a chosen
                  vessel unto Me, to bear My name before the nations, and before kingdoms, and
                  before all Israel.'"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n284-5"/></p>
               <p>"These are your qualities, O divine father, — qualities which it is perhaps easy
                  to admire, but difficult to carry fully into action, even as now also by the
                  watchful labours of your pious soul good deeds have been done to the Church of
                  God. For in Christ Jesus those who were before far off have become near. The pious
                  Anthimus, who will be henceforth renowned for character and faith, the chief
                  priest and true pastor of the Church of the royal city, has of his own will become
                  a communicator with you, pious one, and with us, and walked after our right faith;
                  who has banished and rejected snares and disturbances, and has trampled on
                  transitory and unstable <pb type="page" n="285"/>profit, inasmuch as he has
                  learned to believe that human greatness is nothing,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n285-1"/> and has boldly
                  proclaimed the right and unfailing faith; so that on account of this which has
                  happened how we rejoiced and how we gave thanks to God and what spiritual festival
                  we celebrated, O honoured father ours, it is not possible to say in words."</p>
               <p>"Now he has made a firm covenant in a canonical letter and sent it to our
                  evangelical throne, as indeed your Holiness also has already stated even in your
                  honoured letter. And in the things which he has written he has declared the whole
                  exactitude of the sound and right faith, while he has spurned with the anathemas
                  everything that is deceitful and heretical, professing that he holds and proclaims
                  these things with us, and says these things, since he is a communicator with those
                  in whose communion our holy Church also rejoices, and professing that from those
                  from whom we turn away he also turns away. He has therefore mentioned by name and
                  anathematised those other names of the impious heresy, and the impious Synod held
                  at Chalcedon, and the epistle of Leo. And, when we had with all possible care
                  considered<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n285-2"/> the things written to us by the pious man and minutely
                  examined them all, and had found that nothing in them was alien from the right
                  faith, and we saw that there also everyone who is opposed to us was
                  attacked,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n285-3"/> we all the more admired your judgment upon them; for with the
                  things which were canonically written to you, holy one, by the pious Anthimus upon
                  the divine doctrines we found<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n285-4"/> those also which were written to us to be
                  in accord. Since, therefore, we have found the letter of concord and communion of
                  the holy Anthimus to be of such sort, I will, like the prophet, cry out in due
                  season, 'Let the heavens rejoice from above, and let the clouds sprinkle
                  righteousness,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n285-5"/> because the Lord has had mercy on His people, and such
                  good reforms have been brought to pass for the holy Church of God."</p>
               <p>"With outstretched hand, therefore, we have accepted the event, and on our own
                  part also hasten to conclude similar <pb type="page" n="286"/>covenants; and we
                  have admitted the pious man to the closest communion with us, and have
                  indited<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n286-1"/> a return letter to him, in which we have clearly set forth the
                  right faith of the fathers and exposed the evil character of the faith which
                  pollutes feeble understandings. And of the document on account of which we have
                  entered into communion with him, and will give it to any who shall be hereafter,
                  of this we have sent a copy to your fatherhood, because we did not wish that any
                  of .your rights should cause you jealousy,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n286-2"/> and especially those which
                  have to do with our holy Church. And then of necessity I say that the fact that
                  you observe towards the evangelical see the prime honour which is due to it, and
                  express the same in writing, as the things written to me declared you to do, was
                  in truth worthy of your holy soul, which is careful to do everything with judgment
                  and in accordance with the will of God. But I plainly declare my feeling that my
                  chief honour, and one which gives me great joy, is that honour which is justly
                  paid to you by everyone. With confidence, therefore, pious father ours, I
                  unhesitatingly assent to whatever<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n286-3"/> rightly seems good to you with regard
                  to the holy Church, considering that, as<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n286-4"/> befits your fatherhood, you will
                  not cease from action and advice which will be of benefit to the Church."</p>
               <p>"But so much for these things. But as to ourselves, O honoured father ours, by
                  what distresses and human humiliation we are now surrounded, every kind of
                  plot<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n286-5"/> being concerted against us, in order that we may either flee of our
                  own accord, or that we may be expelled by force by others, while they may be
                  granted time<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n286-6"/> here also to do their own deeds and lead astray the holy
                  Church, I wished to declare in this letter <pb type="page" n="287"/>also (for thus
                  especially should we incite you, who sympathise with us, to prayer on our behalf),
                  but it is not right for us to add load to load and burden to burden. But by only
                  saying this much about the greatness of the stress<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n287-1"/> I make it plain that
                  we are in very truth in need of your pious prayers."</p>
               <p>And so on with the rest of the epistle.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n287-2"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.25">
               <head>Chapter 25</head>
               <head>The twenty-fifth chapter, the epistle of Anthimusto Theodosius of
                  Alexandria</head>
               <p>"To<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n287-3"/> our all-pious and all-holy brother and fellow-minister, the
                  patriarch, my lord Theodosius, Anthimus greeting in our Lord."</p>
               <p>"Christ Jesus our God, who called simple and unlearned men and fishermen to be
                  apostles and teachers, and called those who were before these from feeding a flock
                  to be kings and prophets, who has chosen weak things and despised things, as the
                  divine apostle said,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n287-4"/> He it is who has now called me also, the mean one,
                  to the work of this spiritual ministry in the judgments which He knows, to be the
                  head of this holy Church of Constantinople. I therefore, the sinner, remembering
                  the utterance of the Lord spoken<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n287-5"/> through Ezekiel, 'As for thee, son of
                  man, I have given thee as a watchman unto them of the house of Israel; and, if
                  thou hear<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n287-6"/> the word at My mouth, and give forewarning<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n287-7"/> from Me,
                  saying unto the sinner. If thou sin, thou shalt die the death, and thou tell not
                  the sinner, that he may take warning, nor yet the impious, that he may turn from
                  his way and live, the wicked man shall die in his wickedness,<pb type="page"
                     n="288"/>but his blood will I require at thine hands,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n288-1"/> and the
                  commandment of the apostle to Timothy about the blamelessness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n288-2"/> of the
                  bishop's office, am beset with fear and trembling. And, when besides these things
                  I contemplate also the turmoil which is increasing in the holy Churches and on the
                  side of those who do not believe rightly, because they have reckoned religion as a
                  means of profit for a time, and speak wickedness on high against their head, and
                  divide God the Word, who became incarnate without variation and became perfectly
                  man, I am beset with weeping and groans, and I mourn over myself, because I am
                  unworthy. But trust<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n288-3"/> in God comforts me, as it is said, 'Look<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n288-4"/> at
                  the generations of old and see; who hath trusted in the Lord and been confounded?
                  or who hath abode in His fear and been forsaken? or hath called upon Him and He
                  turned away from him? Because the Lord is compassionate and merciful, and
                  forgiveth sins and saveth in time of affliction.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n288-5"/> Therefore all my hope
                  and my thoughts<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n288-6"/> are set upon Him, that He will see our state and will
                  hear,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n288-7"/> He who made the eyes and planted the ears, and that He will reprove
                  the turbulence of those who prevent right ways, and will call like the true
                  shepherd who laid down his life for his sheep, because He said, 'No man shall
                  snatch them out of mine hands':<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n288-8"/> for He foreordained your Holiness to
                  stand at the head of the people of Alexandria the great, and established you as a
                  tiller of the Church, not in calm, but in the turmoil of storms, that you might
                  guide the ship above the waves into the peace of the harbour of Christ our God by
                  the holy and adored Spirit.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n288-9"/> For by the prayers of your holy fathers, the
                  former rulers, you have, as it were, received the trust of standing at the head of
                  a people which walks after the teaching of the fathers, and contends for its
                  pastor unto death in word and deed."</p>
               <pb type="page" n="289"/>
               <p>"Embracing, therefore, union with you and brotherly- unanimity in Christ and the
                  laws<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n289-1"/> of the Church, we declare by this Synodical epistle that we cleave
                  to the one definition of faith, that of our three hundred and eighteen holy
                  fathers at Nicaea, which also the one hundred and fifty who assembled here against
                  the fighters against the Spirit ratified, and to the holy Synod which met at
                  Ephesus with the assent of Celestine and in the presence of Cyril, who in the
                  twelve chapters demolished the doctrine of Nestorius. To these I assent, and I
                  embrace the rest of his writings; and I receive the formula of Zeno uniting the
                  Churches, which aimed at the annulling of the Synod of Chalcedon and of the
                  Tome<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n289-2"/> of Leo. And I confess that God the Word, the only Son, who was
                  begotten of the Father in eternity, through whom all things were made. Light of
                  Light, living image of the Father and sharing His nature, in the last times became
                  incarnate by the Holy Spirit and of Mary the Virgin, and became a man perfectly
                  without variation and confusion, in everything like unto us except sin; and He
                  remained God immutable, and, when He assumed our attributes. He was not diminished
                  in His Godhead; and that which was derived from us He made His own by dispensation
                  by a natural union. For He who was begotten without time and without a body of God
                  the Father, the same underwent a second birth in flesh, inasmuch as in an
                  ineffable manner He became incarnate of a virgin mother; and, after she had borne
                  Him, she continued in her virginity; and we justly confess her to be the
                  Theotokos, and that He who was born of her in the flesh is perfect God and perfect
                  man, the same out of two natures one Son, one Lord, and one Christ, and one nature
                  of God the Word who became incarnate; and each one of the natures which combined
                  to form an indivisible unity remained without confusion. And so He is very rightly
                  one of the holy and connatural Trinity, both before He took flesh and after He
                  took flesh, and a fourth number was not added to the Trinity; and He is impassible
                  in that He is of the nature of the Father, but passible <pb type="page" n="290"
                  />in the flesh in that He is of our nature. For God the Word did not suffer in His
                  own nature, but in flesh of our nature; and He who personally united this to
                  Himself suffered in our likeness. And Gregory the Theologian defined the matter
                  and called Him impassible in His Godhead, passible in the assumption of
                  flesh.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n290-1"/> And He is one in the miracles, and also in the passions, and by
                  dispensation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n290-2"/> He made our passions His own, voluntary and innocent ones,
                  in flesh which was passible and mortal after our<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n290-3"/> nature, endowed with a
                  soul and an intellect, and passible and mortal all the time of the dispensation;
                  for He suffered not in semblance but in reality, and in flesh that was capable of
                  suffering He suffered and died on the cross; and by a Resurrection befitting God
                  He made and rendered it impassible and immortal, and in every way incorruptible,
                  since it came from the union of the womb, which<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n290-4"/>was holy and without sin.
                  While recognising, therefore, the distinction between the elements which have
                  combined to form the unity of nature, I mean between the Godhead and the manhood,
                  we yet do not separate them from one another; also we do not cut the One into or
                  in two natures, nor yet do we confound Him by rejecting the distinction between
                  the Godhead and the manhood, but we confess Him to be one out of two,
                  Emmanuel."</p>
               <p>"And, thus believing and taking my stand upon this belief, as upon a rock, I also
                  anathematise the deviations from the truth of such and such men."</p>
               <p>And the rest, consisting of the greeting in the epistle.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="291"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="9.26">
               <head>Chapter 26</head>
               <head>The twenty-sixth chapter of the ninth Book, the epistle of Theodosius to
                  Anthimus the chief priest</head>
               <p>"To<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n291-1"/> our all-pious and all-holy brother and fellow-minister, the
                  archbishop and patriarch, my lord Anthimus, Theodosius greeting in our Lord."</p>
               <p>"And how else could it have come about that you, a chief priest wise and watchful
                  towards the Creator of all things and their Saviour and God, should in the midst
                  of events openly show yourself crying out like Jeremiah the divine prophet, 'I
                  have not wearied of going after thee, and the day of a man have I not
                  desired,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n291-2"/> except that you despised such human honour, and placed the
                  observance of religion before all things? The thing, therefore, which has been
                  thus done by your Holiness is great without controversy, and all the believers who
                  have heard of it are already wondering at it, while hereafter also all the
                  bond-servants of the Lord who shall be hereafter will wonder at it, when it is
                  duly proclaimed in all the holy Churches. But it is no higher than the rest of
                  your apostolic and truly sublime and holy life. For it was truly fitting for you,
                  who by unceasing energy in ascetic exercise have mortified your earthly members,
                  that you might speak<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n291-3"/> in the words of Scripture, and with Paul are able to
                  say, 'I am crucified with Christ; nevertheless I live, yet now not I, but Christ
                  liveth in me,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n291-4"/> after the manner of Moses the great to esteem the reproach
                  of Christ greater riches than the treasures of this world, and to choose rather to
                  be afflicted with the people of God than to enjoy the temporal<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n291-5"/> pleasure
                  of sin."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n291-6"/></p>
               <p>"For I, who am feeble, judge that it is on account of my shortcomings that I
                  endure all the troubles which befall me; <pb type="page" n="292"/>but, since I am
                  bound to represent the Church which is under the evangelical throne,
                  which<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n292-1"/> is now enduring many ills (and how many it is enduring is not easy
                  to say), therefore in due season I say as the divine Paul said, 'As the sufferings
                  of Christ abound in us, so also is our consolation great in Christ.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n292-2"/> For
                  the fact that you, the pious chief priest and patriarch of the royal city, should
                  use boldness on behalf of the right and apostolic faith, and should be eager to
                  show that in respect of the strict observance of the divine doctrines you are of
                  one mind and one accord with Severus, the holy patriarch of the Eastern Churches,
                  has almost made me forget in the evangelical see and acceptation of the divine
                  Mark the whole of the troubles which are upon us. For, 'what thanks can we render
                  to God?'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n292-3"/> For this apostolic saying also do I use on account of the help
                  with which He has helped His holy Churches, who has now stablished you as a
                  stablisher of these, and as a foremost fighter in the danger to religion. For you
                  have shown, O pious man, that you have dwelling in you the holy utterance<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n292-4"/>
                  of the Lord, which says, 'Fear not them which kill the body, but are not able to
                  kill the soul; but rather fear Him which is able to destroy soul and body in
                  hell,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n292-5"/> and that you 'reckon that the sufferings of this time are not
                  worthy to be compared with the glory which shall be revealed in us.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n292-6"/>
                  While, therefore, your spiritual light so shines before men, God is glorified in
                  this great increase of those that are being saved, which His true Church
                  receives."</p>
               <p>"So it is with joyful exultation and delight that I have canonically<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n292-7"/>
                  received your piety's letter of concord and union, which has just been brought to
                  me,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n292-8"/> because the holy patriarch Severus above mentioned told me beforehand
                  that it was coming to me, who is the cause of all blessings and benefits to the
                  Church of Christ and to me; and he has also sent me, as befitted him, a copy of
                  what you canonically wrote to one <pb type="page" n="293"/>another, which also
                  made it clear that your communion was brought about with great caution and great
                  benefit. And, while inditing this letter with my whole heart, I say the same
                  things to your Holiness which also I wrote to him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n293-1"/> that I confess as the
                  one definition of faith and accept that which was laid down by our three hundred
                  and eighteen holy fathers at Nicaea through the Holy Spirit, and ratified by the
                  Synod of one hundred and fifty and by that at Ephesus, which was assembled by our
                  father Cyril, who in the twelve chapters rejected Nestorius; and I accept also the
                  formula of Zeno uniting the Churches, which aimed at the annulling of the Synod of
                  Chalcedon and of the Tome of Leo, while I confess that God the Word, of the nature
                  of the eternal Father, Light of Light, Very God of Very God, became incarnate and
                  also became man by the Holy Spirit and of Mary the ever-virgin, in flesh endowed
                  with a soul and an intellect after our nature, and was made like unto us in
                  everything except sin, for, 'sin He did not, neither was guile found in His
                  mouth,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n293-2"/> as the Scripture said. For it was right and just that the nature
                  which was vanquished in Adam should in Christ put on a crown of triumph over
                  death. And so also the apostle said, 'Since the children partook of flesh and
                  blood,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n293-3"/> He also in like manner partook of the same, that through death He
                  might bring to naught him that had the power of death, that is, Satan, and might
                  deliver them who through fear of death were all their lifetime subject to
                  sin.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n293-4"/> But, if we were vanquished in another nature, and the Word of God
                  did not partake of it or make the same flesh which was assumed from us and
                  personally united to Him impassible and immortal through the union<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n293-5"/> with
                  Him, as some foolishly say, our faith is vain, because it is no great thing that
                  Satan <pb type="page" n="294"/>should be vanquished by the Lord; but in a body
                  which was passible and of our nature He suffered innocent passions, and underwent
                  death, and trampled on the sting of sin, and dissolved the power of death. Now, if
                  He received the seed of Abraham, and in everything was made like unto us His
                  brethren except sin, as the wise Paul said, and through death, which He underwent
                  in His own flesh, vanquished Satan, who had the power of death, while He remained
                  beyond the assault of passions in that He is recognised to be and is justly God,
                  on account of His victory we glory, because we have been delivered from the yoke
                  of bondage. Who is there, therefore, who will not marvel at the accuracy of the
                  divine words, which everywhere supply due direction and in the same words refute
                  the 'semblance' of Eutyches, and those who are like him, and the doctrine of
                  Nestorius? For he says that Christ partook of our likeness in flesh and blood;
                  and, that no one might think that He did so in phantasy, he went on to say that He
                  partook of the same that through death He might bring to naught the power of
                  death."</p>
               <p>"Moreover they contend against those who divide the one Christ into two<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n294-1"/>
                  natures by the example of children. For,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n294-2"/> as the child and the man, who is
                  made up of soul and body, is one out of two, and the two are called one nature,
                  though the soul was not converted into flesh nor the body changed into the
                  essence<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n294-3"/> of the soul; so also Christ, who consists of the two elements,
                  the Godhead and also the manhood, which have a perfect existence, each in its
                  proper sphere, is one and is not divided; and the union is not confused in Him in
                  that [He united to Himself personally flesh of our nature and]<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n294-4"/> allowed it
                  in all the dispensation to be passible and mortal (but the same was holy without
                  sin), and by the Resurrection made and rendered it impassible and immortal and in
                  every <pb type="page" n="295"/>way incorruptible. For our former<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n295-1"/> father
                  Cyril said, 'He first raised His body in incorruption, and He first exalted it to
                  heaven.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n295-2"/> So believing therefore, I anathematise such and such."</p>
               <p>And the rest, consisting of the greeting in the epistle.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n218-1">Cf. bk. 6, ch. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n218-2">526-7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n218-3">αὐτοκράτωρ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n218-4">537.</note>
            <note xml:id="n219-1">The text has "Alexandria," but Halicarnassus is obviously meant,
               as in the heading of the chapter below.</note>
            <note xml:id="n219-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n220-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->l, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n220-2">The word <!--  Add Syriac  --> seems to have dropped out of the
               text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n220-3">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  --> or
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Without
               this the meaning will be, “there is inserted above,” which seems
               contradictory.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-3">This seems to refer to the MS. from which the scribe was copying,
               as the prologue of Moro is not inserted at this place in our MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-4">527.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-5">Bk. 7, ch. 14; 8, 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-6">στρατηγός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-7">See bk. 6, ch. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-8">Mich. fol. 167 v, 168 r; Greg. p. 78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-9">αὐτοκράτωρ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-10">527.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-11">Mich. fol. 162 r.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-12">προνόμια.</note>
            <note xml:id="n221-13">Mich. fol. 161 r.</note>
            <note xml:id="n222-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n222-2">Probably Timostratus (Wright, C. B. M. p. 559).
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> might well fall out before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n222-3">στρατηλάτης.</note>
            <note xml:id="n222-4">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n222-5">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> after <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n222-6">The text has "Justinian," but clearly Justin must be meant.
               ^</note>
            <note xml:id="n223-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n223-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->(?).</note>
            <note xml:id="n223-3">στρατηλάτης.</note>
            <note xml:id="n223-4">Perhaps Hieriphthum (Gelzer, Geo. Cypr. p. 159).</note>
            <note xml:id="n223-5">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n223-6">φόσσα.</note>
            <note xml:id="n223-7"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. Brockelmann quoting this passage gives
               doubtfully "erexit"; but, as <!--  Add Syriac  --> = was wrapped up ("involutus est,"
               Brock.), I take it as above. In Smith's Thesaurus it is proposed to read
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, but this could only mean "beat" or "dashed."</note>
            <note xml:id="n223-8">τρίγωνος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n223-9">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n224-1">The MS. seems to have <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints. The word is a rare one, and generally means "to
               be shaken."</note>
            <note xml:id="n224-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints. For the meaning of the word see p. 199, note 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n224-3">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n224-4">Perhaps the "Simas" of Procopius (Bell. Pers. i. 13).
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> is probably corrupt, the scribe having taken it for a common
               noun.</note>
            <note xml:id="n224-5">χιλίαρχος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n225-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->; cf. Proc.
               l.c.. The Herulians, whom the Greeks frequently called Ἕλουροι, are meant.</note>
            <note xml:id="n225-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n225-3">531.</note>
            <note xml:id="n225-4">φόσσα.</note>
            <note xml:id="n225-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n225-6">χιλίαρχοι.</note>
            <note xml:id="n225-7">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints. See bk. S, ch. 5 (p. 206, note 5).</note>
            <note xml:id="n225-8">Mich. fol. 168 r; Greg. pp. 78, 79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n226-1">στρατηγός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n226-2">Syr. "sister's son."</note>
            <note xml:id="n226-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n226-4">527.</note>
            <note xml:id="n226-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as proposed
               by Prof. Nöldeke [Zeitschr. Deutsch. Morgenländ. Gesellsch. vol. xxxiii. p. 159, note
               1).</note>
            <note xml:id="n227-1">531.</note>
            <note xml:id="n227-2">Syr. "sister's son."</note>
            <note xml:id="n227-3">The native title of the tribal chief: Arm. bdeashkh. See Nöldeke,
               l.c. note 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n227-4">This number cannot be right, as Martyropolis was N. of the Tigris,
               240 stades from Amida and 100 from Attachæ (Proc. Bell. Pers. i. 21).</note>
            <note xml:id="n227-5">532.</note>
            <note xml:id="n227-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-1">ἀξία.</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-2">ὕπαρχος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-3">Lit. "was moving all the stones."</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. I can make nothing of this, and only guess
               at the meaning. The literal rendering is "a palace which he filled," and it is
               perhaps just possible that the idea of bribery is concealed under it; but more
               probably the text is corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-5">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-6">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-7">531-2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-8">φόσσα.</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-9">See bk. 7, ch. 3 (p. 153).</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-10">στρατηγός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-11">Or October. It is not stated whether it was the 1st or 2nd
               Theshrin.</note>
            <note xml:id="n228-12">531.</note>
            <note xml:id="n229-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, from the root <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "to
               swell." This form occurs only here, but the Shafʿel is found in 7. 3, (p. 205, l. 5,
               L.). See Smith's Thesaurus, col. 3795.</note>
            <note xml:id="n229-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n229-3">The rest of this chapter and the following chapter are contained
               in Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n229-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Cod. Rom.
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Cod. Brit, is indistinct; the <!--  Add Syriac  --> seems to
               have been obliterated.</note>
            <note xml:id="n229-5">Mich. fol. 168 r.</note>
            <note xml:id="n229-6">526.</note>
            <note xml:id="n230-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. In bk. 3, ch. 4 (p. 244, l. 11, L.),
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> means "in a mystical sense" (the word <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               being practically equivalent to μυστήριον), and I therefore here translate as above.
               Other possible renderings are "with certain mysterious rites " and "with some
               secrecy." I understand the meaning to be that Moses (or Cyriac?) was worshipped under
               the outward forms of Magism. Mich. adds, "and it was called the monastery of Moses of
               Tarmel."</note>
            <note xml:id="n231-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.The meaning of the reading of Cod. Brit. is "of God."</note>
            <note xml:id="n231-2">Cod. Rom. has the meaningless <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               "epistle."</note>
            <note xml:id="n231-3">532-3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n231-4">"Dion." fol. 182 v*; of. Jo. Mal. p. 477. In the Paris transcript.
               I take the reference from the analysis of "Dionysius," published by M. Nau in the
               Revue de l'Orient Chrétien, Suppl. trim. 1897, fasc. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n231-5">533.</note>
            <note xml:id="n231-6">540.</note>
            <note xml:id="n232-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n232-2">Mich. fol. 168 r; Greg. p. 79.</note>
            <note xml:id="n232-3">χιλίαρχος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n232-4">Mich. fol. 181 r; Greg. H. E. p. 211.</note>
            <note xml:id="n233-1"><!--  Add Syriac  --> (so MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.).
               Mich. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "followed it," which points to a reading
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->. All the remainder of this chapter is exceedingly obscure and
               probably corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n233-2">ἀγωνιστής.</note>
            <note xml:id="n233-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, from Prov. x. 14; cf. bk. 8, ch. 4 (p. 243,
               l. 17, L.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n233-4">Perhaps something has fallen out before this sentence. Mich. has
               "but, after Julian had written that it was his opinion, and the holy man had answered
               him twice, and he would not obey."</note>
            <note xml:id="n233-5">I supply these words from Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n233-6">ὑπόθεσις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n234-1">These letters are contained in Add. MS. 17,200 and in Cod. Syr.
               Vat. 140, from which last extracts are given by the Assemani (Bibl. Vat. MSS. Catal.
               vol. iii. p. 323 ff.). Both these give the Syriac translation of Paul of Callinicus.
               Our author's translation is independent.</note>
            <note xml:id="n234-2">Mich. fol. 181 r.</note>
            <note xml:id="n234-3">Cyr. Ep. 45 (Migne, Patrol. Græc. vol. lxxvii. p. 236).</note>
            <note xml:id="n234-4">Cyr. de Rect. Fid. ad Theod. Imp. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n234-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and
               therefore probably read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "set down the whole matter in a
               sentence." Paul. Call. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, which determines the sense of
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n234-6">I cannot find this in the Quod Beata Maria Sit Deipara.</note>
            <note xml:id="n235-1">Possibly something has dropped out here. See the quotation in ch.
               13 (p. 238); and so Paul. Call. Mich., however, has the same as our text, so that no
               alteration should be made in it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n235-2">ἀντίγραφον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n235-3">Mich. fol. 181 v.</note>
            <note xml:id="n236-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n236-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n236-3">1 Cor. xvi. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n236-4">ἀντίγραφον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n236-5">Mich. fol. 181 v.</note>
            <note xml:id="n236-6">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. The MS. has
               no dot, either above or below the letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="n237-1">Text, "Theodosius." Paul of Callinicus, however, has
               "Athanasius,"' and so Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n237-2">Here begins a short extract in Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n237-3">Here the extract in Cod. Rom. ends.</note>
            <note xml:id="n237-4">Cyr. de Rect. Fid. ad Theod. Imp. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n237-5">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->. So Paul
               of Callinicus.</note>
            <note xml:id="n237-6">Cyr. op. cit. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n237-7">ἀντίγραφον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n237-8">Mich. fol. 181 ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n238-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before •<!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n238-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> seems to be a denominative verb from
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> (Hamilton). Paul. Call. <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n238-3">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->. But the
               sentence seems to be corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n238-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               (<!--  Add Syriac  -->, Paul. Call.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n238-5">Job xxi. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n238-6">Prov. ii. 6, 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-1">Here begins an extract in Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-2">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom. and Paul. Call.; so Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-3">Rom. iii. 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-4">Jas. ii. 20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-5">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom.; so Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-7">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-8">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom.; so Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-9">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. (Paul. Call. <!--  Add Syriac  -->); so Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-10">Gal. iii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-11">Rom. iv. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n240-1">Jas. ii. 21-24. With Cod. Rom. insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->; so Mich. Paul. Call. agrees with Cod. Brit., giving the
               meaning "which confirm faith."</note>
            <note xml:id="n240-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n240-3">This must be supplied in order to make sense. Paul. Call, has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "for the one Abraham, when divided into periods." Mich., like
               our text, omits the verb.</note>
            <note xml:id="n240-4">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n240-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n240-6">Ex. iv. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n240-7">Col. ii. 11, 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n240-8">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.; so Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n240-9">Rom. iv. 9, 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-1">Gen. xv. 5, 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. So Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-3">Jas. ii. 20-23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-6">Gen. xvii. 26, 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-7">Gen. xxii. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-8">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-9">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-10">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-11">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-12">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n242-1">Cod. Rom. here inserts in the margin a sentence from bk. 10, ch. 9
               (see p. 313), which Mai prints as if it were part of the text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n242-2">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n242-3">There is no <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  --> in
               Cod. Rom., as Mai prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n242-4">Gal. v. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n242-5">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> insert with Cod. Rom.
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, which has dropped out in Cod. Brit, through
               homoioteleuton.</note>
            <note xml:id="n242-6">1 Cor. xiii. 4-8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n242-7">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n242-8">John xiv. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n243-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. So Paul. Call. (<!--  Add Syriac  -->) and Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n243-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. So Paul. Call, and Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n243-3">Prov. viii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n243-4">Here the extract in Cod. Rom. ends.</note>
            <note xml:id="n243-5">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n243-6">Paul. Call. has "Felicissimus."</note>
            <note xml:id="n243-7">θεωρία, the inner or allegorical meaning of a book.</note>
            <note xml:id="n244-1">Gal. v. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n244-2">Ep. III. ad Sev. (Add. 17,200, fol. 9 r).</note>
            <note xml:id="n244-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, "felt." Mich, has <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               "bound," and therefore read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n244-4"><!--  Add Syriac  --> "was answered"(?), is unintelligible, unless
               we insert a negative. Mich. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "was stolen," and therefore
               read <!--  Add Syriac  -->. This reading I adopt. Both renderings, however, are very
               doubtful in grammar.</note>
            <note xml:id="n244-5">Add. 17,200, fol. 38 ff. (Latin translation in Mai Spicilegium
               Romanum, x. p. 169).</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-1">δῆμος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-2">532.</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-3">στάσις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-4">ὕπαρχος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. This word apparently occurs only here and
               in 7. 7 (p. 217, l. 11, L.). It is not given in Payne Smith's Thesaurus, and
               Brockelmann, who refers only to p. 217, 11, renders it "cogitavit, spectavit"; but
               from this passage it seems clear that the meaning is as above.</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-6">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-7">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. The
               dictionaries give this word as = λουδάριος, "gladiator" or "brigand," but here and in
               ch. 16 (pp. 257, 258) it seems clear that the meaning is as above
               (=λοίδορος(?)).</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-8">Or, "and he favoured…"</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-9">μέρος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-10">ἐκβόησις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n246-1">ἱππικός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n246-2">στρατηγός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n246-3"><!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n246-4">Mich. fol. 171 ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n247-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "expecting," which represents <!--  Add Syriac  -->; but I
               cannot see any meaning in it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n247-2">At Dr. Hamilton's suggestion I read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich., however, has <!--  Add Syriac  --> "because you (it),"
               and must therefore have read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n247-3">Tit. iii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n247-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich. "the
               apostle said."</note>
            <note xml:id="n247-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n248-1">1Cor. xi. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n248-2">We require <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich., however, also has <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n248-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n249-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n249-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->; so Mich.
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n249-3">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> the MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n250-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints. Mich. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "in your writings."</note>
            <note xml:id="n250-2">I do not know whence this is taken.</note>
            <note xml:id="n250-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n250-4">The words <!--  Add Syriac  --> are accidentally repeated in L.'s
               text, but not in the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n250-5">Dion. Areop. de Div. Nom. i. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n251-1">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n251-2">This is not in the extant portions of the Sermo de Fide.</note>
            <note xml:id="n251-3">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n251-4">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n251-5">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n251-6">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich.
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n252-1">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> insert with Mich.
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n252-2">δέησις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n252-3">πεπραγμένα.</note>
            <note xml:id="n252-4">Mansi, vii. pp. 456, 457.</note>
            <note xml:id="n252-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n253-1">Jo. Eph. Frag. (Anecd. Syr. ii. p. 386).</note>
            <note xml:id="n253-2">534-5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n253-3">536.</note>
            <note xml:id="n253-4">This is not in the text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n253-5">According to the heading the petitioners were not monks but
               bishops. In Mich., however, they are called "bishops and monks."</note>
            <note xml:id="n254-1">Cf. Evag. iv. II.</note>
            <note xml:id="n254-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> seems to have dropped out before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n254-3">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n254-4">Read<!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n254-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n255-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before ,<!--  Add Syriac  --></note>
            <note xml:id="n255-2">Ex. xiv. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n255-3">Heb. vi. 13, 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n255-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> (ἀσφάλεια) for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n255-5">Eccles. viii. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n255-6"><!--  Add Syriac  --> is crossed out in the MS., but a copula of
               some kind is required.</note>
            <note xml:id="n256-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n256-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n256-3">Prov. xx. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n256-4">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n256-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n256-6">Prov. xx. 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n256-7">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> we should perhaps read
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "grains of wheat " (Hamilton). In this case we should probably
               read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> and render "easy for them (the
               reapers) to separate the things that are winnowed . . . from the wheat."</note>
            <note xml:id="n257-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n257-2">This sentence is very awkward and obscure. The general sense I owe
               to Dr. Hamilton, and I arrive at it by omitting <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n257-3">Only <!--  Add Syriac  -->… is visible. Read
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n257-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. See p. 245, note 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n257-5">βίος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n257-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints. Logically we require another <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n257-7">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->. It is
               doubtful whether the letter is really in the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n258-1">Deut. xiv. 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n258-2">Prov. xvi. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n258-3">τάξις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n258-4">See above, and p. 245, note 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n258-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n258-6">For <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "I am,'' we should perhaps read
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, or <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "I was."</note>
            <note xml:id="n259-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n259-2">I owe the translation of this difficult passage to Dr. Hamilton.
               For .<!--  Add Syriac  --> we should have expected <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n259-3">1 Pet. ii. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n259-4">Quoted shortly from the third letter of Severus to Julian (Add.
               MS. 17,200, fol. 17).</note>
            <note xml:id="n259-5">οὐσία.</note>
            <note xml:id="n260-1">Read [.ili. for ..ClL.</note>
            <note xml:id="n260-2">If <!--  Add Syriac  --> is right, it would seem to be connected
               with <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "to impel." Ct., however, p. 73, 1. 8, 21 (L.), where the
               verb seems to mean "to revile." I cannot find the source of the quotation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n260-3">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> we must read either
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> or <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n260-4">Job xxx. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n260-5">John iv. 35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n260-6">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-1">Rom. xii. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-3">πολιτεία.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-4">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-5">534-535.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-6">στρατηγός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-7">533.</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. See bk. 1, ch. 1 (p. 16, note 8).</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-2">The negative <!--  Add Syriac  --> has fallen out of the
               text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-5">ὕπαρχος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-6">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-7"><!--  Add Syriac  --> "outer garments," can hardly be
               right.</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-8">We must either insert another <!--  Add Syriac  --> or omit
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, rendering "the prince was not there."</note>
            <note xml:id="n263-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n263-2">The rest of this sentence is contained in Cod. Rom. Instead,
               however, of "and is rich and fertile," it has "and the chief city and capital of the
               country is called Carthage."</note>
            <note xml:id="n263-3">I.e. Arians—followers of the Synod of Ariminum.</note>
            <note xml:id="n263-4">534.</note>
            <note xml:id="n263-5">ἱππικός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n263-6">δῆμος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n263-7">Cf. Jo. Mal. p. 479.</note>
            <note xml:id="n264-1">I.e. Theodoric; see bk. 7, ch. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n264-2">Or Demonicus.</note>
            <note xml:id="n264-3">Lit. “From the reading of Scriptures.” Possibly some words have
               fallen out.</note>
            <note xml:id="n264-4">σύγκλητος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n264-5">βούλη.</note>
            <note xml:id="n264-6">If the singular is genuine, the Gothic commandant, or possibly the
               king, would seem to be meant; but perhaps we should read <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               “their chief men.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n265-1">536. The text is <!--  Add Syriac  -->, which is a confusion
               between "Τρισκαιδέκατον'' and "τεσσαρεσκαιδέκατον." Read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, which
               is the nearer to historical fact.</note>
            <note xml:id="n265-2">Jo. Eph. Fragm. (Anecd. Syr. ii. p. 386).</note>
            <note xml:id="n265-3">535-6. In chs. 15 and 16 the date is rightly given as the
               thirteenth year of the Indiction (534-5). "τρίς" (<!--  Add Syriac  -->) and
               "τέσσαρες" (<!--  Add Syriac  -->) are easily confused: see note 1 above.</note>
            <note xml:id="n265-4">Cf. Evag. iv. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n266-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n266-2">Mich. fol. 170.</note>
            <note xml:id="n266-3">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->. So
               Mich. <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n266-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich.
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n266-5">What follows is contained in an abbreviated form in Add. MS.
               12,154, fol. 151.</note>
            <note xml:id="n266-6">Mich. l.c.; Greg. H. E. p. 205 ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n266-7">17,202 has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and 12,154
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, while Mich. and Greg. have <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Asylus of
               Rhesaina is mentioned in Elijah's life of John of Constantia (ed. Kleyn, p. 59),
               whence I follow the reading of 17,202.</note>
            <note xml:id="n266-8">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               12,154: similarly Mich. and Greg.</note>
            <note xml:id="n266-9">The MS. seems to have <!--  Add Syriac  --> (βιβλία), not
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n266-10">Wright, C. B. M. pp. 493-501.</note>
            <note xml:id="n267-1">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               12,154. Similarly Greg.</note>
            <note xml:id="n267-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n267-3">536.</note>
            <note xml:id="n267-4">This sentence is not in 17,202, but, being in 12,154 (which,
               however, omits the portents following) and in Mich., it must be presumed to have
               formed part of the original text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n267-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, a very awkward phrase, the rendering of
               which I owe to Dr. Hamilton. The usual meaning of <!--  Add Syriac  --> is "to be
               anxious,'' or "to neglect"; but, as <!--  Add Syriac  --> means "a storm," and Mich,
               has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, we may fairly render as above.</note>
            <note xml:id="n267-6">537.</note>
            <note xml:id="n267-7">Instead of the rest of this sentence 12,154 has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "and had been brought up with him," which is probably an error
               for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "and shared his opinions."</note>
            <note xml:id="n268-1">Cf. Evag. iv. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n268-2">Here the extract in 12,154 breaks off owing to the loss of a leaf
               in the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n268-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n268-4">This passage is repeated in a ninth cent. chronicle in Brit. Mus.
               Add. MS. 14,642, fol. 29 v, which, however, in place of <!--  Add Syriac  --> has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "and he tore it with his teeth."</note>
            <note xml:id="n268-5">Mich. fol. 178.</note>
            <note xml:id="n269-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> I read <!--  Add Syriac  --> but the
               sentence is extremely obscure. Mich. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "bringing." Dr.
               Hamilton suggests <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "strength."</note>
            <note xml:id="n269-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. With the MS.
               reading we must render "desertion."</note>
            <note xml:id="n269-3">This sentence is hopelessly corrupt in the text. I take the sense
               from Mich., who seems to have omitted <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and read
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and <!--  Add Syriac  --> for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n269-4">Logically the <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               should be omitted.</note>
            <note xml:id="n269-5">Gen. xxxv. 2, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n269-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n270-1">Job xviii. 8-10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n270-2">Isa. xliii. 1-3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n270-3">Lev. xxvi. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n270-4">2 Cor. ii. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n271-1">Mich. fol. 174.</note>
            <note xml:id="n271-2">Luke xii. 48.</note>
            <note xml:id="n271-3">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n271-4">Ps. xxiv. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n271-5">Gen. xviii. 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n271-6">Ps. xxii. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n271-7">To get this sense we should probably read <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich., however, has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "part," which
               points to a reading <!--  Add Syriac  -->. With the MS. reading the meaning will be
               "mock and divide.''</note>
            <note xml:id="n271-8">Ps. cxix. 53.</note>
            <note xml:id="n272-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n272-2">Tit. iii. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n272-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. The sentence
               is awkward, but the sense is clear from Mich. <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n272-4">The reference seems to be to Isa. xl. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n272-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n272-6">Read<!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as in the
               parallel passage in ch. 25 (p. 289).</note>
            <note xml:id="n273-1">MS. not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L., but <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               changed into <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Perhaps read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n273-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n274-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as in the parallel passage in ch. 25 (p. 290).</note>
            <note xml:id="n274-2">Greg. Naz. Or. xl. 45.</note>
            <note xml:id="n274-3">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  --> or
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n274-4">If "the womb" is the antecedent we must read <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               for <!--  Add Syriac  -->; but possibly the antecedent is "the union." Cf. p. 290,
               note 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n274-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, "ran," here and in the parallel passage in
               ch. 25 seems to be used to represent συνέδραμον, though no such meaning is recognised
               in lexicons.</note>
            <note xml:id="n275-1">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n275-2">After this name the names of Theodoret and Andrew are accidentally
               repeated in the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n275-3">πρόσωπον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n275-4">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n275-5">ἰδιώτης.</note>
            <note xml:id="n275-6">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> (παῤῥησία) Mich. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> (παράδεισος).</note>
            <note xml:id="n275-7">I do not know from what part of Basil's works this quotation is
               taken.</note>
            <note xml:id="n275-8">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               which L. does not print.</note>
            <note xml:id="n275-9">There seems to have been another letter before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and I insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->. So Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n276-1">Given by Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n276-2">Mich. fol. 174.</note>
            <note xml:id="n276-3">The sentence, as it stands, is ungrammatical, but this is clearly
               the meaning; there is the same difficulty in Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n276-4">2 Cor. ix. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n276-5">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n277-1">Gen. xxi. 33.</note>
            <note xml:id="n277-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. Perhaps the original Syriac translator of
               this letter wrote <!--  Add Syriac  -->, the chief see; but Mich. has the same as our
               text, and, as the divergences between him and our text in these letters show that he
               drew not from our author but from a common source, we must not emend.</note>
            <note xml:id="n277-3">φάντασις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n277-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n277-5">What follows in Mich. is entirely different from our text.
               Moreover, not only is the transition at this point abrupt, but the sentence is of
               doubtful grammar, the personal <!--  Add Syriac  --> being used with a feminine
               pronoun. Probably, therefore, a leaf has been lost; but, as what follows is not in
               Mich. and cannot easily be joined on to his text, I leave the text as it stands. A
               leaf ends at this point.</note>
            <note xml:id="n277-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n277-7">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n278-1">This is an awkward construction, and we should perhaps insert a
               word, rendering "resembling us in our passions. "</note>
            <note xml:id="n278-2">1 Cor. xv. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n278-3">1 Cor. xv. 21, 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n278-4">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n278-5">Heb. ii. 14-17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n278-6">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n278-7">Probably some words have dropped out in this sentence.</note>
            <note xml:id="n278-8">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n278-9">It would accord better with the following clause if instead
               of<!--  Add Syriac  --> we read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "the passions and
               miracles."</note>
            <note xml:id="n279-1">Eccles. iii. 14. I owe this reference and the translation of the
               difficult sentence which follows to Dr. Hamilton. I can scarcely think that this
               sentence represents what Severus wrote, but, as Mich. has practically the same, any
               corruption must be older than our author. See p. 277, note 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n279-2">Mich. fol. 175.</note>
            <note xml:id="n279-3">Mich. omits "but," and in place of <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               "parables," has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "the Scripture," making the clause run, "as is
               said in the Scripture in the spirit of Scripture, saying."</note>
            <note xml:id="n279-4">The reference is probably to 1 Cor. xiv. 2, as Dr. Hamilton
               suggests.</note>
            <note xml:id="n279-5">A fragment of the letter not contained in our author is found in
               Add. MS. 12,155, fol. 110, and the whole intervening portion, including this
               fragment, is given in Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n279-6">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n279-7">Sir. xxvii. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-1">Hab. ii. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-3">Ps. cix. 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-6">Heb. xii. 22, 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-7">Sir. xxvii. 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-8">Mich, has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "with the arms of the Spirit,"
               and therefore probably read <!--  Add Syriac  --> instead of <!--  Add Syriac  -->.
               The former, no doubt, represents what Severus wrote.</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-9">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-10">Eph. iv. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-11">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n281-1">Isa. xxvi. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n281-2">Mich. fol. 175 ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n281-3">Judg. i. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n281-4">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               which L. does not print.</note>
            <note xml:id="n281-5">Severus must have written "their open attacks"; but, as Mich. also
               has the singular possessive, we must not emend. See p. 277, note 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n282-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n282-2">Job xxvii. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n282-3">Josh. xxii. 31, iv. 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n282-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n282-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n282-6">Mich. "beyond the other evangelists."</note>
            <note xml:id="n282-7">John xx. 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n282-8">MS. Theopomptus.</note>
            <note xml:id="n282-9">πάντως.</note>
            <note xml:id="n282-10">Mich. "with us.''</note>
            <note xml:id="n283-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n283-2">1 Sam. xi. 1, 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n283-3">Ps. lxxix. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n283-4">Mich. fol. 176, 177 r.</note>
            <note xml:id="n284-1">Possibly we should read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "for us"; so
               Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n284-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n284-3">Rom. viii. 35.</note>
            <note xml:id="n284-4">Jer. i. 9, 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n284-5">Acts ix. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n285-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n285-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n285-3">Lit. "shot at with arrows."</note>
            <note xml:id="n285-4">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n285-5">Isa. xlv. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n286-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n286-2">Mich, "to deceive you in any of our affairs." He read therefore
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <!--  Add Syriac  --> for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, which
               probably represents what Theodosius wrote.</note>
            <note xml:id="n286-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n286-4">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n286-5">I read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. No point
               either above or below the letter is visible in the MS. Mich.
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n286-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n287-1">ἀνάγκη.</note>
            <note xml:id="n287-2">Given in Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n287-3">Mich. fol. 177.</note>
            <note xml:id="n287-4">1 Cor. i. 27, 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n287-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and so it
               appears to be corrected in the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n287-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n287-7">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints. So Mich., though it cannot represent what
               Anthimus wrote.</note>
            <note xml:id="n288-1">Ezek. iii. 17, 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n288-2">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n288-3">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n288-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n288-5">Sir. ii. 10, 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n288-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n288-7">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n288-8">John x. 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n288-9">Or, "wind."</note>
            <note xml:id="n289-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n289-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n290-1">Greg. Naz., Or. xl. 45.</note>
            <note xml:id="n290-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as in the
               parallel passage in ch. 21 (p. 274).</note>
            <note xml:id="n290-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n290-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->; or, perhaps,
               rather omit <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and take <!--  Add Syriac  --> as the antecedent,
               as in ch. 21 (p. 274, note 4).</note>
            <note xml:id="n291-1">Mich. fol. 177 v.</note>
            <note xml:id="n291-2">Jer. xvii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n291-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n291-4">Gal. ii. 20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n291-5">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n291-6">Heb. xi. 25, 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n292-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n292-2">2 Cor. i. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n292-3">1 Thess. iii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n292-4">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> after <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n292-5">Matt. x. 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n292-6">Rom. viii. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n292-7">Perhaps read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "your canonical letter"; so
               Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n292-8">What follows in our text is omitted by Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n293-1">Not in the letter given above (ch. 24), but in the letter of
               Theodosius to Severus upon his election to the see (Brit. Mus. Add. MS. 14,602, fol.
               2-4).</note>
            <note xml:id="n293-2">1 Pet. ii. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n293-3">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> after <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               necessitated by the plural following. So also in the letter to Severus (Add. MS.
               14,602).</note>
            <note xml:id="n293-4">Heb. ii. 14, 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n293-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n294-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n294-2">Mich. fol. 177 v, 178 r.</note>
            <note xml:id="n294-3">οὐσία.</note>
            <note xml:id="n294-4">The sentence, as it stands in the text, is unintelligible, and
               from a comparison with the letter to Severus in Add. 14,602 it is clear that the
               bracketed words have fallen out.</note>
            <note xml:id="n295-1"><!--  Add Syriac  --> has perhaps crept in from below
               (Hamilton).</note>
            <note xml:id="n295-2">I do not know the source of this quotation.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
