<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book" n="12">
            <head>Book 12</head>
            <div type="section" n="12.4">
               <head>Chapter 4</head>
               <p>… earnestly [admonished] her not to do this in a vile manner<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n320-1"/> and injure
                  her spirit on account of the future<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n320-2"/> righteous judgment. And she said to
                  him, " How can I worship Him, when He is not visible and I do not know Him?" And
                  after this one day, while she was in her park<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n320-3"/> (and these things were in
                  her mind<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n320-4"/>), in a fountain of water which was in the park she saw a picture
                  of Jesus our Lord, painted on a linen cloth, and it was in the water; and on
                  taking it out she was surprised that it was not wet. And, to show her veneration
                  for it, she concealed it in the head-dress<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n320-5"/> which she was wearing, and
                  brought it and showed it to the man who was instructing her; and on the head-dress
                  also was imprinted an exact copy of the picture which came out of the water. And
                  one picture came to Cæsarea some time after our Lord's passion, and the other
                  picture was kept in the village of Camulia, and a temple was built in honour of it
                  by Hypatia, who became a Christian. But some time afterwards another woman from
                  the village of Dibudin, mentioned above,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n320-6"/> in the <pb type="page" n="321"
                  />jurisdiction<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n321-1"/> of Amasia, when she learned these things, was moved with
                  enthusiasm, and somehow or other brought one copy of the picture from Camulia to
                  her own village; and in that country men call it "ἀχειροποίητος," that is, "not
                  made with hands"; and, moreover, she also built<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n321-2"/> a temple in honour of it.
                  So much for these things.</p>
               <p>In the twenty-seventh year of the reign of Justinian, the year three,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n321-3"/> a
                  marauding band of barbarians came to the village of Dibudin and burned it and the
                  temple, and carried the people into captivity. And certain earnest men, natives of
                  the country, informed the serene king of these things, and begged him to give a
                  contribution<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n321-4"/> and to have the temple and the village restored(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n321-5"/>
                  and the people ransomed. And he gave what he pleased. But one of the men attached
                  to the king's person in the palace advised him to have the picture of our Lord
                  carried on a circular progress<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n321-6"/> through the cities by these priests, and a
                  sum of money sufficient for the building of the temple and the village collected.
                  And behold! from the year three until the year nine<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n321-7"/> they have been
                  conveying it about.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n321-8"/> And I believe that these things happened under the
                  direction of Providence, because there are two comings of Christ according to the
                  purport of the Scriptures, one in humility, which also took place five hundred and
                  sixty-two years before this year nine, which is also the thirty-third of the reign
                  of Justinian, and a future one in glory, which we are awaiting; and this same
                  thing is a type of the progress<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n321-9"/> of the mystery and picture and wreathed
                  image<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n321-10"/> of the King and Lord of those above and those below, which shall
                  be quickly revealed. And, indeed, I admonish my own self and my brethren, since
                  there is fear <pb type="page" n="322"/>of falling into the hands of God, that
                  every man devote himself to affliction and penitence, for he shall be requited for
                  his deeds; for the coming of our God, the righteous Judge, is already near; to
                  whom with His Father and the Holy Spirit be glory. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="12.5">
               <head>Chapter 5</head>
               <head>The fifth chapter treats of the powder, consistingof ashes, which fell from
                  heaven</head>
               <p>In addition to all the evil and fearful things described above and recorded below,
                  the earthquakes and famines and wars in divers places, and the abundance of
                  iniquity and the deficiency of love and faith, which have happened and are
                  happening, there has also been fulfilled against us and against this last
                  generation the curse of Moses in Deuteronomy, when he admonished the people who
                  had come out of Egypt, when they were just about to enter the land of promise, and
                  said to them, "If thou wilt not hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God, and
                  wilt not observe and do all His statutes and His commandments, which I command
                  thee this day, all these curses shall come upon thee and overtake thee";<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n322-1"/>
                  and a little further on he speaks thus: "The Lord shall give for the rain of thy
                  land powder; and dust from heaven shall He send down upon thee, until He destroy
                  thee. And He shall smite thee before thine enemies; and thy carcase shall be meat
                  unto the fowls of heaven and unto the beasts of the earth, and there shall be no
                  man to fray them away."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n322-2"/></p>
               <p>Such fearful things and more fearful things are coming; for in the year
                  four,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n322-3"/> on the first Sabbath, which is the Sabbath before<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n322-4"/> the
                  feast of unleavened bread, the heavens above us <pb type="page" n="323"/>were
                  covered with stormy(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n323-1"/> clouds, brought by the east winds, and instead of
                  the usual rain and moistening water dropped upon the earth a powder composed of
                  ashes and dust by the commandment of God. And it showed itself upon stones and
                  fell upon walls; and discerning men were in fear and trepidation and anxiety, and
                  instead of the joy of the Passover they were in sorrow, because all the things
                  that are written had been fulfilled against us on account of our sins. Now it was
                  the twenty-eighth year of this king.</p>
               <p>Now, as regards the scope and sequence of the work, the book has brought us down
                  in chronological order as far as the year four; but as to one chapter, concerning
                  an event which happened here at the end of the year one,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n323-2"/> which before
                  this year four we omitted, we have retraced our steps like men on the sea through
                  the violence of the waves and record it briefly, it being as follows:—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="12.6">
               <head>Chapter 6</head>
               <head>The sixth chapter of the twelfth Book, concerning Basiliscus, a presbyter of
                  Antioch, who went to Amida with Audono(?) the duke</head>
               <p>In the summer of the year one,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n323-3"/> when the year was now just drawing to an
                  end, and a council of bishops was being held in the royal city, certain men, their
                  representatives<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n323-4"/> in the cities here, whose names I forbear to record, some
                  of <pb type="page" n="324"/>them, as I think, acting out of jealousy(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n324-1"/>
                  or spite, wrote to their bishops, who were sojourning in the West, in order to
                  please them and also to gratify their ears, saying, "There are certain
                  Schismatics,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n324-2"/> that is, dividers, in the district, and especially in the
                  land between the Rivers, who are holding councils and are, as it were,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n324-3"/>
                  attracting the whole people from one end to the other to join them, and are in
                  separation from our Church." And the bishops there brought the communication which
                  they had received before the king, and he ordered Audono(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n324-4"/> the duke, who
                  was at Hamimtho, to investigate the matter in conjunction with Basiliscus, a
                  presbyter of Antioch; and they were to reconcile them, if willing, to the Church.
                  And, while the matter so stood. Bar Korgis,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n324-5"/> a presbyter of Amida, joined
                  them at Hamimtho; and he assembled the priests and the inhabitants of the villages
                  in the district of the trench and put constraint on them, as<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n324-6"/> well as from
                  the property,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n324-7"/> so to speak, of Dith, a believing man, who had lately
                  died,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n324-8"/> and from Ingilene and Tzophanene. And, when these men reached the
                  city of Amida, then they put pressure on the five chaste cloisters of
                  monks<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n324-9"/> there with the intention of ejecting them; and they spoke with them
                  and listened to them. And they readily met them, and especially the gentle John
                  the archimandrite, of whom we have mentioned<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n324-10"/> that he was
                  providentially<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n324-11"/> present, a Greek and a grammarian, and the earnest
                  Sergius, their visitor; which men stood at their <pb type="page" n="325"/>head,
                  supported by the learned and believing men, John and Sobbo, and Stephen, an
                  archiatros of the city. And they did not expel the cloister societies of monks,
                  but they retired to Izlo.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n325-1"/> And, since Peter, the master of the offices,
                  arrived in the year two,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n325-2"/> and heard from the monks about the threats made
                  against them, he withdrew them. The duke he restrained from again expelling the
                  monks, and censured him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="12.7">
               <head>Chapter 7</head>
               <head>The seventh chapter treats of the map<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n325-3"/> of the world which was made by
                  the diligence of Ptolemy Philometor, king of Egypt</head>
               <p>Yet again about the space of one hundred and thirty years after him Ptolemy
                  Philometor also was honourably moved and exerted himself, and by means of
                  ambassadors and letters and presents, which he sent and dispatched to the rulers
                  of the countries of the nations, he urged them to write down and send to him the
                  limits of the lands under their sway and of the neighbouring peoples, and also a
                  description of their habitations and their customs. And they wrote and sent them
                  to him except the northern region extending to the East <pb type="page" n="326"
                  />and to the West. And we have thought it necessary to write it out here at the
                  end for the understanding of the discerning. And the account is as follows:—</p>
               <p>[At this point follows an epitome of the geography of Claudius Ptolemæus, whom our
                  author has taken for an Egyptian king. As no good purpose would be served by
                  publishing a translation of this section, I omit it. A portion of it is also
                  contained under Zachariah's name in Add. MS. 14,620, fol. 28, with considerable
                  variations from our MS. After the description of the province of Africa this MS.
                  has the curious addition, "and they speak Syriac and Latin." There is another
                  addition to Ptolemy in the notice of the Scenitæ of Arabia Felix,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n326-1"/> where
                  our author adds, "who are called Sabæans," to which 17,202 further adds, "the same
                  is Shʾba," while in place of the Sabæans, whom Ptolemy mentions lower
                  down,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n326-2"/> our author has "the Ofirians, the same is Ofir."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n326-3"/> These
                  additions are of course due to our author himself or some earlier Christian
                  translator; but there are others which point to a difference of reading. Thus in
                  place of "Ἀθάκαι Αἰθίοπες"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n326-4"/> he has "others who live in the water, who eat
                  fruit," and to the notice of the Sachalites he adds, " from whence come pearls,
                  and they sail on the water on bladders," an addition which in Nobbe's text of
                  Ptolemy is printed as the note of a Scholiast.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n326-5"/> Again to the notice of the
                  frankincense country in Ethiopia<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n326-6"/> he adds, "thence comes beet." There are
                  a few other places where our author throws some light on Ptolemy's text. Thus in
                  place of the Πεχῖνοι<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n326-7"/> of Ethiopia he has "cubit-men," and, therefore,
                  perhaps read Πηχῖνοι, while among the tribes of Arabia Felix in the place where
                  Nobbe's text has Δωρηνοί our author's reading<!--  Add Syriac  --> (14,620,
                  <!--  Add Syriac  -->) shows that he read "Δωσαρηνοί," as in the text of <pb
                     type="page" n="327"/>Montanus.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n327-1"/> Other variations from Ptolemy's text
                  are probably due to carelessness or misunderstanding. There is, however, one
                  peculiar variation, of which it is hard to see the origin, in the account of
                  Taprobane, where our author has "and their women are deaf," the corresponding
                  statement in Ptolemy being "ἥ τις ἐκαλεῖτο πάλαι Σιμούνδου, νῦν δὲ Σαλίκη· καὶ οἱ
                  κατέχοντες αὐτὴν κοινῶς Σάλαι, μαλλοῖς γυναικείοις εἰς ἅπαν
                  ἀναδεδεμένοι."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n327-2"/> I continue the translation at p. 336, l. 13, of Land's
                  text.]</p>
               <p>This description of the peoples of the world was made, as recorded above, by the
                  exertions of Ptolemy Philometor and in the thirtieth year of his reign, one
                  hundred and fifty years before the birth of our Saviour, so that the space of time
                  from that day to the present, which is the twenty-eighth year of the reign of
                  Justinian, the serene king of our days, the eight hundred and sixty-sixth year of
                  Alexander, and the three hundred and thirty-third Olympiad,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n327-3"/> will be found
                  to be a space of seven hundred and eleven years. In such a space of time,
                  therefore, how many cities have been built and added among all peoples in the
                  world from the time of Ptolemy down to the present day, and especially since the
                  birth of our Saviour! And peace has reigned among nations and kindreds and
                  tongues, and they have not observed their former custom, nor has nation stood up
                  to make war or to use their swords against nation, nor have they contended in
                  battle, in that the prophecy has been fulfilled in them which says, "They shall
                  beat<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n327-4"/> their swords into plowshares and their spears into
                  pruning-hooks."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n327-5"/></p>
               <p>And besides these there are also in this northern region five believing peoples,
                  and their bishops are twenty-four, and their Catholic lives at Dʾwin, the chief
                  city of Persian Armenia. The name of their Catholic<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n327-6"/> was Gregory, a
                  righteous and a distinguished man.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="328"/>
               <p>Further Gurzan,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n328-1"/> a country in Armenia, and its language is like Greek; and
                  they have a Christian prince, who is subject to the king of Persia.</p>
               <p>Further the country<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n328-2"/> of Arran in the country of Armenia, with a language
                  of its own, a believing and baptized people; and it has a prince subject to the
                  king of Persia.</p>
               <p>Further the country of Sisagan, with a language of its own, a believing people,
                  and there are also heathens living in it.</p>
               <p>The country of Bazgun,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n328-3"/> with a language of its own, which adjoins and
                  extends to the Caspian Gates and sea, the Gates in the land of the Huns. And
                  beyond the Gates are the Bulgarians with their own language, a heathen and
                  barbarous people, and they have cities; and the Alans, and they have five cities;
                  and the men of the race of Dadu(?), and they live on the mountains and have
                  strongholds; the Unnogur, a people living in tents, the Ogor, the Sabir, the
                  Bulgarian,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n328-4"/> the Khorthrigor, the Avar, the Khasar, the Dirmar(?), the
                  Sarurgur(?), the Bagarsik(?), the Khulas(?), the Abdel, the Ephthalite, these
                  thirteen peoples dwelling in tents; and they live on the flesh of cattle and fish
                  and wild beasts and by arms; and beyond them the tribe of the pigmies and of the
                  dog-men, and north-west of them the Amazons,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n328-5"/> women with one breast each,
                  who live entirely by themselves and fight in arms and on horseback; and there is
                  no male among them, but, when they wish to pair, they go<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n328-6"/> in peaceful
                  fashion to a tribe near their country and hold intercourse with them for a month
                  of days and return to their country; and, when they bear a child, if it is a male,
                  they kill it, and, if it is a female, they preserve it alive; and in this way they
                  keep up their ranks. And the tribe which lives near them is the Harus(?), tall,
                  big-limbed(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n328-7"/>' men, who have no weapons of war, and <pb type="page"
                     n="329"/>horses cannot carry them because of the bigness of their limbs(?). And
                  to the east again verging on the north are three other black tribes.</p>
               <p>Now in the land of the Huns about twenty years and more ago some men translated
                  some books into the native tongue; and the origin of it, which the Lord brought
                  about, I will relate as I heard it from certain truthful men, John of Rhesaina,
                  who was in the monastery founded by Ishokuni close to Amida, and Thomas the
                  tanner, who were carried into captivity when Kawad carried away captives fifty
                  years and more ago. And, when they reached the land of the Persians, they were
                  again sold<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n329-1"/> to the Huns and went beyond the gates and were in their
                  country more than thirty years; and they took wives and begot children there. But
                  after about this space of time they returned and told us the story with their own
                  mouths as follows:—</p>
               <p>After the coming of the captives from the land of the Romans, whom the Huns had
                  taken away with them, and after they had been in their country for thirty-four
                  years, then an angel appeared to a man named Kardutsat, bishop of the country of
                  Arran, as the bishop related, and said to him, "Take three pious priests and go
                  out into the plain and receive from me a message sent to thee by the Lord of
                  spirits, because I am guardian of the captives who have gone from the land of the
                  Romans to the land of the nations and have offered up their prayer to God. And he
                  told me what to say to thee." And, when this same Kardutsat, which, when
                  translated into Greek, is Theokletos<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n329-2"/> had gone zealously out into the
                  plain and had…<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n329-3"/> called upon God, he and the three<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n329-4"/> presbyters,
                  then the angel said to them, "Come, go into the land of the nations and warn the
                  children of the dead, and ordain priests for them, and give them the mysteries,
                  and strengthen them; and behold! I am with you and will deal graciously with you
                  there, and signs shall ye do there among <pb type="page" n="330"/>the nations, and
                  all that is needed for your service ye shall find." And four others went with
                  them; and in a country in which no peace is to be found these seven priests from
                  evening to evening found a lodging and seven<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n330-1"/> loaves of bread and a jar of
                  water. And they did not enter by way of the Gates, but were guided over the
                  mountains. And, when they reached the place, they told these things to the
                  captives, and many were baptized, and they made converts among the Huns also. They
                  were there for a week of years,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n330-2"/> and there they translated books into the
                  Hunnic tongue.</p>
               <p>Now at that time Probus happened to be sent on an embassy<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n330-3"/> to those parts
                  by the king, in order to hire some of them to meet the nations in war. And, when
                  he heard from the Huns about these holy men and understood their story also from
                  the captives, he was very eager and desirous to see them. And he saw them, and
                  received a blessing from them, and showed them much honour before the eyes of
                  those nations.</p>
               <p>And our king, when he heard from them<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n330-4"/> the facts recorded above, which the
                  Lord so brought about, loaded thirty mules from the territories of the
                  neighbouring Roman cities and sent them to them, and also flour and wine and oil
                  and linen cloths and other commodities and sacramental vessels. And the animals he
                  gave as a present to them, because Probus was a believing and a kindly man.</p>
               <p>Now another Armenian bishop also, whose name was Maku(?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n330-5"/> was stirred to
                  emulation by such noble deeds and went out after two more weeks of years; and he
                  was honourably moved and went to the country of his own accord and some of his
                  priests with him. And he built a brick church and planted plants and sowed various
                  kinds of seeds and did signs and baptized many. When the rulers of these nations
                  saw something new happening, they admired the men and were greatly pleased with
                  them and honoured them,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n330-6"/> each <pb type="page" n="331"/>one<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n331-1"/> among
                  them inviting them to his own district and his own people, and beseeching them to
                  be his instructors: and behold! they are there to this day. And this same thing is
                  a token of the mercies of God, Who cares for everyone that is His in every place.
                  And henceforth it is the time which is placed in His own power, that the fulness
                  of the peoples may come in, as the apostle said.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n331-2"/></p>
               <p>For for one week of years the king of Persia also, as those who know relate, has
                  separated himself from the eating of things strangled and blood, and from<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n331-3"/>
                  the flesh of unclean beasts and birds, from the time when Tribonian the archiatros
                  came down to him, who was taken captive<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n331-4"/> at that time, and from our serene
                  king came Birowi, a perfect<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n331-5"/> man, and after him Kashowi, and now<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n331-6"/>
                  Gabriel, a Christian of Nisibis. From that time<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n331-7"/> he has understood his
                  food, and his food is not polluted(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n331-8"/> according to the former practice,
                  but rather it is blessed, and then he eats. And Joseph also, the Catholic of the
                  Christians, is high in his confidence, and is closely attached to him, because he
                  is a physician, and he sits before him on the first seat after the chief of the
                  Magians, and whatever he asks of him he receives.</p>
               <p>Out of kindness towards the captives and the holy men he has now by the advice of
                  the Christian physicians attached to him made a hospital,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n331-9"/> a thing not
                  previously known, and has given 100 mules and 50 camels laden with
                  goods(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n331-10"/> from <pb type="page" n="332"/>the royal stores, and 12
                  physicians, and whatever is required is given; and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n332-1"/> in the king's
                  retinue(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n332-2"/>…</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n320-1">As there is room for another letter before <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               and before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, I read <!--  Add Syriac  --> and
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Land’s text is unintelligible.</note>
            <note xml:id="n320-2">There is room for another letter before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and
               we should probably insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n320-3">παράδεισος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n320-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n320-5">φακιόλιον (Brockelmann ποικίλη).</note>
            <note xml:id="n320-6">In the lost beginning of the chapter(?).</note>
            <note xml:id="n321-1">The word <!--  Add Syriac  --> generally expresses metropolitan
               jurisdiction, so that the expression is equivalent to "in the province of
               Helenopontus.''</note>
            <note xml:id="n321-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n321-3">554-5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n321-4">φιλοτιμία.</note>
            <note xml:id="n321-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. I can find no parallel for this use of the
               word in the lexicons, but it may perhaps be so rendered at p. 213, l. 10 (L.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n321-6">ἐγκυκλία.</note>
            <note xml:id="n321-7">561.</note>
            <note xml:id="n321-8">There is perhaps a gap here, as Land marks, though it is not
               certain that there ever was anything written there. So also in the next line.</note>
            <note xml:id="n321-9">ἐγκυκλία.</note>
            <note xml:id="n321-10">λαυρᾶτον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n322-1">Deut. xxviii. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n322-2">Deut. xxviii. 24-26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n322-3">556.</note>
            <note xml:id="n322-4">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n323-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. The adverb <!--  Add Syriac  --> occurs in
               1. 1 (p. 3, l. 22, L.), 7. 6 (p. 215, l. 2), and 7. 9 (p. 224, l. 13); see p. 13,
               note 6. Here, by a slight alteration of meaning, we may render it "violent" or
               "stormy," a meaning supported by the expression <!--  Add Syriac  --> (stormy
               water?), which is quoted by Payne Smith from the Lexicon of Bar ʿAli. We might,
               however, read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "thick," as proposed by Smith on 7. 9. The
               adjective also occurs in 1. 7 (p. 73, 1. 5) as an epithet of words, where the meaning
               seems to be "heated," "violent."</note>
            <note xml:id="n323-2">Summer 553.</note>
            <note xml:id="n323-3">553.</note>
            <note xml:id="n323-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n324-1">I read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as Dr.
               Hamilton suggests.</note>
            <note xml:id="n324-2">ἀποσχίσται.</note>
            <note xml:id="n324-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n324-4">This perhaps represents the Teutonic Audwin or Aldwin ; or we
               might make the easy correction <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and
               translate "Evodian."</note>
            <note xml:id="n324-5">The MS. has .£0.^0X3, not .Ca^.JQjO, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n324-6">It is probable that something has here dropped out.</note>
            <note xml:id="n324-7">οὐσία.</note>
            <note xml:id="n324-8">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n324-9">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n324-10">In the lost portion. After this it is probable that something has
               been lost, since the following statements can hardly apply to John. In this case we
               may render "of whom we have mentioned that […, and X.,] who was providentially
               present."</note>
            <note xml:id="n324-11">By "πρόνοια."</note>
            <note xml:id="n325-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n325-2">553-4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n325-3">σκάριφος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n325-4">Elʿazar is meant.</note>
            <note xml:id="n326-1">Ptol. Geog. vi. 7. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n326-2">Idid. vi. 7. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n326-3">Similarly in place of "τῶν Ἀσαβῶν ὀρῶν" (vi. 7. 24) he has "the
               mountains of Ofir."</note>
            <note xml:id="n326-4">Ptol. Geog. iv. 9. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n326-5">Ibid. vi. 7. 11. Montanus prints it as part of the text, and so it
               is in the Athos MS. reproduced by Langlois. Wilberg brackets it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n326-6">Ibid. iv. 7. 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n326-7">Ibid.</note>
            <note xml:id="n326-8">Ibid. vi. 7. 23. "Δωρηνοί" is the reading of nearly all the
               MSS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n327-1">So in the case of the tribe who in Nobbe's text are called
               Ὀμαγκῖται, and in Montanus' Ὀμανῖται, our author's reading, <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               (14,620, <!--  Add Syriac  -->), though corrupt, is nearer to the latter than the
               former, and nearer still to Ὀμαμῖται, which is read by several MSS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n327-2">Ibid. vii. 4. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n327-3">555.</note>
            <note xml:id="n327-4">The MS. has ^QAjJ, not vQ-i>!J. as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n327-5">Isa. ii. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n327-6">Probably the word "first" has dropped out.</note>
            <note xml:id="n328-1">I.e. Georgia or Iberia.</note>
            <note xml:id="n328-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n328-3">I.e. Abasgia.</note>
            <note xml:id="n328-4">This is probably a corruption or confusion, as the Bulgarians are
               said above to have had cities. The people here meant are perhaps the "Βουρούγουνδοι"
               of Agath. v. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n328-5">Cf. Strabo, xi. 5. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n328-6">The MS. has<!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n328-7"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. This should mean "cut limb from
               limb."</note>
            <note xml:id="n329-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               which L. does not print.</note>
            <note xml:id="n329-2">From Armenian kardal, to call, and Astuats, God.</note>
            <note xml:id="n329-3">MS. apparently <!--  Add Syriac  -->, certainly not
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n329-4">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, without division; there is no
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> before it, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n330-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n330-2">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n330-3">πρεσβεία.</note>
            <note xml:id="n330-4">Perhaps we should read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "from him."</note>
            <note xml:id="n330-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n330-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n331-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n331-2">Rom. xi. 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n331-3">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n331-4">The MS. reading seems to be <!--  Add Syriac  -->, for which we
               must read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n331-5">Only <!--  Add Syriac  --> is visible, but the word must be
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as no other word beginning with those letters suits the
               context.</note>
            <note xml:id="n331-6">L. prints only <!--  Add Syriac  -->; the second letter seems to
               be <!--  Add Syriac  -->: read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n331-7">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n331-8">Only <!--  Add Syriac  --> is visible. I guess at the meaning.
               Perhaps <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n331-9">ξενοδοχεῖον (text ξενόδοχος).</note>
            <note xml:id="n331-10"><!--  Add Syriac  --> possibly, as Payne Smith suggests, =
               κλῆρος; or perhaps κελλάριον, "store-room," might stand for "stores."</note>
            <note xml:id="n332-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n332-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. At this point the MS. breaks off, which
               makes it hard to tell the meaning of this word. The ordinary meaning "division" or
               "half" seems impossible, and I therefore take it to be the other
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> which perhaps = φάλαγξ: cf. Bedjan, Act. Mart, et Sanct. vol.
               ii. p. 540, l. 10, where James, the Persian martyr, is said to have been in the
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> at court. Across the last page of the MS. some illegible words
               are written in another hand.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
