<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book" n="4">
            <head>Book 4</head>
            <div type="section" n="0">
               <p>This fourth Book also, inasmuch as it is from[#n61-1] the History of Zachariah the Rhetorican, relates (in its twelve chapters that are written down distinctly below) and makes known the events occurring after the death of Marcian, and Morian, and Anthemius, and Severus, and Olybrius, who reigned in all twelve years, as the Chronicle testifies — these events (I say) it makes known which took place in Alexandria, and in Ephesus, in the days of Leo, and Leo, during a period of twenty years. It tells about the consecration of Timothy the Great, surnamed the "Weasel." And how Proterius, who was appointed as the successor of Dioscorus by the Synod of Chalcedon, was killed; and how, after his death, his clergy presented a libel to Timothy, and sought to come to the Church; but the zealous priests, on the side of Timothy, and the people would not allow them. Whereupon they went to Rome, and informed Leo about the matter; who wrote a letter to Leo the king censuring the consecration of Timothy.</p>
               <p>But this Book, further, tells about the letter of Timothy to Leo censuring the additions which had been made in the Synod, and the Tome.</p>
               <p>And, moreover, it tells about John, who was the bishop in Ephesus after the resignation of Bassianus; and about the encyclical letter of Leo the king, which he wrote to the bishops, with the object of eliciting from them their written opinions respecting the definitions that were made in the Synod. And they all, with the exception of Amphilochius of Side, wrote in praise of these definitions. [n61-1]Or, "being, so far as it goes, drawn from,'' etc. This may be an intimation that our Syriac text is a compilation of extracts from the original Greek.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="62"/>
               <p>This Book, further, tells how Timothy was banished to Gangra, and from Gangra to Cherson; and that his successor was one of the Proterian party, another Timothy surnamed Salophaciolus.[#n62-1]</p>
               <p>And it, moreover, tells about Isaiah the bishop, and Theophilus the presbyter, who showed themselves to be Eutychians; and about the letter which Timothy wrote respecting them, and by which he exposed them.</p>
               <p>The first chapter tells about the consecration of Timothy the Great, surnamed the " Weasel "; and the events which then occurred.</p>
               <p>The second chapter shows how Proterius was killed, and dragged away; and his body was burned with fire.</p>
               <p>The third chapter explains how after Timothy appeared as the sole bishop, the other clergy also, who were adherents of Proterius, presented a libel by which they showed themselves desirous of coming to the Church; but[#n62-2] the zealous priests, on the side of Timothy, would not allow them.</p>
               <p>The fourth chapter tells how these men, because they were not received by Timothy, got ready and went up to Rome and gave information to the chief priest Leo (respecting the matter).</p>
               <p>The fifth chapter tells about Timothy; and also what happened in Ephesus to John the successor of Bassianus.</p>
               <p>The sixth chapter, moreover, explains about the petition[#n62-3] of Timothy which he wrote to the king, which contained a censure upon Leo and his letter.</p>
               <p>The seventh chapter tells about the replies to the Encyclical respecting the Synod, which were sent to Leo the king by the bishops; and how Amphilochius did not agree with the others in what he wrote.</p>
               <p>The eighth chapter tells about the letter of Anatolius to the king, proving him to have influenced the bishops, as to the purport of their replies respecting the Synod.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="63"/>
               <p>The ninth chapter tells about the banishment of Timothy, and the events which happened at his departure from Alexandria.</p>
               <p>The tenth chapter explains about the other Timothy, who was the bishop of the Proterian party, and was called Salophaciolus.</p>
               <p>The eleventh chapter tells about the removal of Timothy from Gangra to Cherson.</p>
               <p>The twelfth chapter tells about Isaiah and Theophilus, the Eutychians; and about the letter which Timothy wrote respecting them, and by which he exposed them.</p>
               <p>But the time occupied by this Book is two or three years of Leo the First, and seventeen years of Leo the Second, less by two months, as the Chronicle informs us. For Timothy the Great was about two years, more or less, bishop in Alexandria; and then he was banished to Gangra, and after the lapse of eighteen years he returned to his see; and he very soon died.</p>
               <p>This fourth Book is a narrative of the consecration of Timothy, and of the events which occurred in the days of King Leo the First, and Leo the Second.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="64"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
               <head>Chapter 1</head>
               <p>The first chapter of the fourth book, telling about the consecration of Timothy the Great,surnamed Ælurus,[#n64-1] and the events whichhappened then</p>
               <p>The Alexandrian Church being in the condition that we have described above, suddenly the report of the death of Marcian reached them, and they all took courage, and consulted with the whole order of the monks as to whom they should make the bishop of the believing party. For[#n64-2] at that time Dionysius the general[#n64-3] was not there, but was on a visit to Egypt.[#n64-4] And they agreed upon Timothy, a man expert in business[#n64-5] and of ascetic life; who had been brought from the wilderness, by force, to Cyril, and ordained as presbyter by him. Moreover, he was of the same faith as Dioscorus; and he was well versed in all the truth of the faith of the doctors of the Church. This man the people of Alexandria along with the monks seized, and brought to the great Church which is called Cæsarian. And they sought for three bishops, according to the canonical statute, to consecrate him. And since two Egyptian bishops were present, it was necessary that some other bishop should be found. And on making diligent inquiry, some of the people heard of Peter the Iberian, who had left Palestine and was sojourning there in Alexandria. And they ran quickly and laid hold of the man; and carried him on their shoulders, not letting him touch the ground. And as they were bringing him along, a voice was heard in the minds of the clergy, and of the monks, and of the believing citizens, like that voice which Philip heard respecting the eunuch of Candace the queen, saying, "Consecrate him by force, even though he be unwilling, and set him on the throne <pb type="page" n="65"/>of Mark." And he was weak in body through much self- mortification; so that, on account of his emaciation, the Proterian party used jestingly to style him the "Weasel." And when Dionysius the general[#n65-1] heard of the matter, he became uneasy, lest he might receive blame for there being two bishops in the city, when the king heard it. And accordingly he returned, and taking the whole Roman force with him, he made Timothy prisoner. And many were killed. And Dionysius gave orders that they should carry him off to a place called Cabarsarin.[#n65-2] And upon his departure the conflict between the citizens and the Romans became severe.[#n65-3] And there was a great tumult, and slaughters were matters of daily occurrence; more especially as he (Dionysius) kept inciting and urging on[#n65-4] the Romans called Cartadon,[#n65-5] who were passionate men and Arians. And so the custodian of the Church funds expended them upon the Romans who were contending with the people. But it happened that numbers of them and of their wives fell and perished in the conflict. And they were divided into parties, and fought one against another. And when confusion like this had prevailed in the city for many days, Dionysius was at his wits' end, so he brought a certain monk Longinus, celebrated for chastity and virtue, and he intrusted Timothy to him; that he might restore the bishop to the city and to his church, upon the condition that the fighting should cease, and that there should be no more slaughter.</p>
               <p>And when Timothy had returned to the great church from which he had been forcibly removed, and Proterius had taken for himself the church which is called Quirinian, and Easter[#65-6] <pb type="page" n="66"/>time came round, children without number were brought to Timothy to be baptized; so that because of their multitude those who were writing and reading out their names became weary; but only five were brought to Proterius. And the people were so devotedly[#n66-1] attached[#n66-2] to Timothy that they drove Proterius out of the church of Quirinus; and slaughter ensued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="2">
               <head>Chapter 2</head>
               <p>The second chapter shows how Proterius was slain,and dragged through the city; and how his body was, at last, burned with fire</p>
               <p>And[#n66-3] when Proterius continued to threaten the Romans, and to display his rage against them; because they took his gold, but did not fill their hands with the blood of his enemies: then, indeed, a certain Roman was stirred to anger in his heart, and was boiling over with rage; and he invited Proterius to look round and he would show him the corpses of the slain as they lay. And suddenly and secretly, he drew his sword and stabbed Proterius in the ribs along with his Roman comrades, and they despatched him, and dragged him to the Tetrapylum, calling out respecting him as they went along, "This is Proterius." And others suspected that it was some crafty plot. But the Romans left the body, and went away. Then the people, perceiving this, became also greatly excited, and they dragged off the corpse, and burnt it with fire in the Hippodrome. Thus the end of death overtook[#n66-4] Proterius, who had done evil to the Alexandrians, just as George the Arian, and he suffered at their hands in like manner, and so was it done to him.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="67"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="3">
               <head>Chapter 3</head>
               <p>The third chapter tells how, after Timothy appearedas the sole bishop, the other clergy also expressed, by means of a libel, their desire to repent and be united with him; but the people and the zealous priests of his party would not allow them</p>
               <p>But Timothy, when he appeared before them as the only chief priest of Alexandria, showed that he was really what a priest should be. For the silver and the gold that were given to the Romans in the days of Proterius, he expended upon the poor, and the widows, and the entertaining of strangers, and upon the needy in the city. So that, in a short time, the rich men, perceiving his honourable conduct, lovingly and devotedly supplied him with funds,[#n67-1] both gold and silver. But the presbyters and all the clergy belonging to the Proterian party, since they knew all his virtues and his angelic mode of life, and the devotion of the citizens to him, joined themselves together and made libels in which they entreated him that they might be received. They also promised that they would go to Rome to Leo, and admonish him concerning the novelties which he had written in the Tome. Among these persons there were some who were ready and eloquent, and of great wealth and dignity, and of high birth also, who had been called to the clerical order by Cyril; and who were honoured in the eyes of the citizens of Rome; and they presented the petition on their behalf to Timothy. And Eustace of Berytus wrote also recommending their reception.</p>
               <p>But the jealousy and hatred of the citizens against these persons were great, on account of the events which had occurred in the days of Proterius, and the various sufferings which they had endured. So they would not consent to their reception, but they prepared the others to cry out, "Not one <pb type="page" n="68"/>of them shall set his foot here, neither shall the transgressors be received."</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="4">
               <head>Chapter 4</head>
               <p>The fourth chapter tells how these men got ready and went up to Rome, and gave information respecting the treatment which they had suffered</p>
               <p>This was the reason why matters were disturbed and thrown into confusion. For when these men were ignominiously refused, they betook themselves to Rome, and there they told about the contempt of the canons, and about the dreadful death of Proterius; and they said that he died for the sake of the Synod and for the honour of Leo; and that they themselves, also, had endured many indignities; and further, that Timothy had come forward in a lawless manner and taken the priesthood. So they rendered the latter odious, and made the whole business appear disgraceful in the eyes of Leo; and they stirred him up against Timothy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5">
               <head>Chapter 5</head>
               <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="6">
               <head>Chapter 6</head>
               <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7">
               <head>Chapter 7</head>
               <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="8">
               <head>Chapter 8</head>
               <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9">
               <head>Chapter 9</head>
               <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="10">
               <head>Chapter 10</head>
               <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="11">
               <head>Chapter 11</head>
               <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="12">
               <head>Chapter 12</head>
               <p></p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n62-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, "shaking cap"; again (ch. 10) <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "crooked cap," from Σαλοφακίολος, hence I translate uniformly Salophaciolus.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-2">Probably <!--  Add Syriac  --> has dropped out of the text, and the translation should be as in the heading of Chap. III.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. δέησις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. αἴλουρος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-2">Evag. ii. 8; Liberat. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. στρατηγός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-4">I.e. Upper Egypt, see Evag.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. πρακτικός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. στρατηγός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, otherwise called <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <!--  Add Syriac  --> (Life of Peter lb., ed. Raabe, p. 67) = Ταφοσίριον (see Euseb. H. E. vi. 40). Clearly then <!--  Add Syriac  --> τάφος, and the name was taken to mean "Tomb of Osiris" (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-4">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->.I cannot even guess what this word may mean.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, unleavened bread.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-3">Evag. ii. 8; Liberat. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n67-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. οὐσίας.</note>
            <note xml:id="n69-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. χειροτονία.</note>
            <note xml:id="n69-2">Liberat. 15; Evag. ii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-1">Evag. ii. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-2">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. δέησις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71-1">Matt. xxviii. 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71-2">Migne, Patr. Græc. vi. p. 274.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71-4">Matt. xxii. 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n72-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n72-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-1">Imperfectly written in MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->. "Mich. has 'that they hold fast,' reading <!--  Add Syriac  -->; but it is hard to explain the corruption in the text" (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-3">See bk. 7, ch. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-5">Mansi, vol. vii. p. 539 ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-1">Leo, Ep. 156, ch. ii.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-2">Evag. ii. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. στρατηλάτης.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-5">Evag. ii. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-1">Mansi, vol. vii. p. 537.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> i.e. ὑπομνήματα.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-3">Prov. xviii. 3 (LXX).</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for<!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-5">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. πρόσταγμα.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. στρατηγός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-5">Liberat. 15 and 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-7">Perhaps we should read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and trans. “more than ten thousand persons were killed there in the attempt to rescue,” etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. πάραλος, the province of Phœnice Maritima.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, see note 1, p. 62.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-2">Liberat. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. πρόσταγμα.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. δημοτικός</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. Ὀρφανοτροφεῖον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-3">Evag. ii. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. Ὀρφανοτρόφος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n81-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->; and for the defective word<!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-1"> Num. xx. 17; Prov. iv. 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-2">A free quotation from Eccles. vii. 16-18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-4">Ps. cxlii. (Syr. cxli.) 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-7"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  --> as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-8">John i. 42; Matt. xvi. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n83-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. μοχλοί.</note>
            <note xml:id="n83-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n83-3">Heb. ii. 14-18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n83-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n84-1">Orat. ii., contra Arian. 74.</note>
            <note xml:id="n84-2">The words <!--  Add Syriac  --> must have dropped out of the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n84-3">1 Cor. iii. 11, 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n84-4">De Incarn. Dei Verbi (Migne, Patr. Græc. vol. xxviii. p. 25).</note>
            <note xml:id="n85-1">Athan. ad Epict. 8, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n85-2"> Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n85-3">This is the best I can make of it, the text may be corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n85-4">Ibid. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n86-1">Migne, Patr. Lat. vol. viii. p. 874.</note>
            <note xml:id="n86-2">John xvii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n86-3">Migne, Patr. Lat. vol. viii. p. 929.</note>
            <note xml:id="n86-4">John i. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n86-5">1 Cor. vi. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-1">Migne, Patr. Græc. vol. x. p. 1128ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-3">0010, MS., which L. omits.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-4">Supplied from the Greek.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-5">Heb. xiii. 8. This quotation is not in the Greek.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-1">Phil. ii. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-2">Luke xxiv. 36-43; John xx. 19-27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-3">MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, which L. omits.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-4">Migne, Patr. Græc. vol. x. p. 1117. Here Mich. has "of the same."</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-5">This is only an attempt at translating the sentence; a comparison with the Greek shows that the text is corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n89-1">Migne, Patr. Græc. vol. xxix. pp. 673, 680, 681.</note>
            <note xml:id="n89-2">Ibid. vol. xlv. p. 601.</note>
            <note xml:id="n89-3">The source of this quotation we are not able to find.</note>
            <note xml:id="n90-1">Not in any of the extant works of Pseudo-Julius.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-2">De Capt. Eutrop. 8. Here, and at the beginning of the next quotation, Mich. has “of the same,” which must therefore have dropped out of our text (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-3">Ibid. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-4">This quotation does not occur in either of the extant sermons on the Nativity.</note>
            <note xml:id="n92-1"> Migne, Patr. Græc. vol. xxviii. p. 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n92-2"> Probably for <!--  Add Syriac  --> we should read <!--  Add Syriac  --> (Gk. υἱὸν Θεοῦ), and transl. "two dwelling together, One the Son of God, of the same nature," etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="n92-3"> Gal. i. 8, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n92-4">Sixth Paschal Letter, Migne, Patr. Græc. vol. Ixv. p. 60.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-1">The Greek οὐρανίου λαβόμενος σώματος shows that for <!--  Add Syriac  --> we should read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-2">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  --> (Gr. πηλῷ), and for <!--  Add Syriac  --> read<!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-3">This and the latter part of the preceding are probably from the lost part of the fifth Paschal Letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-4">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-1">Heb. ii. i6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-2">Migne, Pair. Grac. vol. Ixxvi. p. 372.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-3">The rest is not in the Greek. Mich, has "OF THE SAME," which must therefore have dropped out of our text (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-1">Cyr. Ep. 46. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-2">We must insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->; the Greek is ποῦ τὸ τέλειον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-3"> For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, Gk. εἰ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-4">Mark v. 41.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-5">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, L., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-7">Pusey's Libr. of the Fathers (Cyr. 5 Tomes, p. 368); cf. Migne, Patr. Græc. 76, p. 1429, where, however, the extract begins after this sentence.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-8">John vi. 48.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. ὕπαρχοι.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. φάλσον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-4">A word has been erased here from the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-1"><!--  Add Syriac  --> MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-2">1 John iv. 1-3; 2 John 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-3">2 John 10, 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-4">Gal. i. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-5">Tit. iii. 10, 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-1">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  --> (or <!--  Add Syriac  -->, Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-3">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-4"><!--  Add Syriac  --> i.e. στάσις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-1">The MS. here adds <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "Fourth Book."</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
