<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book" n="6">
            <head>Book 6</head>
            <div type="section" n="6.0">
               <p>The sixth Book taken from the work of <persName>Zachariah</persName>, containing seven chapters.</p>
               <p>The first tells about the Separatists<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n132-1"/> from the communion of <persName>Peter</persName>,
                  because he received the Henotikon.</p>
               <p>The second tells of <persName>Cosmas</persName> the Spatharius who was sent by <persName>Zeno</persName>; and the
                  transactions which took place in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> with the seceding monks.</p>
               <p>In the third there is an account of <persName>Peter</persName> and <persName>Isaiah</persName> the monk.</p>
               <p>In the fourth we are told about <persName>Arsenius</persName> the prefect, who was sent to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>;
                  and how he acted towards the Separatists.</p>
               <p>Then the fifth tells of the letter of Fravitta, who was bishop in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>,
                  to <persName>Peter</persName>.</p>
               <p>The sixth contains a record of the letter of <persName>Peter</persName> to <persName>Fravitta</persName>.</p>
               <p>The seventh gives information respecting the chief priests who were in the days of
                  <persName>Zeno</persName>; and also concerning the length of <persName>Zeno</persName>'s life.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="133"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="6.1">
               <head>Chapter 1</head>
               <head>The first chapter of this sixth Book tells about those who seceded from the
                  communion of <persName>Peter</persName>, because there was no express anathemaof the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>
                  and the Tome of <persName>Leo</persName>, either in the Henotikon or in the letters of the chief priests
                  to him</head>
               <p>Matters having been thus arranged by the king's Henotikon, and three or four of
                  the chief priests, namely, the bishops of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, and of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, and of
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, together with the bishops in their jurisdictions,
                  being united and agreed together according to the purport of this Henotikon of
                  <persName>Zeno</persName>, and having received and subscribed to it; then <persName>Julian</persName> and <persName>John</persName>, presbyters
                  of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and <persName>Helladius</persName> and <persName>Serapion</persName>, deacons, venerable men belonging to the
                  Church there, and <persName>Theodore</persName> the bishop of <placeName>Antinoe</placeName>, and <persName>John</persName> and another Egyptian,
                  and <persName>Andrew</persName> the great archimandrite,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n133-1"/> and <persName>Paul</persName> the Sophist, and other
                  illustrious monks, seceded from the communion of <persName>Peter</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>. But they
                  took this course because there was no clear and decided anathema of the Synod and
                  the Tome, either in the Henotikon or in the letters of the chief priests to <persName>Peter</persName>.
                  And gradually the number of these Separatists was increased, and they received a
                  considerable accession to their numbers in the monastery. And <persName>Acacius</persName> of the royal
                  city, having heard it, wrote to urge them to be reunited.</p>
               <p>But <persName>Peter</persName> in his public address,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n133-2"/> and the other apologies which he made
                  before the people, continued to revile the Synod. And, at length, <persName>Acacius</persName> heard
                  this also, and he sent his presbyter to inquire into the freedom and the faith of
                  <persName>Peter</persName>. And there ensued an investigation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n133-3"/> before the judge<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n133-4"/> of the
                     <pb type="page" n="134"/>city on this point, that the Synod had not been
                  expressly anathematised by <persName>Peter</persName>, and the report of this reached the ears of many
                  and proved a stumbling-block to them. And many demands were made of him by the
                  seceding archimandrite and bishop. Then <persName>Peter</persName> the Iberian, the bishop of <placeName>Gaza</placeName>, who
                  was sojourning there, and <persName>Elijah</persName> the monk, surnamed the potter, were appointed to
                  consider and examine into these matters. And having examined into them, together
                  with the council of the monks, they selected four of <persName>Peter</persName>'s discourses concerning
                  the faith, and they said to him, <quote>If thou dost agree to these, sign them</quote>; and he
                  signed them. Whereupon several of them entered into communion with him, because he
                  thereby anathematised the Synod and the Tome, when he delivered those discourses
                  in the ears of the people. However, the others remained unwilling to hold
                  communion with <persName>Peter</persName>. And the latter, seeing this, took away the monastery of
                  Bishop Theodore, and thrust out that wonderful man, who had opened the eyes of a
                  blind man by the aspersion of water from the baptismal font. Upon which there
                  arose a great agitation among the monks, and they sent <persName>Nephalius</persName>, who was one of
                  those that had been ejected by <persName>Peter</persName>, and was also a disturber of the people, to
                  <persName>Zeno</persName> the king.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="6.2">
               <head>Chapter 2</head>
               <head>The second chapter of his sixth Book tells about <persName>Nephalius</persName>, who went up to the
                  king, and madea complaint against <persName>Peter</persName>; and how <persName>Cosmas</persName> the Spatharius was sent (to
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>), and whatwas done upon his entry there</head>
               <p><persName>Nephalius</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n134-1"/> a monk,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n134-2"/> and by his disposition and habits a disturber
                  of the people, made preparations and went up to <persName>Zeno</persName> the king, bringing with him a
                  letter from his fellow <pb type="page" n="135"/>Separatists; in which they
                  testified against <persName>Peter</persName> that he had plundered<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n135-1"/> them, and ejected them, and
                  taken away their monasteries.</p>
               <p>And the king, when he heard it, was very angry with <persName>Peter</persName>, and sent <persName>Cosmas</persName> his
                  Spatharius with a letter containing threats against <persName>Peter</persName>, and declaring that his
                  Majesty had been so indulgent as to appoint him the bishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, with the
                  object of uniting the people together, and not keeping them divided into two
                  parts.</p>
               <p>And <persName>Cosmas</persName> having arrived, in company with <persName>Nephalius</persName>, and the letter having been
                  delivered to <persName>Peter</persName>: then the monks assembled at the Martyr Church of <persName>St. Euphemia</persName>,
                  to the number of about thirty thousand, and ten bishops with them. But a message
                  was sent to them, that they should not enter the city lest the people should be
                  excited, and a tumult<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n135-2"/> should ensue. However, <persName>Theodore</persName> the bishop, and
                  <persName>John</persName>, and <persName>Julian</persName> and <persName>John</persName> the presbyters, and <persName>Palladius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n135-3"/> and <persName>Serapion</persName> the
                  deacons, and <persName>Andrew</persName> the Great, and <persName>Paul</persName> the Sophist, with about two hundred
                  archimandrites, were selected as representatives; and they entered the great
                  church to have an interview with <persName>Peter</persName>. Then they had a long conversation with
                  <persName>Cosmas</persName> the <persName>Spatharius</persName> and the prefect of the city. And the king's letter was read
                  aloud.</p>
               <p>Then <persName>Peter</persName> delivered an apologetic address to them, anathematising, in their ears,
                  the Synod and the Tome. And he further wrote in his own hand to the following
                  effect: I, <persName>Peter</persName>, the bishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, do now, as I have often before,
                  anathematise all that was said and devised in <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> against the true faith of
                  the holy fathers, the three hundred and eighteen bishops; and also the Tome of
                  <persName>Leo</persName>. And I confess that these are my own works, and that anyone not agreeing with
                  them, whether bishop, or presbyter, or deacon, or monk, or layman, is an alien.
                  And if I (or any other person) shall ever write in agreement with the transactions
                  of the Synod and the contents of the Tome, I shall become thereby a castaway from
                  the Holy Trinity."</p> <!-- [Ending quote but no starting quote found] -->
               <pb type="page" n="136"/>
               <p>However, the monks would not accept this confession, for they said that <persName>Peter</persName>
                  associated in communion with the chief priests, who had uttered no express
                  anathema against the Synod and the Tome, as he had done.</p>
               <p>And Peter replied, "My reason for holding communion with them is that they have <!-- [Quote Starts but does not finish] -->
                  accepted the king's Henotikon, which cancels all additions, and the transactions
                  of every place, except the three holy Synods, I mean those of <placeName>Nicea</placeName>, <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, and
                  <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. And in my public address I explained the Henotikon, and showed you
                  how it nullified the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, by accepting the twelve Heads of the
                  blessed <persName>Cyril</persName>, and by anathematising <persName>Nestorius</persName>, and <persName>Eutyches</persName>, and every other who
                  would assert the duality of the Natures in <persName>Christ</persName>, and would ascribe the miracles
                  to one and the sufferings to the other, and would divide the Persons in properties
                  and in operations.</p>
               <p>But after all this discussion, even then only a few of the monks consorted with
                  Peter. And the others presented a libel against him to <persName>Cosmas</persName>. And they took their
                  monasteries and dwelt in them, assembling by themselves. But they endeavoured to
                  appoint a bishop instead of <persName>Peter</persName>. However, <persName>Theodore</persName> the bishop, being an orderly
                  man, restrained them, saying, <quote>It is not fitting treatment for one who believes as
                  we do, and anathematises the Synod and the Tome (even though he may hold communion
                  with those that have received and signed the Henotikon), lest we be blamed for
                  rejecting him, and be accounted as disorderly persons.</quote> But they say that <persName>Theodore</persName>
                  took this course because he was one of the bishops who laid hands upon <persName>Peter</persName>.</p>
               <p>The people, however, since they received <persName>Peter</persName> without dispute when he
                  anathematised the Synod, were greatly incensed against the monks. But they were
                  restrained by the chiefs and by <persName>Peter</persName>, so that there was no public tumult.</p>
            </div> 
            <pb type="page" n="137"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="6.3">
               <head>Chapter 3</head>
               <head>The third chapter tells how <persName>Cosmas</persName>, when returning to the king, passed through
                  to <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, inorder to take with him <persName>Peter</persName> the Iberian and <persName>Isaiah</persName> the monk,
                  according to the king’s orders</head>
               <p>But <persName>Cosmas</persName> on his return passed through <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, and sought for <persName>Peter</persName> the
                  Illustrious and <persName>Isaiah</persName> the able<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n137-1"/> monk. However, he could not find <persName>Peter</persName>,
                  because the latter had previous intimation of his coming, and had departed from
                  before him.</p>
               <p>But <persName>Isaiah</persName> prayed to God that a sickness might overtake him; lest, if he were to
                  go up to the royal city, he might show himself a flatterer of the rich men there.
                  And so it befell him.</p>
               <p>And when <persName>Cosmas</persName> reached him and gave him the king's letter, he showed him his
                  sickness and infirmity, saying, <quote>As I am a sick man, I cannot possibly endure to
                  embark upon the sea, lest I die at once. And then I could not appear before the
                  king; and you would be censured both by God and the king if you were to carry a
                  corpse round the world.</quote> And in this way he succeeded in escaping. And shortly
                  afterwards he recovered. And he persevered in the exercise of his habits, and of
                  his conflicts all the days of his life. This man was indeed a seer, a sharer (as
                  we may say) in the name and in the actions of the prophet <persName>Isaiah</persName>.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="138"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="6.4">
               <head>Chapter 4</head>
               <head>The fourth chapter tells how <persName>Arsenius</persName> was sent asprefect to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> by the
                  king, when thelatter learned the state of affairs from <persName>Cosmas</persName> respecting the
                  Separatist monks andthe orders then given by the prefect</head>
               <p>When <persName>Cosmas</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n138-1"/> the Spatharius returned to the king, and presented a written
                  communication informing him of the affairs in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and about the Separatist
                  monks, and their leaders, and the bishops; then he sent <persName>Arsenius</persName> there as prefect,
                  and also gave him authority over the Romans. And he ordered that <persName>Theodore</persName> and <persName>John</persName>
                  the bishops, and <persName>Agathon</persName>, and <persName>Julian</persName>, and <persName>John</persName> the presbyters, and <persName>Helladius</persName> and
                  <persName>Serapion</persName> the deacons, and <persName>Paul</persName> and <persName>Andrew</persName> the archimandrites, and all the others
                  should be called to unity, according to the terms of the faith laid down in the
                  Henotikon, once or twice, by <persName>Peter</persName> the bishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>; and that, in the
                  event of their refusing to join in communion with him, they should be ejected from
                  their monasteries.</p>
               <p>And upon the arrival of <persName>Arsenius</persName>, this <persName>Nephalius</persName>, the disturber of the people,
                  again attached himself to him. Then he brought together the bishops and the
                  presbyters and the archimandrites; and he showed them the king's command, which he
                  read aloud in their hearing. And <persName>Peter</persName> also readily repeated to them his
                  explanation and anathema, at the same time entreating them to join in communion
                  with himself However, they would neither accept nor be satisfied with this. But
                  <persName>Theodore</persName> the bishop said to him, <quote>If you make a written statement abjuring the
                  communion of the other chief priests and sign it,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n138-2"/> then we will enter into
                  communion with you.</quote> And <persName>Peter</persName>, in reply, made the same defence as before, saying,
                  <quote>It is right for me to associate with those who receive the Henotikon, which
                  teaches the true faith.</quote></p>
               <pb type="page" n="139"/>
               <p>Whereupon these men were compelled by <persName>Arsenius</persName> to go to the king, and personally
                  to lay their petitions and wishes before him; so that then his command might be
                  fully carried out. And they all went, with the exception of <persName>Theodore</persName>, who withdrew
                  himself. And when they appeared before the king, he was astonished both at their
                  chastity and at their reasoning with him about everything which was displeasing to
                  them in his transactions.</p>
               <p>But while they were there, <persName>Acacius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n139-1"/> the bishop of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> died. And
                  <persName>Fravitta</persName> was appointed as his successor; a gentle and believing man, who wrote a
                  letter, after the canonical manner, and sent it by some clergy, to <persName>Peter</persName> of
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>. And <persName>Peter</persName> received it gladly; and he also wrote a reply, in which he
                  expressly anathematised the Synod and the Tome of <persName>Leo</persName>. And while this was on its
                  way, <persName>Fravitta</persName> died. And <persName>Euphemius</persName>, a man of <placeName>Apamea</placeName>, who was educated at
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, was appointed as his successor. However, he was tainted with the
                  Nestorian heresy.</p>
               <p>And when he received the letter he was very indignant. And he was even angry with
                  <persName>Longinus</persName> the presbyter and <persName>Andrew</persName> the deacon, the clergy who conveyed this letter;
                  and he brought an accusation against them. But they deprecated his accusation by
                  showing the zeal of the people of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>. And <persName>Euphemius</persName> severed himself from
                  <persName>Peter</persName>'s communion; and he sought to bring about the deprivation of <persName>Peter</persName>,
                  intending for that purpose to convene a separate Synod. But <persName>Archelaus</persName> the bishop
                  of <placeName>Caesarea</placeName>, a man of wonderful learning, restrained him, saying, <quote>It is not
                  possible for the great bishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> to be accused and ejected by a Synod
                  of one province; only a General Council could do that.</quote> But when <persName>Peter</persName> heard it,
                  he also uttered threats against <persName>Euphemius</persName>; that, just as the blessed <persName>Cyril</persName> had
                  sent <persName>Nestorius</persName> to <placeName>Oasis</placeName>, so he would in like manner eject <persName>Euphemius</persName> from his see.
                  However, <persName>Peter</persName> also departed this life. But his letter was seen<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n139-2"/> in
                  <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and it convinced many that he was a believer. And <persName>John</persName> and <persName>Julian</persName>
                  the Alexandrians, and the rest of their associates who happened to be there, the
                  Separatists, on seeing <pb type="page" n="140"/>his letter to <persName>Fravitta</persName>, changed
                  their minds; and they were ready on their return to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> to join in
                  communion with him. But while they were returning, he died. And his
                  successor<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n140-1"/> was Athanasius, an eloquent, believing, and peace- loving man.
                  He, desiring and exerting himself to bring the Separatist monks into communion
                  with the Church, in the course of his address to the people mentioned the names of
                  <persName>Dioscorus</persName> and <persName>Timothy</persName>, but he purposely omitted to mention the name of <persName>Peter</persName> in
                  order to try them. Whereupon they became greatly excited (and they would not be
                  quiet) until he named <persName>Peter</persName> also in his discourse.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="6.5">
               <head>Chapter 5</head>
               <head>The fifth chapter of this Book gives the letter of <persName>Fravitta</persName> of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>
                  to <persName>Peter</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, in the following terms</head>
               <p><quote>To our holy father, and God-loving fellow-minister, <persName>Peter</persName>, from <persName>Fravitta</persName>, who
                  sends greetings in the Lord. When I weigh mine own natural weakness, and I wonder
                  at the merciful acts of God towards me, I truly perceive that it is absolutely(?)
                  that <quote>He raises up the poor from the dunghill to set him with the princes of the
                  people.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n140-2"/> And it is well known that this mercy of God is not the
                  consequence of any meritorious deeds on man's part; but that it results from the
                  divine grace which arises, time after time, upon the sons of the Church, through
                  the love of the Father. So that it is not the wise, nor the disputers, nor the
                  eloquent of this world whom grace raises up as leaders by the election.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Now, before the Law, <persName>Abel</persName>, though not learned,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n140-3"/> was acceptable to God; as
                  were also the righteous fathers who came after him. But under the Law, grace
                  marked out shepherds and herdsmen, and gatherers of sycamore fruit,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n140-4"/> and
                  raised them up as prophets. And after the Law, the same <pb type="page" n="141"
                  />grace appointed fishermen, and a tent-maker, to be the preachers of the living
                  word from heaven. That thus the power of God might be truly known to be made
                  manifest and perfect in the weak. And such are the mysteries of Christians who
                  hold fast the Incarnation of <persName>Christ</persName>; according to His own word in the Gospel, <quote>I
                  thank Thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, that Thou hast hidden these things
                  from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them unto babes: even so, Father, for
                  such is Thine own will.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n141-1"/></p>
               <p><quote>For <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> our God is the foundation and the corner-stone of the Holy
                  Church. And therefore these blessings, which we have received, are not a strange
                  display of His mercy. But we hope<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n141-2"/> that from them we shall understand His
                  equal mercy towards other men; and we shall show ourselves gentle and kind to our
                  brethren in the flesh and in the faith, and to the priests who are our
                  fellow-ministers and <persName>Christ</persName>-loving brothers. Thus we shall endeavour<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n141-3"/> to
                  rule the Holy Church everywhere in the same right faith, and in perfect love. And
                  by the events which are taking place (the Lord helping us) we shall show the
                  rational flock which has been intrusted to our care in all places to be one; that
                  of the Great Shepherd, Who has appointed us to be the leaders of His flock. And we
                  shall drive out those grievous wolves, the accursed heresies, more especially of
                  <persName>Nestorius</persName> and <persName>Eutyches</persName>, by preaching and holding the faith of the holy fathers,
                  who maintained the truth and preserved the order of the Church, and in our day
                  teaching the right faith to the people and to mankind, as well as they.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>But, using brotherly love and concord in my salutation, I now present to thy
                  Holiness the pledge of my affection, by the hands of <persName>Longinus</persName> the presbyter and
                  <persName>Andrew</persName> the deacon. And to complete what is right, I send my greetings to all the
                  pastors, and the honourable priests, and the chaste monks, and the believing
                  people of thy jurisdiction. We, <pb type="page" n="142"/>moreover, entreat thy
                  Holiness to pray along with us, that we may show ourselves wise men and rulers in
                  all matters, like <persName>Solomon</persName>, and like <persName>Paul</persName> and <persName>Peter</persName> and the rest of the apostles,
                  in preaching the truth to the sons of the Church; and that in everything about
                  which you refer to us, we may be able, to the best of our ability, to render
                  fitting aid to the other Churches; and also in those matters taking place in the
                  <persName>Christ</persName> - loving city, through the enactment of the <persName>Christ</persName>-loving and indulgent
                  king, who is watchful and studious and desirous to bring about the peace of the
                  Churches, and the concord of the priests, and the unity of the people.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>I and the brethren with me send our best respects to thy Chastity, and to the
                  brethren with thee.</quote></p>
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter" n="6.6">
               <head>Chapter 6</head>
               <head>The sixth chapter of this sixth Book tells aboutthe letter of <persName>Peter</persName> the bishop
                  of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, which he wrote in reply to <persName>Fravitta</persName> of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, in the
                  following terms</head>
               <p><quote>To my pious and God-loving brother and fellow-minister, my lord <persName>Fravitta</persName>, from
                  <persName>Peter</persName>, who sends greetings in the Lord.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>In consequence of the election of thine Eminence, it is time now for us to say,
                  <quote>Ye heavens above be glad, and let the earth with her fulness rejoice, and let her
                  sing with<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n142-1"/> joy,</quote> according to the word of the prophet.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n142-2"/></p>
               <p><quote>For also, our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, Who is the one only-begotten Son of God the
                  Father, has not redeemed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n142-3"/> us with corruptible things, as silver and gold;
                  but He rather laid down His life for us, as a lamb without blemish; and He offered
                  a sacrifice of sweet savour to God His Father; and <pb type="page" n="143"/>gave
                  His body as a substitute for the life of the whole human race. He Who is honoured
                  by all creation, and is equal to the Father, God the Word, became incarnate; yet
                  He suffered thereby no variation nor change; but He as man remains the same, and
                  He is in truth alive for ever, the Word of His Father, and of the same nature.
                  Come then, as with one tongue and one believing, <persName>Christ</persName>-loving mind, let us offer
                  to Him thanksgiving, and say with the blessed <persName>Baruch</persName>, <quote>This is our God, there is
                  none other beside Him. He found out the whole way of wisdom, and gave it to <persName>Jacob</persName>
                  His servant, and to <placeName>Israel</placeName> His beloved. And afterwards. He appeared upon the
                  earth, and had converse with men.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n143-1"/> For there was not indeed One the Son
                  of God, Who existed before the times and ages, through Whom all things were made;
                  and another who, in the last time, was born in the flesh from the Theotokos;
                  according to the notion of <persName>Nestorius</persName>. But rather He, being the same, took the seed
                  of <persName>Abraham</persName>, according to the word of the blessed <persName>Paul</persName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n143-2"/> and also He was
                  partaker of our flesh and blood, and was made like us in all points, sin only
                  excepted. For neither do we say that the body of our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is from
                  heaven, as <persName>Eutyches</persName> in his folly affirms; nor that He became incarnate in
                  semblance or imagination; on the contrary, we anathematise all such teachers. But
                  we confess one only-begotten Son of God the Father, Who is our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>.
                  And we know that He, God the Word of the Father, Who became incarnate for our
                  redemption, in His divine nature took the likeness of a servant, by the
                  dispensation.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>This is the faith of the Church of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, by which we are all adorned, both
                  we, and the God-fearing bishops and clergy, and the monks, and all the people of
                  God. And the congregation of the people grows and multiplies exceedingly in the
                  Churches, while we are obedient to the apostle, who says, <quote>If any man shall preach
                  to you any other gospel than what we have preached, let him be
                  accursed.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n143-3"/></p>
               <p><quote>But the cause of all these blessings so dear and acceptable to us, was the
                  election of thy <persName>Piety</persName>'s Eminence, which <pb type="page" n="144"/>has been
                  mentioned above; and also the goodwill of the believing and <persName>Christ</persName>-loving King
                  <persName>Zeno</persName>, who consented to thine election. And he also, for the sake of the unity of
                  the people, and that we might be established in power and in the truth, by what he
                  wrote so faithfully in the Henotikon, anathematised all the rash thoughts and
                  words of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and the Tome of <persName>Leo</persName>.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And we consent to this same document; and we preach it, by word of mouth and by
                  writing, to the believing nations; as also our ever-memorable and holy brother and
                  fellow-minister <persName>Acacius</persName> was seen to hold and teach until his death, when the
                  Alexandrians testified to us his true faith, as thy Holiness is also persuaded.
                  For it is right for the <persName>Christ</persName>-loving king, not only to subdue enemies, and to set
                  the Barbarian races beneath his feet; but also to expose the snares of these
                  intellectual enemies, and to cause the true faith to shine upon the believing
                  people. For thy Holiness has risen up and bloomed forth for us like the plant of
                  peace. And this is the gift of the believing king to us, by the will of God, Who
                  chose him before, as we have already said. And, therefore, we are delighted at
                  this, that such a good priest should arise and appear for the believing nations.
                  May God keep him, and may He adorn him with the heavenly crown by His own rich
                  Hand, as we hope and pray that he may be found walking in the whole way of the
                  truth, in the footsteps of the holy fathers, a believing chosen priest, by the
                  mercy of our Saviour <persName>Christ</persName>, through Whom, to the Father, with the Holy Spirit, be
                  glory for evermore!</quote></p>
               <p><quote>But we welcomed affectionately the bearers of the letter of thy Righteousness the
                  excellent <persName>Longinus</persName> the presbyter and <persName>Andrew</persName> the deacon; and we now send them back
                  in peace to thy Holiness.</quote></p>
               <p>But <persName>Athanasius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n144-1"/> also wrote in the same strain, two years afterwards, to
                  <persName>Palladius</persName>, who was <persName>Peter</persName>'s successor in <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, expressly anathematising the
                  Synod, and quoting freely from the Henotikon.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n144-2"/></p>
               <pb type="page" n="145"/>
               <p>And <persName>John</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n145-1"/> was appointed as the successor of <persName>Athanasius</persName>; and when anyone
                  would ask<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n145-2"/> him to give an anathema of the Synod and the Tome in writing,
                  he would give it cheerfully and without fear. Now <persName>Flavian</persName>, who was the successor
                  of <persName>Palladius</persName> in <persName>Antioch</persName>, sent <persName>Solomon</persName>, a presbyter of his Church, to this <persName>John</persName> of
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>. And <persName>Solomon</persName> asked <persName>John</persName> for a letter to <persName>Flavian</persName>, concerning the concord
                  in the faith. But <persName>John</persName> would not consent to do this for him, until he should
                  receive from him a sworn statement that he would send him a letter from <persName>Flavian</persName> in
                  which there would be an anathema of the Synod and the Tome. And <persName>John</persName>, his namesake
                  and successor, was believing and acting in like manner.</p>
               <p>Now after <persName>Zeno</persName> had reigned seventeen years, and matters had been thus carried on
                  in the Church; and also the tyrants <persName>Basiliscus</persName> and <persName>Marcus</persName> had risen up against
                  him, and been driven out, as we have related above; and again, <persName>Illus</persName> and <persName>Leontius</persName>
                  and <persName>Euprepius</persName> had rebelled against him and been slain in the East; and again, in
                  his days, one <persName>Theodoric</persName> a tyrant had taken captives from <placeName>Thrace</placeName> and many other
                  places, and had gone to <placeName>Rome</placeName> and subdued it, because <persName>Odoacer</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n145-3"/> the
                  Anti-<persName>Caeesar</persName> there fled before him to <placeName>Ravenna</placeName> a city of <placeName>Italy</placeName>; <persName>Zeno</persName> died in the
                  year eight hundred and two, according to the Greek mode of reckoning.</p>
               <p>And <persName>Anastasius</persName>, his successor, received the kingdom on the fourth day of the Great
                  Week; when <persName>Euphemius</persName> was the bishop of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>; and <persName>Flavian</persName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>; and
                  <persName>Athanasius</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>; and <persName>Sallustius</persName>, the successor of <persName>Martyrius</persName>, of
                  <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>; and <persName>Felix</persName>, the successor of <persName>Simplicius</persName>, of <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="6.7">
               <head>Chapter 7</head>
               <head>The seventh chapter tells who were the chief priests in the days of <persName>Zeno</persName></head>
               <p>But the following were the chief priests in the days of <persName>Zeno</persName>. In <placeName>Rome</placeName>, after
                  <persName>Hilarus</persName>, <persName>Simplicius</persName>, the author of the <pb type="page" n="146"/>letter to <persName>Zeno</persName>
                  respecting <persName>John</persName> the liar, who was ejected from <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>; and after him <persName>Felix</persName>,
                  who was still living when <persName>Anastasius</persName> became the emperor.</p>
               <p>In <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, <persName>Timothy</persName> the Great, who was recalled from banishment; and <persName>Timothy</persName>
                  <persName>Salophiaciolus</persName>; and <persName>John</persName>, who was forthwith ejected; and <persName>Peter</persName>; and his successor,
                  <persName>Athanasius</persName>.</p>
               <p>In <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, <persName>Anastasius</persName>; and <persName>Martyrius</persName>; and <persName>Sallustius</persName>.</p>
               <p>In <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, <persName>Martyrius</persName>, who was ejected; and <persName>Julian</persName>; and <persName>Stephen</persName>; and the other
                  <persName>Stephen</persName>; and <persName>Peter</persName> the Believer; and <persName>Calandion</persName>, who was ejected; and <persName>Palladius</persName>;
                  and <persName>Flavian</persName>, his successor, who was ejected in the days of <persName>Anastasius</persName>.</p>
               <p>In <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, after <persName>Gennadius</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n146-1"/> <persName>Acacius</persName>; and <persName>Fravitta</persName>, his successor;
                  and <persName>Euphemius</persName>, his successor, who was ejected in the days of <persName>Anastasius</persName>.</p>
               <p>But in this sixth Book and in the fifth Book preceding it, which have been
                  translated concisely and briefly (so to speak) in contracted style, for the
                  information of the Syriac reader, from the Greek History of <persName>Zachariah</persName> the
                  Rhetorician; which he wrote thus far, in protracted style, after the manner of
                  Greek amplification;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n146-2"/> there is a period of seventeen years, comprising
                  only the life of the Emperor <persName>Zeno</persName>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>                  
            <note xml:id="n132-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀποχίσται</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n133-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n133-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">προσφώνησις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n133-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρᾶξις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n133-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔκδικος</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n134-1">Evag. iii. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n134-2">A similar account of him is given in das Leben des Severus (ed.
               Spanuth), pp. 26 and 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n135-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n135-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στάσις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n135-3">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> we should probably read
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <persName>Helladius</persName>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n137-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρακτικός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n138-1">Evag. iii. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n138-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, L. The MS. is indistinct, probably we
               should read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n139-1">Evag. iii. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n139-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n140-1">Evag. iii. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n140-2">Ps. cxiii. 7, 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n140-3">So MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n140-4">Amos vii. 14 (Syriac).</note>
            <note xml:id="n141-1">Luke x. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n141-2">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and for
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->. The whole passage is difficult to
               translate, owing to defects in the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n141-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n142-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n142-2">It seems to be a free quotation from Isa. xliv. 23 or xlix.
               13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n142-3">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n143-1">Bar. iii. 35-37.</note>
            <note xml:id="n143-2">Heb. ii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n143-3">Gal. i. 8 and 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n144-1">Evag. iii. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n144-2">Or using more freedom of speech than the Henotikon.</note>
            <note xml:id="n145-1">Liberat. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n145-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n145-4">Text, <quote>Arcadius</quote>, from the confusion between <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               and <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n146-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n146-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πλάτος</foreign>.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
