<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book" n="5">
            <head>Book 5</head>
            <div type="section" n="5.0">
               <p>The fifth Book (in its twelve chapters, which are written down distinctly below)
                  tells of <persName>Basiliscus</persName> and <persName>Marcus</persName> the Illustrious;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n101-1"/> and the encyclical letter
                  which they wrote to the bishops of their dominion, in which also they
                  anathematised the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and the Tome. For after eighteen years of
                  banishment in <placeName>Gangra</placeName> and <placeName>Cherson</placeName>, <persName>Timothy</persName> the Great returned and arrived at
                  <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>; and then he and <persName>Paul</persName> the Sophist, and <persName>James</persName>, and <persName>Theopompus</persName>, his
                  chosen monks, persuaded <persName>Basiliscus</persName> to write the Encyclical. It also tells about
                  the petition<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n101-2"/> sent by the bishops of <placeName>Asia</placeName>, who met at <persName>Ephesus</persName> and
                  subscribed to the Encyclical.</p>
               <p>Moreover, it tells about some Eutychian monks then residing at <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>,
                  who, along with <persName>Zenaia</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n101-3"/> the king's wife, basely conspired against <persName>Timothy</persName>
                  to have him sent again into banishment. Whereupon he departed to <persName>Ephesus</persName>. And by
                  means of a Synod, which he convened, he reinstated <persName>Paul</persName> there, and gave him the
                  rights<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n101-4"/> of the Patriarchate that the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> had taken away
                  from him, and had given to the royal city, through the flattery and treachery of
                  <persName>John</persName>, whom they made bishop instead of <persName>Bassian</persName>. For the latter resigned, and
                  departed and went into banishment. Now <persName>Timothy</persName> was received with much state. And
                  without any rancour he admitted to his communion the penitents from the Proterian
                  party and from that of <persName>Timothy</persName> <persName>Salophaciolus</persName>, who was driven out<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n101-5"/> before
                  him by the king's command.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="102"/>
               <p>But this Book also relates the deeds of <persName>Acacius</persName> in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and how he
                  raised an insurrection and rebellion against <persName>Basiliscus</persName>; and he took possession of
                  the Churches; and he compelled <persName>Basiliscus</persName> to write the Antencyclical, and to deny
                  his former letter. And the bishops again subscribed to this Antencyclical, with
                  the exception of <persName>Amphilochius</persName> of Side and <persName>Epiphanius</persName> of <placeName>Magdolum</placeName>. And then <persName>Zeno</persName>
                  returned and became emperor, and he thrust out <persName>Basiliscus</persName>, and cancelled every law
                  and enactment which he had made. And when he was wishing to depose <persName>Timothy</persName>, the
                  latter died, having retained his See to the end; and <persName>Peter</persName>, who became bishop in
                  his stead, hid from the threats of <persName>Zeno</persName>.</p>
               <p>Then <persName>Timothy</persName> <persName>Salophaciolus</persName> returned, and took possession of the church, and sought
                  for <persName>Peter</persName>. But this Book further tells about <persName>John</persName> the archimandrite, who was sent
                  to <persName>Zeno</persName> with the petition of the party of <persName>Timothy</persName> <persName>Salophaciolus</persName>, praying for an
                  order that, after the death of <persName>Timothy</persName>, one of their side should be the bishop in
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>. Now this <persName>John</persName> coveted the see for himself. And <persName>Zeno</persName> heard it; and,
                  with the object of trying him, he required from him an oath in the presence of the
                  Senate, and also of Bishop <persName>Acacius</persName>, that he would not take the bishopric.</p>
               <p>And <persName>John</persName> then returned to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, bearing an order from the king that, in
                  succession to <persName>Timothy</persName>, any of his party whom the citizens might desire should be
                  appointed as bishop. But about the same time it happened that this <persName>Timothy</persName>
                  <persName>Salophaciolus</persName> died. And then <persName>John</persName> transgressed his oath, and used bribery to get
                  the bishopric there for himself. But when <persName>Zeno</persName> heard of it, through the report of
                  eminent believers among the monks there who went up to him and informed him of all
                  the events which had occurred in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> from the time of the Synod, he was
                  greatly moved; and he changed his mind, and wrote a letter called the
                  <quote>Henotikon.</quote></p>
               <p>And he gave orders that <persName>Peter</persName> should return to his place, upon the condition of
                  his receiving the Henotikon, and that <persName>John</persName> the liar should be deprived. Whereupon
                  <persName>John</persName> repaired to <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and declared that he had suffered deprivation for <pb
                     type="page" n="103"/>the sake of the Synod and the Tome. And then <persName>Zeno</persName> wrote to
                  the Patriarch there, and exposed <persName>John</persName>.</p>
               <p>But <persName>Peter</persName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> also returned and convened a Synod, and received the
                  Henotikon.</p>
               <p>And in like manner, <persName>Acacius</persName> of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> and <persName>Martyrius</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, the
                  successor of <persName>Anastasius</persName>.</p>
               <p>And they all, except the bishop of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, wrote synodical letters, and received
                  <persName>Peter</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> into their communion.</p>
               <p>But certain zealous monks withdrew from <persName>Peter</persName> and became separatists, because he
                  had received the Henotikon in which there was no express anathema of the Synod.
                  And <persName>Peter</persName> thrust them out from their monasteries. Accordingly some of them went up
                  to <persName>Zeno</persName> and persuaded him to send back with them <persName>Cosmas</persName> the Spatharius, to
                  inquire<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n103-1"/> into their matter; and at another time he sent <persName>Arsenius</persName> the
                  prefect, and a prolonged dispute ensued.</p>
               <p>These, indeed, are the matters which are written expressly in the twelve chapters
                  of this fifth Book, which (so to speak) has been translated<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n103-2"/> from the same
                  Greek History of <persName>Zachariah</persName>, and has here been written in the Syriac language for
                  the study and instruction of the diligent, that they may learn the events that
                  occurred in former times.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5.1">
               <head>Chapter 1</head>
               <head>The first chapter of this book tells how <persName>Timothy</persName> returned from banishment after
                  the death of <persName>Leo</persName>; and that it was he who urged <persName>Basiliscusto</persName> write the encyclical
                  letter</head>
               <p>When <persName>Timothy</persName> had completed eighteen years in banishment, and <persName>Leo</persName> the emperor was
                  dead, and <persName>Zeno</persName>, his successor, had received the kingdom, the people of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>,
                  observing this crisis in imperial affairs, sent a petition by certain chosen, and
                  (as we may say) illustrious and noble monks, among them Amon who was called the
                  wild bull, and <persName>Paul</persName> who had been a <pb type="page" n="104"/>sophist, and <persName>Theorion</persName>
                  and <persName>James</persName> the miracle-workers, and <persName>Theopompus</persName> the brother of the master of the
                  offices.</p>
               <p>However,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n104-1"/> in consequence of a rebellion that was raised against <persName>Zeno</persName> by
                  <persName>Basiliscus</persName>, the brother of <persName>Verina</persName> the wife of <persName>Leo</persName>, who had been associated with
                  <persName>Zeno</persName> in the command of the army<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n104-2"/> in the days of <persName>Leo</persName>, <persName>Zeno</persName>[#104-3] had
                  betaken himself to the strongholds called <placeName>Salmon</placeName>; and <persName>Basiliscus</persName> had assumed the
                  crown. And he appointed <persName>Theoctistus</persName> his physician, an Alexandrian, the brother of
                  this <persName>Theopompus</persName> the monk, as master of the offices.</p>
               <p>Now<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n104-4"/> when these monks entered into the royal presence, the king, and the
                  courtiers, and the queen were struck with admiration of them. But also <persName>Theoctistus</persName>
                  the master of the offices and <persName>Acacius</persName> the bishop rendered them assistance.</p>
               <p>So <persName>Basiliscus</persName> issued an order that <persName>Timothy</persName> should return from banishment.</p>
               <p>And at first <persName>Acacius</persName> was preparing a lodging for him at the church called <persName>Irene</persName>;
                  and he was setting apart some of his own clergy for his retinue and service. But
                  afterwards, because he thought that they were forming a plan to make <persName>Theopompus</persName>
                  bishop at the royal city instead of him, <persName>Acacius</persName> was distressed and indignant; and
                  he endeavoured to put a stop to <persName>Timothy</persName>'s coming. However, he did not succeed. For
                  he returned, and was welcomed with great state by the Alexandrian sailors and the
                  people who happened to be then in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. And he went to lodge in the
                  king's palace. And large numbers were coming to him to be blessed, and to be
                  sanctified, and to receive healing from him. And becoming intimate both with
                  <persName>Basiliscus</persName> and his wife, <persName>Timothy</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n104-5"/> along with those who happened to be
                  there with him and on his behalf, persuaded the king, so that he consented to
                  write encyclical letters, in which he would anathematise the Tome and the addition
                  which was made at <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>. For <persName>Paul</persName> the monk, who was a rhetorician and a
                  sophist, drew them up. And it was he who, in a discussion with <persName>Acacius</persName> the
                  patriarch, <pb type="page" n="105"/>was able to show that the heresies of
                  <persName>Nestorius</persName> and <persName>Eutyches</persName> are one and the same; though they are generally thought to
                  be diametrically opposed to each other. For the one, indeed, making objection
                  declares that it would be a degradation to God to be born of a woman, and to be
                  made in all points like as we are, by becoming partaker of flesh and blood;
                  whereas He was only partaker by identity of name, and by power and indwelling, and
                  by operation. But the other, indeed, for the purpose of liberating and exalting
                  God, so that He should not suffer degradation and contempt by association with a
                  human body, publishes the doctrine that He became incarnate from His own essence,
                  and that He assumed a heavenly body; and that just as there is no part of the seal
                  left upon the wax, nor of the golden signet upon the clay, so neither did there
                  cleave to <persName>Christ</persName> any portion of humanity whatsoever.</p>
               <p>And when he spoke in this way, <persName>Acacius</persName> was astonishedat the solidity of his
                  reasoning, and he assented and agreed. And he went to <persName>Timothy</persName> and conversed with
                  him, in a friendly manner, respecting the rights of his see. However, when he was
                  requested by <persName>Timothy</persName> to sign the Encyclical, he hesitated.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5.2">
               <head>Chapter 2</head>
               <head>The second chapter tells about the encyclical letter of <persName>Basiliscus</persName> and <persName>Marcus</persName>,
                  which is tothe following effect<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n105-1"/></head>
               <quote>
                  <p>The king <persName>Basiliscus</persName>, the believing, victorious, all-virtuous ruler,
                     <persName>Augustus</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n105-2"/> along with <persName>Marcus</persName> the most illustrious <persName>Caesar</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n105-3"/> to
                     <persName>Timothy</persName> the reverend and God-loving archbishop of the great city <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.
                     Concerning all the laws justly and righteously enacted by the believing and
                     memorable kings who have gone before us, for the salvation and good guidance of
                     all <pb type="page" n="106"/>the world, and in defence of the true faith as taught
                     by the apostles and holy fathers; it is our will that all these laws should be
                     ratified, and not lightly annulled. Rather do we agree to them, and hold them to
                     be of equal validity with our own.</p>
                  <p>And earnestly desiring to honour the fear of God more than any affair of man,
                     through zeal for the Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> our God, to Whom we owe our creation,
                     exaltation, and glory; moreover also, being fully persuaded that the unity of His
                     flock is the salvation of ourselves and our people, and is the sure and immovable
                     foundation, and the lofty bulwark of our kingdom; we now, moved by a wise impulse,
                     are bringing union and unity to the Church of <persName>Christ</persName> in every part of our
                     dominion, namely, the faith of the three hundred and eighteen bishops, who being
                     previously prepared by the Holy Ghost, assembled at <placeName>Nicea</placeName>, the security and
                     well-being of human life, the faith which we hold, like all who have been before
                     us, and in which we believe and are baptized, that it may hold and rule<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n106-1"/>
                     all the Churches with their chosen canons: the faith which is complete and perfect
                     in all piety and true belief, and which rejects and exposes all heresies, and
                     thrusts them out of the Church: the faith which the one hundred and fifty bishops,
                     being assembled here to oppose and condemn the fighters against the Spirit, the
                     Holy Lord confirmed, and with which they concurred and agreed: the faith which was
                     also confirmed by the transactions of the two Councils at Ephesus, along with the
                     chief priests of <placeName>Rome</placeName> and <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, <persName>Celestine</persName> and <persName>Cyril</persName>, and <persName>Dioscorus</persName>, in
                     condemnation of the heretic <persName>Nestorius</persName>, and all who after him have held similar
                     opinions, and have confounded the order of the Church, and disturbed the peace of
                     the world, and cleft asunder the unity; we mean the Tome of <persName>Leo</persName>, and the decrees
                     of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, whether by way of definition of the faith, or doctrine, or
                     interpretation,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n106-2"/> or addition, or whatsoever other innovation was said or
                     done contrary to the faith and the definition of the three hundred and
                     eighteen.</p>
                  <p>And therefore we command that wherever, here or elsewhere, such written doctrine
                     be found, it shall be anathematised and burnt in the fire. For in accordance with
                     this order, our <pb type="page" n="107"/>blessed predecessors in the kingdom,
                     <persName>Constantine</persName> the Great and <persName>Theodosius</persName>, in like manner, commanded and ordained. And
                     also, the three subsequent Synods, that of the one hundred and fifty bishops here,
                     and the two of <persName>Ephesus</persName>, ratified only the faith of <placeName>Nicea</placeName>, and agreed to the true
                     definition there made.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, we anathematise everyone who does not confess that the only-begotten
                     Son of God truly became incarnate by the Holy Ghost from the <persName>Virgin Mary</persName>; not
                     taking a body from heaven, in mere semblance or phantasy. And also we anathematise
                     all the false teaching of all those heresies which are contrary to the true faith
                     of the fathers," and so on with the rest of the Encyclical.</p>
               </quote>
               <p>To<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n107-1"/> this document <persName>Timothy</persName> agreed and subscribed; as did also <persName>Peter</persName> of
                  <placeName>Antioch</placeName> and <persName>Paul</persName> of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, who were recalled from banishment, and the bishops of
                  <placeName>Asia</placeName> and the East, and <persName>Anastasius</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, and those of his jurisdiction; so
                  that the number of bishops who subscribed to the Encyclical is found to be about
                  seven hundred, less or more. And they anathematised the Tome of <persName>Leo</persName> and the Synod;
                  and they sent a petition<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n107-2"/> to <persName>Basiliscus</persName> and <persName>Marcus</persName>, which was as
                  follows:—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5.3">
               <head>Chapter 3</head>
               <head>The third chapter gives information respecting the petition of the bishops of
                  <placeName>Asia</placeName>, who were assembled at <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, and signed the Encyclical, and who wrote to
                  <persName>Basiliscus</persName> and <persName>Marcus</persName> to the following effect</head>
               <quote>
                  <p>To<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n107-3"/> the believing, and <persName>Christ</persName>-loving, victorious kings <persName>Basiliscus</persName> and
                     <persName>Marcus</persName> the Augusti—<persName>Paul</persName> and <persName>Pergamius</persName>, and <persName>Gennadius</persName>, and <persName>Zenodotus</persName>, and <persName>Zoticus</persName>,
                     and <persName>Gennadius</persName>, and <persName>Theophilus</persName>, and the other bishops assembled at <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>:— <pb
                        type="page" n="108"/>In all things ye have shown yourselves to be believing and
                     <persName>Christ</persName>-loving beings; so that when the true faith suffered persecution by the
                     malice of men, ye also were persecuted along with it. For there are rebellious and
                     vainglorious men, of a corrupt mind, foolish and void of the faith of the Son of
                     God, Who humbled Himself for our sake and became incarnate, and rendered us meet
                     for the adoption of sons. Be glad, then, and rejoice, and exult, and glory that ye
                     have been counted worthy to suffer persecution with the faith. For there is
                     reserved for these men the everlasting judgment of fire which devours the
                     persecutors, and also the threat of your punishment which is upon them; because
                     they have despised us, and slandered and belied us, and forced us with violence to
                     agree to their doctrine.</p>
                  <p>But now that the light of the true faith has arisen upon us, and the dark cloud
                     of error been rolled away from us, we make known by this declaration<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108-1"/> our
                     true faith to your Majesties<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108-2"/> and to all the world. And we say that freely
                     and with willing consent, by the aid of <persName>John</persName> the Evangelist as our teacher, we
                     have signed this Encyclical; and we agree to it and to everything in it, without
                     compulsion, or fear, or favour of man. And if at any future time violence shall
                     meet us from man, we are prepared to despise fire and sword and banishment and the
                     spoiling of our goods, and to treat all bodily suffering with contempt; so that we
                     may adhere to the true faith. We have anathematised and we do anathematise the
                     Tome of <persName>Leo</persName> and the decrees of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>; which have been the cause of much
                     blood-shedding, and confusion, and tumult, and trouble, and divisions, and strifes
                     in all the world. For we are satisfied with the doctrine and faith of the apostles
                     and of the holy fathers, the three hundred and eighteen bishops; to which also the
                     illustrious Council of the one hundred and fifty in the <placeName>Royal City</placeName>, and the two
                     other holy Synods at <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> adhered, and which they confirmed. And we join with
                     them in anathematising <persName>Nestorius</persName>, and everyone who does not confess that the
                     only-begotten Son of God was incarnate by the Holy Ghost, <pb type="page" n="109"
                     />of the <persName>Virgin Mary</persName>; He becoming perfect man, while yet He remained, without
                     change and the same, perfect God; and that He was not incarnate from Heaven in
                     semblance or phantasy. And we further anathematise all other heresies." But they
                     wrote down some other things. And they applauded with loud voice<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n109-1"/> and
                     approved.</p>
               </quote>
               <p>But the other bishops also of the various districts wrote another declaration, the
                  beginning of which was to this effect:</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>With the consent of our heart, we hold your Majesties to be in such accord with
                     our fathers, the three hundred and eighteen bishops, as to make the three hundred
                     and nineteenth: for you are very zealous<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n109-2"/> for their true faith, that it
                     may prosper and be preached among all nations in your dominion.</p>
               </quote>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5.4">
               <head>Chapter 4</head>
               <head>The fourth chapter of this same fifth book narratesthe events which occurred in
                  <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> and <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> after the publication of the Encyclical</head>
               <p>When<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n109-3"/> the purport of the king's Encyclical letters became generally known,
                  certain monks holding opinions similar to those of <persName>Eutyches</persName>, who happened to be in
                  the <placeName>Royal City</placeName>, came in a body to <persName>Timothy</persName>, supposing him to be of their way of
                  thinking, and disputed with him about the terms of the Encyclical; because it
                  anathematised everyone who affirmed that <persName>Christ</persName> was incarnate in semblance. But
                  when he said to them, <quote>What then is your opinion respecting the Incarnation?</quote> then
                  they brought up to him the illustration of the signet-ring which, after the
                  impression, leaves no part of its substance upon the wax or the clay.</p>
               <p>And having discovered their sentiments, he admonished and instructed them, that
                  the Scriptures teach us that <persName>Christ</persName> <pb type="page" n="110"/>was made in all
                  points, like unto us, and took our nature perfectly, yet without the motions of
                  sin. And although He was born supernaturally<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n110-1"/> without copulation,
                  nevertheless He became perfect Man, having been conceived in the <persName>Virgin Mary</persName>, and
                  from her born, through the Holy Ghost. And being incarnate He yet remained the
                  same and without change in His Godhead.</p>
               <p>Then <persName>Timothy</persName>, having learned by the whole tenor of the conversation of those who
                  came to him what their mind was, made a written statement, declaring that <persName>Christ</persName>
                  was like unto us in everything belonging to humanity. Whereupon the monks of the
                  place separated themselves from him, saying, <quote>We will have no communion with the
                  Alexandrians.</quote></p>
               <p>But the others, having discovered that he had no tendency to the Eutychian
                  doctrine, attached themselves to him.</p>
               <p>Then the Eutychianists, joining with their fellows, advised <persName>Zenona</persName>, the wife of
                  King <persName>Basiliscus</persName>, a professor of their creed, that <persName>Timothy</persName> should be banished
                  again. However, <persName>Theoctistus</persName>, the master of the offices, having heard what was
                  likely to befall him, urged him to leave the city and to proceed without delay to
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>. And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n110-2"/> he left; and having, on his journey, arrived at <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>,
                  he convened a Synod, and he reinstated <persName>Paul</persName> who had formerly been the bishop
                  there, but was in exile at that time for not accepting the decrees of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>.
                  To him <persName>Timothy</persName> canonically restored the rights of his see, which the Council of
                  <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> had snatched from it, and had given by partiality to the throne of the
                  <placeName>royal city</placeName>.</p>
               <p>And <persName>Timothy</persName> arrived at <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and he was received with great state, with
                  torches, and also songs of praise by the various people and languages there, and
                  even by the members of the Proterian party, who beheld the affection for him
                  displayed by the citizens. But the band of the priests, and the monks, and the
                  sisters in <persName>Christ</persName>, and all the people in a body, chanting their hymns, and saying,
                  <quote>Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord,</quote> conducted him into the great
                  church. For <persName>Timothy</persName> <persName>Salophaciolus</persName> had by the king's command gone out before
                  him.</p>                   
               <pb type="page" n="111"/>
               <p>And in asmuch as he was a peaceable and kind man, and also gentle in his words, and
                  by no means passionate, he remitted to the members of the Proterian party the term
                  of repentance, which he had written and appointed for the penitents when he was in
                  banishment.</p>
               <p>And even <persName>Prolatius</persName>(?) himself, who had taken and dragged him from the font of the
                  Baptistery, he received just as kindly and peaceably as the others, weeping and
                  comforting him as to his former rebellious and insolent conduct towards
                  himself.</p>
               <p>For, such is the rule of the leaders of the Church, which <persName>Timothy</persName> truly showed
                  towards the many, that brotherly charity which seeks not her own, and is not
                  easily provoked.</p>
               <p>But certain persons, who were ignorant of the rights of divine love, severed
                  themselves from him on account of his gentleness and mildness towards the
                  penitents, in that he required nothing else from them except that they should
                  anathematise the Synod and the Tome, and confess the true faith; and because he
                  did not hold them aloof, even for a little while, from the communion which they
                  had made desolate.</p>
               <p>But at the head of these persons was <persName>Theodoret</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n111-1"/> the bishop of <placeName>Joppa</placeName>, who
                  had been consecrated by <persName>Theodosius</persName> some time before. And he was then filled with
                  envy because he had not also been received back again to his see. And, lo! the
                  illustrious <persName>Peter</persName> the Iberian did not return to <placeName>Gaza</placeName>; and he did not at all agree
                  with this faction, but he was warmly attached to <persName>Timothy</persName>, and he proved that his
                  conduct and actions were in conformity with the will of God. But the Separatists
                  who sided with <persName>Theodotus</persName> fell into such error that they even practised
                  reanointing, and they were called Anachristo-Novatians.</p>
               <p>But the affection of the people for <persName>Timothy</persName> being great was increased the more
                  because, by the king's command, he brought the bones of <persName>Dioscorus</persName> and of <persName>Anatolius</persName>
                  his brother, along with him, in a silver coffin, and he buried him with great
                  state, laying him in the place of the bishops, and honouring <pb type="page"
                     n="112"/>him as a confessor. But his charity was so profuse that of his own
                  free will he appointed that one denarius a day should be given by the Church, for
                  expenditure and use, to <persName>Timothy</persName>, who was deposed, and who had been since then
                  supporting himself by the work of his hands, by weaving baskets and selling
                  them.</p>
               <p>And he gave to the great men and rulers of the city a gift, assigning to<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n112-1"/>
                  each of them three paxamatia<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n112-2"/> apiece. And to King <persName>Basiliscus</persName> and to the
                  patricians he only sent the same. And at one time the tax-gatherer<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n112-3"/> came
                  to him with a royal letter, and he gave him just the same; and he answered and
                  said, <quote>I want a gift of denarii.</quote> And he said, <quote>It is the duty of the Church to
                  expend them upon the widows and orphans.</quote></p>
               <p>But the people heard that the prefect there, <persName>Boetius</persName> by name, was an Eutychian;
                  and they cried out in the church, <quote>Pope!<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n112-4"/> pronounce an anathema upon
                  <persName>Nestorius</persName> and <persName>Eutyches</persName>.</quote> And he at once anathematised them- by word of mouth in
                  the presence of the prefect. And thereby he was cleared from the suspicion of
                  associating with the prefect as an Eutychian.</p>
               <p>Such were the transactions at <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5.5">
               <head>Chapter 5</head>
               <head>The fifth chapter of this same fifth book tells about the preparations which
                  were made by <persName>Acacius</persName> of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>; and about the <quote>Antencyclicals</quote>; and also
                  about <persName>Peter</persName> and <persName>Paul</persName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> and of <persName>Ephesus</persName>, who were again deposed when <persName>Zeno</persName>
                  the King returned and <persName>Basiliscus</persName> was driven out</head>
               <p>But<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n112-5"/> <persName>Acacius</persName> of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, having heard respecting <persName>Paul</persName> of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>
                  that the rightful authority of his see, according <pb type="page" n="113"/>to its
                  former constitution, had been restored to him by <persName>Timothy</persName>; and further, that <persName>Peter</persName>
                  had returned to <placeName>Antioch</placeName>; and that they were preparing to hold a Synod against him
                  at <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> with the intention of deposing himself and appointing <persName>Theopompus</persName>,
                  brother of the master of the offices, in his stead: he, having heard all this,
                  stirred up the monks and urged them on, and brought down <persName>Daniel</persName> from the pillar,
                  and took possession of the churches, and raised an insurrection against
                  <persName>Basiliscus</persName>, declaring that he was a heretic. Whereupon <persName>Basiliscus</persName>, for the report
                  reached him at the same time that <persName>Zeno</persName> was returning with a great army, was
                  compelled to make the <quote>Antencyclicals,</quote> by which he cancelled his former
                  letter.</p>
               <p>Then <persName>Zeno</persName>, upon his return, and the ejection of <persName>Basiliscus</persName>, passed a law whereby
                  all the proceedings of <persName>Basiliscus</persName> were to be cancelled. He also deposed <persName>Peter</persName> of
                  <placeName>Antioch</placeName> and <persName>Paul</persName> of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n113-1"/> and he uttered severe threats against
                  <persName>Timothy</persName>. However, the latter died, departing to be with his Lord; and he was
                  buried with great state, the obsequies being performed by <persName>Peter</persName>, who was
                  canonically consecrated as his successor by the bishops of the country.</p>
               <p>But the bishops of <placeName>Asia</placeName> made a libel to <persName>Acacius</persName>, finding fault with the <quote>
                  Encyclicals</quote>; and they subscribed to the Antencyclicals. In like manner also, the
                  Eastern bishops made a libel to <persName>Calandion</persName>, <persName>Peter</persName>'s successor, whereby they, too,
                  anathematised the <quote>Encyclicals.</quote></p>
               <p>But <persName>Anastasius</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> persevered in his integrity, holding with him the
                  three provinces of <placeName>Palestine</placeName>; and he would not give himself over to this party,
                  nor would he deny the Encyclicals; although he freely associated with the bishops
                  who came together to him.</p>
               <p>In like manner also <persName>Epiphanius</persName> of <placeName>Magdolum</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n113-2"/> of <placeName>Pamphylia</placeName>, impelled by the
                  greatness of his soul, departed to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and was sojourning in the
                  monasteries there, and was honoured by <persName>Timothy</persName> and by his successor <persName>Peter</persName>.</p>
               <p>But King <persName>Zeno</persName> was greatly enraged when he heard about <persName>Peter</persName>; and he sent threats
                  of which <persName>Peter</persName> had previous intima<pb type="page" n="114"/>tion, and he hid
                  himself in the city by moving about from one house to another. But, by the command
                  of King <persName>Zeno</persName>, <persName>Timothy Salophaciolus</persName>, who had been ejected, returned and took
                  possession of the great church, and a tumult and slaughter ensued upon his entry
                  there.</p>
               <p>And <persName>Theoctistus</persName>, the prefect of the city, was searching for <persName>Peter</persName> to apprehend
                  him, when a Voice was heard, saying, <quote>I will hide him, and I will protect him,
                  because he has known My Name; he shall call upon Me, and I will answer him; in the
                  day of trouble I will sustain him, and I will honour him.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n114-1"/></p>
               <p>But <persName>Timothy</persName> exerted himself by all ways and means to keep the people on his side.
                  He preached the faith of <persName>Nicea</persName> and of the one hundred and fifty; he confessed and
                  agreed to the transactions of <persName>Ephesus</persName>; he anathematised <persName>Nestorius</persName>; and he wrote in
                  the diptych the names of <persName>Cyril</persName> and <persName>Dioscorus</persName>, and read them out; and he did more
                  besides, and yet he was unable to draw the people to himself.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5.6">
               <head>Chapter 6</head>
               <head>The sixth chapter of this same book tells about <persName>Martyrius</persName>, who was the
                  successor of <persName>Anastasiusin</persName> <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>; that he also was preachingthe true faith to
                  the people, and was anathematising <persName>Nestorius</persName> and the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName></head>
               <p>And <persName>Martyrius</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> was also one of those who, following <persName>Anastasius</persName> his
                  predecessor, separated himself from the Antencyclical, and exerted himself greatly
                  to unite the people. And he gained over <persName>Marcianus</persName>, an excellent monk; and this man
                  received him, and admonished the other monks to do the same. But those who did not
                  receive him he expelled. And they say that, after his death, one of his disciples,
                  who was quite blind, prayed to God, saying, <quote>If the doctrine of our master be
                  indeed the right one, when I lay mine eyes upon his corpse, let them receive their
                  sight</quote>; and he received his sight.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="115"/>
               <p>The Public Address<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n115-1"/> of <persName>Martyrius</persName></p>
               <quote>
                  <p><persName>Christ</persName> is our peace, Who hath made both one, and has taken down the middle wall
                     of partition, and has destroyed the enmity by His flesh. For, behold, the Church
                     is receiving back her sons, who never, indeed, of their own accord, departed far
                     from her! And now they have shown<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n115-2"/> this to us by deed, and it is time for
                     us to say, <quote>Glory to God in the highest, and peace upon earth.</quote></p>
                  <p>Wherefore, to their face we the God-loving bishops have blamed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n115-3"/> these
                     chaste archimandrites and the excellent clergy, in order in your presence to
                     convince the rest of our brethren that we have no other true definition of the
                     faith but that into which we have been and are being baptized. For thus have they
                     been baptized, and believe as we do.</p>
                  <p>Whosoever, then, holds or has held or learned doctrine contrary to this
                     definition of the faith which was framed by the three hundred and eighteen holy
                     fathers, the bishops assembled at Nicea; to which definition the one hundred and
                     fifty believing and true bishops, assembled in the royal city, adhered, ratifying
                     and confirming the same, as did also the Synod held in <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>: whosoever (I say)
                     holds or has held or learned what is contrary to this definition, let him be
                     accursed, if he have any other teaching or doctrine defined elsewhere, whether in
                     <placeName>Rimini</placeName>, or in <placeName>Sardica</placeName>, or in <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, or in any other place whatsoever,
                     according to the saying of the apostle, <quote>If any man preaches to you more than what
                     we have preached to you, let him be accursed.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n115-4"/></p>
               </quote>
               <p>And again, the same <persName>Martyrius</persName> spoke in the following terms:</p>
               <quote>
                  <p>If any man teaches,
                     or brings in as new, or thinks or<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n115-5"/> interprets, or holds any other
                     definition or faith contrary to this approved and orthodox doctrine of faith of
                     the three hundred and eighteen holy bishops and the one hundred and fifty, and
                     them of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, he is an alien to the holy Church.</p>
                  <pb type="page" n="116"/>
                  <p>And, behold, I adjure you in the sight of God and His <persName>Christ</persName>, and the Holy
                     Spirit, and the elect angels, that you do not suffer any man to lead you astray
                     from this faith! But the confession, signed with your own signatures, lo, it is
                     recorded in Heaven above! And you shall give account before the fearful and
                     righteous Judgment-Seat, if you accept anything more or less than the true faith.
                     I am clear from your blood; I have not desisted from speaking unto you.</p>
               </quote>
               <p>By using language such as this, the bishops were admonishing those who separated
                  from them.</p>
               <p>But in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> not one believer would consent to hold communion with <persName>Timothy</persName>
                  and his followers.</p>
               <p>Then the monks and certain learned and wise men took counsel together and they
                  made a supplication<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n116-1"/> to the chiefs of the cities, begging of them that, in
                  the event of the death of <persName>Timothy</persName>, they would not accept as bishop any other
                  member of his party; but that they would only be satisfied with Peter the
                  believer, who was the lawfully-appointed bishop, although he was then hidden in
                  retirement. And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n116-2"/> the partisans of <persName>Timothy</persName> having heard of this, drew up a
                  petition and sent it to the king by John, a presbyter of the Martyr Church of St.
                  <persName>John</persName> the Baptist, a monk, and also one of the Tabennesiots.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n116-3"/> And in it
                  they besought the king that, in the event of the death of <persName>Timothy</persName>, none but a
                  member of his party should be made bishop, and that the people of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>
                  should not receive Peter.</p>
               <p>And when <persName>John</persName> was admitted into the presence of the king, the latter said to him,
                  for the purpose of trying him, <quote>We think it well that you should yourself be the
                  bishop there.</quote> For the king had previously learned that he was in league with
                  <persName>Julius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n116-4"/> the general,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n116-5"/> who, on account of his command over the
                  king's army, was preparing an insurrection against the king, in conjunction with
                  <persName>Leontius</persName> and <persName>Euprepius</persName>. <pb type="page" n="117"/>And <persName>John</persName> disclosed this to
                  <persName>Julius</persName>; and he said to the king, <quote>I am not worthy.</quote> Then he told him to take
                  counsel upon it. And when <persName>Julius</persName> heard it he said to him, <quote>Conceal your feelings,
                  and be careful not to disclose them before the king.</quote> Then he took an oath in the
                  presence of <persName>Acacius</persName> and the senators that he would never be the bishop.</p>
               <p>And the king issued an order, and gave it to <persName>John</persName>, to the effect that any
                  brother<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n117-1"/> whom the clergy and the people of the city might choose, should
                  be the successor of <persName>Timothy</persName>.</p>
               <p>But when he returned to the city, he delivered a letter from <persName>Julius</persName> to <persName>Theognostus</persName>
                  the prefect there, who was one of the conspirators with <persName>Julius</persName>, and he promised
                  that if he should become bishop he would give the royal vessels which <persName>Arcadius</persName> the
                  king devoted to the sanctuary, and presented to <persName>Theophilus</persName>, who was the bishop at
                  that time, and he built a church there and called it after his name.</p>
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter" n="5.7">
               <head>Chapter 7</head>
               <head>The seventh chapter of the fifth books tells about <persName>John</persName>, how he lied, and
                  obtained the bishopric by bribery, after the death of <persName>Timothy</persName>; and about <persName>Cyrus</persName> the
                  presbyter, who was in league with him; and also how <persName>Peter</persName> returned to his
                  see</head>
               <p>After<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n117-2"/> a few more days of life only, <persName>Timothy</persName> died. Then <persName>John</persName> belied his
                  own sworn promises, and gave a bribe to <persName>Theognostus</persName>, and obtained the bishopric
                  for, himself.</p>
               <p>But he drew over to his side <persName>Cyrus</persName> a presbyter, one of those who had formerly been
                  in association with <persName>Dioscorus</persName>, and had afterwards forsaken him. This man also
                  coveting the primacy, at one time<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n117-3"/> would attach himself to <persName>Acacius</persName> of
                  <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and at another time to that <persName>Timothy</persName> who died; and again, he would
                  mock<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n117-4"/> and revile <persName>Timothy</persName> the Great and <persName>Peter</persName> his successor. So that the
                  Alexandrians <pb type="page" n="118"/>used to ridicule him on account of his
                  tergiversations, holding up unripe dates before him in the public street, and
                  charging him with vile conduct in connexion with a married woman. The blessed
                  <persName>Dioscorus</persName> cursed this man, saying, <quote>As God is true, <persName>Cyrus</persName> will die a layman.</quote> And
                  so, indeed, it happened to him, as is written below.</p>
               <p>But the king, when he heard about <persName>John</persName>, was very indignant, because the latter had
                  belied his sworn promises, and obtained the bishopric for himself.</p>
               <p>But there were in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> at that time some chosen monks who were pleading
                  for <persName>Peter</persName>. And they showed him, by written documents respecting them, the sad
                  afflictions which, time after time, had occurred in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and
                  in the other adjacent districts, on account of the Synod. And the king acceded to
                  their request, and he issued an order that <persName>John</persName> should be ejected from the see as
                  a liar, and that <persName>Peter</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n118-1"/> should be restored to the Church, upon the
                  condition of his subscribing to the Henotikon which <persName>Zeno</persName> wrote and sent there, and
                  to <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and to <placeName>Pentapolis</placeName>, and of his receiving and holding communion with all
                  the other bishops who would agree to the Henotikon; and, moreover, with those in
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> called Proterians, as many of them as would confess that they agreed to
                  the doctrines of the Henotikon, which indeed was framed by the counsel of <persName>Acacius</persName>
                  the bishop, and was sent to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> in the charge of <persName>Pergamius</persName>, the newly-
                  appointed prefect there in the room of <persName>Theognostus</persName>.</p>
               <p>This <persName>Pergamius</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n118-2"/> upon his arrival at the city, managed the matter
                  prudently. For having discovered that <persName>John</persName> had escaped by flight, he sought out
                  <persName>Peter</persName>, and informed him of the king's order. And he showed him the Henotikon,
                  saying, <quote>You must, after having carefully studied it, subscribe and agree to it ;
                  and further, you must receive the bishops and the other members of the Proterian
                  party without any animosity whatsoever, if only they agree to all that the king
                  has laid down in the same Henotikon.</quote></p>
               <p>And <persName>Peter</persName>, having considered the contents of this document, found that its
                  provisions were framed faithfully and with <pb type="page" n="119"/>all
                  righteousness. But he hesitated somewhat, because there was no clear and express
                  anathema of the Synod and the Tome in it, and consequently he feared that it might
                  prove a stumbling-block to the people. However, he decided to accept it, in as much
                  as it proclaimed the definition of the faith laid down by the three hundred and
                  eighteen; and it confessed the truth of the one hundred and fifty bishops; and it
                  also agreed to the twelve Heads of <persName>Cyril</persName>; and it anathematised <persName>Nestorius</persName> and
                  <persName>Eutyches</persName>; and it also confessed that the body of <persName>Christ</persName>, derived from the Virgin,
                  was of the same nature as our body. Accordingly he subscribed to it. And he also
                  promised that, if the others would repent and accept all the provisions of the
                  Henotikon, and persuade the people to that effect, he would receive them into
                  communion with himself from all orders.</p>
               <p>Then the prefect, and the duke, and the chief men, and the clergy, and the monks,
                  and the sisters, and the believing people assembled together at the place where he
                  was; and they set him upon a chariot, and with pomp<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n119-1"/> and praise as one who
                  kept the true faith, and doing homage before him, they brought him to the great
                  church. And <persName>Pergamius</persName> urged him to receive the other<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n119-2"/> members of the
                  Proterian party. But he first declared to the people the interpretation of the
                  meaning of the Henotikon, and explained it, saying, <quote>It is well and faithfully
                  written, inasmuch as it accepts the twelve Heads of <persName>Cyril</persName>, and it anathematises
                  <persName>Nestorius</persName> and <persName>Eutyches</persName>, and it confesses the body of <persName>Christ</persName>, derived from the
                  Virgin, to be of the same nature as our body, and that the sufferings which He
                  endured in the flesh, and the miracles which He wrought, belong to the same God
                  <persName>Christ</persName>. And this document further cancels and condemns the whole doctrine of
                  <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and the Tome, because <persName>Dioscorus</persName> and <persName>Timothy</persName> the Great also thought and
                  expounded similarly.</quote></p>
               <p>And he delivered a further address<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n119-3"/> to the people, to the following
                  effect: "It is right for all of us, men, women, and children, to offer with the  <!-- double quote opens but closing end found ( opening of paragraph discussed?) --> 
                  open mouth of thanksgiving, prayer, <pb type="page" n="120"/>and supplication to
                  our Lord and God, on behalf of the faithful reign of the victorious King <persName>Zeno</persName>,
                  whose noble actions and virtuous morals are urging the prudent in every place to
                  this. For when our fathers, the chaste monks, presented a petition to him
                  concerning the reformation of the faith, and informed him of the occurrences here,
                  and of the tumults from which our people had suffered time after time; then he
                  wept, and he looked up to heaven, and called God to help him, and to put it into
                  his heart to command whatever would be in conformity with the divine will, and
                  would conduce to the welfare of men and the unity of the people, by exerting
                  himself to abolish the stumbling-blocks which were in all the Churches,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n120-1"/>
                  on account of all the rash innovations and additions which were made at
                  <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n120-2"/></p>
               <p>"And now, beloved children, we have the light of the true faith of the holy <!-- double quote opens but closing end found -->
                  fathers in this written statement of his Orthodoxy, which will now be read aloud
                  in your presence, and heard by your ears. For by confessing herein the true faith,
                  and accepting the twelve Heads of the blessed <persName>Cyril</persName>, and anathematising <persName>Nestorius</persName>
                  and <persName>Eutyches</persName>, and proclaiming that God the Word, Who became incarnate, is one
                  nature, sufferings and miracles; by all this he rejects the whole teaching of the
                  Diphysites. For their doctrine and that of the Tome is quite the opposite of this;
                  and against them our holy fathers, <persName>Dioscorus</persName> and <persName>Timothy</persName>, true witnesses of
                  <persName>Christ</persName>, earnestly contended.</p>
               <p><quote>But pray for him, that the Lord may keep him in the true proportion of his love 
                  and faith. For we trust, by the mercy of <persName>Christ</persName> our God, that when your praises
                  and prayers are heard, we shall not fail to obtain any of those other petitions
                  which we are rightly asking of Him; but that He may freely receive your
                  supplication and grant your requests.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n120-3"/></p>
               <p><quote>Hear this honourable document, the Henotikon, which <pb type="page" n="121"/>he
                  faithfully ordained, and which will now be read in your presence.</quote></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5.8">
               <head>Chapter 8</head>
               <head>The eighth chapter comes next, containing the Henotikon of <persName>Zeon</persName></head>
               <p><quote>Imperial<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n121-1"/> <persName>Caesar</persName>, <persName>Zeno</persName> the king, believing, victorious, triumphant, <!-- double quote opens and closes, but may be quotes that started paragraphs-->
                  mighty, ever-worshipful, <persName>Augustus</persName>, to the bishops and the people in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>,
                  and in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and in <placeName>Libya</placeName>, and also in <placeName>Pentapolis</placeName>. Since we know that the origin
                  and stability and invincible might<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n121-2"/> of our empire is the only right and
                  true faith, which, by Divine Inspiration the three hundred and eighteen holy
                  fathers in Council at <placeName>Nicea</placeName> declared, and which in like manner the one hundred and
                  fifty holy fathers gathered at <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, attested: We, by night and by day,
                  employ constant prayers, and diligence, and enactments, that thereby the Holy
                  Catholic and Apostolic Church in every place, which is the incorruptible and
                  imperishable mother of the sceptre of our kingdom, may be increased. That thus the
                  believing people, being kept in godly peace and concord, may offer up, in
                  conjunction with the pious and holy bishops, and the God-fearing clergy, and the
                  archimandrites and monks, acceptable prayers on behalf of our empire. For if the
                  great God and our Saviour <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, Who became incarnate from <persName>Mary</persName> the holy
                  Virgin and <persName>Theotokos</persName>, shall approve and readily receive our unanimous praise and
                  service, the race of enemies shall be destroyed and obliterated; and all men will
                  bow the neck to our sway, which is next<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n121-3"/> to that of God; and then
                  peace,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n121-4"/> and its consequent blessings, and genial temperature, and
                  abundance of fruits, and all those things which are adapted<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n121-5"/> for man's
                  good, shall be liberally granted. This unblemished faith, then, being thus the
                  preserver of ourselves and of the Roman affairs, petitions have been presented to
                  us <pb type="page" n="122"/>by God-loving archimandrites and other hermits
                  entreating us with tears that there may be unity to the Holy Churches; and that
                  the limbs may be joined together which the haters of good have for a long time
                  been striving to separate; because they knew that when one makes war with the
                  whole and perfect body of the Church he is defeated.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>For it has happened that of the generations without number which Time, during  <!-- double quote opens and closes, but may be quotes that started paragraphs-->
                  these many years of life, has removed; some, deprived of the Laver of
                  Regeneration, have passed away; and others, without participation in the divine
                  Communion, have been carried off by the inevitable journey of mankind. And they
                  have been wasted by myriads of murders; and through the profuse blood-shedding,
                  not the earth alone, but even the very air itself has been defiled. Who would not
                  pray<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n122-1"/> that this state of things may be exchanged for a good one? For which
                  reason, then, we desired you to know that both we and the holy Churches of the
                  orthodox everywhere, and the God-loving priests who rule them, neither hold, nor
                  have held, nor know any man holding, any other symbol, or doctrine, or seal of the
                  faith, or creed, than that which we have mentioned above, the holy symbol of the
                  three hundred and eighteen holy fathers, which was also attested by the one
                  hundred and fifty holy fathers who met in Council here. And if there be any man
                  holding such, we account him an alien. For, as we have already said, we are
                  confident that this only preserves our kingdom; and also all people who are
                  counted worthy of life-giving Baptism are baptized upon the simple reception of
                  this creed alone. And, moreover, all the holy fathers, who met in Council at
                  <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, and deposed the wicked <persName>Nestorius</persName> and all his successors in doctrine,
                  followed the same faith.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>This <persName>Nestorius</persName>, together with <persName>Eutyches</persName>, inasmuch as they held doctrines contrary <!-- double quote opens and closes, but may be quotes that started paragraphs-->
                  to what have been here declared, we anathematise. And we also receive the twelve
                  Heads delivered by the ever-memorable, God-loving <persName>Cyril</persName>, formerly archbishop of
                  the Catholic Church of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>. But we confess that the only-begotten Son of
                  God, Himself God, <pb type="page" n="123"/>our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, Who truly became
                  man; He Who is of the same nature with the Father in the Godhead; He Who is also
                  of the same nature with us in the manhood; He Who came down and assumed flesh,
                  through the Holy Ghost, and from <persName>Mary</persName> the Virgin and <persName>Theotokos</persName>, — is one Son and
                  not two. For we affirm that the miracles which He wrought, and the sufferings
                  which He freely endured in the flesh, belong to one Son of God alone. Moreover, we
                  altogether reject those who either divide or confound, or introduce the phantasy.
                  For the true and sinless Incarnation from the <persName>Theotokos</persName> did not cause the addition
                  of a Son. For the Trinity remained even though God the Word, Who is one of the
                  Trinity, became incarnate.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Since, then, you know that both the Holy Orthodox Churches everywhere and the <!-- double quote opens and closes, but may be quotes that started paragraphs-->
                  God-loving priests who rule them, and our own Royalty, neither have received nor
                  do receive any other symbol or definition of the faith than the holy doctrine
                  which has been declared above; be united together without doubting. For we have
                  written this, not to make any innovation in the faith, but to assure you.</quote></p> 
               <p><quote>And here we anathematise all who have held, or hold, now or at any time, whether <!-- double quote opens and closes, but may be quotes that started paragraphs-->
                  in <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> or in any other Synod whatsoever, any different belief; but chiefly
                  those already mentioned, <persName>Nestorius</persName> and <persName>Eutyches</persName> and all their followers in the
                  doctrine.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Be joined, then, to your spiritual mother, the Church, and delight in her,<!-- double quote opens and closes, but may be quotes that started paragraphs-->
                  together with us, in divine fellowship, according to that one definition of the
                  faith alone which was framed by the holy fathers, as we have declared above. For
                  our all-holy mother, the Church, longs for you, that she may embrace you as
                  beloved children. And, for a considerable time, she has been eager to hear your
                  sweet<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n123-1"/> voice.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Hasten, therefore! For by so doing you will attract to yourselves the goodwill of <!-- double quote opens and closes, but may be quotes that started paragraphs-->
                  our God and Saviour <persName>Christ</persName>; and you will also be commended by our own
                  Royalty.</quote></p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="124"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="5.9">
               <head>Chapter 9</head>
               <head>The ninth chapter of this fifth book tells about the
                  separatists<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n124-1"/></head>
               <p>These matters having been thus transacted, some of the more ardent spirits were
                  very indignant; because in the king's document, the Henotikon, there was no
                  express anathema of the additions imposed at <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>. However, they all remained
                  in communion with <persName>Peter</persName> because he defended himself before them ; and especially
                  as he said, <quote>The king will not fail us in any of the requests that we shall make
                  to him.</quote></p>
               <p>Then the rest of the Proterians, seeing how matters were, went off to a suburb of
                  the city, called <placeName>Canopus</placeName>, and they kept crying out evil words.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n124-2"/> However,
                  they were feeble and few, and at their head were some readers,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n124-3"/> and <persName>Cyrus</persName>
                  the presbyter, concerning whom we have already stated<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n124-4"/> that he was at one
                  time a follower of <persName>Dioscorus</persName>, but he afterwards deserted him. <persName>Pergamius</persName>, hearing
                  of this secession, sent for <persName>Cyrus</persName> to have a conversation with him. And the latter
                  agreed to do what he was asked. So when he returned to them, he pleaded earnestly
                  with his companions at <placeName>Canopus</placeName>, saying, <quote>It is right for us to join in fellowship
                  with the others, and to obey the king's command.</quote> But the zealous and believing
                  priests who were on <persName>Peter</persName>'s side, hearing about it, were greatly distressed. And
                  they refused<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n124-5"/> to hold communion with <persName>Cyrus</persName>. And although they received a
                  large number of his associates upon their subscribing to the Henotikon, and
                  anathematising everyone who thought differently from what was in it; yet they
                  refused <persName>Cyrus</persName> himself And even when he subscribed they would not have him. For
                  they said to <pb type="page" n="125"/><persName>Pergamius</persName> that the very sight of him would
                  be enough to bring his deeds into the remembrance of the people, and to put a
                  stumbling-block in the way of many. So <persName>Cyrus</persName> remained a layman; and thus he died,
                  according to the curse of the holy <persName>Dioscorus</persName>.</p>
               <p>Then they were all associated in fellowship with <persName>Peter</persName> and <persName>Peter</persName> the Iberian,
                  wonderfully celebrated, and the able<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n125-1"/> monk <persName>Isaiah</persName>, and the other
                  Palestinians, certain blessed monks of the monasteries of <persName>Romanus</persName> and
                  <persName>Theodore</persName>.</p>
               <p>And <persName>Peter</persName>, the bishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, sent <persName>Paul</persName>, surnamed <persName>Arcadius</persName>, to the king
                  about certain matters of one kind and another that required correction.</p>
               <p>But <persName>John</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n125-2"/> who had been bishop, went off to <placeName>Rome</placeName>; and there, with tears,
                  he told <persName>Simplidus</persName> the patriarch what had befallen him; alleging that he continued
                  in danger<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n125-3"/> for the sake of the Synod and the Tome. Whereupon the king,
                  hearing of it, wrote a letter and sent it to the same Simplicius by the hand of
                  Uranius the tax-gatherer,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n125-4"/> in which he set forth to him all the wickedness
                  and lying treachery of <persName>John</persName>, and declared that by his own command <persName>Peter</persName> had been
                  appointed bishop there in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, with the object of bringing the people into
                  one communion.</p>
               <p>But <persName>Calandion</persName>[#125-5] of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, having heard about the Alexandrian affairs, was
                  much distressed, and wrote letters to <persName>Acacius</persName>, and to <persName>Zeno</persName> the king, and to
                  <persName>Simplicius</persName> of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, in which he called <persName>Peter</persName> a false teacher,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n125-6"/> and he
                  praised the Tome and the Synod. But he was closely attached to <persName>Nestorius</persName>, because
                  in his letter he called <persName>Cyril</persName> a fool.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n125-7"/></p>
               <p>However, as he took the side of <persName>Julius</persName>, and <persName>Leontius</persName>, and <persName>Euprepius</persName>, in the
                  rebellion which they eventually raised against <persName>Zeno</persName> the king in the East, he was
                  ejected from his place. And by the king's commands,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n125-8"/> <persName>Peter</persName>, who had once
                  and <pb type="page" n="126"/>twice contended and suffered on behalf of the true
                  faith, was restored to his see. And the people of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> received him with great
                  pomp and glory as <persName>Simon Peter</persName>. Then he convened the Synod of his province, and he
                  healed and closed the divisions, and set matters right. The Synod also, which he
                  convened, drew up a letter of fellowship in canonical fashion, and sent it to
                  <persName>Peter</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>. It was to the following effect:—</p>
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter" n="5.10">
               <head>Chapter 10</head>
               <head>The tenth chapter of this fifth book tells aboutthe synodical letter, which was
                  sent to Peterof Alexandria by the council that was convenedat <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, in the days
                  when <persName>Peter</persName> wasbishop there</head>
               <p><quote>To our Father, the God-loving, holy, Archbishop <persName>Peter</persName>, from the Synod now
                  convened at <placeName>Antioch</placeName>.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Just as <persName>Joshua</persName> the son of <persName>Nun</persName>, the leader of the host,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n126-1"/> and invested with
                  the mysteries of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> our God, showed care and solicitude for the
                  possession and rights of the tribes of <persName>Reuben</persName>, and <persName>Gad</persName>, and <persName>Manasseh</persName>; when,
                  according to the command of <persName>Moses</persName>, who delivered to him the leadership, they in
                  conjunction with their brethren crossed the <placeName>Jordan</placeName> armed, and entered the land of
                  promise to possess it; and continued to help in the war until God caused their
                  brethren, like themselves, to rest in peace there: in like manner we
                  judge<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n126-2"/> it to be the endeavour of thine Excellency, O bishop, that we also,
                  being the bishops from <placeName>Arabia</placeName> and <persName>Libanus</persName> of <placeName>Phoenice</placeName>, and <persName>Syria Secunda</persName>, and
                  <persName>Euphratesia</persName>, and <persName>Cilicia</persName>, should come to <placeName>Antioch</placeName> armed,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n126-3"/> until our Eastern
                  brethren shall possess the inheritance of their Churches from God. But how, after
                  the troubles and conflicts that have befallen us, <pb type="page" n="127"/>we are
                  earnestly desirous of peace; and how, by the letters of the indulgent king, we
                  have been now called to meet at <placeName>Antioch</placeName>; thy son the beloved and illustrious
                  <persName>Uranius</persName> the tax- gatherer will tell thee. For he, in the execution of the king's
                  will and command, communicated and showed to us the letter sent by him to thy
                  Holiness, and to the chaste monks, and to the believing people.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>But we, having met together and been received with the rights of divine love by
                  our believing father <persName>Peter</persName> the patriarch, who showed us kindness and meekness with
                  prudence, were in concord with him in all matters and he with us; and we joined in
                  fellowship one with the other in spiritual ministration. We were honoured also by
                  the citizens, who met and welcomed him with joy and gladness, and with ministering
                  praise; and extolled him as <persName>Peter Kepho</persName> our leader the Apostle. And, moreover, we
                  heard about the transactions in the royal city, how, from the jurisdiction of the
                  holy Archbishop <persName>Acacius</persName>, they had met together by the king's command; and about
                  their unity with him and with one another; and how he wrote to thy Blessedness,
                  showing and explaining the will of the believing king; and that the contents of
                  his excellent document the Henotikon were in complete accord with the faith of the
                  holy fathers of <placeName>Nicea</placeName>; in which also the one hundred and fifty assembled in the
                  royal city concurred; and which was confirmed by the Council of <persName>Ephesus</persName> in the
                  days of <persName>Celestine</persName> and <persName>Cyril</persName>; the latter of whom also in the twelve Heads exposed
                  and anathematised all the false doctrine of <persName>Nestorius</persName> and <persName>Eutyches</persName>, and the other
                  heresies.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>These things, indeed, brought the Egyptians<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n127-1"/> into full accord with the
                  Easterns, or rather, we should say, with all who in every place are devoted to
                  peace, and who love unity and the true faith.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And we believe and are confident that the diligence and prayers of Thy Holiness
                  have tended to bring about this happy result for the believing people everywhere,
                  by the will of our Lord and Brother <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, Whom we beseech to <pb
                     type="page" n="128"/>preserve for us the life of thy <persName>Chastity</persName>, prospering in
                  all virtue, and rejoicing in the Lord at what was done here upon the return of
                  thine honourable brother our chaste father, through the diligence of this thy son
                  <persName>Uranius</persName>, whom we commend to thy godly love, that thou mayest write and send thanks
                  to the believing king. For he is indeed serving him with all his might, by
                  carrying out his command, and earnestly endeavouring to promote the unity of the
                  Churches of <persName>Christ</persName>, and to impart peace to His beloved sons.</quote></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5.11">
               <head>Chapter 11</head>
               <head>The eleventh chapter contains the letter of <persName>Acacius</persName> of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> to <persName>Peter</persName>
                  of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n128-1"/></head>
               <p><persName>Acacius</persName>, indeed, desisting from his former mind, which was in favour of the Synod,
                  and connecting himself in loving agreement with the principles of the Henotikon,
                  also wrote a letter to <persName>Peter</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> in the following terms:—</p>
               <p><quote>To our pious and God-loving fellow-minister and brother <persName>Peter</persName>, <persName>Acacius</persName> sends
                  greeting. The very name of peace, indeed, is delightful; but its effect is very
                  sweet. For when, in accordance with the unity and the faith of the Church, it is
                  perfected, it imparts the more abundant grace to the prudent, and works in them
                  joy, for it announces great things.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Now we were blest with such joy as this in the congregations of our own city,
                  when reports reached us respecting thy faith, which troubled us. And, moreover,
                  they produced agitation and distress among many of the chaste monks here, and the
                  people, and our excellent clergy. However, thine honoured letter, having been
                  conveyed and delivered to us and to the illustrious chiefs here, exposed the
                  entire falsehood of the rumour respecting thee, and rolled away the darkness of
                  the cloud, and displayed the brilliancy and the purity of thy godly virtues. So
                  that it is now time for us to <pb type="page" n="129"/>say, <quote>Glory to God in the
                  highest.</quote> For it is producing and manifesting the peace, which is in the land of
                  our faith, and the goodwill amongst the men of our great God and Saviour the Lord
                  <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>. And, therefore, that glory of which the angels from heaven in their
                  companies were the first to sing in the ears of the shepherds over the earth, at
                  <placeName>Bethlehem</placeName>, that same glory the shepherds and leaders of the sheep. His people,
                  being joined together hand in hand in their union and concord, now ascribe in
                  their song of praise to our Lord God, Who is the true Head and Shepherd of the
                  flock.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>But also the triumphant Star of <persName>Christ</persName> from the East is now the believing and
                  God-fearing king.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And just as that star guided those of old to <persName>Christ</persName> our God, that they might
                  repair to the cave and offer gifts for the honour of His worship; so he also now
                  has manifested and caused to shine forth the splendour of the true faith to the
                  whole cave of his dominion. And he has also taken down the middle wall of
                  partition that divided<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n129-1"/> and cleft asunder the unity of the members of the
                  holy Church; thereby making them grow into a perfect man of complete stature. So
                  that he has displayed the body in one Person and figure, and he has made of two
                  one. For we understand also from the thankful letter of thy Holiness that he too
                  like <persName>David</persName>, in prophesying and in reigning, has now slain <persName>Goliath</persName> in the
                  field<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n129-2"/> with the Cross alone; and having smitten the evil one as with a
                  sling, he has overthrown and destroyed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n129-3"/> him by his faithful letter which
                  he wrote; and by the true sword of the Spirit which he displayed, he has cut off
                  and taken away those heresies and stumbling-blocks which are the very heads of the
                  Dragon; whom also having overthrown, he has thrust into outer darkness, and has
                  bound and imprisoned him in the lower parts of the earth.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Accordingly <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> above, the mother of the firstborn,shall rejoice, and also
                  in her daughters the Churches she shall exult and sing, giving praise to God, with
                  prayer for <pb type="page" n="130"/>the triumph of the king, and saying, <quote>Glory be
                  to the Most High Lord, Who is greatly to be praised.</quote> For we also were amazed at
                  the triumph of God, when we learned from thy letter that the Henotikon, which in
                  our own presence was despatched to thy Holiness by the hands of <persName>Pergamius</persName>, had
                  reached thee, and that thou hast agreed to it. And we exult in thy faith, and we
                  pray that the Lord may preserve<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n130-1"/> for us the life of this believing king
                  who has united us to the truth. And now I, and those who are with me, sending
                  greetings to thy Chastity, and to the excellent clergy, and to the chaste monks,
                  and to the believing people, have written this letter of reply.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n130-2"/></p>
               <p>The end of the letter of <persName>Acacius</persName> of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5.12">
               <head>Chapter 12</head>
               <head>The twelfth chapter tells about the letter of <persName>Martyrius</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, which he
                  wrote to <persName>Peter</persName> who had become bishop in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, in the following
                  terms<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n130-3"/></head>
               <p><quote><persName>Martyrius</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> — to the pious and <persName>Christ</persName>- loving chief priest, my lord,
                  and brother, and fellow-minister <persName>Peter</persName>.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>It is time for us now to say, like the prophet, <quote>I praise Thee, O Lord God; and I
                  glorify Thy Name: for Thou hast done marvellous things; for Thy will is true of
                  old. Amen, O Lord!</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n130-4"/> For our mouth is filled with gladness and our tongue
                  with praise; because we have certainly seen the heart of the king in the Hand of
                  the Lord, fulfilling His will in truth continually; and he has united again the
                  severed members.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And now that we have received thine Affection's reply, our people join with this
                  prophet in crying aloud, <quote>Lift <pb type="page" n="131"/>up thine eyes round about
                  thee, and behold thy children gathering together unto thee.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n131-1"/> For which
                  blessing, as is right, we exult; and we greet thy Holiness in the Lord. And,
                  singing psalms with the prophet David, we say, <quote>May the Lord increase you more and
                  more, you and your children; blessed are ye of the Lord, Who made heaven and
                  earth.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n131-2"/> I and those who are with me, send our best respects in the Lord
                  also to the priests who are with thy Chastity, and to the believing people, and to
                  the pious monks.</quote></p>
               <p>The end of this letter of <persName>Martyrius</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp> 
            <note xml:id="n101-1"><!--  Add Syriac  --> i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπιφανέστατος</foreign>. <quote>Probably
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <foreign xml:lang="grc">καῖσαρ</foreign>, has dropped out</quote> (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-2">
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">δέησις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-3">In ch. 4 <!--  Add Syriac  -->, really <quote>Zenonis.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n101-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">δίκας</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n103-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n103-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, L., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n104-1">Evag. iii. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n104-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n104-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., an evident mistake for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n104-4">Evag. iii. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n104-5">Evag. iii. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n105-1">Evag. iii. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n105-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and omit
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and thus bring into harmony with the Greek <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀεισέβαστος</foreign>
               (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n105-3"><!--  Add Syriac  --> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπιφανέστατος καῖσαρ</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n106-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n106-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n107-1">Evag. iii. 5; Liberat. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n107-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">δέησις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n107-3">Evag. iii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀναφορά</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               φωνάς.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109-3">Evag. iii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n110-1"><!--  Add Syriac  --> MS., not<!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n110-2">Evag. iii. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n111-1">Evidently a mistake for <persName>Theodotus</persName>; see below, and Evag. iii.
               6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112-1">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->; it seems to represent <foreign xml:lang="grc">παξουμάτια</foreign>
               (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παξαμάτια</foreign>), but the meaning can hardly be <quote>little cakes.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n112-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρακτήρ</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">παππᾶς</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112-5">Evag. iii. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n113-1">The text has, <quote><persName>Paul</persName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> and <persName>Peter</persName> of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>,</quote> an evident
               mistake.</note>
            <note xml:id="n113-2">I.e. Magyda.</note>
            <note xml:id="n114-1">Ps. xci. 14, 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">προσφώνησις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-4">Gal. i. 8, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n116-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔντευξεις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n116-2">Evag. iii. 12; Liberat. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n116-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS.; but in <foreign xml:lang="ge">Das Leben des Severus</foreign> (ed.
               Spanuth), p. 6, it is written <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and said to be the name of a
               monastery situated in <placeName>Canopus</placeName>.— <quote>Presbyter Tabennesiotis</quote> (Lib.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n116-4">I.e. Illus.</note>
            <note xml:id="n116-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n117-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>whomsoever</quote>
               (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n117-2">Evag. ii. 12; Liberat. 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n117-3">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n117-4">Reading<!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, p. 42,
               note 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n118-1">Liberat. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n118-2">Evag. iii. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n119-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n119-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n119-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. προσφώωησις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n120-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n120-2">The rendering of this passage is somewhat conjectural, owing to
               defects in the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n120-3">Or, " when the report of your praises and prayers reaches him, he
               will not fail us in any of the other things which we justly ask from him, but will
               readily receive your petition and grant your requests."</note>
            <note xml:id="n121-1">Evag. iii. 14; Liberat. 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n121-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n121-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n121-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n121-5">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  --> =
               <foreign xml:lang="grc">λυσιτελοῦντα</foreign> (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n122-1">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n123-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, sweet; Evag.
               <foreign xml:lang="grc">γλυκείας</foreign>; Liberat. dulcem. The word is written over an erasure in the MS.
               (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n124-1"><!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e.
               ἀποσχίσται.</note>
            <note xml:id="n124-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">φώνας</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n124-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀναγνῶσται</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n124-4">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  -->for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n124-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n125-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρακτικός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n125-2">Evag. iii. 15; Liberat. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n125-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">κίνδυνος</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n125-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρακτήρ</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n125-5">Evag. iii. 16; Liberat. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n125-6">Literally, <quote>an adulterer</quote>; perhaps it is intended to express
               illegal occupation of the see.</note>
            <note xml:id="n125-7">See Mansi, vol. iv. p. 893.</note>
            <note xml:id="n125-8"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n126-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n126-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               as.L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n126-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, L., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n127-1">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n128-1">Cf. Evag. iii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n129-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n129-2">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> perhaps we should read
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, Barbarian.</note>
            <note xml:id="n129-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-3">Cf. Evag. iii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-4">Isa. xxv. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-1">Isa. lx. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-2">Ps. cxv. 14, 15.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
