<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
 <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb type="page" n="39"/>
         <div type="book" n="3">
            <head>Book 3</head>
            <div type="section" n="0">
               <p>The beginning of the third Book, which (inasmuch as it is from the history of
                  <persName>Zachariah</persName> the believer, who wrote in Greek to one <persName>Eupraxius</persName> by name, a minister of
                  the king, and engaged in his service) records the events that took place in the
                  <placeName>Synod</placeName>, which met at <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, after the death of <persName>Theodosius</persName>, in the days of
                  <persName>Marcian</persName>, in the year seven hundred and sixty-four by the reckoning of the Greeks.
                  And the number of the bishops was five hundred and sixty-seven, who were brought
                  together in consequence of the exertion of <persName>Leo</persName> of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and the letter that he
                  wrote to the king and his wife <persName>Pulcheria</persName>. And the Synod sent <persName>Dioscorus</persName> of
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> away to <placeName>Gangra</placeName> of <persName>Thrace</persName>, and appointed <persName>Proterius</persName> bishop in his stead,
                  and received the letter of <persName>Leo</persName>, which is called the <persName>Tome</persName>. And the other matters,
                  which occurred in <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, or in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, or in other places during the life
                  of <persName>Marcian</persName>, that is, a space of six years and a half; behold they are written down
                  here distinctly in these twelve Books below and the chapters contained in
                  them.</p>
               <p>The first chapter relates the events which occurred in the Synod of <persName>Chalcedon</persName>,
                  until the public address of <persName>Marcian</persName> the king to the bishops assembled there.</p>
               <p>The second chapter tells about the banishment of <persName>Dioscorus</persName> to <placeName>Gangra</placeName>, and the
                  consecration of <placeName>Proterius</placeName> in his stead; and the events which occurred in
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> upon his entry there.</p>
               <p>The third chapter relates the events which occurred in <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, concerning
                  Juvenalis of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, who broke his promises, and separated from <placeName>Dioscorus</placeName>, and
                  agreed to the Synod. And when the citizens of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> and the <pb type="page"
                     n="40"/>Palestinian monks learned this, they appointed, as bishop in his stead,
                  one <persName>Theodosius</persName>, a monk; who, in his zeal, had attended and watched the Synod
                  closely, and then went back to <placeName>Palestine</placeName> and told what had occurred at
                  <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The fourth chapter tells of <persName>Peter</persName> the hostage, the son of the king of the
                  Iberians, a wonderful man, who was taken by the people of <placeName>Gaza</placeName>; and they brought
                  him to <persName>Theodosius</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, by whom he was consecrated as their bishop.</p>
               <p>The fifth chapter tells about the flight of <persName>Theodosius</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, in
                  consequence of the king's threats; and also about the return of <persName>Juvenalis</persName>, by
                  force, to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, and the great slaughter that ensued upon his entry there.</p>
               <p>The sixth chapter gives an account of a certain blind Samaritan, who smeared his
                  eyes with the blood of the slain, and they were opened.</p>
               <p>The seventh chapter tells how <persName>Christ</persName> appeared in vision to <persName>Peter</persName> the Iberian,
                  bishop of <placeName>Gaza</placeName>, and told him to depart from thence, and also himself to suffer
                  banishment of his own accord.</p>
               <p>The eighth chapter tells about a certain monk, named <persName>Solomon</persName>, who acted cunningly,
                  and went in to Juvenalis of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, and threw a basketful of dust upon his
                  head, and reproached him.</p>
               <p>The ninth chapter tells how <persName>Theodosius</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> was taken, and was imprisoned
                  in a house containing lime, and there he ended his life.</p>
               <p>The tenth chapter tells about the heresy of <persName>John</persName> the Rhetorican, and how this
                  heresy was anathematised by <persName>Timothy</persName>, the bishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, after
                  him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n40-1"/></p>
               <p>The eleventh chapter tells about the mission of <persName>John</persName> the Silentiarius, from the
                  king to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The twelfth chapter tells about <persName>Anthemius</persName>, and <persName>Severus</persName>, and <persName>Olybrius</persName>, and <persName>Leo</persName> the
                  Less, and what happened in the seven years of their reign.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n40-2"/></p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="41"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
               <head>Chapter 1</head>
               <p>The<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41-1"/> first chapter of this book tells about theevents which occurred in the
                  Synod, beingtaken from the history of one <persName>Zachariah</persName> by name, who begins to write in
                  Greek to <persName>Eupraxius</persName> as follows</p>
               <p>Since it is acceptable unto you, and desired by you, Christ-loving
                  <persName>Eupraxius</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41-2"/> who are dwelling in the royal palace, and are occupied in the
                  service of kings, to learn what happened, in the reign of <persName>Marcian</persName>, to the holy
                  Church of God; and who they were who, in regular succession, were the chief
                  priests in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, and <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>,
                  from the time of the Council of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> — that Council which, ostensibly
                  convened about the matter of <persName>Eutyches</persName>, introduced and increased the heresy of
                  <persName>Nestorius</persName>; and shook all the world; and added evil upon evil; and set the two
                  heresies, one against the other; and filled the world with divisions; and
                  confounded <ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41-3"/> the faith delivered by the apostles, and the good
                  order<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41-4"/> of the Church; and tore into ten thousand rents the perfect Robe of
                  <persName>Christ</persName>, woven from the top throughout: therefore we, anathematising those two
                  heresies, and every wicked teacher of doctrine corrupt and contrary to the Church
                  of God, and to the orthodox faith of the three holy Synods, which skilfully
                  maintained the true doctrine; shall, to that end, employ this history which you
                  urged us to undertake.</p>
               <p>After the death of the holy <persName>Cyril</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, who carried on the conflict
                  against many corrupt doctrines, and exposed them, <persName>Dioscorus</persName> received the throne as
                  his successor; <pb type="page" n="42"/>and he was a peaceable man, and also a
                  champion;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-1"/> although he had not the same promptitude and boldness as
                  <persName>Cyril</persName>.</p>
               <p>At that time <persName>Theodoret</persName> and <persName>Hibo</persName>, who, along with <persName>Flavian</persName> of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> and
                  <persName>Eusebius</persName>, were deposed by the second Synod of <persName>Ephesus</persName>, which met there in the days
                  of <persName>Theodosius</persName>, about the matter of <persName>Eutyches</persName> and <persName>Flavian</persName> — Theodoret of <persName>Cyrrhus</persName>,
                  because he wrote twelve censures upon <persName>Cyril's</persName> Heads against <persName>Nestorius</persName>; and <persName>Hibo</persName> of
                  <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, because he wrote a letter to <persName>Moris</persName> of <placeName>Nisibis</placeName>, reviling <persName>Cyril</persName> — were, both
                  of them, upholding the doctrine of <persName>Theodore</persName> and <persName>Diodorus</persName>. And <persName>Theodoret</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-2"/>
                  went up to <persName>Leo</persName> of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and informed him about all these matters; and, with the
                  gift which blinds the eyes of the soul, he got the better of him. Whereupon <persName>Leo</persName>
                  composed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-3"/> that letter which is called the Tome, and which was ostensibly
                  written to <persName>Flavian</persName> against Eutychianism. But <persName>Leo</persName> also wrote to <persName>Marcian</persName> the king,
                  and his wife <persName>Pulcheria</persName>, and warmly commended <persName>Theodoret</persName> to them.</p>
               <p>This<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-4"/> <persName>Marcian</persName> favoured the doctrine of <persName>Nestorius</persName>, and was well disposed
                  towards his; and so he sent by <persName>John</persName> the Tribune, to recall <persName>Nestorius</persName> from his
                  place of banishment in Oasis; and to recall also <persName>Dorotheus</persName>, the bishop who was
                  with him. And it happened while he was returning, that he set at naught<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-5"/>
                  the holy Virgin, the <persName>Theotokos</persName>, and said, <quote>What is <persName>Mary</persName>? Why should she indeed be
                  called the <persName>Theotokos</persName>?</quote> And the righteous judgment of God speedily overtook him (as
                  had been the case formerly with <persName>Arius</persName>, who blasphemed</p>
               <p>against the Son of God). Accordingly he fell from his mule, and the tongue<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42-6"/>
                  of this <persName>Nestorius</persName> was cut off, and his mouth was eaten by worms, and he died on
                  the roadway. And his companion Dorotheus died also. And the king, hearing of it,
                  was greatly grieved; and he was thinking upon <pb type="page" n="43"/>what had
                  occurred, and he was in doubt as to what he should do.</p>
               <p>However, written directions from <persName>Marcian</persName> the king<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-1"/> were delivered by <persName>John</persName>
                  the Tribune to Dioscorus and Juvenalis, calling upon them to meet in Council, and
                  <persName>John</persName> also informed them of what had happened to <persName>Nestorius</persName> and to <persName>Dorotheus</persName>.</p>
               <p>And when the bishops of every place, who were summoned, were preparing to meet at
                  <placeName>Nicea</placeName>, Providence<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-2"/> did not allow them; for the king<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-3"/> issued a new
                  order that the assembly should be convened to <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, so that <placeName>Nicea</placeName> might not
                  be the meeting-place of rebels.</p>
               <p>Then<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-4"/> the <persName>Nestorian</persName> party earnestly urged and besought the king that
                  <persName>Theodoret</persName> should be appointed the president of the Synod, and that, according to
                  his word, every matter should be decided there.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-5"/> And when they met at
                  <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, <persName>Theodoret</persName> entered in and lived there boldly, like an honoured bishop;
                  he who a little time before had been ejected<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-6"/> from the priesthood by their
                  means. And <persName>Dioscorus</persName> and the chief bishops were vexed and troubled on account of
                  the haughty insolence which the man displayed; but they could not put a stop to
                  it, because of the royal authority, though they saw that the canons were despised
                  by him, and by <persName>Hibo</persName> also, with the help of the Roman legates of <persName>Leo</persName>, who were
                  aiding and abetting them.</p>
               <p>And when <persName>Dioscorus</persName> was proclaiming the doctrine of the faith in the Synod, and
                  with him Juvenalis, and <persName>Thalassius</persName> of <placeName>Cappadocia</placeName>, and <persName>Anatolius</persName>, and <persName>Amphilochius</persName>
                  of <placeName>Side</placeName>, and <persName>Eusebius</persName> of <placeName>Ancyra</placeName>, and <persName>Eustace</persName> of <placeName>Berytus</placeName>; then, as by a miracle,
                  <persName>Eusebius</persName> of <placeName>Dorylaeum</placeName> also agreed with them; for they saw that the Nestorian
                  doctrine of the two natures was confirmed, and established there, by the
                  co-operation of <persName>John</persName> of <placeName>Germanicia</placeName>, who fiercely contended, in the course of the
                  dispute there, with the side which said, <quote>It is right for <pb type="page" n="44"
                  />us to confess <persName>Christ</persName> after His incarnation as one Nature from two, according to
                  the belief of the rest of the Fathers, and not to introduce any innovation or add
                  any novelty to the faith.</quote></p>
               <p>Wherefore, <persName>John</persName> of <placeName>Germanicia</placeName>, and the rest of the Nestorian party, with <persName>Theodoret</persName>
                  at their head, brought about the deprivation of <persName>Dioscorus</persName>; because he said, "It is
                  right for us to believe that <persName>Christ</persName> became incarnate from two natures; and we
                  should not confess two natures after the union, like <persName>Nestorius</persName>.</p>
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44-1"/> then <persName>Anatolius</persName>, the bishop of the royal city, cried out in words to
                  this effect, <quote>Not for the faith is <persName>Dioscorus</persName> deposed; but he is set at
                  nought<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44-2"/> for refusing to hold communion with the chief priest, my lord
                     <persName>Leo</persName>.</quote></p>  
               <p>And after the outcry of many, and after the things had been spoken which have been
                  written in the Acts<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44-3"/> of that Council, at last those bishops being forced to
                  do so, defined our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> to be in two natures. And they praised the
                  Tome of <persName>Leo</persName>, and they called that an orthodox definition which said, <quote>There are
                  two Persons, and two Natures, with their properties and their operations.</quote> And
                  this being so, they were required to subscribe under compulsion; those very
                  priests who, a little time before in the days of the blessed <persName>Theodosius</persName>, being
                  assembled at the second Council of <persName>Ephesus</persName>, cried out many times, <quote>If anyone shall
                  say <quote>Two natures to two,</quote> let the Silentiarius come up!</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44-4"/></p>
               <p>And when they repeated this over to <persName>Dioscorus</persName>, by means of <persName>John</persName> the chief of the
                  Silentiarii, and asked him to agree to it, and to subscribe, and get back his
                  throne; he said, courageously, <quote>Sooner would <persName>Dioscorus</persName> see his own hand cut off,
                  and the blood falling on the paper, than do such a thing as that.</quote> Whereupon he
                  was sent into banishment to <placeName>Gangra</placeName>, <pb type="page" n="45"/>because the Nestorian
                  party published the report about him, that his opinions were the same as those of
                  <persName>Eutyches</persName>.</p>
               <p>And I think it well, omitting many of his sayings, both what he spoke and wrote to
                  <persName>Domnus</persName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, and in the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> itself, which testify concerning
                  the faith of the man, that his faith was like that of <persName>Athanasius</persName>, and <persName>Cyril</persName>, and
                  the other doctors, I think it well (I say) to make a written extract out of what
                  he wrote from his place of banishment to <persName>Secundinus</persName>, in the following words: —</p>
               <p>"Omitting many urgent matters, this I declare, that no man shall say that the holy  <!-- quotes start but do not end ? -->
                  flesh, which our Lord took from the Virgin <persName>Mary</persName>, by the operation of the Holy
                  Spirit, in a manner which He Himself knows, was different to and foreign from our
                  body. And, indeed, since this is so, they who affirm that <persName>Christ</persName> did not become
                  incarnate for us, give the lie<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n45-1"/> to <persName>Paul</persName>. For he has said, <quote>Not from angels
                  did He take (the nature), but from the seed of the House of <persName>Abraham</persName></quote>; to which
                  seed <persName>Mary</persName> was no stranger, as the Scriptures teach us. And again, <quote>It was right
                  that in everything He should be made like unto His brethren,</quote> and that word <quote>in
                  everything</quote> does not suffer the subtraction of any part of our nature: since in
                  nerves, and hair, and bones, and veins,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n45-2"/> and belly, and heart, and kidneys,
                  and liver, and lungs, and, in short, in all those things that belong to our
                  nature, the flesh which was born from <persName>Mary</persName> was compacted with the soul of our
                  Redeemer, that reasonable and intelligent soul, without the seed of man, and the
                  gratification and cohabitation of sleep.</p>
               <p>"<quote>For if, as the heretics think, this was not so, how is He named <quote>our brother,</quote>
                  supposing that He used a body different from ours? And how, again, is that true
                  which He said to His Father, <quote>I will declare Thy name to My brethren?</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n45-3"/> Let
                  us not reject, neither let us despise, those who think in this way. For He was
                  like us, for us, and with us, not in phantasy, nor in mere semblance, according to
                  the heresy <pb type="page" n="46"/>of the Manichaeans, but rather in actual reality
                  from <persName>Mary</persName>, the Theotokos. To comfort the desolate<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46-1"/> and to repair the vessel
                  that had been broken, He came to us new. And as <persName>Immanuel</persName>, indeed, He is confessed;
                  for He became poor for us, according to the saying of <persName>Paul</persName>, <quote>that we, by His
                  humiliation, might be made rich.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46-2"/> He became, by the dispensation, like us;
                  that we, by His tender mercy, might be like Him. He became man, and yet He did not
                  destroy that which is His nature, that He is Son of God; that we, by grace, might
                  become the sons of God. This I think and believe; and, if any man does not think
                  thus, he is a stranger to the faith of the apostles.</quote>"</p>
               <p>And although<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46-3"/> this apostolic man had been well versed in this confession of
                  faith from the beginning of his life, yet he was deposed and sent into banishment,
                  because he would not worship the image, with its two faces, which was set up by
                  <persName>Leo</persName> and by the Council of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>; and because he refused to hold communion with
                  <persName>Theodoret</persName> and <persName>Hibo</persName>, who had been deprived on account of their blasphemies.</p> 
               <p>But the story goes that when, on one occasion, he saw <persName>Theodoret</persName> sitting upon the
                  throne in the Council, and speaking from it, and not standing and making his
                  defence, as one should who had been canonically deposed from the priesthood; then
                  he himself arose and descended from the throne and sat upon the pavement, saying,
                  <quote>I will not sit with the wicked, nor with vain persons will I enter in.</quote></p> 
               <p>Whereupon the partisans of <persName>Theodoret</persName> cried out, <quote>He has deposed himself.</quote> But the
                  other bishops cried out, <quote>Our faith<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46-4"/> is perishing. If Theodoret, who holds
                  the opinions of <persName>Nestorius</persName>, be accepted, we reject <persName>Cyril</persName>.</quote> And then <persName>Basil</persName>, the
                  bishop of <placeName>Tripolis</placeName>, stood up and said, <quote>We ourselves have deposed <persName>Theodoret</persName>.</quote></p>  
               <p>But they say that <persName>Amphilochius</persName> was beaten on his head by <persName>Aetius</persName> the deacon, to
                  make him sign. It was this <persName>Aetius</persName> who went to <persName>Theodoret</persName> by night, and made a
                  complete copy <pb type="page" n="47"/>for him of the Symbol of the two Natures;
                  and when<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-1"/> it was accepted by the bishops, and they agreed to it, then
                  <persName>Theodoret</persName> insolently<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-2"/> derided<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-3"/> them, saying, <quote>See how I have made
                  them taste the leaven of the doctrine of Nestorius, and they are delighted with
                  it!</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-4"/></p>
               <p>"But Eustace of Berytus, when he signed the document, wrote in short hand,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-5"/> <!-- Quote starts but do not finish-->
                  <quote>This have I written under compulsion, not agreeing with it.</quote> And he wept very
                  much, as did also others who proclaimed the compulsion and exposed the
                  hypocritical profession of faith which was made, because the chief senators were
                  present time after time at the discussions, and closely watched the proceedings of
                  the Synod. But, at last, the king came there, with his wife <persName>Pulcheria</persName>, and he
                  delivered a public address<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-6"/> in the Martyr Church of <persName>Euphemia</persName> in the
                  following terms: —</p>
               <p><quote>From<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-7"/> the first time that we were chosen and accounted worthy of the
                  kingdom by God, amidst all the care of public business, no concern whatever in
                  which we might be involved<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-8"/> was allowed to hinder us, but we made it our
                  choice to honour the true faith of the Christians, and to accustom<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-9"/> the
                  minds of men to it, with purity; all novelty of false doctrines and preachings
                  that do not agree with the well proved doctrine of the Fathers, being taken out of
                  our midst. Therefore we summoned this holy Synod that it might cleanse away all
                  darkness, and put away filth of thoughts: that so, in pure mind, the doctrine of
                  the faith which is in our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> might be established,</quote> and so on, to
                  the same effect.</p>
               <p>When the king had finished his public address, the bishops praised him and the
                  Senate, and also the letter of <persName>Leo</persName>, affirming with respect to it that it agreed
                  with the faith of the Apostle <persName>Peter</persName>.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="48"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="2">
               <head>Chapter 2</head>
               <p>The second chapter tells about the banishment of <persName>Dioscorus</persName>, and the consecration of
                  <persName>Proteriusin</persName> his stead; and about the slaughter which ensued upon his coming in;
                  and the churchfunds, which he expended upon his allies the Romans, but which, by
                  right, belonged to the poor.</p>
               <p>The Synod having received such an end as this, <persName>Dioscorus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-1"/> was decreed to be
                  a confessor, and was sent away to live in <placeName>Gangra</placeName>; and <persName>Proterius</persName> was appointed
                  bishop in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, in his stead. This <persName>Proterius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-2"/> had been a presbyter on
                  his side, and had contended earnestly against the Synod at first, but afterwards,
                  with the object of snatching the see for himself, he became like <persName>Judas</persName>, a betrayer
                  of his master, and like <persName>Absalom</persName>, of his father; and he showed himself a rapacious
                  wolf in the midst of the flock. And many who were unwilling he afflicted and
                  ill-treated, to force them into agreement with himself. And he sent them into
                  banishment, and he seized their property by means of the governors<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-3"/> who
                  obeyed him in consequence of the king's command.</p>
               <p>Whereupon, indeed, the priests, and the monks, and many of the people, perceiving
                  that the faith had been polluted, both by the unjust deposition of <persName>Dioscorus</persName> and
                  the oppressive conduct of <persName>Proterius</persName> and his wickedness, assembled by themselves in
                  the monasteries, and severed themselves from his communion. And they proclaimed
                  <persName>Dioscorus</persName>, and wrote his name in the book of life as a chosen and faithful priest
                  of God.</p>
               <p>And <persName>Proterius</persName> was very indignant, and he gave gifts into the hand of the Romans,
                  and he armed them against the people, and he filled their hands with the blood of
                  believers, who were slain; for they also strengthened themselves,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48-4"/> and made
                  war. And many died at the very Altar, and in the Baptistery, who had fled and
                  taken refuge there.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="49"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="3">
               <head>Chapter 3</head>
               <p>The third chapter narrates the events whichoccurred in <placeName>Palestine</placeName> respecting
                  Juvenalis of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, who broke his promises, and separated himself from
                  <persName>Dioscorus</persName>. And the monksand the citizens of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> heard of the matter from
                  <persName>Theodosius</persName>, a monk, who, through zeal, was present at <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, and who,
                  afterhaving carefully watched the proceedingsthere, came to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> and gave
                  informationabout them; and they made him bishop by force, instead of Juvenalis</p>
               <p>And in <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, indeed, there were evils like these, and worse. But from what
                  cause I shall now tell. When Juvenalis was summoned to <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, and he learned
                  from <persName>John</persName> the Tribune the will of the king; and also that <persName>Nestorius</persName>, who had been
                  recalled, died on his return from banishment; then he (in as much as he was
                  persuaded that the doctrine of the Tome, which favoured the opinion of <persName>Nestorius</persName>,
                  was corrupt) summoned the clergy, and gathered the monks and the people together;
                  and he exposed this false doctrine, and anathematised it. And he confirmed the
                  souls of many in the true faith. And he charged them all, that if he should be
                  perverted in the Synod, they should hold communion with him no more.</p>
               <p>And at first when he went there, he made a great struggle, along with <persName>Dioscorus</persName>,
                  on behalf of the faith. But because the royal pressure<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49-1"/> was brought to
                  bear; and because of the flattery and compliments of the king, who himself waited
                  personally upon the bishops at the banquet, and showed great condescension to
                  them; and because the king also promised that he would give the three provinces of
                  <placeName>Palestine</placeName> to the honour of the see of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>; then the eyes of his mind were
                  darkened, and he left <persName>Dioscorus</persName> the champion<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49-2"/> alone, and <pb type="page"
                     n="50"/>he went over to the opposite side. And he treated with contempt the
                  oaths which he had made in the name of God. And both he and the bishops who were
                  with him agreed and subscribed.</p>
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50-1"/> when <persName>Theodosius</persName> the monk, and his companions who were in close
                  fellowship with him, and who zealously watched what was taking place in the Synod,
                  heard about this they returned quickly to <placeName>Palestine</placeName>; and they came to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>,
                  and told about the betrayal of the faith. And they called all the monks together,
                  and gave full information to them.</p>
               <p>And the monks assembled, and prepared themselves, and went to meet Juvenalis as he
                  was coming. And they reminded him of his promises, and that he had failed to keep
                  them. And they made this one request of him, that he would censure the proceedings
                  which had taken place, and anathematise them. But he showed himself like Pilate,
                  saying, <quote>What I have written, I have written.</quote> And the monks said to him, <quote>We will
                  not receive you then, for you have broken<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50-2"/> your oaths and your promises.</quote>
                  So he returned to the king.</p>
               <p>But the assembly of monks and clergy went back to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>. And the people, and
                  the bishops who were with them, were distressed,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50-3"/> and they consulted
                  together as to what they should do. And they decided to appoint another bishop
                  instead of Juvenalis. When they were speaking of the chaste monks, Romanus and
                  Marcian, and of other men of wonderful excellence; at length<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50-4"/> it was agreed
                  that they should appoint <persName>Theodosius</persName>, who had been found zealous, and who also had
                  contended for years on behalf of the faith. And they took him by force, while he
                  persisted in refusing, and conjuring them not to do so, and begging them to allow
                  him to be the helper of the person whom they appointed from amongst themselves.
                  However, they would not yield to his entreaties; but blessed him and placed him on
                  the throne. And when <pb type="page" n="51"/>the other cities of <placeName>Palestine</placeName> heard
                  it; in as much as they knew him to be a man of surpassing virtue, and zealous for
                  the truth; they severally<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-1"/> brought persons to receive his blessing and be
                  admitted to the priesthood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="4">
               <head>Chapter 4</head>
               <p>The fourth chapter tells about <persName>Peter</persName> the Iberian;and how he also was taken, and
                  was broughtto <persName>Theodosius</persName> by the people of <placeName>Gaza</placeName>; and he became their bishop</p>
               <p>Among these also was <persName>Peter</persName> the Iberian, a man wonderfully celebrated throughout
                  the world, a king's son, who had been given as a hostage to <persName>Theodosius</persName>; and who
                  was beloved by him and by his wife <persName>Eudocia</persName>, on account of his excellent parts. And
                  he was brought up in the king's palace; and he was placed in charge of the royal
                  horses. But he resigned this appointment, and gave himself up to the discipline of
                  <persName>Christ</persName> along with <persName>John</persName> the Eunuch also, who was his sponsor, and his father by
                  water and the Spirit. And they prospered, and God wrought signs by their means in
                  <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. And they fled from thence, and betook themselves next to the
                  wilderness of <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, and there they loved and cultivated the monastic life.
                  And although after this manner they desired to be hidden, yet they became greatly
                  celebrated; and they wrought signs like the apostles.</p>
               <p>And as they were changing from place to place, they arrived opposite to <placeName>Gaza</placeName> and
                  <placeName>Majuma</placeName>. And the men and the women and the people of all ranks and ages went out
                  and seized <persName>Peter</persName>, and brought him to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> to <persName>Theodosius</persName>, whom they besought
                  to make him their bishop.</p>
               <p>And he laid many charges against himself, and refused ordination. And against his
                  will <persName>Theodosius</persName> laid his hand upon his head and consecrated him, for he knew the
                  man.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="52"/>
               <p>And when he became violently agitated, and called himself a heretic; then
                  <persName>Theodosius</persName> hesitated<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n52-1"/> a little, and said to him, <quote>My cause and thine are
                  before the Judgment Seat of <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote> And he changed his words, saying, <quote>A heretic
                  indeed I am not, but a sinner.</quote> And <persName>Theodosius</persName>, being well acquainted with the
                  man, blessed him as priest for the people of <placeName>Gaza</placeName>.</p>
               <p>But there were other excellent deeds done by this man, which, however, I omit,
                  lest I should make my narrative too long.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="5">
               <head>Chapter 5</head>
               <p>The fifth chapter tells about the flight of <persName>Theodosius</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, in consequence
                  of the King’s threats; also about Juvenalis, who returnedwith an army of Romans;
                  and the great slaughter that ensued upon his entry there</p>
               <p>And when <persName>Theodosius</persName> was prospering in this manner, the report<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n52-2"/> of all that
                  he was doing reached <persName>Marcian</persName> the king. And Juvenalis returned, having with him
                  Count <persName>Dorotheus</persName> and an army; for the purpose of taking <persName>Theodosius</persName>, and making him
                  a prisoner, and deposing all the bishops whom he had made in his district, and
                  punishing<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n52-3"/> the monks and the people, and expelling them in consequence of
                  their insolence and rashness in setting up <persName>Theodosius</persName> as bishop in <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>. But,
                  by the desire of the queen, <persName>Peter</persName> the Iberian alone was to be spared; even though
                  he should not consent to hold communion with the other bishops.</p>
               <p>And when Juvenalis arrived at <placeName>Neapolis</placeName>, he found a large number of monks there;
                  and at first he tried to seduce them, simple men as they were, and single-minded,
                  whose arms and helmet were the true faith and works of righteous<pb type="page"
                     n="53"/>ness. These he endeavoured to persuade to hold communion with himself.
                  And when they turned away from this proposal with disgust, unless he would
                  anathematise the violent transactions of <persName>Chalcedon</persName>; he then said, <quote>It is the
                  king's will.</quote> And they still refused. Whereupon he gave orders to the Romans and
                  the Samaritans, who smote and killed these monks, while they were singing psalms
                  and saying, <quote>O God, the heathen are come into Thine inheritance, and they have
                  defiled Thy holy temple; and behold they are making <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> a waste place!</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n53-1"/></p>
               <p>And some of the Romans were overcome with pity, and wept. But some of them, along
                  with the Samaritans, killed many of the monks, whose blood also was poured out
                  upon the ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="6">
               <head>Chapter 6</head>
               <p>The sixth chapter tells about a certain blind Samaritan who drew near with faith,
                  andsmeared his eyes with the blood of those thatwere slain; and his sight was
                  restored<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n53-2"/></p>
               <p>There was a certain blind Samaritan who deceived his own guide, and said, <quote>Since
                  mine eyes cannot see the blood of the slaughter of these Christians, so that I may
                  delight myself in it; bring me near and I shall feel it.</quote> And when the guide
                  brought him near and caused him to feel it, he dipped his hands in the blood. And
                  he prostrated himself upon the ground; and he wept, with prayer and supplication,
                  that he might be a sharer in their martyrdom. Then he arose, and smeared his eyes,
                  and lifted up his hands to heaven; and his eyes were opened, and he received his
                  sight.</p>
               <p>And all who were witnesses of this miracle, were astonished and believed in God.
                  And the blind man also believed, and was baptized.</p>
               <p>But the party who administered the king's orders, laid <pb type="page" n="54"
                  />hold upon the surviving believers, and expelled<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54-1"/> them from the whole
                  district.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7">
               <head>Chapter 7</head>
               <p>The seventh chapter related how our Lord appeared to <persName>Peter</persName> the Iberian, of <placeName>Gaza</placeName>;
                  and told himthat he must depart along with those whowere expelled</p>
               <p>But they say that Peter the Illustrious was at rest, being left undisturbed by
                  all, both on account of the king's orders, and the loving care of the queen for
                  him.</p>
               <p>But he saw the Lord in a vision, saying to him indignantly, <quote>How now, <persName>Peter</persName>! Am I
                  being expelled in My believing servants, and art thou remaining quiet and at
                  rest?</quote> Then <persName>Peter</persName> repented and obeyed, and he arose and left <placeName>Gaza</placeName>; and he joined
                  those who were expelled, and departed with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="8">
               <head>Chapter 8</head>
               <p>The eighth chapter tells about a certain zealousmonk, named <persName>Solomon</persName>; who acted
                  cunningly,and went in to Juvenalis, as if he desired to be blessed by him, and
                  threw a basketful<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54-2"/> of dust upon his head, and reproached him</p>
               <p>And Juvenalis, having by means of the armed force<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54-3"/> of the Romans expelled
                  the believers and the monks who were in the country district, arrived at <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>
                  and sat upon the throne. And he paid no regard<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54-4"/> at all to his promises, nor
                  to the slaughter which had occurred upon his entry there, nor to the falsehood of
                  his oaths.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="55"/>
               <p>Then a certain monk, <placeName>Solomon</placeName> by name, was stirred in his spirit; and in this
                  honourable garb of chastity, and as if desiring to be blessed by the chief priest
                  himself, acted cunningly, and filled a basket with dust and ashes, and placed it
                  under his armpit, and drew near to Juvenalis. And the latter was glad when the
                  monk came in to him. And Solomon, being received by him, said to him, <quote>Let my lord
                  bless me.</quote> And, as the Roman guard permitted him to draw near and come close to
                  Juvenalis, he took out the basket of dust and emptied it on his head, saying, <quote>
                  Shame upon thee, shame upon thee, liar and persecutor!</quote> And when the Roman guard
                  were about to strike him, Juvenalis would not allow it. And he was not enraged,
                  but was rather moved to penitence by this, and shook the dust from his head. So
                  they only put out the monk from his presence. And he ordered that money for his
                  expenses<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-1"/> should be given to him, and that he should leave his country. The
                  monk, however, refused the money, but left the country.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9">
               <head>Chapter 9</head>
               <p>The ninth chapter tells how <persName>Theodosius</persName>, being sought for by the Roman army, was
                  taken andimprisoned in a house containing lime; whereat length he died</p>
               <p>But <persName>Theodosius</persName>, when he was sought for by the king's orders<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-2"/> through the
                  whole province,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-3"/> assumed the garb of a Roman, having on his head hair and a
                  helmet; and he went about confirming and encouraging the believers. At length,
                  however, when he arrived at the parts about Sidon, he was taken and delivered up
                  to the Romans by one of his own friends.</p>
               <p>And the Nestorian party were so enraged against him, because he had been going
                  about through the whole world, and <pb type="page" n="56"/>exposing and
                  anathematising the false doctrine of <persName>Nestorius</persName>, that they went up to the king, and
                  persuaded him to grant that the man should be given into their charge and keeping.
                  And they took him and imprisoned him in a small house, belonging to the monks, in
                  which there was quicklime.</p>
               <p>And these followers of <persName>Nestorius</persName> used to go to him in troops, and dispute with
                  him, hoping that under pressure of great affliction he would change his mind, and
                  agree to their will. And he prevailed over them all and repulsed them; and as they
                  departed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n56-1"/> from him ashamed and confounded, he said, <quote>Even though I am
                  imprisoned and thereby prevented from going about in the different places,
                  according to my former custom; yet as long as the breath is in my nostrils, the
                  word of God shall not be imprisoned in me; but it shall preach that which is true
                  and right in the ears of the hearers.</quote></p>
               <p>But the Eutychian party also imagined that he would agree with them; and they came
                  together to him, and entered into discussion with him. And in like manner,
                  contrary to their expectation, he showed them to be in agreement with <persName>Valentinus</persName>,
                  and <persName>Manes</persName>, and <persName>Marcion</persName>; and that their heresy was a wicked one, worse even than
                  that of <persName>Paul</persName> of <placeName>Samosata</placeName>, and <persName>Apollinaris</persName>, and <persName>Nestorius</persName>. And so they, in their
                  turn, departed from him, being condemned by him.</p>
               <p>And because they laid one affliction after another upon him, his soul also
                  continued steadfast in the good fight.</p>
               <p>While there he met with some writings of <persName>John</persName> the Rhetorician from <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>,
                  which were full of false doctrine and very defective, and it is a heresy; and he
                  exposed the man and anathematised him. And having finished his course, and
                  contended in the fight, and kept his faith, at length he died. And departing from
                  the prison, he went to be with <persName>Christ</persName> our Lord. And he left the example of courage
                  to the believers.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="57"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="10">
               <head>Chapter 10</head>
               <p>The tenth chapter gives a record of the heresy of <persName>John</persName> the Rhetorician of
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>; and howit was rejected and anathematised</p>
               <p><persName>John</persName> was an adherent of <persName>Palladius</persName> the Alexandrian sophist, and was second to him;
                  and for that reason he was called the Rhetorician; because that next to sophistry
                  comes rhetoric, and therefore by that name the philosopher is
                  surnamed.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n57-1"/></p>
               <p>This man, in the days of Proterius who succeeded Dioscorus, saw that the whole
                  city of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> hated <persName>Proterius</persName>, some in consequence of their zeal for the
                  faith, and others because they had been plundered and persecuted by him, with the
                  object of making them agree to the Synod and accept the Tome. He then sought to
                  ingratiate himself with the people, and to present a fine appearance, and to
                  collect money for himself, and to be celebrated with this empty glory. And not
                  having read the Holy Scriptures, and not understanding the meaning of their
                  mysteries, and not having exercised himself in the writings of the ancient doctors
                  of the holy Church, and not knowing what he was saying, or that about which he was
                  contending, he was puffed up[#57-2] to write a sort of proof that, after the
                  manner of a seed, God the Word was wrapped up in the body; and that He suffered in
                  His own Nature, if indeed He suffered at all. But he denied that the Word was
                  united to a human body; and he would not confess the natures from which One <persName>Christ</persName>
                  appeared. But he prepared and collected words, saying, <quote>It can by no means be
                  called a nature, as indeed without the seed of a man in the Virgin the Incarnation
                  took place.</quote> And he said, <quote>Therefore <persName>Christ</persName> was neither by her nor from her.</quote> And
                  he did not agree with the doctors of the Church, who declare that the <pb
                     type="page" n="58"/>human nature was united to God the Word, and that He became                     
                  man.</p>       
               <p>And with vain words such as these he used to chatter; and he also wrote books. And
                  in these he was self-contradictory; sometimes agreeing with <persName>Apollinaris</persName>, sometimes
                  with <persName>Eutyches</persName>; and again, stating what was quite new. And because he was in doubt
                  about the subject of his writings, lest they should be reviled,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n58-1"/> he did not
                  subscribe his books with his own name. But at one time he wrote the name of
                  <persName>Theodosius</persName>, the bishop of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, upon one; and again, the name of <persName>Peter</persName> the
                  Iberian upon another; that even the believers might be deceived by them and accept
                  them.</p>
               <p>But they say, that on one occasion, <persName>Peter</persName> the Iberian met with one of them, which
                  had been written in his own name, in a certain monastery; and when he took it and
                  read it he was full of indignation, arid he anathematised the man who wrote it.
                  And not there alone, but also in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and in <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, and in <placeName>Syria</placeName>, both
                  he and <persName>Theodosius</persName> anathematised the writings of this man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="11">
               <head>Chapter 11</head>
               <p>The eleventh chapter tells how <persName>John</persName> the Silentiariuswas sent by the King, after
                  the death of <persName>Dioscorus</persName> at <placeName>Gangra</placeName>, to exhort the Alexandrians to be united
                  to <persName>Proterius</persName></p>
               <p>But when the report of the death of <persName>Dioscorus</persName> reached the Alexandrians, there was
                  great trouble and sorrow. And after his death, on account of the love that they
                  had for him, they proclaimed him as a living man,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n58-2"/> and his name was set in
                  the Diptych. But let no man even of those, whose endeavour it is to revile what is
                  not done in exact order, find fault.</p>
               <p>But the believing party were desirous of appointing a bishop instead of <persName>Dioscorus</persName>.
                  However, they were afraid of <pb type="page" n="59"/>the threats of <persName>Marcian</persName> the
                  king; for he was sending letters in every direction, and fulminations against all
                  who would not agree to the Synod and receive the Tome. For so it was, that when he
                  heard of the men of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and of their intention to appoint a bishop for
                  themselves after the death of <persName>Dioscorus</persName>, he sent <persName>John</persName>, the chief of the
                  <placeName>Silentiarii</placeName>, with a letter from himself exhorting the Alexandrians to be united to
                  <persName>Proterius</persName>.</p>
               <p>And this <persName>John</persName> was of the same mind as the king, and he was an astute<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n59-1"/> man.
                  And when he came and saw the crowd, the numbers of monks arrayed in chastity, and
                  possessing readiness of speech in defence of the faith, and also the strong body
                  of the common people who were believers, with whom he had to deal, he was
                  astounded, and said, <quote>I am ready, if the Lord will, to inform the king and to
                  plead with him on your behalf.</quote> And he received from them a petition — which gave
                  information concerning their faith; and concerning all that happened to them at
                  the hands of <persName>Proterius</persName>; and concerning the impious conduct of the man, and his
                  wickedness, and the Church property which he expended upon vanity — written at
                  length in words which I omit to reproduce here, lest I should be tedious to the
                  reader.</p>
               <p>And when <persName>John</persName> returned to the king and told him about these matters, he said to
                  him, <quote>We sent you, indeed, to persuade and exhort the Egyptians to obey our will:
                  but you have returned to us, not according as we wished, since we find you an
                  Egyptian.</quote> However, when he perceived the things that were written about
                  <persName>Proterius</persName>, in the petition which the monks sent, he blamed the pride and the
                  craftiness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n59-2"/> of the man. And while he was occupied with this matter, he
                  died, having reigned six years and a half.</p>
               <p>But Morian<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n59-3"/> also, who reigned four years along with him, died.</p>
               <p>And after him, <persName>Anthemius</persName>, and <persName>Severus</persName>, and <persName>Olybrius</persName> received the kingdom. And one
                  year after, Leo the First was associated with them. So that the lives of these
                  four made up seven years.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="12">
               <head>Chapter 12</head>
               <p>The twelfth chapter tells about <persName>Anthemius</persName>, and <persName>Severus</persName>, and <persName>Olybrius</persName>, and <persName>Leo</persName>; who
                  reigned together and in succession, seven years</p>
               <p>When <persName>Anthemius</persName> had reigned five years he was killed by <persName>Ricimer</persName>. And <persName>Severus</persName>,
                  having reigned one year with him, died. And <persName>Olybrius</persName>, who reigned after <persName>Severus</persName>
                  along with <persName>Anthemius</persName> for one year, died. And <persName>Leo</persName> the First also died, having
                  reigned with <persName>Anthemius</persName> for three years, and two years after.</p>
               <p>In the first year of <persName>Leo</persName> indeed, <placeName>Antioch</placeName> was overturned by the earthquakes which
                  occurred; and there was also a great fire. And in the second year of his reign,
                  <persName>Sulifos</persName>, the Gothic tyrant, was killed. And in the third year of his reign, <persName>Aspar</persName>
                  the general<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n60-1"/> and his sons were killed.</p>
               <p>But there is in this third Book and in its chapters, which are written above, a
                  period of thirteen and a half years. And it is made up in the following manner: —
                  Of <persName>Marcian</persName> and <persName>Morian</persName> six years and a half; and of <persName>Anthemius</persName>, and <persName>Severus</persName>, and
                  <persName>Olybrius</persName>, and <persName>Leo</persName> the First, who reigned in succession and together, seven
                  years.</p>
               <p>And this period begins from the third<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n60-2"/> year of the three hundred and fifth
                  Olympiad, and it ends in the three hundred and eighth Olympiad.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n40-1">Probably <!--  Add Syriac  --> has fallen out, and the translation
               should be <quote>after <persName>Proterius</persName>.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n40-1">Here the text adds, <quote>The thirteenth Book tells about the accession
               of Marcian, and about the council of bishops which came to <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, and what took
               place in the council until the public address of the king to the bishops.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n41-1">Evag. ii. 4, 18; Liberat. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>Eupraxius of illustrious and Christ-loving
               memory, who was one of the eunuchs of the royal bedchambers,</quote> das Leben des Severus
               (ed. Spanuth), p. 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41-3">
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. εὐταξία.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. ἀγωνιστής</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-2">Jo. Eph. ap. "Dion." See Introd. p. 4, note.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-3">Here an extract in Cod. Rom. begins.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-4">Evag. ii. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. This word occurs again in this chapter (p.
               47, note 3), and probably in bk. 7, ch. 7 (p. 117, note 4); the Lexicons do not give
               any other reference.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42-6">Evag. i. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="[grc">πρόνοια</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-3">Evag. ii. 2; Liberat. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-4">Jo. Eph. (Anecd. Syr. ii. p. 363). See Introd. l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-5">Here extract in Cod. Rom. ends.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-1">Mansi, vol. vii. p. 104.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-2">I do not know what <!--  Add Syriac  --> means. Probably it is a
               copyist's error.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="[grc">πεπραγμένα</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-4">The words are written over an erasure in the MS. The Synodal Acts
               give εἰς δύο τέμνε. Probably <!--  Add Syriac  --> is a mistake for
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> and<!--  Add Syriac  --> has crept in from below. Transl. <quote>Cut
               in two the man who speaks of two natures</quote> (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n45-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n45-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n45-3">Ps. xxii. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L., and for
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-2">2 Cor. viii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-3">Here an extract in Cod. Rom. begins.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-4">The faith (Cod. Rom.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-1">Jo. Eph. Fr. (Anecd. Syr. ii. p. 363). See Introd. l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, p. 199, note 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, see p. 42, note 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-4">Here an extract in Cod. Rom. ends.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-5">In signs <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="[grc">ἐν σημείοις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="[grc">προσφώνησις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-7">Mansi, vol. vii. p. 132.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-8"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-9"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-1">Evag. ii. 5; Liberat. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-2">Here begins an extract in Cod. Rom. which continues to end of chap.
               viii.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-4">Or, "became exasperated."</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="[grc">ἀνάγκη</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, <foreign xml:lang="[grc">ἀγωνιστής</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-1">Evag. ii. 5</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-3">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->.
               Transl. "and they gathered the people and the bishops who were with them."</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-4">Evag. ii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->.
               Trans. "brought persons to him."</note>
            <note xml:id="n52-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> Cod. Rom. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n52-2">Evag. ii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n52-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n53-1">Ps. Ixxix. I.</note>
            <note xml:id="n53-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and
               for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="[grc">σπυρίς</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, <foreign xml:lang="[grc">παράταξις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="[grc">ἀνάλωμα</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="[grc">διατάγματα</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="[grc">ὑπαρχία</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="[grc">ἐπαρχία</foreign>.
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> has probably crept into the text by mistake from the line above
               (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n56-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n57-1">An exact translation of this passage is impossible. I have tried to
               give what appears to be the sense of it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n57-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. See note 4, p. 199.</note>
            <note xml:id="n58-1">Or, remain unknown.</note>
            <note xml:id="n58-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n59-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. See note, p. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n59-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n59-3">I.e. Majorian.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. στρατηλάτης.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
