<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book" n="8">
            <head>Book 8</head>
            <div type="section" n="8.0">
               <p>The eighth Book in the chapters, as given below,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n188-1"/> gives information, the
                  first about the accession of <persName>Justin</persName> and about <persName>Amantius</persName> the provost, who was killed
                  in the palace, and about <persName>Theocritus</persName> his domestic, and <persName>Andrew</persName> the chamberlain; in
                  the second it treats of <persName>Vitalian</persName> the tyrant, who was killed in the palace, he and
                  <persName>Paul</persName> his notary and <persName>Celer</persName> his domestic; in the third chapter it tells the story of
                  the martyrs who were killed in <placeName>Nagrin</placeName>, in the royal city of the land of the
                  Homerites, by the Jewish tyrant; in the fourth chapter it describes the flood of
                  water which entered <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, and how the flow of the waters of <placeName>Shiluho</placeName> in <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>
                  was stopped, and how <placeName>Antioch</placeName> was overthrown<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n188-2"/> by an earthquake, and the
                  temple of <persName>Solomon</persName> in the city of <placeName>Heliopolis</placeName> was burnt;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n188-3"/> in the fifth
                  chapter it gives an account of the negotiations which were held on the frontier,
                  and of <persName>Mundhir</persName>, king of the Saracens, who invaded the Roman territory, and of the
                  bishops who were banished; the sixth chapter, stating who were chief priests in
                  the days of this king <persName>Justin</persName>; the seventh chapter, concerning the prologue of <persName>Moro</persName>
                  the bishop. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="8.1">
               <head>Chapter 1</head>
               <head>The first chapter of the Book, concerning the accession of <persName>Justin</persName></head>
               <p>In<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n189-1"/> the year eight hundred and twenty-nine according to the reckoning of
                  the Greeks,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n189-2"/> on the tenth of July, when the year eleven was already
                  drawing to an end, on the death of <persName>Anastasius</persName>, <persName>Justin</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n189-3"/> became king after
                  him; and he was an old man of a handsome presence with white hair and was cura
                  palati, and he was illiterate. This man <persName>Marinus</persName> of <placeName>Apamea</placeName>, an able man, who was
                  chartulary,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n189-4"/> depicted in the public baths,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n189-5"/> as he had come from
                  the fortress<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n189-6"/> of <persName>Mauriana</persName> in <placeName>Illyricum</placeName> to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> with all the
                  history of his entry into <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and how he had been advanced from step
                  to step until he became king. And, when this same <persName>Marinus</persName> was accused on this
                  ground and came into danger, trusting in his astuteness, he readily rendered an
                  answer, saying, <quote>I have represented these things in pictures for the consideration
                  of the observant and the understanding of the discerning, in order that magnates
                  and rich men and men of high family may not trust in their power and their riches
                  and the greatness of their noble family, but in God, who raises the poor man out
                  of the mire and places him as chief over the people, and rules in the kingdom of
                  men to give it to whom He will, and to set the lowest among men over it, and
                  chooses men of low birth in the world, and men that are rejected, and men that are
                  not, that he may bring to naught men that are.</quote> And he was accepted, and escaped
                  from the danger.</p>
               <p>Now<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n189-7"/> <persName>Amantius</persName> the provost,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n189-8"/> he and Andrew the chamber-<pb
                     type="page" n="190"/>lain, his associate, favoured and cherished <persName>Theocritus</persName> his
                  domestic; and after the death of <persName>Anastasius</persName> he gave a large sum of gold to this
                  old man, the cura palati <persName>Justin</persName>, for the purpose of making largesses<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n190-1"/> to
                  the scholarians and the other soldiers, in order that they might make <persName>Theocritus</persName>
                  king. But he by giving the gold to these men gained their favour, and they made
                  him king, because the Lord willed it. And,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n190-2"/> because he shared the opinions
                  of the inhabitants of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, he gave strict orders that the Synod and the Tome of
                  <persName>Leo</persName> should be proclaimed. And this <persName>Amantius</persName> tried to prevent it, saying, <quote>The
                  signature of the three patriarchs and the principal bishops of your dominions, who
                  have written and anathematised the Synod, is not yet dry.</quote> And,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n190-3"/> because
                  he spoke with freedom, this same <persName>Amantius</persName> the provost was immediately put to
                  death, and so were <persName>Theocritus</persName> his domestic and <persName>Andrew</persName> the chamberlain. Now a year
                  afterwards <persName>John</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n190-4"/> the bishop of the city, died, and <persName>Epiphanius</persName> succeeded
                  him. And, since Severus withdrew from <placeName>Antioch</placeName> for fear of the threats of the king,
                  who<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n190-5"/> had ordered his tongue to be cut out, <persName>Paul</persName> succeeded him, who was
                  called <quote>the Jew.</quote> And, because he celebrated the memory of <persName>Nestorius</persName>, he was
                  driven out, and <persName>Euphrasius</persName> succeeded him, who was burnt in a cauldron blazing with
                  aromatic wax during the earthquake of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="8.2">
               <head>Chapter 2</head>
               <head>The second chapter of the eighth Book treats of <persName>Vitalian</persName> the tyrant, how he was
                  killed in the palace, he and <persName>Paul</persName> his notary and <persName>Celer</persName> his domestic.</head>
               <p><persName>Vitalian</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n190-6"/> the tyrant was general<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n190-7"/> in the days of <persName>Anastasius</persName>; and
                  he was a Goth and a stout-hearted warrior, and barbarians<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n190-8"/> followed him.
                  Of him it was said that he <pb type="page" n="191"/>wished to raise a rebellion
                  against <persName>Anastasius</persName>; and he exacted an oath from him, and he did not keep it, but
                  rebelled and induced barbarian tribes to follow him, and made an attack upon the
                  dominions of <persName>Anastasius</persName>, and took cities and their villages; and he marched
                  forward as far as the royal city, and blockaded it,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n191-1"/> and he annoyed the
                  king in many ways; and he caused him anxiety, because he had taken <persName>Hypatius</persName>, who
                  had gone out against him, prisoner and routed his army, and carried him about with
                  him, treating him with indignity and insult, and exposing him to contumely; but
                  for a large sum of gold which he received for him he sent him back. And, when
                  <persName>Anastasius</persName> was dead, a letter was written to him by this old man <persName>Justin</persName>,
                  entreating him and appeasing him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n191-2"/> in order that he might not again act
                  unjustly and rebel in his days, as he was accustomed to do. And then various
                  tribes also followed him, and the Goth came confidently;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n191-3"/> and the king
                  went out to the Martyr's Chapel of <persName>Euphemia</persName> at <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, and they swore oaths to
                  one another and entered the city; and he became one of the
                  generals<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n191-4"/>-in-chief; and in the fulness of power he went in and out of the
                  palace, and presided over the conduct of affairs. And he was united by a spiritual
                  relationship<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n191-5"/> to <placeName>Flavian</placeName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, who was driven out; and he nursed
                  great resentment against the holy <placeName>Severus</placeName>, who succeeded <placeName>Flavian</placeName>, but he was not
                  able to injure him in the days of <placeName>Anastasius</placeName>. However, at the beginning of the
                  reign of this old man <placeName>Justin</placeName> an order was issued that, wherever he was caught, his
                  tongue<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n191-6"/> should be cut out, they say, by the advice of <placeName>Vitalian</placeName>.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="192"/>
               <p>Now it happened some days afterwards that, while <placeName>Vitalian</placeName> was bathing in the royal
                  city, he received a command from the king to come to a banquet, he and <placeName>Justinian</placeName>
                  the general,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n192-1"/> his colleague; and he was coming from the baths, he and <placeName>Paul</placeName>
                  his notary and <placeName>Celer</placeName> his domestic, and, men having been posted ready to stab him
                  as he was going from one house to the other, he was killed, he and his notary and
                  his domestic; and God requited him for the evil which he did in the days of
                  <placeName>Anastasius</placeName> and the violation of his oaths; and his army did no injury.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="8.3">
               <head>Chapter 3</head>
               <head>The third chapter of the Book treats of the martyrs who were killed in <placeName>Nagrin</placeName>,
                  the royal city of the country of the Homerites, in the year eight hundred and
                  thirty-five of the Greeks, the sixth year of the reign of <persName>Justin</persName>,as <persName>Simeon</persName>, bishop
                  and <persName>Apokrisiarios</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n192-2"/> of the believers in the land of the Persians, wrote to
                  <persName>Simeon</persName>, archimandrite of <placeName>Gabbula</placeName>, as follows<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n192-3"/></head>
               <p><quote>We<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n192-4"/> inform your affection that on the twentieth of January in this year
                  eight hundred and thirty-five of <pb type="page" n="193"/>the Greeks<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n193-1"/> we
                  left the camp of <placeName>Nuʿman</placeName> in company with <persName>Abraham</persName> the presbyter, the son of
                  <persName>Euphrasius</persName>, who had been sent to <placeName>Mundhir</placeName> by <persName>Justin</persName> the king to make peace, of
                  which we wrote also in our former epistle; and here we, even all the believers,
                  express our thanks to him for his assistance to our side; and he knows what we
                  wrote formerly and what we are writing now. For we travelled ten days' journey <!-- quote end but do not start -->
                  through the desert towards the south-east, and we came upon <persName>Mundhir</persName> over against <!-- [mundhir is a person or place? google says person] -->
                  the hills called <quote>the hills of sand,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n193-2"/> and in the Saracen language
                  <quote>Ramlah.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n193-3"/> And, as we were entering the encampment of <persName>Mundhir</persName>, some
                  Saracens, heathens and <persName>Maʿdoye</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n193-4"/> met us, and said to us, <quote>What can you do?
                  for, behold! your <persName>Christ</persName> has been expelled by the Romans and the Persians and the
                  Homerites.</quote> And when we were insulted by the Saracens it distressed us; and in
                  addition to the distress sorrow also fell upon us, because, while we were present,
                  there came an envoy, who had been sent by the king of the Homerites to <persName>Mundhir</persName>,
                  and gave him an epistle full of boasting; and in it he had written to him as
                  follows: 'The king whom the Ethiopians set up in our country died; and, because <!-- quote starts but could not finde ending -->
                  the winter season had begun, they were not able to march out into our country and
                  appoint a Christian king, as they generally do. Accordingly, I became king over
                  the whole country of the Homerites, and I resolved first to slay all the
                  Christians who confessed Christ, unless they became Jews like us. And I killed two
                  hundred and eighty men, the priests who were found, and besides them also the
                  Ethiopians who were guarding the church. And I made their church into a synagogue
                  for us. And then with a force of 120,000 men I went to <placeName>Nagrin</placeName>, their royal city.
                  And, when I had sat down before it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n193-5"/> for some days and was not able to take
                  it, I swore oaths to them, and their chiefs <pb type="page" n="194"/>came out to
                  me; but I judged it right not to keep my word to the Christians, my enemies. And I
                  arrested them, and required them to bring their gold and their silver and their
                  possessions; and they brought them to me, and I took them. And I asked for <persName>Paul</persName>
                  their bishop; and, when they told me that he was dead, I did not believe them,
                  until they showed me his grave: and I dug up his bones and burnt them,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n194-1"/> as
                  well as their church and their priests and everyone who was found seeking refuge
                  there. And the rest I urged to deny <persName>Christ</persName> and the Cross, and become Jews; and
                  they would not, but, confessing that He is God and the Son of the Blessed, they
                  even chose to die for His sake. And their chief said many things against
                  us,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n194-2"/> and insulted us. And I ordered all their magnates<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n194-3"/> to be put
                  to death. And we fetched their wives, and told<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n194-4"/> them, now that they had
                  seen their husbands put to death for Christ, to deny, and have mercy on their sons
                  and on their daughters. And we urged them, and they would not; but the nuns strove
                  hard to be put to death first; and the wives of the magnates were angry with them,
                  and said,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n194-5"/> <quote>We ought to die after our husbands.</quote> And they were all put to
                  death by our order except <persName>Rhumi</persName>, the wife of the king who was to have reigned
                  there, whom we would not permit to die; but we kept requiring her to deny <persName>Christ</persName>
                  and live, having mercy upon her daughters, and retaining everything which she
                  possessed by becoming a Jew. And we bade her go and take counsel, attended by
                  guards from our army. And she went out, going round the streets and squares of the
                  city with her head uncovered, a woman whose person no one had seen in the street
                  since she grew up. And she cried and said, "Women of Nagrin, my Christian <!-- no ending qoute -->
                  companions, and the rest of you also who are Jews and heathens, listen!<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n194-6"/>
                  My <pb type="page" n="195"/>birth and my family, and whose Christian daughter I
                  am, you know; and that I have gold and silver and slaves, male and female,
                  and[n195-1] many lands and revenues; and, now that my husband has been put to
                  death for <persName>Christ</persName>'s sake, if I wish to be married to a husband, I have 40,000
                  denarii, and gold ornaments, and much silver and pearls and raiment, splendid and
                  magnificent, besides the treasures of my husband; and that these things have not
                  been falsely spoken by me you know of yourselves; and that to a woman there are no
                  days of joy like the days of her marriage; for from that time forward there are
                  distresses and lamentation, at the birth of children, and when<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n195-2"/> she is
                  deprived of them, and when she buries them; but I from this day forward am free
                  from them all. And on the days of my first marriage I was full of joy, and now,
                  behold! it is in the gladness of my heart that I have adorned my five virgin
                  daughters for <persName>Christ</persName>. Look<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n195-3"/> upon me, my companions, for, lo! you have
                  twice seen me,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n195-4"/> at my first marriage, and at this second one; for it was
                  with my face exposed before you all that I went to my former bridegroom; and now
                  it is with my face exposed that I am going to <persName>Christ</persName>, my Lord and my God, and the
                  Lord and God of my daughters, even as He in His love humbled Himself and came to
                  us and suffered for our sake.</quote></p> 
               <p><quote>Imitate<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n195-5"/> me and my daughters, and consider that I am not inferior to
                  you in beauty; and, behold! I am going to <persName>Christ</persName> my Lord resplendent in that
                  beauty, undefiled, as it is, by Jewish denial, that my beauty may be a witness
                  before my Lord that it could not lead me astray to commit the sin of denial, and
                  my gold and silver and all that I have may be witnesses that I did not love them
                  as I loved my God. And <pb type="page" n="196"/>that rebellious king permitted me
                  to deny and live. Far be it from me, my companions, far be it from me to deny
                  Christ my God in whom I have believed! and I and my daughters have been baptized
                  in the name of the Trinity, and I worship His cross, and for His sake I and my
                  daughters joyfully die, even as<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n196-1"/> He suffered in the flesh for our sake.
                  Behold! I resign everything that is pleasant to the eyes and to the bodily senses
                  on the earth and passes away, that I may go and receive from my Lord that which
                  does not pass away. Blessed are you, my companions, if you will hear my words and
                  know the truth and love <persName>Christ</persName>, for whose sake I and my daughters die. Then shall
                  there be rest and peace to the people of God. The blood of my brothers and my
                  sisters who have been slain for <persName>Christ</persName> shall be a wall to this city, if it hold
                  fast to <persName>Christ</persName> my Lord. Behold,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n196-2"/> with my face exposed I pass away from
                  this city, in which I have been as in a temporary tabernacle, that I may go with
                  my daughters to an everlasting city, for it is there that I have betrothed them.
                  Pray for me, my companions, that <persName>Christ</persName> my Lord may receive me and may pardon me
                  for having remained alive these three days after my husband.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n196-3"/></p> <!-- [triple quote?] -->
               <p><quote>And, when we heard a cry of lamentation from the city, and those who had been
                  sent came back and, when<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n196-4"/> asked, told us that, as we have written above,
                  <persName>Rhumi</persName> had gone round the city, speaking to the women her companions and
                  encouraging them, and a cry of woe was being raised<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n196-5"/> in the city, then we
                  were enraged with the guards, so much so that, had we not been persuaded not to do
                  so, we would have put them to death for allowing her to act in this manner. But at
                  last she came out from the city like a madwoman, with her head uncovered,
                  accompanied by her daughters; and she came and stood before me without shame, and
                  holding <pb type="page" n="197"/>her daughters, who were attired as for marriage,
                  by the hand. And she loosened the bands of her hair and turned them round with her
                  hands, and stretched out her neck, and bowed her head, crying, <quote>I am a Christian,
                  and so are my daughters; for <persName>Christ</persName>'s sake we die. Cut off our heads, that we may
                  go and find our brothers and our sisters and the father of my daughters.</quote> But
                  after all this madness I exhorted her to deny <persName>Christ</persName>, and only to say that He was
                  a man; and she would not, but one of her daughters insulted us for saying this.
                  And, since I saw<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n197-1"/> that it was not possible to induce her to deny <persName>Christ</persName>,
                  for the sake of striking terror into the other Christians I gave orders, and they
                  threw her to the ground, and her daughters' throats were cut, and their blood ran
                  down into her mouth, and afterwards her head was cut off. And by <persName>Adonai</persName> I swear
                  that I was much distressed because of her beauty and that of her daughters. Now
                  the chief priests and I thought that in accordance with the purport of the laws
                  children ought not to die because of parents; and I distributed them, both the
                  boys and the girls, among the army to bring them up; and, as soon as they are
                  grown up, if they become Jews, they shall live; and, if they confess <persName>Christ</persName>, they
                  shall die. And these things<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n197-2"/> I have described and related to your Majesty,
                  and I beg you not to suffer a Christian among your people, unless he denies and
                  stands on your side. Now, as for the Jews also, my brethren, who are in your
                  dominions, treat them kindly, my brother, and write and send me word what you wish
                  me to send you in return for this.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>All these things were written to him after we had reached<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n197-3"/> the
                  place:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n197-4"/> and he assembled his army, and the epistle was read before him,
                  and the envoy related how the Christians had been put to death and banished from
                  the land of the Homerites. And <persName>Mundhir</persName> said to the Christians in his army,
                  <quote>Behold! you have heard what has happened. Deny <persName>Christ</persName>; <pb type="page" n="198"
                  />for I am no better than the other kings who have persecuted the Christians.</quote> And
                  a certain man of high position in his army, who was a Christian, was moved with
                  zeal, and boldly said to the king, <quote>It was not in your time that we became
                  Christians, that we should deny <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote> And <persName>Mundhir</persName> was enraged, and said, <quote>Do
                  you dare to speak in my presence?</quote> And he said, <quote>Because of the fear of God I
                  speak without fear, and no one shall stop me; for my sword is no shorter than the
                  swords of others, and I will not shrink<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n198-1"/> from fighting unto death.</quote> And
                  because of his birth, and because he was a great and distinguished man and valiant
                  in war,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n198-2"/> <persName>Mundhir</persName> was silent.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And, when we returned to the camp of <persName>Nuʿman</persName> in the first week of the fast, we
                  found a Christian envoy,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n198-3"/> who had been sent by the king of the Homerites
                  before he died. This man, when he heard about the people who had been slaughtered
                  by this Jewish tyrant, immediately hired a man from the camp of <persName>Nuʿman</persName>, and sent
                  him to <persName>Nagrin</persName> to bring him intelligence of what he saw and learned as to the
                  events which had happened there. And, when he returned, he also in our presence
                  related to the former Christian envoy the things which are recorded above, and
                  that three hundred and forty of the magnates had been put to death,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n198-4"/> who
                  had come out to him from the city, and he swore to them, and perjured himself to
                  them; and as to their chief, <persName>Harith</persName> the son of <persName>Khanab</persName>, the husband of <persName>Rhumi</persName>, that
                  the Jew insulted him, and said to him, <quote>Trusting<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n198-5"/> in <persName>Christ</persName>, you have
                  rebelled against me; but have mercy upon your old age and deny Him, or else you
                  shall die with your companions.</quote> And he answered and said to him, <quote>Truly I am
                  distressed for all my companions and my brothers, because they would not listen to
                  me when I told <pb type="page" n="199"/>them that you were lying, and said that we
                  should not<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n199-1"/> go out to you nor trust your words, but fight with you. And I
                  trusted in <persName>Christ</persName> that I should have overcome you, and the city would not have
                  been taken, for there was nothing lacking in it. And you are not a king, but a
                  perjurer: and I have myself seen many kings who are truthful and do not lie. And I
                  will not deny <persName>Christ</persName> my God to become a Jew like you, and a liar. And now I know
                  that He loves me; and I have lived<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n199-2"/> long in the world, and have had
                  children and grandchildren, and I have daughters<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n199-3"/> and many kinsmen, and I
                  have won renown in wars by the power of <persName>Christ</persName>. And I am sure that, even as a vine
                  which is pruned and gives forth much fruit, so shall our Christian people be
                  multiplied in this city; and the church, which has been burnt by you, shall
                  increase and be built up, and Christianity shall have dominion and give commands
                  to kings, and shall reign, and your Judaism shall be blotted out, and your kingdom
                  shall pass away, and your dominion shall come to an end. Boast not that you have
                  done anything, nor be puffed up<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n199-4"/> with glorying.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n199-5"/></p>
               <p><quote>And, when the great <persName>Harith</persName> the son of <persName>Khanab</persName>, the venerable old man, had said
                  these things, he turned round and said in a loud voice to his believing companions
                  who surrounded him, <quote>Did you hear, my brothers, what I said to this Jew?</quote> And they
                  said, <quote>We heard everything which you said, father ours.</quote> And again he said, <quote>Is it
                  true or not?</quote> And they cried, <quote>It is true.</quote> And he said, <quote>If any man fears the
                  sword and denies <persName>Christ</persName>, let him be separated from among us.</quote> And they cried, <quote>Far
                  be it from us! Be of <pb type="page" n="200"/>good cheer, father ours: we are all
                  like you,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n200-1"/> and with you will we die for <persName>Christ</persName>'s sake, and no one amongst
                  us will remain after you.</quote> And he cried and said, <quote>Ye Christian people<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n200-2"/>
                  who surround me, and ye heathens and Jews, hear. If any man of my family and my
                  relations and of my kin denies <persName>Christ</persName> and joins this Jew, he has no part with me,
                  and he shall not inherit anything that is mine, but all that belongs to me shall
                  go to the expenses of the church that shall be built. But, if any man of my kin
                  does not deny <persName>Christ</persName> and survives me, he shall inherit my property; but three
                  fields, whichever the Church shall choose<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n200-3"/> in my estate,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n200-4"/> shall go
                  to the expenses of the Church.</quote> And, when he had said these things, he turned to
                  the king and said, <quote>You and everyone who denies <persName>Christ</persName> I deny. Behold! we stand
                  before you.</quote> And his companions were emboldened, and said, <quote>Behold! <persName>Abraham</persName> the
                  patriarch will look upon you and us with you; but everyone who denies <persName>Christ</persName> and
                  remains alive after you we deny.</quote> And he ordered them to be taken to the gully
                  called <persName>Wadiya</persName>, and their heads to be cut off and their bodies thrown into it. And
                  they stretched out their hands to heaven and said, <quote>Christ, our God, come to our
                  aid, and put strength within us, and receive our souls. And may the blood of Thy
                  bond- servants, which is shed for Thy sake, smell sweet unto Thee; and make us
                  worthy of Thy sight; and confess us before Thy Father, as Thou promisedst. And may
                  the church be built, and may a bishop be appointed in the stead of <persName>Paul</persName>, Thy
                  bond-servant, whose bones they burnt.</quote> And they bade one another farewell; and the
                  old man <persName>Harith</persName> made the sign over them, and he bowed his head and received the
                  sword. And his companions rushed forward and crowded together and smeared
                  themselves with his blood; and they were all martyred.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And a child of three years old, whose mother was coming <pb type="page" n="201"
                  />out to be put to death and was holding him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n201-1"/> with her hand, ran up (and
                  it happened that, when he saw the king sitting clad in royal apparel, he left his
                  mother and ran up and kissed the king on the knees); and the king took hold of him
                  and began to caress him and to say to him, <quote>Which would you like, to go and die
                  with your mother, or to stay with me?</quote> The boy said to him, <quote>By our Lord, I would
                  like to die with my mother; and for this purpose I am going with my mother; for
                  she said to me, <quote>Come, my son, let us go and die for <persName>Christ</persName>'s sake.</quote>" But release
                  me, that I may go to my mother, lest she die and I do not see her, because she
                  says to me, <quote>The king of the Jews has commanded that everyone who does not deny
                  <persName>Christ</persName> shall die,</quote> and I will not deny Him.</quote> And he said to him, <quote>Whence<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n201-2"/>
                  do you know <persName>Christ</persName>?</quote> The boy said to him, <quote>Every day I see Him in the church with
                  my mother, whenever I go to the church.</quote> And he said to him, <quote>Do you love me, or
                  your mother?</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n201-3"/> And again he said to him, <quote>Do you love me, or <persName>Christ</persName>?</quote> He
                  said to him, <quote><persName>Christ</persName> more than you.</quote> And he said to him, <quote>Why did you come and
                  kiss my knees?</quote> The boy said to him, <quote>I thought that you were the Christian king,
                  whom I used to see in the church, and I did not know that you were the Jew.</quote> He
                  said to him, <quote>I will give you nuts and almonds and figs.</quote> And the boy said, <quote>No,
                     by <persName>Christ</persName>, I will not eat the Jews' nuts; but let me go to my mother.</quote> And he said
                  to him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n201-4"/> <quote>Stay with me, and you shall be a son to me.</quote> And the boy said,
                  <quote>No, by <persName>Christ</persName>, I will not stay with you, because your smell is foul and fetid,
                  and not sweet like my mother.</quote> And the king said to those that were standing by,
                  <quote>Look at this evil root, whom from his boyhood <persName>Christ</persName> has deceived so as to make
                  him love <pb type="page" n="202"/>Him.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n202-1"/> And one of the magnates said to
                  the boy, <quote>Come with me, and I will take you, that you may be a son to the queen.</quote>
                  And the boy said to him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n202-2"/> <quote>You are smitten on the face. My mother, who
                  takes me to the church, is more to me than the queen.</quote> And, when he saw that they
                  held him tight, he bit the king on the thigh, and said, <quote>Release me, you wicked
                  Jew, that I may go to my mother and die with her.</quote> And he gave him to one of the
                  magnates, and said, <quote>Take care of him until he grows up; and, if he denies <persName>Christ</persName>,
                  he shall live; and, if not, he shall die.</quote> And, while this man's slave was
                  carrying him off, he struggled with his feet and cried to his mother, <quote>My mother,
                  come and take me, that I may go with you to the church.</quote> And, crying out<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n202-3"/>
                  before him, she said, <quote>Go, my son; you are intrusted to <persName>Christ</persName>'s care; do not
                  weep; wait for me in the church in <persName>Christ</persName>'s presence till I come.</quote> And, when she
                  had said this, they cut off her head.</quote></p>  
               <p><quote>And owing to this letter and the reports that have been received distress has
                  fallen upon all the Christians here. And, in order that the things which have
                  happened in the land of the Homerites may be made known to the pious believing
                  bishops, and that they may celebrate the memory of the illustrious martyrs, we
                  have written<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n202-4"/> these things; and we beg your affection to let them be made
                  known at once to the archimandrites and bishops, and especially to the chief
                  priest of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, in order that he may write to the king of the Ethiopians to
                  come at once and help<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n202-5"/> the Homerites. But let the chief priests of the
                  Jews in <placeName>Tiberias</placeName> also be arrested, and be compelled to send to this Jewish king, 
                  who has appeared, and tell him to put an end to the tribulation and persecution in
                  the land of the Homerites."<!-- [Ending quote but no starting quote ] --> And so the rest, consisting of 
                  <pb type="page" n="203"/>salutations to the chief priests and bishops of that time and the believing
                  archimandrites, which are contained in the epistle.</quote></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="8.4">
               <head>Chapter 4</head>
               <head>The fourth chapter of the eighth Book treats of the flood of water which
                  entered <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, and how the flow of the waters of <placeName>Shiluho</placeName> in <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> was
                  stopped, and <placeName>Antioch</placeName> was overthrown by an earthquake, and the temple of <persName>Solomon</persName> in
                  the city of <placeName>Heliopolis</placeName> was burnt</head>
               <p>While <persName>Asclepius Bar Malohe</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n203-1"/> the brother of <persName>Andrew</persName> and of <persName>Demosthenes</persName> the
                  prefect,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n203-2"/> held the see of <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, having become bishop there after <persName>Paul</persName>,
                  who showed an outward appearance of being orthodox,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n203-3"/>— (Now this man was
                  ostentatious in his person, and polished. And, when he was a bishop in <placeName>Edessa</placeName> in
                  the days of <persName>Flavian</persName>, before <persName>Asclepius</persName>, he drew up a written statement for him,
                  which did not anathematise the Synod, because he had been<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n203-4"/> his synkellos:
                  and this book came into the hands of the holy <persName>Severus</persName>, who succeeded <persName>Flavian</persName>; and,
                  when this <persName>Paul</persName> went up to salute him, he gave it him, and in divine love forgave
                  him his offence, that is, on his assurance that he was a believer; and this wise
                  man, who kept knowledge hidden, as it is written,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n203-5"/> did not expose him. And
                  in the days of this king he at first firmly refused to accept the Synod, while the
                  people of <placeName>Edessa</placeName> supported him, and even suffered loss and outrage on his account
                  every day; however, on being banished to <placeName>Euchaita</placeName> he conformed, and returned to
                  <placeName>Edessa</placeName>; and after surviving a short time he was struck with shame and soon after
                  died, and <persName>Asclepius</persName> succeeded him. And he <pb type="page" n="204"/>was a
                  Nestorian; but he was just in his deeds, and showed kindness to the tillers of the
                  soil, and was gentle towards them, and was not greedy after bribes. In his body he
                  was chaste, and in outward matters he did much good to his church, and paid its
                  debts. But he was active and violent against the believers; and many were banished
                  by him and outraged with every kind of torture, or died under the hard treatment
                  inflicted on them at the hands of <persName>Liberius</persName>, a Goth, a cruel governor, who was
                  called <quote>the bull-eater.</quote>)</p>
               <p>And,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n204-1"/> while affairs in <placeName>Edessa</placeName> were in this position, in the year eight
                  hundred and thirty-six of the Greeks, the year three,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n204-2"/> on the
                  twenty-second of April, the river <placeName>Scirtus</placeName>, which enters and passes through the
                  city, rose and overflowed, and overthrew two sides of the wall, and drowned many
                  persons; for it was supper-time, and while their food was in their mouth the
                  waters rushed in upon them, the flooded <placeName>Scirtus</placeName>. But this <persName>Asclepius</persName> escaped, and
                  so did <persName>Liberius</persName>. And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n204-3"/> the flow of the waters of <placeName>Shiluho</placeName>, which are in
                  <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, in the southern quarter of it, was stopped for fifteen years; and the
                  temple of <persName>Solomon</persName> in the city of <placeName>Heliopolis</placeName> in the forest of <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>, as to which
                  Scripture mentions that <persName>Solomon</persName> built it and stored arms in it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n204-4"/> [was
                  burnt].<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n204-5"/> And to the south of it are three wonderful stones, on which
                  nothing is built, but they stand by themselves, joined and united together and
                  touching one another; and all three are distinguished by effigies, and they are
                  very large. And in a mystical sense they are set, as it were, to represent the
                  temple of the knowledge of the faith in the adorable Trinity, the calling of the
                  nations by the preaching of the gospel tidings. There came down lightning from
                  heaven, while the rain fell in small quantities: it struck the temple and reduced
                  its stones to powder by the heat, and overthrew its pillars, and broke it to
                  pieces and destroyed it. But the three stones<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n204-6"/> it did not touch, but they
                  remain perfect; and now a <pb type="page" n="205"/>house of prayer has been built
                  there, dedicated to <persName>Mary</persName> the Holy Virgin, the Theotokos.</p>
               <p>And a year afterwards, in the year four,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n205-1"/> <placeName>Antioch</placeName> was overthrown by a
                  great earthquake of unwonted severity, and countless myriads of people perished in
                  it. For it was summer time; and, while they were feasting, and their food was in
                  their mouth, their houses<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n205-2"/> were thrown down upon them, as upon the sons of
                  Job in the proving of <persName>Satan</persName>. And <persName>Euphrasius</persName> was chief priest there, who succeeded
                  <persName>Paul</persName> who was called <quote>the Jew</quote>; and he fell into a boiling<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n205-3"/> cauldron of
                  wax, and perished.</p>
               <p>And his successor[#205-4] was <persName>Ephraim</persName> of <placeName>Amida</placeName>, who was <persName>Comes Orientis</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n205-5"/> at
                  that time. And this man in the authority which he exercised in various countries
                  was a man just in his deeds, and was not greedy after bribes, and was able and
                  successful. And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n205-6"/> for years he had been infected with the teaching of the
                  <persName>Diphysites</persName> through some books which his mother <persName>Mako</persName>(?) had inherited from a
                  certain <persName>Bar Shalumo</persName> of <placeName>Constantia</placeName>, of the school of <persName>Diodorus</persName> and <persName>Theodore</persName>; and he
                  corrupted and won over many persons, some by subtilty and moderation, and some by
                  the threats of the king, who was fond of him, and paid attention to what he wrote
                  to him.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="206"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="8.5">
               <head>Chapter 5</head>
               <head>The fifth chapter of the same eighth Book treats of the negotiations which were
                  held upon the frontier; and of <persName>Mundhir</persName>, king of the Saracens, who went up into the
                  territory of <persName>Emesa</persName> and <persName>Apamea</persName>, and took a large number of captives and
                  carried<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n206-1"/> them away with him; and of the believing bishops of the east who
                  were banished and withdrew from their churches</head>
               <p><persName>Kawad</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n206-2"/> king of the Persians, kept making pressing demands for the payment
                  of the tribute of 500 lbs. weight of gold which was paid to him by the king of the
                  Romans on account of the expense<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n206-3"/> of the Persian force which guarded the
                  gates facing the land of the Huns; and for this reason he used from time to time
                  to send his own Saracens into the territory of the Romans, and they plundered and
                  carried off captives. The Romans also invaded <placeName>Arzanene</placeName>, a country which belonged
                  to him, and the district of <placeName>Nisibis</placeName>, and did damage. On this account
                  negotiations<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n206-4"/> were held, and the two kings sent envoys, <persName>Justin</persName> sending
                  <persName>Hypatius</persName> and the old man <persName>Farzman</persName>, and <persName>Kawad Asthebid</persName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n206-5"/> and much discussion
                  took place on the frontier, which was reported to the two kings by their magnates
                  through couriers;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n206-6"/> and no peaceful message was sent by them, but they were
                  hostile to one another.</p>
               <p>And <persName>Mundhir</persName>, the Saracen king, went up into the territory of <persName>Emesa</persName> and <persName>Apamea</persName> and
                  the district of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> on two occasions; and he carried off many people, and took
                  them away with him. And four hundred virgins, who were suddenly <pb type="page"
                     n="207"/>made captive<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n207-1"/> among the congregation in the church of <persName>Thomas</persName>
                  the Apostle at <placeName>Emesa</placeName>(?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n207-2"/> he sacrificed in one day in honour of <persName>ʿUzzai</persName>.
                  <persName>Dodo</persName> also the anchorite, an old man, who was made captive among the congregation,
                  saw it with his eyes, and told me.</p>
               <p>Now of the bishops of the East, and especially those in the jurisdiction of the
                  learned <persName>Severus</persName>, some<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n207-3"/> were banished, and others withdrew to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>
                  and various other countries, walking in the footsteps of the chief priest, <persName>Severus</persName>
                  the doctor. And <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n207-4"/> of <placeName>Hierapolis</placeName> had been sent into exile at
                  <placeName>Gangra</placeName>; and he was imprisoned over the kitchen in the hospital<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n207-5"/> there, and
                  was suffocated<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n207-6"/> by the smoke, as he states in his epistle;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n207-7"/> and at
                  last he died. And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n207-8"/> <persName>Antoninus</persName> of <placeName>Berrhoea</placeName>, and <persName>Thomas</persName> of <placeName>Damascus</placeName>, and
                  <persName>Thomas</persName> of <placeName>Dara</placeName>, and <persName>John</persName> of <placeName>Constantia</placeName>, and <persName>Thomas</persName> of <placeName>Amrin</placeName>(?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n207-9"/> and <persName>Peter</persName>
                  of <placeName>Rhesaina</placeName>, and <persName>Constantine</persName> of <placeName>Laodicea</placeName>, and <persName>Peter</persName> of <placeName>Apamea</placeName>, and others
                  withdrew, and lived in hiding wherever it was convenient for them. But the see of
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> had not been disturbed, and <persName>Timothy</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n207-10"/> succeeded <persName>Dioscorus</persName>; and
                  he did not withdraw nor accept the Synod in the days of <persName>Justin</persName>; and the fugitive
                  believing priests who sought refuge with <pb type="page" n="208"/>him he received
                  affectionately, and honoured and encouraged them.</p>
               <p>Now<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n208-1"/> <persName>Nonnus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n208-2"/> of <placeName>Seleucia</placeName>, who came from <placeName>Amida</placeName>, had withdrawn to
                  his own city and taken up his abode in his mansion there, because he came of a
                  wealthy family, and had been governor<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n208-3"/> and great steward of the Church in
                  his city in the days of <persName>John</persName> the bishop, who came from the monastery of <placeName>Karthamin</placeName>,
                  a righteous man. He in his days blessed <persName>Nonnus</persName>, and said, <quote>I am confident in my
                  Lord that you will die as bishop in my see.</quote> And the event was delayed, inasmuch
                  as after the captivity of <persName>Amida</persName> the gracious <persName>Thomas</persName> became bishop there, who built
                  <placeName>Dara</placeName>. He, when the couriers<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n208-4"/> came to seize him, in order that either he
                  might accept the Synod or they might drive him out, fell ill<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n208-5"/> in
                  accordance with his prayer, and died suddenly and at once while in possession of
                  his see, the couriers being in the city; and this caused many to marvel.
                  Accordingly, in order that the blessing of <persName>John</persName> might be fulfilled, the men of
                  <persName>Amida</persName> seized <persName>Nonnus</persName> and appointed him bishop there; and he lived a few months, and
                  departed.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n208-6"/></p>
               <p>And in succession to him again, in the presence of three bishops, as the canons
                  require, <persName>Nonnus</persName> of <placeName>Martyropolis</placeName>, <persName>Arathu</persName>(?) of <placeName>Ingila</placeName>, and <persName>Aaron</persName> of <placeName>Arsamosata</placeName>, who
                  were on the spot, they ordained <persName>Moro Bar Kustant</persName>, the governor,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n208-3"/> who was
                  steward of the Church, an abstemious man and righteous in his deeds, chaste and
                  believing; and he was fluent and practised in the Greek tongue, having been
                  educated in the monastery of <persName>St. Thomas</persName> the Apostle of <placeName>Seleucia</placeName>, which in zealous
                  faith had removed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n208-7"/> and had settled at <placeName>Kenneshre</placeName> on the river <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>,
                  and there been rebuilt<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n208-8"/> by <persName>John</persName> the <pb type="page" n="209"
                  />archimandrite, a learned man, who was at that time an expleader(?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n209-1"/> a
                  native of <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, the son of <persName>Aphthonia</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n209-2"/> And this <persName>Moro</persName> had been trained up
                  in all kinds of right instruction and mental excellence from his boyhood by
                  <persName>Shʾmuni</persName> and <persName>Morutho</persName>, his grave, chaste, and believing sisters.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n209-3"/> And after
                  remaining a short time in his see he was banished to <placeName>Petra</placeName>, and from <placeName>Petra</placeName> to
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>; and he stayed there for a time, and formed a library there containing
                  many admirable books; and in them there is abundance of great profit<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n209-4"/> for
                  those who love instruction, the discerning and studious. These were transferred to
                  the treasury of the Church of <placeName>Amida</placeName> after the man's death. And in every matter
                  which I record, in order not to cause annoyance by blaming one man or praising
                  another, I have related whatever the truth of the matter is without any falsehood.
                  However, the man progressed more and more in reading in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and there he
                  fell asleep. And his body was conveyed by his sisters, who were with him and
                  ministered to him, comforting him in affliction, as it is written,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n209-5"/> and
                  laid in his own Martyrs' Chapel in the village of <placeName>Beth Shuro</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n209-6"/> And as a
                  record of the eloquent expression of his love of instruction I will set down at
                  the end of this Book the prologue composed by him in the Greek tongue and inserted
                  in his Tetreuangelion.</p>
               <p>Now<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n209-7"/> the believing cloistered monks in the East had also, moreover, been
                  expelled and had withdrawn from the year three until the year nine,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n209-8"/> one
                  week, that is, of years, from their cloisters in the district of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> and in
                  <placeName>Euphratesia</placeName>, and also in <placeName>Osrhoene</placeName> and <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>. And the cloister of <persName>Thomas</persName> at
                  <placeName>Seleucia</placeName> with the brotherhood came to <placeName>Kenneshre</placeName> <pb type="page" n="210"/>on the
                  <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>, and was there settled by the learned <persName>John</persName> the archimandrite, the son of
                  <persName>Aphthonia</persName>. And <persName>Cyrus</persName>, <persName>archimandrite</persName> of the Syrians in <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, was expelled,
                  together with the brotherhood of the monastery<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n210-1"/> of <persName>Thel ʿAddo</persName>, and the
                  monastery of <persName>Romanus</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n210-2"/> and S<persName>imeon of Lʾgino</persName>, and <persName>Ignatius</persName>, archimandrite
                  of the monastery of ʿ<persName>Akibo</persName> at <placeName>Chalcis</placeName>, and the monastery of <persName>Sʾnun</persName>, and <persName>John</persName>,
                  archimandrite of <placeName>Khafro dʾBirtho</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n210-3"/> and the monastery of my lord <persName>Bassus</persName>,
                  and <persName>John</persName> of the Orientals, and the monks of the Arches, and the monastery of
                  <persName>Magnus</persName>(?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n210-4"/> and <persName>Sergius</persName> of the Quarry, and <persName>Thomas</persName> of the house of <placeName>Natsih</placeName>,
                  and <persName>Isaac</persName> of the house of ʿʾbedyeshuʿ, and the cloisters of ʿArab<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n210-5"/> in <!-- [Last name? Quotes? place? ] -->
                  <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName> and <persName>Izlo</persName> and <persName>Beth Gaugal</persName>, and five metropolitan cloisters in <placeName>Amida</placeName>,
                  <persName>Hananyo</persName> and <persName>Abraham</persName> called <quote>the humble,</quote> a worker of miracles, and <quote>Daniel</quote>, visitor
                  of the cloister of <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, and <persName>Elijah</persName> of the house of <placeName>Ishokuni</placeName>, and <persName>Simai</persName> and
                  <persName>Cosmas</persName> of the foundation of <persName>John</persName> the Anzetenian,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n210-6"/> and <persName>Maron</persName> of the
                  Orientals, and <persName>Solomon</persName> of the house of my lord <persName>Samuel</persName>, and <persName>Cyrus</persName> of <placeName>Sugo</placeName>, and the
                  monks of the Watch-tower and of Thiri, near <placeName>Rhesaina</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Now for this reason four or five communities of hermits also settled in the
                  desert: at <placeName>Ramsho Mori</placeName>, a chaste man and of honourable character; and at <placeName>Natfo</placeName>
                  <placeName>Sergius</placeName>, a plain and simple man, and after him <persName>Antony</persName>, a mild and peaceful man,
                  and that kindly old man <persName>Elijah</persName>, our countryman, and <persName>Simeon</persName> of <placeName>Chalcis</placeName>, and
                  <persName>Sergius</persName>, who has now rebuilt <placeName>Sodakthe</placeName>(?), and the community on the
                  <placeName>Harmosho</placeName>(?),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n210-7"/> the <pb type="page" n="211"/>monastery founded by my lord
                  <persName>John</persName> at <placeName>Hauro</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n211-1"/> And <persName>Simeon</persName>, archimandrite of the monastery of my lord
                  <persName>Isaac</persName> at <placeName>Gabbula</placeName>, which is now polluted<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n211-2"/> with the heresy of <persName>Julian</persName> the
                  Phantasiast, was at that time zealous in the faith, he and those who were with
                  him; and <persName>Bar Hakino</persName> of the house of my lord <persName>Hanino</persName>, a worker of miracles, was
                  similarly moved with zeal, insomuch as to go up to the royal city and in his own
                  person admonish and reprove the king, although he was not received; and this is
                  witnessed by <persName>Akhsʾnoyo's</persName> epistle of thanks which he wrote to him from <placeName>Gangra</placeName>; and
                  similarly with the monks of the house of my lord <persName>Zakhkhai</persName> at <placeName>Callinicus</placeName>, and of
                  the foundation of my lord <persName>Abbo</persName>, and of <persName>Beth Rʾkum</persName>.</p>
               <p>And so the desert was at peace, and was abundantly supplied with a population of
                  believers who lived in it, and fresh ones who were every day added to them and
                  aided in swelling the numbers of their brethren, some from a desire to visit their
                  brethren out of Christian love, and others again because they were being driven
                  from country to country by the bishops in the cities. And there grew up, as it
                  were, a commonwealth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n211-3"/> of illustrious and believing priests, and a tranquil
                  brotherhood with them; and they were united in love and abounded in mutual
                  affection, and they were beloved and acceptable in the sight of everyone; and
                  nothing was lacking, for the honoured heads of the corporation, which is composed
                  of all the members of the body, accompanied them, the pious <persName>John</persName> of <placeName>Constantia</placeName>, a
                  religious and ascetic man, (he would not even partake of the desirable bread, <quote>the
                  foundation of the life of man,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n211-4"/> and so he progressed in the reading of
                  the Scriptures and became a gnostic and a theoretic;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n211-5"/> for he used to raise
                  his understanding upwards by the study of spiritual things for the space of three
                  hours, marvelling and meditating on the wisdom of the works of God; and for three
                  hours more, from the sixth to the ninth, he continued in joy <pb type="page"
                     n="212"/>and peace with every man, in intercourse with those who came to him
                  upon necessary business)—and <persName>Thomas</persName> of <placeName>Dara</placeName> again, while undergoing many labours,
                  conversed much upon physics.</p> 
               <p>Now in the year nine,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n212-1"/> in the fifth year of the reign of this serene king,
                  <persName>Justinian</persName>, the king of our day, being moved by God our Lord, who had foreknowledge
                  of his deeds, he distributed justice, and ordered that all orders should return
                  from exile and from the countries to which they had withdrawn in zeal for the
                  faith, while he summoned the believing bishops to come up to him. And, after this
                  had happened in the year nine, in the year ten<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n212-2"/> a multitude of Huns
                  entered the Roman territory and massacred those whom they found outside the
                  cities; and they crossed the river Euphrates, and advanced as far as the district
                  of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. Accordingly, under the direction of God, as he said, <quote>My people, enter
                  thou into thy chambers, and hide thyself until My indignation be
                  overpast,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n212-3"/> and by order of the king, the believers in the East again
                  retired into hiding. But <persName>John</persName> the hermit of <placeName>Anastasia</placeName>, a man of honourable
                  character, had been killed in the desert by the Huns; but <persName>Simeon</persName> the hermit, who
                  was called <quote>the horned,</quote> had not been hurt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="8.6">
               <head>Chapter 6</head>
               <head>The sixth chapter of the eighth Book, stating who were chief priests in the
                  days of <persName>Justin</persName>, who, after reigning nine years died in the year five,and this
                  Justinian of our day, his sister’s son, became king after him</head> <!-- [Justician a name? ] -->
               <p>The chief priests<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n212-4"/> in the days of <persName>Justin</persName> are as follows:— Of <placeName>Rome</placeName>,
                  <persName>Hormisda</persName>; of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, <persName>Timothy</persName>; of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, <persName>Peter</persName>, who succeeded <persName>John</persName>; and of
                  <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, <persName>Paul</persName> the Jew, who was driven out, and after him <persName>Euphrasius</persName>, who was <pb
                     type="page" n="213"/>burnt in the earthquake of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> in the year
                  four<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-1"/> and after him was <persName>Ephraim</persName> of <placeName>Amida</placeName>; of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, <persName>Epiphanius</persName>.
                  There is comprised in this space of time<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-2"/> a space of nine years.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="8.7">
               <head>Chapter 7</head>
               <head>The seventh chapter. In it is contained below the prologue composed by <persName>Moro</persName>,
                  bishop of <placeName>Amida</placeName>, in the Greek tongue in the Tetreuangelion<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-3"/></head>
               <p><quote>In order<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-4"/> to gather together the sense of a long treatise a man stores up
                  a knowledge of these things succinctly under a few heads in his mind and
                  memory<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-5"/> and understanding. And we may understand these things from the
                  heads<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-6"/> which are set down in this book; and these again cause the inner
                  meaning<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-7"/> of all that is in them to pass rapidly and succinctly into the
                  mind, when heard and considered<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-8"/> in due order. For, if a man gathers
                  together the record of the Gospels, he will learn from it that God became
                  incarnate, and that divine<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-9"/> as well as human properties are His, by which
                  He made<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-10"/> the <pb type="page" n="214"/>foundations of the world, which at
                  His second coming He will make clearly to appear. And so everyone who examines
                  these things severally will find first a notice of the census before His
                  Incarnation, and then next the birth of <persName>John</persName> the Baptist for a testimony to the
                  God of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, which happened in accordance with the previous annunciation of the
                  angel; and he will find that the supernatural birth of <persName>Jesus</persName>, who is God, took
                  place in the Virgin <persName>Mary</persName> and from her, and that every man has his beginning from
                  the earth according to the saying of the Baptist,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n214-1"/> but He who is not from
                  the earth is <persName>Jesus</persName> from heaven.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Now the testimonies to His Incarnation mentioned<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n214-2"/> in the book of the
                  Gospel are those spoken in the spirit by <persName>Elizabeth</persName> and by the angel to the Virgin
                  and <persName>Joseph</persName> and the shepherds at the annunciation of His birth by the assembly of
                  watching angels; and again the prophecy of <persName>Zachariah</persName>, and the rising of the star,
                  which betokened<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n214-3"/> the indestructible reign of the Son of God, who was born;
                  and the prophecy of <persName>Simeon</persName> the priest and <persName>Anna</persName> about the coming of <persName>Christ</persName> for the
                  salvation of the world and of <placeName>Israel</placeName>; and besides these also the proclamation of
                  the Baptist, who testified that he was from earth and our Saviour from heaven.
                  And, further, in the Gospel-record a man will understand His divine dispensation,
                  which was effected by infinite wisdom, and not through book-wisdom and the pursuit
                  of learning; and His power of performing wonderful mighty works in deed and word,
                  and His knowledge about everything, and that He did no sin; and again that it was
                  at His own pleasure to suffer in His own time and not to suffer when it was not
                  time; and that it was in His power<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n214-4"/> to destroy sufferings by His voluntary
                  sufferings in the body, and to do away death by His Resurrection and to ascend to
                  heaven. And the record plainly states that He became incarnate of the Virgin in
                  flesh endowed with a soul and an intellect; it states His nine months' human
                  conception, His natural and <pb type="page" n="215"/>supernatural<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n215-1"/> birth,
                  and that He was wrapped in swaddling- clothes and sucked milk, and was also
                  circumcised according to law; and, further, that He fled before the threats of
                  Herod into <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, carried by His mother, and that He came up from <placeName>Egypt</placeName> for the
                  renovation of <placeName>Israel</placeName> and after the manner of <placeName>Israel</placeName>; and again,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n215-2"/> that He
                  increased in stature, and was subject to His mother and to <persName>Joseph</persName> her husband, and
                  was baptized with water by <persName>John</persName> to signify the renovating birth of mankind, which
                  is in him renewed in a figure, because<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n215-3"/> His baptism bestowed upon us the
                  holy birth of the Spirit; and He was tempted by the devil as a man, but as God
                  easily overcame the tempter in the contest and the argument; and He was ministered
                  to by angels; and He gave peace to our race by restoring us to Paradise; further,
                  He associated with the disciples in human fashion, and withdrew at one time from
                  the persecutors, and hungered<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n215-4"/> and thirsted<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n215-5"/> and was weary; but He
                  showed that He did not submit to these things merely from the necessity of
                  nature<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n215-6"/> in human fashion, as though He were not God,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n215-7"/> by the fact
                  that it is testified that He verily fasted forty days and was afterwards hungry
                  (in a similar manner He also slept; but, because He was on a mountain in quiet, He
                  kept watch in prayer, and this prayer He made to the Father in human fashion on
                  behalf of men; but on the sea and in the storm He slept in the ship for the
                  instruction of the disciples, that they might believe that it is He who stills the
                  storms of the seas and the sound of their waves); and, further, that, when they
                  sought to throw Him down from the brow of the hill they could not do so, but,
                  while<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n215-8"/> they stood all around Him, He passed through the midst of them and
                  went His way; and, <pb type="page" n="216"/>when wounded by the lance on the
                  Cross, His life did not pass away of necessity, but He bowed His head and gave up
                  the ghost; and in every respect divine and human qualities are His. But the
                  reforms which <persName>Christ</persName> effected in the world are His rebuke of the deceiver, and the
                  demons which He drove out, and the fiends which He ejected, and the sore diseases
                  which He healed, and the dead which He raised, and the divers temptations which He
                  thrust away, and certain passions which He brought to naught; which reforms were
                  types and figures of the future world, which shall be far removed from evil, the
                  world which is looked for by us with hope and faith and love. And the teaching of
                  our Saviour draws men away from the passion<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n216-1"/> of the love of money and the
                  love of glory and pleasure, and raises them up that they may serve God in
                  uprightness of will.</quote></p>
               <p>Now there was inserted in the Gospel of the holy <persName>Moro</persName> the bishop, in the
                  eighty-ninth canon, a chapter which is related only by <persName>John</persName> in his Gospel, and is
                  not found in other manuscripts, a section running thus: <quote>It happened<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n216-2"/> one
                  day, while <persName>Jesus</persName> was teaching, they brought Him a woman who had been
                  found<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n216-3"/> to be with child of adultery, and told Him about her. And <persName>Jesus</persName>
                  said to them (since as God He knew their shameful passions and also their deeds),
                  <quote>What does He command<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n216-4"/> in the law?</quote> And they said to Him, <quote>That at the
                  mouth of two or three witnesses she should be stoned.</quote> But He answered and said to
                  them, <quote>In accordance with the law, whoever is pure and free from these sinful
                  passions, and can bear witness with confidence and authority, as being under no
                  blame in respect of this sin, let him bear witness against her, and let him first
                  throw<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n216-5"/> a stone at her, and then those that are after him, and she shall be
                  stoned.</quote> But they, because <pb type="page" n="217"/>they were subject to
                  condemnation and blameworthy<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n217-1"/> in respect of this sinful<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n217-2"/> passion,
                  went out one by one from before Him and left the woman. And, when they had gone,
                  <persName>Jesus</persName> looked upon the ground and, writing in the dust there, said to the woman,
                  <quote>They who brought thee here and wished to bear witness against thee, having
                  understood what I said to them, which thou hast heard, have left thee and
                  departed. Do thou also, therefore, go thy way, and commit not this sin
                  again.</quote></quote></p>
            </div> 
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n188-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->. as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n188-2">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n188-3">The word <!--  Add Syriac  --> has dropped out before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as appears from the heading of the chapter below.</note>
            <note xml:id="n189-1">vii. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n189-2">518.</note>
            <note xml:id="n189-3">vii. 14; Mich. fol. 161 r; cf. Jo. Mal. p. 410.</note>
            <note xml:id="n189-4">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n189-5"><foreign xml:lang="grc">δημόσιον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n189-6"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κάστρον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n189-7">Cf. Jo. Mal. pp. 410, 411.</note>
            <note xml:id="n189-8"><foreign xml:lang="grc">πραιπόσιτος</foreign>, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="Latin">praepositus sacri cubiculli.</foreign></note>
            <note xml:id="n190-1"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ῥόγας</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n190-2">Mich. loc. cit.</note>
            <note xml:id="n190-3">Cf. Jo. Mal. loc. cit.</note>
            <note xml:id="n190-4">Cf. Theoph. A.M. 6012.</note>
            <note xml:id="n190-5">Cf. Evag. iv. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n190-6">vii. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n190-7"><foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n190-8">There is no <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L., but the letter must be inserted.</note>
            <note xml:id="n191-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. The usual meaning of this word is <quote>take,</quote>
               which is here impossible. The word sometimes, however, means <quote>shut,</quote> and the
               rendering in the text seems justified by the use in vii. 5 (p. 212, l. 23,
               L.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n191-2">Cf. Jo. Mal. p. 412; Evag. iv. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n191-3">It is very probable that we should insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, translating, <quote>various tribes also and Goths following
               him, he came confidently.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n191-4"><foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n191-5">In bk. 3, ch. 4 this word means <quote>godfather</quote>; but, since this
               meaning seems to be here out of place, I have given it the indefinite rendering
               above. The relation meant is that of the <foreign xml:lang="grc">σύντεκνος</foreign>, which we can hardly express in
               English (<persName>Smith</persName>, Thesaurus, col. 4342).</note>
            <note xml:id="n191-6">Cf. Evag. iv. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n192-1"><foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n192-2">There is probably some mistake in the heading, as a bishop could
               not be an apokrisiarios. Jo. Eph. (ap. <quote>Dion.</quote>) omits the word, while Mart. Areth.
               speaks of a <foreign xml:lang="grc">Συμεωνίτου πρεσβυτέρου καὶ ἀποκρισιαρίου.</foreign></note>
            <note xml:id="n192-3">This chapter is contained in Cod. Rom. Mai's text is, however, not
               taken from the MS. but is a copy of that of Assemani (B. O. vol. i. p. 364 ff.),
               taken not from our author, but from <persName>John</persName> of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> (ap. <quote>Dion.</quote>). The letter also
               exists in a much longer form in Brit. Mus. Add. MS. 14,650, fol. 155, and in a MS. in
               the Museum Borgianum at Rome, which has been edited by Prof. <persName>Guidi</persName> [<foreign xml:lang="it">Atti dell’
               Accademia de’ Lincei</foreign>, Ser. 3, Tom. 7, 1881). It exists also in Brit. Mus. Add. MS.
               14,641, fol. 157, where the text is not a copy of 14,650, as Guidi states on the
               authority of Wright, but is similar to that in our author and in Jo. Eph., and, being
               followed by the later history of the little boy, as in Jo. Eph. , is plainly derived
               from that author. A Greek account of the same events, derived in part from this
               letter, is contained in the Martyrium Arethæ (Boissonade, Anecd. Græc. vol. v.), and
               a slightly different one in Simeon Metaphrastes (Migne, Patr. Græc. 115, p. 1249
               ff.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n192-4">Jo. Eph. ap. <quote>Dion.</quote> (Assem., B. O. p. 364 ff.); Mich. fol. 166
               ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n193-1">524.</note>
            <note xml:id="n193-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n193-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. (marg.), Jo. Eph., 14,650, and Cod. Borg.</note>
            <note xml:id="n193-4">I.e. emigrants or nomads, a name applied to certain Arab tribes:
               Ar. Maʿaddiyya.</note>
            <note xml:id="n193-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom., <quote>Dion.</quote> 14,650, and Cod. Borg. 14,641 agrees with 17,202.</note>
            <note xml:id="n194-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n194-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints. So Cod. Rom., which, however, has <!--  Add Syriac  --> instead of
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n194-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n194-4">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n194-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n194-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n195-1">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod. Rom., <quote>Dion.,</quote> 14,650, and
               Cod. Borg. 14,641 agrees with 17,202.</note>
            <note xml:id="n195-2">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom., <quote>Dion.,</quote> 14,650, and Cod. Borg. 14,641 agrees with 17,202.</note>
            <note xml:id="n195-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n195-4">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> after <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Jo.
               Eph. 14,650 and Cod. Borg. have <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>my face.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n195-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. and Jo. Eph.</note>
            <note xml:id="n196-1">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  --> with Cod.
               Rom., 14,650, Cod. Borg., and "Dion."</note>
            <note xml:id="n196-2">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom., <quote>Dion.,</quote> 14,650, and Cod. Borg.</note>
            <note xml:id="n196-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  --> as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n196-4">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom., Jo. Eph., 14,650, and Cod. Borg.</note>
            <note xml:id="n196-5">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom. and Jo. Eph.</note>
            <note xml:id="n197-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               which L. does not print.</note>
            <note xml:id="n197-2">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom., Jo. Eph., 14,650, and Cod. Borg.</note>
            <note xml:id="n197-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n197-4">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  --> as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n198-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n198-2">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom. and Jo. Eph.</note>
            <note xml:id="n198-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom., Jo. Eph., 14,650, and Cod. Borg.</note>
            <note xml:id="n198-4">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               which L. does not print.</note>
            <note xml:id="n198-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n199-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom. and 14,641. <quote>Dion.</quote> has <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n199-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n199-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. and Jo. Eph.</note>
            <note xml:id="n199-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. This word occurs again in 1. 7 (p. 73, l.
               7, L.) and 9. 3 (p. 257, l. 14), where the meaning seems to be as above, not "vafer
               fuit," as Payne Smith. Cf. also 3. 1 (p. 123, l. 12) and 3. 10 (p. 130, l. 22). In 7.
               2 (p. 203, l. 3) <!--  Add Syriac  -->, from the cognate <!--  Add Syriac  -->, seems
               to bear the same meaning.</note>
            <note xml:id="n199-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. Jo. Eph. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, which gives the same sense.</note>
            <note xml:id="n200-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n200-2">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and read
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod. Rom. and Jo. Eph. 14,650
               and Cod. Borg. also give the same sense.</note>
            <note xml:id="n200-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n200-4"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n201-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n202-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n202-3">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> there follow in Jo. Eph., 14,650, and
               Cod. Borg. the words <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>He said to him, <quote>By our Lord, my
               mother.</quote></quote> This answer (absent in both MSS.) seems to have been accidentally omitted
               by our author.</note>
            <note xml:id="n202-4">Insert CTLJi after ;io|o, with Cod. Rom., Jo. Eph., 14,650, and
               Cod. Borg.</note>
            <note xml:id="n202-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, So Jo. Eph. (not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               Assem. prints) and Mich. (<!--  Add Syriac  -->).</note>
            <note xml:id="n202-2">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> after <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom., Jo. Eph., 14,650, and Cod. Borg.</note>
            <note xml:id="n202-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n202-4">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  --> with Cod.
               Rom. and Jo. Eph.</note>
            <note xml:id="n202-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. and Jo. Eph.</note>
            <note xml:id="n203-1">I.e. <quote>son of sailors.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n203-2"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὕπαρχος</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n203-3">Here the sentence breaks off, being taken up again lower
               down.</note>
            <note xml:id="n203-4">We should probably insert another <!--  Add Syriac  --> in order
               to express the pluperfect, which is necessary for the sense, since a bishop could not
               be a synkellos.</note>
            <note xml:id="n203-5">Prov. x. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n204-1">Mich. fol. 161 r, 164 f.</note>
            <note xml:id="n204-2">525.</note>
            <note xml:id="n204-3">Mich. fol. 164.</note>
            <note xml:id="n204-4">1 Kings ix. 18, 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n204-5">The word <!--  Add Syriac  --> has dropped out of the text, and
               must be supplied from the heading. The verb is also omitted in Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n204-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n205-1">526.</note>
            <note xml:id="n205-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n205-3">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n205-4">Mich. fol. 165; Greg. H. E. i. p. 201.</note>
            <note xml:id="n205-5"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κόμης ἀνατολῆς</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n205-6">Two leaves in the MS. have here been transposed. I pass on from p.
               244, l. 26 (Land) to p. 246, l. 16. The intermediate portion has nothing to do with
               the subject of this chapter, but belongs to the next. This is also evident from a
               comparison with Michael and Gregory.</note>
            <note xml:id="n206-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n206-2">Mich. fol. 164 r; Greg. p. 78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n206-3"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀνάλωμα</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n206-4"><foreign xml:lang="grc">τράκτατον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n206-5">The name meant is <persName>Sphahpat </persName>(<foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἀσπεβέδης</foreign>), the title of the Persian
               commander-in-chief (Josh. Styl. 59, and Wright’s note). Cf. also 9. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n206-6"><foreign xml:lang="grc">βερηδάριοι</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n207-1">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n207-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> seems to be corrupt. There is no authority
               for the form <!--  Add Syriac  --> for Emesa, and only a few lines above our author
               writes <!--  Add Syriac  -->; but it may be an accidental corruption. Mich. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">δήμιος</foreign>?), but a name of a town seems to be required.</note>
            <note xml:id="n207-3">Mich. fol. 162 r.</note>
            <note xml:id="n207-4">Jo. Eph. ap. Mich. fol. 161 v, Greg. H. E. pp. 195, 197, from
               Philox. Ep. ad Mon. Sen. (Brit. Mus. Add. MS. 14,597, fol. 35 ff.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n207-5"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ξενοδοχεῖον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n207-6">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Greg.
               and Mich. So also Philoxenus himself (fol. 89 v).</note>
            <note xml:id="n207-7">Cf. 7. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n207-8">Cf. Jo. Eph. l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n207-9">I cannot identify this place. <!--  Add Syriac  --> should stand
               for Amorium; but, as it is mentioned among the Mesopotamian sees, this is out of the
               question. John of <!--  Add Syriac  --> is mentioned among the Mesopotamian bishops
               in Mich. fol. 161 v. In a chronicle of the ninth cent. in Brit. Mus. Add. MS. 14,642,
               fol. 29 r, he is called <persName>Thomas</persName> of <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as here; cf. Assem., B. O.
               2, Diss. de Monoph. lxiii.</note>
            <note xml:id="n207-10">Mich. fol. 162 r.</note>
            <note xml:id="n208-1">Jo. Eph. ap. <quote>Dion.</quote> (Assem., B. O. 2, pp. 48, 49); Mich.
               l.c.</note>
            <note xml:id="n208-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. The former
               form occurs twice lower down.</note>
            <note xml:id="n208-3"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἡγεμών</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n208-4"><foreign xml:lang="grc">βερεδάριοι</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n208-5">Logically, we require <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "ill," for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>illness</quote>; but the meaning is clear.</note>
            <note xml:id="n208-6">At this point we go back to fol. 140 (see p. 205, note 6).</note>
            <note xml:id="n208-7">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n208-8">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n209-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. This seems to represent <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀπὸ δικανικῶν</foreign>, as
               in 7. 10; but the meaning does not suit this passage very well.</note>
            <note xml:id="n209-2">Not <persName>Aphthonius</persName>; see <persName>John</persName>'s life in Brit. Mus. Add. MS. 12,174,
               fol. 84.</note>
            <note xml:id="n209-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n209-4">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.,
               not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n209-5">2 Cor. i. 4(?); 1 Thess. iii. 7(?).</note>
            <note xml:id="n209-6">In Jo. Eph. (Land, Anecd. Syr. ii. p. 110, l. 3) <quote>Beth Shurʿo.</quote>
               <quote>Dion.</quote> <quote>in the temple of Beth Shilo.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n209-7">Mich. fol. 163.</note>
            <note xml:id="n209-8">525-531.</note>
            <note xml:id="n210-1">Mich. <quote>was expelled together with the brotherhood, and the monks
               of the monastery…</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n210-2">Of <!--  Add Syriac  --> I can make nothing, and take the meaning
               from Mich. <!--  Add Syriac  -->). Read either <!--  Add Syriac  --> or
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Dr. <persName>Hamilton</persName> proposes <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>that of my lord
               Romanus.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n210-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Cf. Wright,
               C. B. M. pp. 605, 755, etc.; Mich. <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n210-4">Text, <quote>Magos</quote>; so Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n210-5"> The last letter of this word, left blank by L., is
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n210-6">See bk. 7, ch. 4 (p. 156, note 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="n210-7">Or, <quote>near Harmosho.</quote> I find no trace of either of these names, and
               suspect both to be corrupt. Mich, omits both, writing merely <quote>Sergius, and the
               monastery… Hauro.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n211-1">At this point we return to fol. 142.</note>
            <note xml:id="n211-2">Mich. has the masculine, <quote>who is now polluted.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n211-3"><foreign xml:lang="grc">πολιτεία</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n211-4">Sir. xxix. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n211-5">I.e. learned in the inner or allegorical meaning.</note>
            <note xml:id="n212-1">531.</note>
            <note xml:id="n212-2">531-2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n212-3">Isa. xxvi. 20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n212-4">Cf. Mich. fol. 167 v.</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-1">526.</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-2">We should probably read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>book,</quote> for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-3">This chapter is contained in Cod. Rom., where the heading is, <quote>The
               prologue composed concisely under heads by the holy Moro, bishop of Amida, a man
               deserving of blessed memory, upon the Gospel and the dispensation of Christ in the
               flesh.</quote>—Cf. p. 221.</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-4">Mich. fol. 162 ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints, before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-7"><foreign xml:lang="grc">θεωρία</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-8">Instead of <!--  Add Syriac  -->, Cod. Rom. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>repeated.</quote> Mich. agrees with Cod. Brit.</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-9">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom. So Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-10">Cod. Rom. seems to have <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as Mai prints; and, as Mich. also has <quote>made,</quote> this must be the
               right word. The participle, however, cannot here stand alone, so that we must either
               read <!--  Add Syriac  --> or suppose <!--  Add Syriac  --> to have dropped
               out.</note>
            <note xml:id="n214-1">John iii. 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n214-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> , with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n214-3">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n214-4">Cod. Rom., "that it is now in His power.''</note>
            <note xml:id="n215-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n215-2">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n215-3">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> after <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n215-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n215-5">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n215-6">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom. So. Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n215-7">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom. So. Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n215-8">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. So Mich. (<!--  Add Syriac  -->).</note>
            <note xml:id="n216-1">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom. So. Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n216-2">John viii. 1-11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n216-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n216-4">Cod. Rom., like Cod. Brit., has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as Mai prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n216-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. L. prints <!--  Add Syriac  -->, but there is no point either above or below the
               letter in the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n217-1">Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> as Cod. Brit., not
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> as Mai prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n217-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom. The reading of Cod. Brit, is doubtful.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
