<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book" n="4">
            <head>Book 4</head>
            <div type="section" n="4.0">
               <p>This fourth Book also, in as much as it is from<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n61-1"/> the History of <persName>Zachariah</persName> the
                  Rhetorican, relates (in its twelve chapters that are written down distinctly
                  below) and makes known the events occurring after the death of <persName>Marcian</persName>, and
                  <persName>Morian</persName>, and <persName>Anthemius</persName>, and <persName>Severus</persName>, and <persName>Olybrius</persName>, who reigned in all twelve years,
                  as the Chronicle testifies — these events (I say) it makes known which took place
                  in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and in <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, in the days of <persName>Leo</persName>, and <persName>Leo</persName>, during a period of
                  twenty years. It tells about the consecration of <persName>Timothy</persName> the Great, surnamed the
                  <quote>Weasel.</quote> And how <persName>Proterius</persName>, who was appointed as the successor of <persName>Dioscorus</persName> by
                  the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, was killed; and how, after his death, his clergy presented
                  a libel to <persName>Timothy</persName>, and sought to come to the Church; but the zealous priests, on
                  the side of <persName>Timothy</persName>, and the people would not allow them. Whereupon they went to
                  <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and informed <persName>Leo</persName> about the matter; who wrote a letter to <persName>Leo</persName> the king
                  censuring the consecration of <persName>Timothy</persName>.</p>
               <p>But this Book, further, tells about the letter of <persName>Timothy</persName> to <persName>Leo</persName> censuring the
                  additions which had been made in the Synod, and the Tome.</p>
               <p>And, moreover, it tells about <persName>John</persName>, who was the bishop in <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> after the
                  resignation of <persName>Bassianus</persName>; and about the encyclical letter of <persName>Leo</persName> the king, which
                  he wrote to the bishops, with the object of eliciting from them their written
                  opinions respecting the definitions that were made in the Synod. And they all,
                  with the exception of <persName>Amphilochius</persName> of Side, wrote in praise of these definitions.
                  [n61-1]Or, <quote>being, so far as it goes, drawn from,</quote> etc. This may be an intimation
                  that our Syriac text is a compilation of extracts from the original Greek.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="62"/>
               <p>This Book, further, tells how <persName>Timothy</persName> was banished to <placeName>Gangra</placeName>, and from <placeName>Gangra</placeName> to
                  <placeName>Cherson</placeName>; and that his successor was one of the Proterian party, another <persName>Timothy</persName>
                  surnamed <persName>Salophaciolus</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62-1"/></p>
               <p>And it, moreover, tells about <persName>Isaiah</persName> the bishop, and <persName>Theophilus</persName> the presbyter, who
                  showed themselves to be Eutychians; and about the letter which <persName>Timothy</persName> wrote
                  respecting them, and by which he exposed them.</p>
               <p>The first chapter tells about the consecration of <persName>Timothy</persName> the Great, surnamed the
                  <quote> Weasel</quote>; and the events which then occurred.</p>
               <p>The second chapter shows how <persName>Proterius</persName> was killed, and dragged away; and his body
                  was burned with fire.</p>
               <p>The third chapter explains how after <persName>Timothy</persName> appeared as the sole bishop, the
                  other clergy also, who were adherents of <persName>Proterius</persName>, presented a libel by which
                  they showed themselves desirous of coming to the Church; but<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62-2"/> the zealous
                  priests, on the side of <persName>Timothy</persName>, would not allow them.</p>
               <p>The fourth chapter tells how these men, because they were not received by <persName>Timothy</persName>,
                  got ready and went up to <placeName>Rome</placeName> and gave information to the chief priest <persName>Leo</persName>
                  (respecting the matter).</p>
               <p>The fifth chapter tells about <persName>Timothy</persName>; and also what happened in <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> to <persName>John</persName>
                  the successor of <persName>Bassianus</persName>.</p>
               <p>The sixth chapter, moreover, explains about the petition<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62-3"/> of <persName>Timothy</persName> which
                  he wrote to the king, which contained a censure upon <persName>Leo</persName> and his letter.</p>
               <p>The seventh chapter tells about the replies to the Encyclical respecting the
                  Synod, which were sent to <persName>Leo</persName> the king by the bishops; and how <persName>Amphilochius</persName> did
                  not agree with the others in what he wrote.</p>
               <p>The eighth chapter tells about the letter of <persName>Anatolius</persName> to the king, proving him to
                  have influenced the bishops, as to the purport of their replies respecting the
                  Synod.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="63"/>
               <p>The ninth chapter tells about the banishment of <persName>Timothy</persName>, and the events which
                  happened at his departure from <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The tenth chapter explains about the other <persName>Timothy</persName>, who was the bishop of the
                  Proterian party, and was called <persName>Salophaciolus</persName>.</p>
               <p>The eleventh chapter tells about the removal of <persName>Timothy</persName> from <placeName>Gangra</placeName> to
                  <placeName>Cherson</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The twelfth chapter tells about <persName>Isaiah</persName> and <persName>Theophilus</persName>, the Eutychians; and about
                  the letter which <persName>Timothy</persName> wrote respecting them, and by which he exposed them.</p>
               <p>But the time occupied by this Book is two or three years of <persName>Leo</persName> the First, and
                  seventeen years of <persName>Leo</persName> the Second, less by two months, as the Chronicle informs
                  us. For <persName>Timothy</persName> the Great was about two years, more or less, bishop in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>;
                  and then he was banished to <placeName>Gangra</placeName>, and after the lapse of eighteen years he
                  returned to his see; and he very soon died.</p>
               <p>This fourth Book is a narrative of the consecration of <persName>Timothy</persName>, and of the events
                  which occurred in the days of King <persName>Leo</persName> the First, and <persName>Leo</persName> the Second.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="64"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="4.1">
               <head>Chapter 1</head>
               <head>The first chapter of the fourth book, telling about the consecration of <persName>Timothy</persName>
                  the Great,surnamed <persName>Aelurus</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-1"/> and the events whichhappened then</head>
               <p>The Alexandrian Church being in the condition that we have described above,
                  suddenly the report of the death of <persName>Marcian</persName> reached them, and they all took
                  courage, and consulted with the whole order of the monks as to whom they should
                  make the bishop of the believing party. For<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-2"/> at that time <persName>Dionysius</persName> the
                  general<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-3"/> was not there, but was on a visit to <placeName>Egypt</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-4"/> And they
                  agreed upon <persName>Timothy</persName>, a man expert in business<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-5"/> and of ascetic life; who had
                  been brought from the wilderness, by force, to <persName>Cyril</persName>, and ordained as presbyter by
                  him. Moreover, he was of the same faith as <persName>Dioscorus</persName>; and he was well versed in
                  all the truth of the faith of the doctors of the Church. This man the people of
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> along with the monks seized, and brought to the great Church which is
                  called Caesarian. And they sought for three bishops, according to the canonical
                  statute, to consecrate him. And since two Egyptian bishops were present, it was
                  necessary that some other bishop should be found. And on making diligent inquiry,
                  some of the people heard of <persName>Peter</persName> the Iberian, who had left Palestine and was
                  sojourning there in Alexandria. And they ran quickly and laid hold of the man; and
                  carried him on their shoulders, not letting him touch the ground. And as they were
                  bringing him along, a voice was heard in the minds of the clergy, and of the
                  monks, and of the believing citizens, like that voice which <persName>Philip</persName> heard
                  respecting the eunuch of <persName>Candace</persName> the queen, saying, <quote>Consecrate him by force, even
                  though he be unwilling, and set him on the throne <pb type="page" n="65"/>of
                  <persName>Mark</persName>.</quote> And he was weak in body through much self- mortification; so that, on
                  account of his emaciation, the Proterian party used jestingly to style him the
                  <quote>Weasel</quote>. And when <persName>Dionysius</persName> the general<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65-1"/> heard of the matter, he became
                  uneasy, lest he might receive blame for there being two bishops in the city, when
                  the king heard it. And accordingly he returned, and taking the whole Roman force
                  with him, he made <persName>Timothy</persName> prisoner. And many were killed. And <persName>Dionysius</persName> gave
                  orders that they should carry him off to a place called <placeName>Cabarsarin</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65-2"/> And
                  upon his departure the conflict between the citizens and the Romans became
                  severe.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65-3"/> And there was a great tumult, and slaughters were matters of daily
                  occurrence; more especially as he (<persName>Dionysius</persName>) kept inciting and urging on<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65-4"/>
                  the Romans called Cartadon,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65-5"/> who were passionate men and Arians. And so the
                  custodian of the Church funds expended them upon the Romans who were contending
                  with the people. But it happened that numbers of them and of their wives fell and
                  perished in the conflict. And they were divided into parties, and fought one
                  against another. And when confusion like this had prevailed in the city for many
                  days, <persName>Dionysius</persName> was at his wits' end, so he brought a certain monk <persName>Longinus</persName>,
                  celebrated for chastity and virtue, and he intrusted <persName>Timothy</persName> to him; that he might
                  restore the bishop to the city and to his church, upon the condition that the
                  fighting should cease, and that there should be no more slaughter.</p>
               <p>And when <persName>Timothy</persName> had returned to the great church from which he had been forcibly
                  removed, and <persName>Proterius</persName> had taken for himself the church which is called <placeName>Quirinian</placeName>,
                  and Easter[#65-6] <pb type="page" n="66"/>time came round, children without number
                  were brought to Timothy to be baptized; so that because of their multitude those
                  who were writing and reading out their names became weary; but only five were
                  brought to <persName>Proterius</persName>. And the people were so devotedly<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66-1"/> attached<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66-2"/> to
                  <persName>Timothy</persName> that they drove <persName>Proterius</persName> out of the church of <placeName>Quirinus</placeName>; and slaughter
                  ensued.</p>
            </div>                    
            <div type="chapter" n="4.2">     
               <head>Chapter 2</head>
               <head>The second chapter shows how <persName>Proterius</persName> was slain,and dragged through the city;
                  and how his body was, at last, burned with fire</head>
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66-3"/> when <persName>Proterius</persName> continued to threaten the Romans, and to display his
                  rage against them; because they took his gold, but did not fill their hands with
                  the blood of his enemies: then, indeed, a certain Roman was stirred to anger in
                  his heart, and was boiling over with rage; and he invited <persName>Proterius</persName> to look round
                  and he would show him the corpses of the slain as they lay. And suddenly and
                  secretly, he drew his sword and stabbed <persName>Proterius</persName> in the ribs along with his Roman
                  comrades, and they despatched him, and dragged him to the Tetrapylum, calling out
                  respecting him as they went along, <quote>This is <persName>Proterius</persName>.</quote> And others suspected that
                  it was some crafty plot. But the Romans left the body, and went away. Then the
                  people, perceiving this, became also greatly excited, and they dragged off the
                  corpse, and burnt it with fire in the Hippodrome. Thus the end of death
                  overtook<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66-4"/> Proterius, who had done evil to the Alexandrians, just as <persName>George</persName>
                  the Arian, and he suffered at their hands in like manner, and so was it done to
                  him.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="67"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="4.3">
               <head>Chapter 3</head>
               <head>The third chapter tells how, after <persName>Timothy</persName> appearedas the sole bishop, the
                  other clergy also expressed, by means of a libel, their desire to repent and be
                  united with him; but the people and the zealous priests of his party would not
                  allow them</head>
               <p>But <persName>Timothy</persName>, when he appeared before them as the only chief priest of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>,
                  showed that he was really what a priest should be. For the silver and the gold
                  that were given to the Romans in the days of <persName>Proterius</persName>, he expended upon the poor,
                  and the widows, and the entertaining of strangers, and upon the needy in the city.
                  So that, in a short time, the rich men, perceiving his honourable conduct,
                  lovingly and devotedly supplied him with funds,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n67-1"/> both gold and silver. But
                  the presbyters and all the clergy belonging to the Proterian party, since they
                  knew all his virtues and his angelic mode of life, and the devotion of the
                  citizens to him, joined themselves together and made libels in which they
                  entreated him that they might be received. They also promised that they would go
                  to <placeName>Rome</placeName> to <persName>Leo</persName>, and admonish him concerning the novelties which he had written in
                  the Tome. Among these persons there were some who were ready and eloquent, and of
                  great wealth and dignity, and of high birth also, who had been called to the
                  clerical order by <persName>Cyril</persName>; and who were honoured in the eyes of the citizens of
                  <placeName>Rome</placeName>; and they presented the petition on their behalf to <persName>Timothy</persName>. And <persName>Eustace</persName> of
                  <placeName>Berytus</placeName> wrote also recommending their reception.</p>
               <p>But the jealousy and hatred of the citizens against these persons were great, on
                  account of the events which had occurred in the days of <persName>Proterius</persName>, and the various
                  sufferings which they had endured. So they would not consent to their reception,
                  but they prepared the others to cry out, <quote>Not one <pb type="page" n="68"/>of them
                  shall set his foot here, neither shall the transgressors be received.</quote></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="4.4">
               <head>Chapter 4</head>
               <head>The fourth chapter tells how these men got ready and went up to <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and gave
                  information respecting the treatment which they had suffered</head>
               <p>This was the reason why matters were disturbed and thrown into confusion. For when
                  these men were ignominiously refused, they betook themselves to <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and there
                  they told about the contempt of the canons, and about the dreadful death of
                  <persName>Proterius</persName>; and they said that he died for the sake of the Synod and for the honour
                  of <persName>Leo</persName>; and that they themselves, also, had endured many indignities; and further,
                  that <persName>Timothy</persName> had come forward in a lawless manner and taken the priesthood. So
                  they rendered the latter odious, and made the whole business appear disgraceful in
                  the eyes of <persName>Leo</persName>; and they stirred him up against <persName>Timothy</persName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="4.5">
               <head>Chapter 5</head>
               <head>The fifth chapter tells the following matters respecting <persName>Timothy</persName>; and also what
                  happened in <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> to <persName>John</persName> the successor of <persName>Bassianus</persName></head>
               <p>But how it came about that <persName>Timothy</persName> was given up, I shall now relate. <persName>Marcian</persName> the
                  king having died, and <persName>Anthemius</persName>, and <persName>Severus</persName>, and <persName>Olybrius</persName> having reigned for only
                  short lives, in <placeName>Italy</placeName> and the regions beyond, <persName>Leo</persName> the First received the kingdom
                  in the territory of <placeName>Europe</placeName> in conjunction with them and after them. And he was
                  both a believer and vigorous, but simple in the faith.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="69"/>
               <p>And when Leo the king learned the evils which occurred in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and in
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and in <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, and in everyplace; and that many had been disturbed
                  on account of the Synod. And also that in <persName>Ephesus</persName> there had been much slaughter,
                  upon the entrance of <persName>John</persName>, after <persName>Bassianus</persName> had resigned and fled because he would
                  not subscribe the transactions of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>. But this <persName>John</persName>, being inflamed with <!-- Chalcedon not sure if it is a person or a place, found it is a council?  -->
                  desire for pre-eminence, betrayed the rights and honours of the see; so that in
                  <persName>Ephesus</persName> they call him <hi rend="/doubleQuote">the traitor</hi>. unto this day; and they blotted his name out
                  of the book of life. He accordingly, when he received a letter from <persName>Timothy</persName> of
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, was willing to convene a Synod. But <persName>Anatolius</persName>, the bishop of the royal
                  city, prevented him; not, indeed, that he was able to find any fault with the
                  written statement of <persName>Timothy</persName>, but he was very uneasy lest, if a Synod were
                  assembled, it might put an end to all the transactions of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>. And his <!-- Chalcedon not sure if it is a person or a place, found it is a council?  -->
                  anxiety was not for the faith, but rather for the privileges and honours which had
                  been unjustly granted to the see of the royal city.</p>
               <p>Accordingly, <persName>Anatolius</persName> persuaded the king not to assemble a Synod, but by means of
                  written letters, called <persName>Encyclicals</persName>, to inquire what the mind of the bishops was
                  respecting the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and the consecration<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n69-1"/> of <persName>Timothy</persName>.</p> <!-- Chalcedon not sure if it is a person or a place, found it is a council?  -->
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n69-2"/> the king began to write to the bishops about <persName>Timothy</persName> and the Synod of
                  <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, in the encyclical letter, to the following effect : —</p> <!-- Chalcedon not sure if it is a person or a place, found it is a council?  -->
               <quote>
                  <p>Do ye, without fear of man or partiality, and unbiassed by influence or by
                     favour, setting the fear of God alone before your eyes, and considering that to
                     Him alone ye must make your defence and give your account, tell me briefly the
                     common opinion held by you the priests in our dominion, what ye think right,
                     after having carefully investigated the transactions of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, and <!-- Chalcedon not sure if it is a person or a place, found it is a council?  -->
                     concerning the consecration of <persName>Timothy</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.</p>
               </quote>
               <pb type="page" n="70"/>
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n70-1"/> when a letter such as this from the king was given to <persName>Leo</persName> of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, he
                  wrote two letters to Leo the king; one concerning <persName>Timothy</persName>, and the other on behalf
                  of the Proterian party, in which he also asserted of the clergy of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>
                  that they were of the same mind as <persName>Timothy</persName>; and he called <persName>Anatolius</persName>
                  indolent;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n70-2"/> and he defended the Tome which he himself wrote respecting
                  <persName>Eutyches</persName>, and which was accepted in the <placeName>Council of Chalcedon</placeName>. However, in a <!-- Chalcedon not sure if it is a person or a place, found it is a council?  -->
                  similar strain he wrote distinctly concerning the taking of the Manhood by <persName>Christ</persName>
                  in this letter also. And Leo the king sent it on to <persName>Timothy</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>. And,
                  upon the receipt of it, the latter wrote a petition<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n70-3"/> to the king as
                  follows.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="4.6">
               <head>Chapter 6</head>
               <head>The sixth chapter, declaring, by his petition, the faith of <persName>Timothy</persName> and the
                  charges that he made against the letter of <persName>Leo</persName></head>
               <p><quote>O kind and indulgent king! Since among wise men<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n70-4"/> there is nothing more
                  honourable than the soul, and also we have learned to despise the things of the
                  flesh, and not to lose the soul; therefore, as far as in me lies and with all my
                  might, I am careful to keep my soul, lest before the time of judgment I may be
                  condemned as a lover of the flesh, and prepare for myself the fire of Hell. And
                  this I think, that all who are wise concerning that which is good, desire that
                  nothing hateful to their brethren should ever occur. And accordingly, in writing
                  this petition I assure your Serenity that from my youth I have learned the Holy
                  Scriptures, and I have studied the divine mysteries contained in them. And even
                  until now, I have ever been careful to hold the true faith as it was delivered to
                  us by the apostles, and by my <pb type="page" n="71"/>fathers the doctors. And,
                  being united to them by the grace of God our Saviour, I have reached my present
                  age. And I confess the one faith which our Redeemer and Creator <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>
                  delivered when He became incarnate, and sent out the blessed apostles, saying,
                  <quote>Go, teach all nations; baptizing them in the name of the Father, and the Son, and
                  the Holy Spirit.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n71-1"/> For<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n71-2"/> the Trinity is perfect, equal of Nature, in
                  glory and blessedness; and there is not in It anything less or more. For thus also
                  the three hundred and eighteen blessed fathers taught concerning the true
                  Incarnation of our Lord and Saviour <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, that He became man, according to
                  His dispensation, which He Himself knows. And with them I agree and believe, as do
                  all others who prosper<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n71-3"/> in the true faith. For in it there is nothing
                  difficult, neither does the definition of the faith which the fathers proclaimed
                  require addition. And all (whoever they be) holding other opinions and corrupted
                  by heresy, are rejected by me. And I also myself flee from them. For this is a
                  disease which destroys the soul, namely, the doctrine of <persName>Apollinaris</persName>, and the
                  blasphemies of <persName>Nestorius</persName>, both those who hold erroneous views about the
                  Incarnation of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, Who became flesh from us; and introduce into Him the
                  cleavage in two, and divide asunder even the dispensation of the only- begotten
                  Son of God: and those, on the other hand, who say with respect to His Body that it
                  was taken from Heaven, or that God the Word was changed, or that He suffered in
                  His own Nature; and who do not confess that to a human body what pertains to the
                  soul derived from us was united.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And I say to any who have fallen into one or other of these heresies, <quote>Ye are in
                  grievous error, and ye know not the Scriptures.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n71-4"/> And with such I do not
                  hold communion, nor do I love them as believers. But I am joined, and united, and
                  truly agreeing with the faith which was defined at Nicea; and it is my care to
                  live in accordance with it.</quote></p>
               <pb type="page" n="72"/>
               <p><quote>But when <persName>Diomedes</persName>, the distinguished Silentiarius, came to me and gave me the
                  letter of the bishop of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and I studied it, and I was not pleased with its
                  contents; then lest the Church, O Christ-loving man, should be disturbed, I
                  neither, as yet, have publicly read nor censured it.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>But I believe that God has put it into the mind of your Serenity to set right the
                  statements in this letter, which are a cause of stumbling to the believers; for
                  these statements are in accord, and agreement, and conjunction with the doctrine
                  of <persName>Nestorius</persName>; who was condemned for cleaving asunder and dividing the Incarnation
                  of our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, in respect of natures, and persons, and properties, and
                  names, and operations; who also interpreted the words of Scripture to mean two
                  (natures), which are not contained in the Confession of Faith of the three hundred
                  and eighteen. For they declared that the only-begotten Son of God, Who is of the
                  same Nature with the Father, came down, and became incarnate, and was made man;
                  and suffered, and rose again, and ascended to Heaven; and shall come to judge the
                  quick and the dead. And natures, and persons, and properties were not mentioned by
                  them, nor did they divide them. But they confessed the divine and the human
                  properties to be of One by the dispensation.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Accordingly, I do not agree with the transactions of Chalcedon, because I find in
                  them divisions and cleavage of the dispensation.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And now, O victorious king, receive me, for I am speaking this confidently on
                  behalf of the truth; that your Highness may prosper as on earth, so also in
                  Heaven. And accept this my petition with goodwill, for in this letter from the
                  West there runs confusion likely to cause stumbling; for it cleaves asunder the
                  dispensation. And I pray that this letter may be annulled, so that God Christ may
                  be purely<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n72-1"/> confessed by all tongues that He truly suffered in the flesh;
                  while He remained without suffering in His Godhead, which He has with the Father
                  and the Spirit.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And I entreat and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n72-2"/> beseech your honoured Majesty that <pb type="page"
                     n="73"/>orders be sent to all men to hold<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n73-1"/> the Confession of the faith,
                  as defined by our three hundred and eighteen fathers, which, in a few words,
                  declares the truth to all the Churches, and puts an end to every heresy and all
                  false doctrine and causes of stumbling; and which itself stands in no need of
                  correction. But the matters in this letter which appear to me to require
                  correction</quote> (which are not repeated) <quote>are these — </quote>  and because they are given at  <!-- Quote or hi rend?  -->
                  length with quotations refuting them, we do not repeat<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n73-2"/> them here, lest the
                  reader should be wearied. For believers may find, in all places, the censures upon
                  them that have been made by wise men. In the first place, by Dioscorus; and after
                  him, by this <persName>Timothy</persName>; and after him by <persName>Peter</persName>; and by <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName> of <placeName>Hierapolis</placeName>; and
                  by the learned <persName>Severus</persName>, the chief priest of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, in his work Against the
                  Grammarian;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n73-3"/> and by Cosmas; and by <persName>Simeon</persName> of <placeName>Lʾgino</placeName>; and by the letter of
                  the Alexandrines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="4.7">
               <head>Chapter 7</head>
               <head>The seventh chapter tells what the other bishops wrote to Leo; and how<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n73-4"/>
                  they all (with the exception of <persName>Amplilochius</persName> of Side) made known their views in
                  conformity with the doctrine of the Synod, and agreed to it</head>
               <p>But <persName>Timothy</persName> wrote confidently, as above, concerning the letter of <persName>Leo</persName> and the
                  Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>. The other bishops, however, the Metropolitans of every place,
                  having received the encyclical letter of the king, testified to what was done by
                  them in <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, to which also they agreed.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n73-5"/> And they censured the
                  consecration of <persName>Timothy</persName>, whom <persName>Leo</persName>, <pb type="page" n="74"/>the bishop of <placeName>Rome</placeName>,
                  even named <quote>the Antichrist.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-1"/> They say, indeed, that the other bishops also
                  were influenced to write thus by the instigation of <persName>Anatolius</persName>, and his letters to
                  them.</p>
               <p>But<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-2"/> <persName>Amphilochius</persName> of Side alone showed truth and uprightness without fear.
                  And he and the bishops of his province wrote confidently, censuring and reviling
                  the transactions of the Synod, and the doctrine of the Tome, telling of the
                  violence and partiality there displayed, and confirming their statements by proofs
                  and copious testimony from the Holy Scriptures and the Fathers. He, moreover,
                  besought the king that the transactions of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> should be cancelled, since
                  they were a cause of stumbling to the believers, as well as of confusion.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-3"/>
                  Nevertheless, he censured the consecration of <persName>Timothy</persName>, and said that it had been
                  done in an uncanonical manner. This man, indeed, who testified thus confidently
                  and truly to the king respecting the Synod, fell into danger from the Nestorian
                  party, in consequence of the malignity and treachery which they exhibited towards
                  him; for he was the only one of all the bishops who had the courage to revile the
                  Synod with its transactions, and also the Tome. But <persName>Aspar</persName>, who was general<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-4"/>
                  at that time, although he was an Arian, pleaded and begged for him that such a
                  truthful priest should not be exposed to danger. And thus, indeed, <persName>Amphilochius</persName>
                  was delivered from danger.</p>
               <p>But<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-5"/> in his endeavour to correct the evils which were done in the days of
                  <persName>Marcian</persName>, the king was hindered by the bishops. And by their means also <persName>Timothy</persName> was
                  condemned to banishment in <placeName>Gangra</placeName>. Now that <persName>Anatolius</persName> of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> was the
                  one to instigate the bishops to make these statements to the king in the
                  Encyclicals, you will learn from his letter to the king which I have written
                  below.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="75"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="4.8">
               <head>Chapter 8</head>
               <head>The eighth chapter, indeed, tells about the letter of <persName>Anatolius</persName> to the King
                  about the Synod, saying that he had influenced the bishops by
                  writing<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n75-1"/></head>
               <p><quote><persName>Anatolius</persName>, bishop of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, to the believing and Christ-loving king,
                  victorious <persName>Augustus</persName>, <persName>Leo</persName> the emperor. It is a subject of prayer with me,
                  Christ-loving and believing king,</quote> etc. And a little further on he says: <quote>Those
                  audacious acts which have been committed in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, do not suffer me to remain
                  silent. But, as becomes one holding the priesthood of this your royal city, being
                  attached to the peaceable will of your Majesty, which desires that the canons of
                  the Fathers should not be despised, but that the laws should be maintained, I have
                  testified thus to the pious chief priest Leo and the chaste Metropolitans of your
                  dominion. And I weep for the canons which have been despised by the wicked deeds
                  of <persName>Timothy</persName>; since the records<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n75-2"/> sent to your Majesty respecting him declare
                  that he has trampled upon the laws of the Church and of the world; and that he has
                  loved vainglory, according to the saying of Scripture, that the wicked man is a
                  despiser, even when he is falling into the depth of evils.'</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n75-3"/></p>
               <p>And the rest of his letter will be understood<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n75-4"/> from this specimen;
                  how<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n75-5"/> he was the cause of the letters sent by the bishops to the emperor, in
                  which they agreed to the transaction of the Synod. But many senators and citizens,
                  having learned this respecting <persName>Anatolius</persName>, withdrew from his communion.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="76"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="4.9">
               <head>Chapter 9</head>
               <head>The ninth chapter tells about the banishment of <persName>Timothy</persName>, and the events which
                  happened at his departure from <placeName>Alexandria</placeName></head>
               <p>But, because the king's order<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-1"/> respecting the departure of <persName>Timothy</persName> was sent
                  to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> at this time, the general<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-2"/> was consequently much distressed,
                  and felt himself constrained to suffer many things rather than that the city
                  should lose such a priest. However, since he saw<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-3"/> the slaughter which was
                  threatened against him by the Proterian party, and especially as the members of
                  that party had taken refuge<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-4"/> with the king, and were aided by all the
                  bishops; this same <persName>Stilas</persName> the general<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-5"/> thought it well that he and the
                  bishop should betake themselves for refuge to the Baptistery of the great Church.
                  And he did so for two reasons: one was, that they themselves might be preserved
                  from harm; and the other, that they might not be the cause of the loss of life and
                  of slaughter.</p>
               <p>But when <persName>Timothy</persName> had taken refuge at the font of the Baptistery, the clergy of the
                  Proterian party paid no regard either to the priesthood, or to the chastity, or to
                  the age, or to the ascetic life, or to the labours of the man, or indeed to the
                  place where he had taken refuge; but with an armed force, they snatched the chief
                  priest from the very font, and dragged him away. And, as soon as the report of
                  this<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-6"/> reached the people, they killed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-7"/> more than ten thousand there
                  to rescue the priest from them. However, after the Romans had slain many of the
                  Alexandrians, the man was taken; and he went out across <placeName>Egypt</placeName> to <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, that
                  his journey might be along the sea of <placeName>Phoenice</placeName>.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="77"/>
               <p>But when the cities and the inhabitants of <placeName>Palestine</placeName> and the seacoast<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-1"/>
                  heard it, they came to him to be sanctified, and that the sick among them gain
                  healing for their diseases through the grace of God which was attached to his
                  person; and they snatched torn pieces of stuff from his garments, that they might
                  have them as charms to protect them from evil.</p>
               <p>And when he arrived at <placeName>Berytus</placeName>, <persName>Eustace</persName> the bishop urged the citizens there to
                  receive him with public honour.</p>
               <p>And he begged <persName>Timothy</persName>, upon his entry into the city, to pray for it; and the
                  latter stood in the midst of the city and made supplications and prayers to God
                  for it, and blessed it.</p>
               <p>But <persName>Auxonius</persName>, the brother of <persName>Eustace</persName>, who was at that time an interpreter of the
                  law, acting upon the advice of his brother, spent the whole night with <persName>Timothy</persName>,
                  speaking earnestly about the faith, and against <persName>Nestorius</persName>. And during the whole of
                  his long discourse <persName>Timothy</persName> was a silent listener; but when at length <persName>Auxonius</persName>,
                  after many words, ceased speaking, <persName>Timothy</persName> said to him, <quote>Who could persuade me
                  that these three fingers should write upon the paper of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>?</quote> And, upon
                  hearing this, <persName>Auxonius</persName> was very sad, and began to weep. Then <persName>Timothy</persName>, encouraging
                  both him and his brother <persName>Eustace</persName>, who afterwards joined<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-2"/> them, said,
                  <quote>Attach yourselves to me, and let us contend together for the faith, and let us
                  prevail; so that either we shall recover our bishoprics, or else we shall be
                  driven into banishment by our enemies, and live a sincere life with God.</quote> And he
                  alleged as an excuse the dedication of a church, a great temple which <persName>Eustace</persName>
                  built and named <quote>Anastasia</quote>; and <persName>Timothy</persName> said, <quote>Shall we wait for the dedication
                  of an earthly temple? But if you obey me, then we shall hold our festival in the
                  heavenly <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>?</quote></p>
               <p>And <persName>Timothy</persName> received the same kind of honour along the way, until he reached
                  <placeName>Gangra</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="78"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="4.10">
               <head>Chapter 10</head>
               <head>The tenth chapter explains about another <persName>Timothy</persName>, who was the bishop of the
                  Proterian party, and was called <persName>Salophaciolus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-1"/></head>
               <p>But<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-2"/> the members of the Proterian party, because of the order<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-3"/> of
                  the king and the governors of the cities who were obedient to the command, elected
                  one of themselves, also called <persName>Timothy</persName> <persName>Salophaciolus</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-1"/> and placed him upon
                  the episcopal throne. He was a man who sought popularity;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-4"/> and was soft in
                  his manners and feeble in his actions; as events, indeed, proved.</p>
               <p>For when all the people of the city forsook the church, and assembled, along with
                  the believing clergy, in the monasteries, he was neither enraged nor distressed.
                  But when his own clergy were anxious to restrain the people by means of the Roman
                  armed force, he would not allow them.</p>
               <p>Now it happened that a certain woman met him carrying her child, who had just been
                  baptized by the believers, and was being borne along in triumph according to the
                  usual custom. And his attendants were very indignant at it. But he ordered them to
                  bring her to him quietly; and he took up the child and kissed him, and he urged
                  the mother to take whatever she wanted. And he said to his own followers, <quote>Let us
                  and these Christians, each as he thinks right, believe and honour our Lord.</quote>
                  Nevertheless, though he did all this, he could not appease the rage of the
                  citizens; and because he dreaded the fate of <placeName>Proterius</placeName>, he would not walk abroad
                  without the Romans. And just in proportion as the people loved <persName>Timothy</persName> the
                  believer, so they hated<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-5"/> this man. And they never ceased imploring and
                  entreating the king that <persName>Timothy</persName> should be restored to them from banishment.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="79"/>
               <p>But they say of this <persName>Salophaciolus</persName> that he tried hard to persuade the Alexandrians
                  to hold communion with him; and, as if rejecting the Synod, he wrote in the
                  Diptych the name of <persName>Dioscorus</persName>. And when <persName>Leo</persName> of <placeName>Rome</placeName> heard it, he excommunicated
                  him.</p>
               <p>And on one occasion, when he went up to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, he had a great dispute
                  with <persName>Gennadius</persName>, the successor of <persName>Anatolius</persName>, in the king's presence. And he said,
                  <quote>I do not accept the Synod which would make your see the next in importance to
                  <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and cast contempt upon the honour of my see.</quote> And the king laughed when he
                  saw them, and heard the two priests contending for the pre-eminence.</p>
               <p>And he wrote to tell about this dispute to the bishop of <placeName>Rome</placeName>; who at that time
                  replied in writing, that the privileges of each see should be restored according
                  to their original constitution. And he made this known to the king.</p>
               <p>So much about this <persName>Timothy</persName> <persName>Salophaciolus</persName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="4.11">
               <head>Chapter 11</head>
               <head>The eleventh chapter tells how <persName>Timothy</persName> was driven from <placeName>Gangra</placeName> to <placeName>Cherson</placeName>, in
                  consequence of the hatred which the party of Chalcedon entertained against
                  him</head>
               <p>But <persName>Gennadius</persName> of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> and his adherents did not desist from their
                  persecution of <persName>Timothy</persName>, even when he was in banishment. For they persuaded the
                  king to command his removal from <placeName>Gangra</placeName> to <placeName>Cherson</placeName>, which is a region inhabited by
                  barbarous and uncivilised men.</p>
               <p>But the bishop of <placeName>Gangra</placeName> heartily consented to this, on account of the envy which
                  he felt towards the believing, virtuous, and miracle-working <persName>Timothy</persName>, the friend
                  of the poor; because he used to receive gifts from the believers of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> and
                  <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and other places, and to make liberal distribution for the relief of the
                  needy.</p>
               <p>And having embarked on board ship, and launched upon <pb type="page" n="80"/>the
                  sea, though he was tossed in the midst of the winter, yet he reached <placeName>Cherson</placeName>
                  without danger. And when the inhabitants of the country learned the reason, they
                  were filled with admiration for him; and they became followers of his faith, and
                  submitted themselves to his authority.</p>
               <p>But the hatred which the Nestorian party entertained against him was caused by his
                  diligence in continually writing reproaches and censures upon the Synod and the
                  Tome, and sending them forth on all sides; thereby encouraging the believers. And
                  he corroborated his words from the Holy Scriptures, and the doctors of the Church,
                  from the time of Christ’s preaching even to his own day.</p>
               <p>In consequence of these writings, those persons who understood the matter left
                  Gennadius of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> and joined in communion with <persName>Acacius</persName> the presbyter and
                  Master of the Orphans, the brother of <persName>Timocletus</persName> the composer, who joined the
                  believers, and strenuously opposed the Nestorians; and he also set verses<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n80-1"/>
                  to music, and they used to sing them. And the people were delighted with them, and
                  they flocked in crowds to the Orphan Hospital.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n80-2"/></p>
               <p>But the king ordered that the blessed <persName>Mary</persName> should be proclaimed and written in the
                  book of life as <persName>Theotokos</persName>, on account of <persName>Martyrius</persName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, who was an avowed
                  Nestorian, and would not now consent to teach these things, who also was
                  deposed.</p>
               <p>But <persName>Gregory</persName> of <placeName>Nyssa</placeName> (a believing and virtuous man, the namesake of the learned
                  Gregory) was summoned by the king to put an end to the doctrine of the Nestorians
                  at that time; as some monks went on a mission to the king about the matter of
                  <persName>Martyrius</persName>. And <persName>Gennadius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n80-3"/> had died; and <persName>Acacius</persName>, the Master of the Orphan
                  Hospital,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n80-4"/> was appointed as his successor.</p>
               <p>And a promise had been made by the latter that he would put an end to the Tome of
                  <persName>Leo</persName>, and the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>, <pb type="page" n="81"/>and the innovations and
                  additions which had been imposed upon the faith in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="4.12">
               <head>Chapter 12</head>
               <head>The twelfth chapter tells about the Eutychianists, <persName>Isaiah</persName>, bishop of
                  <placeName>Hermopolis</placeName>, and <persName>Theophilus</persName>, a presbyter of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>; and about the letter
                  written by <persName>Timothy</persName> respecting them, in which he exposed their errors</head>
               <div type="chapterParagraphs" n="4.12.1">
                  <p>The affairs of the Church of the royal city, indeed, were in the condition
                     described above.</p>
                  <p>But <persName>Timothy</persName>, when in banishment, wrote not alone against the Nestorians, but
                     also against the Eutychianists. And this appears from his letters to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>
                     and <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, against those who hold the opinions of <persName>Eutyches</persName>, and do not
                     confess <persName>Christ</persName> to be of the same nature with us in the flesh as well as of the
                     same Nature with the Father in the Godhead.</p>
                  <p>And it so happened that the Eutychianists, <persName>Isaiah</persName>, bishop of <placeName>Hermopolis</placeName>, and
                     <persName>Theophilus</persName>, a presbyter of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, were sojourning in the royal city with
                     the desire of making money. And they circulated a report that <persName>Timothy</persName> also was
                     of their way of thinking. And when he heard this he wrote a letter dealing with
                     the doctrines of <persName>Eutyches</persName> and <persName>Nestorius</persName>, which he sent to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> signed
                     with his own signature. And when<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n81-1"/> the bearers of this letter became
                     known, they were treated by these men with contempt; and were exposed to
                     danger, because he called the followers of <persName>Isaiah</persName> <quote>deceivers.</quote> Whereupon he
                     sent again another letter respecting them, confirming it by quotations from the
                     fathers. And it was to the following effect:—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section" n="4.12.2">
                  <head>The Letter of <persName>Timothy</persName></head>
                  <p>Our Lord and God, <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, in order that He might redeem us and set us
                     free from the dominion of <persName>Satan</persName>, and <pb type="page" n="82"/>make us meet for
                     the blessings of Heaven, appointed for us, through the holy fathers, the law of
                     those things which are pleasing to Himself. And He gave commandment that no
                     man, thinking to honour, should insult the Merciful One; but that He should
                     receive the dispensation for our redemption. And He said, <quote>Turn not aside to
                     the right hand or to the left, but walk in the way of the kingdom.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n82-1"/> And
                     again He said, <quote>Be not righteous overmuch, nor count thyself too wise, lest
                     thou fall into error. And do not fall deeply into error, nor be stubborn, lest
                     thou die before the time</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n82-2"/> the meaning of which is, lest the evil one
                     should infuse into thee anything contrary to My commandments, and set a
                     stumbling-block for thee on the way of the kingdom along which thou art
                     walking, and slay thee. For he said, <quote>In the way wherein I walked they laid
                     snares<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n82-3"/> for me.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n82-4"/> Take heed, therefore, to thyself,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n82-5"/> and
                     do not turn aside nor depart from the way of the kingdom. For this is the
                     desire of the evil one, who, if thou shalt fill up much wickedness, will meet
                     thee, and thou wilt fall into danger.</p>
                  <p>For, suppose a man seeking to enter a city surrounded by water; if he attempt
                     to pass through on foot he will sink and be drowned in its depth; if, on the
                     other hand, he be afraid to pass over, he cannot enter the city at all; but if
                     there be a convenient<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n82-6"/> ford, and he try to cross over by it, then he can
                     enter the city. In like manner also we being anxious to enter <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, which
                     is above, if we do not follow the Law of God, which we have learned from the
                     holy doctors, cannot indeed stand upon the rock of our leader <persName>Peter Kepho</persName>, the
                     true faith.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n82-7"/> For thou shalt indeed be called <placeName>Kepho</placeName>, and upon this rock I
                     will build My Church; and the bars of Sheol shall not prevail against
                     it.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n82-8"/> Let no man be so led astray by the evil one as to imagine that he
                     can subvert the true faith; and if he is contending, it is against his own soul
                        <pb type="page" n="83"/>that he contends; but nothing can overcome the
                     faith. And this is the meaning of the expression, <quote>The bars<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n83-1"/> of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>
                     shall not prevail against it.</quote> Wherefore, if any man stand not upon the truth
                     of the faith, but is righteous overmuch, when he thinks to confer honour, he
                     rather offers insult; but if he accept the Law of the Lord, which has been laid
                     down for us by the saints, he survives visions of death and the verge of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>.
                     For we have learned<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n83-2"/> that apart from the standard of the faith, we
                     cannot please God.</p>
                  <p>These things I have written, because I have heard that some persons are
                     contentious, and are not obedient unto the Law of the Lord which has been laid
                     down for us by the saints; and which declares that our Lord, by His
                     incarnation, was of the same nature with us in the flesh which He took from us,
                     which doctrine they have even rejected if they are not of this mind.</p>
                  <p>Accordingly, let no one, thinking to honour God, insult His mercy by refusing
                     to obey the doctrine of the holy fathers, who have declared that our Lord <persName>Jesus
                     Christ</persName> is of the same nature with us in the flesh, and is one with His flesh.
                     For I have heard also the holy apostle teaching and saying, <quote>For as much as the
                     children were partakers of the flesh and the blood, He also (partook of the
                     same) in like manner; that by means of death He might destroy the power of
                     death, who is Satan; and might deliver all who were held in the fear of death,
                     and were subject to bondage, that so they might live for ever. For He did not
                     take (the nature) from angels, but He took it from the seed of <persName>Abraham</persName>. And it
                     was fitting that He should be made in all points like unto His brethren, and
                     that He should be a merciful priest, and faithful with God; and that He should
                     make reconciliation for the sins of the people. For in that He suffered being
                     tempted. He is able to succour them that are tempted.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n83-3"/> For this
                     expression, <quote>He was made like us in all points,</quote> teaches all who desire to be
                     meet for the blessings of heaven and to be redeemed, that they must
                     confess<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n83-4"/> the Incarnation of our Lord Jesus Christ as being from Mary the
                        <pb type="page" n="84"/>holy <persName>Virgin</persName> and <persName>Theotokos</persName>; <persName>Christ</persName> Who was of the
                     same nature with her and with us in the flesh, and is of the same Nature with
                     the Father in His Godhead.</p>
                  <p>For the fathers anathematised, and we also agreeing with them anathematise in
                     like manner, any who do not hold their doctrines.</p>
                  <p>But we have, moreover, in our letter added some quotations from them, attesting
                     the truth of this doctrine:—</p>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.1">
                     <head type="sub">Of <persName>Athanasius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n84-1"/></head>
                     <p>For this, indeed, the apostle writes expressly, that, <quote>other foundation can
                        no man lay (than that which is laid),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n84-2"/> even <persName>Christ</persName>; but let every man
                        take heed how he builds.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n84-3"/> Now it is necessary that a foundation such
                        as this should be in conformity and likeness with those who are built upon
                        it. God the Word, because He is the Word and the only-begotten one, has no
                        peers who could be the sons of the Godhead in the same manner as He. But
                        inasmuch as He became man, of our nature, and clothed Himself with our body,
                        we are of the same nature with Him. Accordingly, in the matter of our
                        humanity He is the foundation; so that we may be precious stones, and be
                        built upon Him, and be a temple for the indwelling of the Holy Spirit.</p>
                     <p>For, in like manner as He is the foundation and we are the stones built upon
                        Him, so also He is the vine and we are the branches, hanging from Him and in
                        Him; not indeed in the nature of the Godhead, for that would not be
                        possible, but in the manhood. Now it is fitting that the branches should be
                        like the vine, because we also are like Him in that body which He took from
                        us.</p>
                     <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n84-4"/> we confess that He is the Son of God, and God in the Spirit, and
                        man in the flesh. And there are not two natures in one Son, one to be
                        worshipped and the other <pb type="page" n="85"/>unworthy of worship; but
                        there is one Nature of God the Word, Who became incarnate, and Who, along
                        with the flesh in which He is clothed, is to be worshipped with one
                        worship.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.2">
                     <head>Of the Same, in his Letter to <persName>Epictetus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n85-1"/></head>
                     <p>Now there are many, hiding themselves and blushing, who imagine that, if we
                        affirm the body of our Lord to be from <persName>Mary</persName>, we introduce a fourth Person
                        into the Trinity; but if we affirm<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n85-2"/> the body to be of the same Nature
                        with the Word, the Trinity thereby remains without the addition of any
                        foreign element. While if we maintain with respect to His body that it is
                        human; then since the body is foreign to the Nature of God, when the Word is
                        in it, there must of necessity be a Quaternity instead of a Trinity, in
                        consequence of the addition of the body.</p>
                     <p>When they talk in this way they do not consider how their own argument
                        breaks down and fails. For even if they deny the body to be from <persName>Mary</persName>, they,
                        no less than those who hold a distinct body,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n85-3"/> also seem to hold a
                        Quaternity. For in like manner as the Son is of the same Nature with the
                        Father, and is not the Father but the Son in Person, yet being of the same
                        Nature with the Father; so also, if the body is of the same Nature with the
                        Word, it is not the Word, and since there is another, the Trinity, even
                        according to their showing, is found to be a Quaternity.</p>
                     <p>But the true, indivisible and perfect Trinity can never receive any
                        addition. What then must be the mind of these persons, and how can they be
                        Christians who hold that there is another besides Him who is God?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.3">
                     <head>Of the Same, from the same Letter<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n85-4"/></head>
                     <p>The body of our Redeemer, derived from <persName>Mary</persName>, was in reality and truth human
                        in nature, because it was like our body; <pb type="page" n="86"/>since <persName>Mary</persName>
                        is our sister, we being all descended from our father <persName>Adam</persName>.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.4">
                     <head>Of <persName>Julius</persName> of <placeName>Rome</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n86-1"/></head>
                     <p>And there is no change whatsoever in the Divine Nature, for It is not
                        subject to diminution or increase. And when He says, <quote>Glorify Me,</quote> that is
                        the voice of the body, and is spoken concerning the body. For glory was
                        affirmed with respect to His whole Being, for He is all one. And by this the
                        <quote>glory which I had with Thee before the world was,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n86-2"/> He testified
                        concerning His Godhead that It is always glorified, for such glory properly
                        belongs to It, even though this affirmation was made equally concerning His
                        whole Being. So in the Spirit He is of the same Nature with the Father
                        invisibly; and since the body also was united to Him in His Nature, it is
                        equally included under the name. And again, also, His Godhead is
                        comprehended under the name because It is united to our nature, and the
                        nature of the body is not converted into the nature of God by the union and
                        conjunction of the name of the nature. Just as the nature of the Godhead was
                        not changed by the conjunction of the human body, and by the appellation of
                        a body of our nature.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.5">
                     <head>Of the Same, from his Letter to <persName>Dionysius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n86-3"/></head>
                     <p>They indeed, who confess that the God of heaven became incarnate from the
                        <persName>Virgin</persName>, and that He being joined to His flesh was one, give themselves
                        needless trouble in contending with the maintainers of the opposite view,
                        who affirm (as I have heard) that there are two natures. Since <persName>John</persName> proved
                        our Lord to be one by saying, <quote>The Word became flesh.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n86-4"/> And <persName>Paul</persName> by
                        saying, <quote>There is one Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, through Whom are all
                        things.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n86-5"/> Now, if He Who was born from the <persName>Virgin</persName> was named <persName>Jesus</persName>,
                        and He it is through Whom were all things; He is one nature because He <pb
                           type="page" n="87"/>is one Person, Who is not divided into two. For the
                        nature of the body was not separate, nor yet did the Nature of the Godhead
                        remain distinct at the Incarnation; but just as man, composed of body and
                        soul, is one nature, so also He, Who is in the likeness of men, is one J<persName>esus
                        Christ</persName>.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.6">
                     <head>Of <persName>Gregory</persName> the Miracle-Worker<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n87-1"/></head>
                     <p>Whosoever says that <persName>Christ</persName> appeared in the world in phantasy, and does not
                        confess Him to have come in the body, as it is written: let him be
                        accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever says concerning the body of <persName>Christ</persName> that it was without
                        soul<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n87-2"/> and without mind, and does not confess His humanity to be
                        perfect. He being the same, according as it is written: let him be
                        accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever says that <persName>Christ</persName> took a part of man only, and does not confess Him
                        to have been in all points like as we are, yet without sin: let him be
                        accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever says that <persName>Christ</persName> was liable to change and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n87-3"/> variation, and
                        does not confess Him to be unchanged in Spirit, and uncorrupt in the flesh,
                        as it is written: let him be accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever says that <persName>Christ</persName> was perfect man separately (and God the Word
                        separately),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n87-4"/> and does not confess Him to be one Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>:
                        let him be accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever says that there was One Who suffered and Another Who did not
                        suffer, and does not confess God the Word, Himself impassible, to have
                        suffered in His flesh, as it is written: let him be accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever says that there was One Who existed before the worlds, the Son of
                        God; and another, who at length came into being; and does not confess Him to
                        be the same Who was before the worlds and at length came into being,
                        according as it is written, <quote>Christ yesterday and to-day </quote>:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n87-5"/> let him
                        be accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever says that <persName>Christ</persName> was of the seed of a man in like manner as the
                        rest of mankind, and does not confess Him <pb type="page" n="88"/>to have
                        been incarnate, and to have become man, of the Holy Spirit and also of the
                        <persName>Virgin Mary</persName>, of the seed of the house of <persName>David</persName>, as it is written: let him be
                        accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever says that the body of <persName>Christ</persName> was of the same nature as His
                        Godhead, and does not confess Him to be God before all worlds, Who <quote>emptied
                        Himself and took upon Him the form of a servant,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n88-1"/> as it is written:
                        let him be accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever says that the body of <persName>Christ</persName> was not a created body, and does not
                        confess the uncreated God the Word to have received incarnation and manhood
                        from created man, as it is written: let him be accursed.</p>
                     <p>For how can one affirm the body of <persName>Christ</persName> to be uncreated; since that which
                        is not created is not susceptible of suffering, or wounds, or contact. But
                        <persName>Christ</persName> Himself, after His resurrection from the dead, showed His disciples
                        the prints of the nails and the wound of the spear, and afforded them bodily
                        contact with Himself. And although the doors were shut He entered, that He
                        might display the power of His Godhead and the reality of His body.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n88-2"/>
                        For the flesh which comes into being after lapse of time, cannot be said to
                        be of the same nature with the eternal Godhead.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n88-3"/> For whatsoever in
                        nature and property is incapable of change is of the same nature.</p>
                     <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n88-4"/> He is the true incorporeal God who appeared in the flesh, a
                        perfect Being; He is not two persons nor two natures. For we do not worship
                        Four, God, and the Son of God, and a man, and the Holy Spirit; but, on the
                        contrary, we anathematise those who act so wickedly, and who would place man
                        in the glory of God. But we hold that God the Word became man for the sake
                        of our redemption, and that He took our likeness upon Him, and that He who
                        came in our likeness is in His true Nature the Son of God, but in the flesh
                        a man, our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n88-5"/></p>
                  </div>
                  <pb type="page" n="89"/>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.7">
                     <head>Of <persName>Basil</persName> of <placeName>Caesarea</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n89-1"/></head>
                     <p>That which is made is not of the same nature as its maker, but that which is
                        begotten is of the same essence as its begetter. Accordingly, that which is
                        created and that which is born are not one and the same. <quote>And again, </quote>The
                        children have the same nature as the parent, even though he that was born
                        has come into being in a different fashion. For <persName>Abel</persName>, who was born as the
                        result of copulation, was in no respect different from <persName>Adam</persName> who was not
                        born, but was formed. <quote>And again, </quote>If they who are different in the manner
                        of their creation are different also in their essential being, then men must
                        be unlike one another in nature. For there is one creation of <persName>Adam</persName>, who was
                        formed out of the earth; and another creation of <persName>Eve</persName>, who was made from a
                        rib; and another of <persName>Abel</persName>, who was from copulation; and another of Him Who
                        was from <persName>Mary</persName>, who was from a virgin alone. And, indeed, the same might be
                        said with respect to birds and beasts.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.8">
                     <head>Of <persName>Gregory</persName>, his Brother<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n89-2"/></head>
                     <p>The nature, indeed, of those who are begotten must of necessity be like
                        their begetters.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.9">
                     <head>Of <persName>Gregory</persName> of <placeName>Nazianzum</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n89-3"/></head>
                     <p>Now these are generally accepted doctrines, that He Who was exalted far
                        above us, for our sake took our qualities upon Him and became man; not that
                        through the body He should thenceforth be limited to the body, for He is not
                        so limited, since His Nature is infinite; but that He might sanctify man by
                        His body He became as leaven to the whole lump, and drew it to Himself. And
                        him who was guilty he released from his guilt. He was, for our sake, in all
                        points like as we are, sin only excepted, in body, soul, mind, <pb
                           type="page" n="90"/>of which the ordinary mortal man is composed. He Who
                        manifested Himself was God in respect of His spiritual being, but human in
                        respect of <persName>Adam</persName> and the Virgin from whom He was derived; from the former as
                        His ancestor, but from the latter who was His mother according to the
                        (natural) law, and who gave Him birth in a manner superior to nature, and
                        not after the (natural) law.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.10">
                     <head>Of <persName>Julius</persName> of <placeName>Rome</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n90-1"/></head>
                     <p>But, again, with respect to the dispensation of our Redeemer in the flesh,
                        we believe that God the Word remaining unchanged, became flesh, with the
                        object of renewing mankind. And He, being the true Son of God by the eternal
                        generation, became man by the birth from the Virgin. And He, Who is perfect
                        God in His Godhead of the same Nature with the Father, and also perfect man
                        of the same bodily nature with mankind by birth from the Virgin, is one and
                        the same. But whosoever says that <persName>Christ</persName> had a body from heaven, or that His
                        body was of His nature: let him be accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever denies that the flesh of our Lord is from the Virgin, of the same
                        nature as ours: let him be accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever holds concerning our Lord and Saviour Who was from the Holy Spirit
                        and from <persName>Mary</persName> the Virgin in the flesh, that He was incomposite and without
                        consciousness, and without reason, and without mind: let him be
                        accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever shall dare to say with respect to <persName>Christ</persName> that He suffered in His
                        Godhead, and not in the flesh, as it is written: let him be accursed.</p>
                     <p>Whosoever would separate and divide our Lord and Saviour, and say that God
                        the Word is one Son, and the man whom He took another, and does not confess
                        Him to be one and the same: let him be accursed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.11">
                     <head>Of <persName>John</persName> <persName>Chrysostom</persName></head>
                     <p>He Who transcends all our conceptions and surpasses <pb type="page" n="91"
                        />all our thoughts, and is exalted above angels and above all intelligent
                        powers, was content to become man; and He took flesh, which was formed from
                        the earth and the clay. And this He did by entering the Virgin's womb, where
                        He was carried for the period of nine months; and after His birth He
                        sucked<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n91-1"/> milk; and indeed He suffered all things pertaining to the
                        human lot. Why<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n91-2"/> was He called a Table? Because when I eat the mystery
                        which is upon Him, I am refreshed. Why was He called a House? Because I
                        dwell in Him. Why was He called an Indweller? Because I am His temple. Why
                        was He called a Head? Because I am His member. When<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n91-3"/> He set His love
                        upon a harlot, what did He do? He did not call her up; for He would not
                        bring a harlot up to Heaven. But He came down; as she was not able to ascend
                        to Him, He descended to her. And coming to her hovel, He Himself was not
                        ashamed; and He found her drunk. And how did He come? Not openly in His own
                        Nature; but He became like the harlot herself in nature though not in will;
                        lest, when she saw Him, she might be confounded through terror and flee. He
                        came to her having become man. And how did He become man? He was conceived
                        in the womb, and He grew gradually.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.12">
                     <head>Of the Same<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n91-4"/></head>
                     <p>This is the day on which the Eternal One was born and became man, a thing
                        which never took place before, though He did not change from being God, for
                        it was not by a change of the Godhead that He became man; neither from a
                        human original by growth did He become God; but the impassible Word suffered
                        no change in His Nature by becoming flesh. He that is seated upon the throne
                        high and lifted up, was laid in the manger. He that is simple and without
                        body, and cannot be touched, was embraced by human hands. He <pb type="page"
                           n="92"/>Who severs the chains of sin, was wrapped in swathing- bands.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.13">
                     <head>Of <persName>Athanasius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n92-1"/></head>
                     <p>If any man teaches doctrine contrary to the Holy Scriptures, and says that
                        the Son of God is One, and he who is man from <persName>Mary</persName> is another, who became a
                        son by grace as we; so that there would be Two dwelling in the
                        Deity;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n92-2"/> One, of the same Nature with God, and the other who became so
                        by grace, the man from Mary: and whosoever, further, says that the body of
                        our Lord was from above, and not from the Virgin <persName>Mary</persName>; or that the Godhead
                        was converted into flesh; or that It was confounded or changed; or that the
                        Godhead of our Lord suffered; or that the body of <persName>Christ</persName>, in as much as it is
                        from men, should not be worshipped, and not that the body is to be
                        worshipped because it is that of our Lord and God;— the man who asserts
                        these things we anathematise, for we obey the apostle when he says,
                        <quote>Whosoever preaches to you a gospel different from that which we have
                        preached to you, let him be accursed.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n92-3"/></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.14">
                     <head>Of Bishop <persName>Ambrose</persName></head>
                     <p>He is the same Person Who speaks, though not always in the same manner. But
                        He had regard in it at one time to the glory of God, and at another time to
                        the passions of men. As God, He teaches divine things, because He is the
                        Word; and as man, He teaches human things, because He speaks in our
                        nature.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.15">
                     <head>Of <persName>Theophilus</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n92-4"/></head>
                     <p>The Word, the living God, the Lord of all, and Creator of the worlds, did
                        not clothe Himself in a heavenly <pb type="page" n="93"/>body<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n93-1"/> as in
                        some costly substance and come to us, but He displayed in clay<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n93-2"/> the
                        greatness of the skill of His art. For, when He would restore and renew man
                        who was formed from the clay, He was born as man from the Virgin, who,
                        corresponding to us in all points, sin only excepted, and coming into being
                        by a miracle, shone upon us and blessed our human nature.</p>
                     <p>However, the first man also came into being in a manner different and
                        distinct from us, as the intercourse and association of man and woman did
                        not minister to his creation. And if they allow, in his case, that he was
                        formed out of the earth by the will of God, no parents having ministered to
                        his birth by the conjunction of male and female; why do they quarrel with
                        the Incarnation of our Lord and Saviour, which was from the Virgin? And when
                        they oppose us in this matter, we ask them whether is it easier that a man
                        should come into being from the earth without parents, or that our Saviour
                        <persName>Christ</persName> should be born from the Virgin, with flesh, and soul, and
                        consciousness? And the first man, indeed, who was from the earth, partook of
                        flesh and blood in all the likeness of humanity; but our Saviour, by His own
                        power, created and prepared from the Virgin a body for Himself with flesh,
                        and blood, and soul, and consciousness. And we confess that He consorted
                        with men, even though in His holy Incarnation the sensual intercourse of man
                        and woman had no part.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.16">
                     <head>Of the Same<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n93-3"/></head>
                     <p>Now it was not difficult for God the Word to prepare for Himself a temple
                        from the Virgin's body, for the purpose of our redemption. For consider,
                        indeed, that God also is never polluted by natural copulation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n93-4"/> when
                        He creates man; and how much more then, by His mercy, may He become <pb
                           type="page" n="94"/>incarnate from the blood of the Virgin, for the
                        purpose of our redemption.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.17">
                     <head>Of <persName>Cyril</persName></head>
                     <p>So, truly, the <persName>Theotokos</persName> still remained a virgin after giving birth to
                        <persName>Christ</persName> by a miracle; and He was partaker, in like manner as we, of flesh and
                        blood, not of His own nature, as the heretics say, but of our nature,
                        according to the saying, <quote>He took the seed of <persName>Abraham</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n94-1"/></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.18">
                     <head>Of the Same<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n94-2"/></head>
                     <p>We assert that the body of the Word was His own, and not that of some other
                        man separately and distinctly who is held to be different from <persName>Christ</persName> the
                        Son. And as the body of each one of us is said to be his own, so also we
                        believe respecting the one <persName>Christ</persName>. And although He took the body from our
                        race and our nature, because He was born of the Virgin; yet it must be held
                        and declared to be His own body. And, since God the Word is the Life in His
                        own Nature, He declared His body to be a life-giving one. And therefore He
                        became to us a blessing, giving life to all.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n94-3"/> And if it be not so,
                        how then is He like us, while yet remaining as He was before, God the Word?
                        However, grant to Him that in the unity of the Person His body is not
                        separated, and do not denude Him of His flesh. And thus I rightly worship
                        one Son, Who is of the same Nature indeed with the Father in the Godhead,
                        but of the same nature with us in the manhood. And as for those who delight
                        to believe this truth, <persName>Christ</persName> will enlighten their knowledge also of Himself
                        by His mysteries.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.19">
                     <head>Of the Same</head>
                     <p>It is right, indeed, for us to say and believe that God the Word, still
                        remaining of the same Nature with God the Father, was sent and became man,
                        of the same nature with us. <pb type="page" n="95"/>He is and He remains as
                        He is, and by becoming man He was not changed. And He was sent to preach
                        deliverance to the captives and light to the blind.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.20">
                     <head>Of the Same, from his Letter to <persName>Succensus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95-1"/></head>
                     <p>They say, if <persName>Christ</persName> be perfect God and perfect man, and the same is of the
                        Nature of the Father in the Godhead and of our nature in the manhood,
                        how<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95-2"/> is He perfect if His human nature is not seen? and how is He of
                        our nature if that actual and self-same nature which is ours be not seen?
                        The answer which we have given at the beginning should suffice to enlighten
                        them. For if,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95-3"/> when speaking of one nature of the Word, we refrained
                        from saying <quote>incarnate,</quote> rejecting the dispensation, their word would be
                        plausible when they ask, <quote>How can He be perfect in manhood and in Nature?</quote>
                        But since our word indeed testifies that He is perfect in manhood and in
                        Nature by saying that He became flesh, therefore let them cease from these
                        objections, and not lean upon a broken reed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection" n="4.12.2.21">
                     <head>Of the Same</head>
                     <p>In the might, indeed, of His Godhead He took the hand of the daughter of
                        <persName>Jairus</persName>, saying, <quote>Maid, arise.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95-4"/> And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95-5"/> He did not give the
                        command in word<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95-6"/> merely, and the work was accomplished according to
                        His own will. But<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95-7"/> that we might believe that His holy body was of
                        the same nature with our bodies, while it also was glorious, and divine, and
                        raised above our measure, it being also His own. He wrought in it. For which
                        reason, also, He called His own body the  <quote>Bread of Life.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95-8"/></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="paragraph" n="4.12.2.22">
                     <p>And so these fathers and holy men like them have with <pb type="page" n="96"
                        />one consent anathematised every man who is not obedient to their
                        doctrine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="paragraph" n="4.12.2.23">
                     <p>And I have written to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, to the clergy, to the monks, to the
                        sisters the virgins in <persName>Christ</persName>, and to the believing people; and I have sent
                        the letter to you, my dear friends; and that ye may know what I have
                        written, I, <persName>Timothy</persName>, have marked the salutation with my own handwriting.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="paragraph" n="4.12.2.24">
                     <p>Whosoever does not believe in the doctrine of the holy fathers, in
                        accordance with the tradition of our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>: let him be accursed.
                        For it is right for each one of us either to stand fast in the faith and to
                        live in it, or else to die on behalf of it, and to live for evermore.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="paragraph" n="4.12.2.25">
                     <p>My brother <persName>Anatolius</persName> the presbyter, and <persName>Theophilus</persName>, and <persName>Cyrus</persName>, and
                        <persName>Christodorus</persName>, and <persName>Gennadius</persName> the deacons, and the members of the brotherhood
                        who are with me, send you their greeting.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="chapterParagraphs" n="4.12.3">
                  <p>The foregoing letter, with the quotations appended thereto, we have written
                     down here. By reading and considering it, lovers of the doctrine will find in
                     it a sufficient refutation of the notion of Nestorius, who holds that there are
                     two Natures in the unity of <persName>Christ</persName>; and also of the teaching of <persName>Eutyches</persName>, who
                     does not confess that God the Word became perfect Man, and remained without
                     change God the Word, One Person who became flesh.</p>
                  <p>And, besides this letter, we have subjoined another explaining the right method
                     of reception in the case of those who repent and turn from heresy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section" n="4.12.4">
                  <head>The letter of <persName>Timothy</persName> which he wrote to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and by which he cut off
                     <persName>Isaiah</persName> and <persName>Theophilus</persName> from communion with the believers</head>
                  <p><persName>Timothy</persName> to the God-loving bishops, and presbyters, and deacons, and
                     archimandrites, and sisters, and faithful people in the Lord, greeting—</p>
                  <p>Inasmuch as <persName>Isaiah</persName> and <persName>Theophilus</persName> have been for a long time heretics in secret,
                     whom I admonished by letter, urging <pb type="page" n="97"/>them to agree to
                     the holy doctrine of the fathers, and they have not been obedient to the
                     letters which I wrote to them to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, containing proofs from
                     Scripture, and the doctors of the Church, that our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> was of the
                     same nature with us in the body; and furthermore they have shown no respect for
                     my sufferings in being banished from place to place, but have behaved
                     treacherously towards the bearers of my letter, and also informed the
                     prefects<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n97-1"/> against them, and they stirred up others, saying, <quote>It is a
                     forgery,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n97-2"/> even though they knew my signature which was on the letter.
                     And I waited a considerable time for them though I knew their disposition, and
                     they made no reply, either by word of mouth or in writing. And upon reflection,
                     I thought it right to send them another letter; so I wrote urging them to come
                     and confess the true faith. And in my admonition I reminded them that God does
                     not condemn nor reject those who repent. And I cited the examples of holy men
                     who sinned and denied the Lord, but who afterwards repented; and God accepted
                     their repentance, and accounted them worthy of their former dignity;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n97-3"/>
                     such was the case of <persName>David</persName>, and <persName>Peter</persName>, and <persName>Paul</persName>.</p>
                  <p>And I wrote to them that in like manner, if they would repent and confess the
                     body of <persName>Christ</persName> to be of the same nature as ours, I would continue to entertain
                     my old esteem and love for them ; and I would maintain them in the honour of
                     their rank. And they showed no affection for me, but treated me with
                     contempt.</p>
                  <p>And after this I waited four years more for them, without exposing them by
                     name. And they still persevered in their disobedience, and showed no sign of
                     repentance, and they neither received the doctrine of the holy fathers nor me.
                     And they associated with some heretics who openly deny that our Lord took a
                     human body, and that He became perfect man from us. And they creep into houses,
                     and greedily grasp at gain,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n97-4"/> which they hold as their god, while they
                     are sojourning in the royal city. And I wrote to them that they should <pb
                        type="page" n="98"/>depart from it, but they would not. And they continued
                     to lead simple folk astray, and to circulate other rumours respecting me, with
                     the object of doing me great harm. And being distressed and saddened by them, I
                     was compelled to excommunicate them by their names lest they should cause many
                     to stumble<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n98-1"/> and err.</p>
                  <p>And I now give sentence upon <persName>Isaiah</persName> and <persName>Theophilus</persName>, who say that the body of
                     the Lord is of His own divine Nature, and not of ours, and who deny His true
                     humanity, thereby cutting themselves off from the fellowship of the holy
                     fathers and mine; that no man henceforth hold communion with them. For <persName>John</persName> the
                     evangelist commands, saying, <quote>My brethren, believe not every spirit, but try
                     the spirits whether they be of God; for indeed, many false prophets have
                     appeared in the world. And hereby the spirit which is from God is known, every
                     spirit which confesses that <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is come in the flesh is of God, and
                     every spirit which does not confess Jesus is not from God. And this is the
                     spirit of the false <persName>Christ</persName>. Because many deceivers have gone forth into the
                     world, who do not confess <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> to have come in the flesh; this is a
                     deceiver and a false <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n98-2"/> And again, <quote>If any man comes to you not
                     preaching this doctrine, do not either receive him into the house or greet him,
                     for he that greets him is partaker with his evil deeds.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n98-3"/> And because of
                     the apostle who says, <quote>Whosoever preaches to you a gospel different from what
                     we have preached to you, let him be accursed.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n98-4"/></p>
                  <p>I am clear from their blood and from that of their associates; for I have not
                     ceased to show them, according to the will of God, what is for their good. For
                     Paul further exhorts us, saying, <quote>After thou hast warned an heretic once or
                     twice, and he has refused thine admonition, avoid him; since by continuing in
                     his sin he is corrupted and guilty.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n98-5"/> But the blessed <persName>Dioscorus</persName> the
                     Confessor wrote sentiments agreeable to these of the holy fathers, and after
                     the same manner, in his letter to Secundinus.<quote> . . . And the letter goes on to
                     say, </quote>Now, I beseech you, brethren, by the <pb type="page" n="99"/>Lord <persName>Jesus
                     Christ</persName>, and by the love of the Spirit, concerning those who repent and turn
                     from the heresy of the Diphysites, as I wrote in a letter a year ago, that you,
                     the bishops, and clergy, and other believers, all who are subject to you, help
                     them, and extend the hand to them in the Lord.</p>
                  <p>And when anyone is converted let him have one year of repentance, and after
                     that let him be established in his former rank, and his dignity be restored to
                     him. And if there be no believing bishop, let the clergy or the believing
                     bishops, who from any cause happen to be in the country, fill the place in the
                     love of God, even though those who repent are not subject to them in
                     jurisdiction.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n99-1"/></p>
                  <p>This same order and regulation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n99-2"/> Cyril and Dioscorus observed of one
                     year's repentance for bishops, presbyters, and deacons; after which they should
                     be established in their former rank.</p>
                  <p>Pray for me that God may help me in this conflict; the Lord be with you.
                     Amen!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="chapterParagraphs" n="4.12.6">
                  <p>Such letters he wrote advising them how they should receive converts from the
                     Proterian party.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n99-3"/></p>
                  <p>And he became so celebrated, even with the people of <placeName>India</placeName>, that when their
                     bishop died they, being of the same faith with him, sent a request to him that
                     he would appoint a bishop for them.</p>
                  <p>But, indeed, the Alexandrians never ceased sending petitions and supplications
                     to the king on his behalf, time after time, and stirring up popular
                     tumult<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n99-4"/> for him. For as soon as they heard of the death of <persName>Leo</persName> and the
                     succession of Basiliscus, they sent a deputation of certain chosen monks, <persName>Paul</persName>
                     the Sophist, and <persName>James</persName>, and <persName>Theopompus</persName>.</p>
                  <p>But the chief priests who held office from the Council of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> until the
                     time of <persName>Basiliscus</persName>, and the encyclical <pb type="page" n="100"/>letters which
                     he and <persName>Marcus</persName> wrote, and up to the reign of <persName>Zeno</persName>, who became emperor, are as
                     follows:—</p>
                  <p>Of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, <persName>Leo</persName>, and his successor <persName>Hilary</persName>.</p>
                  <p>Of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, <persName>Proterius</persName>, who was killed. And his successor was <persName>Timothy</persName> the
                     Great, who was banished. And until he returned by means of the Encyclicals,
                     they appointed another <persName>Timothy</persName>, called <persName>Salophaciolus</persName>.</p>
                  <p>In <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, <persName>Anatolius</persName>, and his successor <persName>Gennadius</persName>, who was succeeded by
                     <persName>Acacius</persName>.</p>
                  <p>In <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, <persName>John</persName>, who took the place of <persName>Bassian</persName>; and <persName>Paul</persName>, who was banished,
                     and who returned by means of the Encyclicals, but was banished again.</p>
                  <p>In <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, <persName>Domnus</persName>, and his successor was <persName>Maximus</persName>, and then Martyrius, who was
                     driven out; and after him <persName>Julian</persName>, who was succeeded by <persName>Stephen</persName>; and then
                     another <persName>Stephen</persName>, who was driven out; and <persName>Peter</persName>, who returned from banishment
                     two or three times.</p>
                  <p>And in <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, <persName>Juvenalis</persName>, and <persName>Anastasius</persName> his successor.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n100-1"/></p>
                  <p>Now King <persName>Leo</persName> the emperor died, and there arose after him <persName>Basiliscus</persName>, and
                     <persName>Marcus</persName>, and <persName>Zeno</persName>, who had retired for a little time to the strongholds of
                     <persName>Salmon</persName>; but he afterwards returned and became emperor, and <persName>Basiliscus</persName> and
                     <persName>Marcus</persName> were driven out.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n100-2"/></p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n62-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>shaking cap</quote>; again (ch. 10)
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>crooked cap,</quote> from  <foreign xml:lang="grc">Σαλοφακίολος </foreign>, hence I translate uniformly
               Salophaciolus.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-2">Probably <!--  Add Syriac  --> has dropped out of the text, and the
               translation should be as in the heading of Chap. III.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">δέησις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">αἴλουρος</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-2">Evag. ii. 8; Liberat. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-4">I.e. Upper Egypt, see Evag.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρακτικός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, otherwise called <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e.
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> (Life of <persName>Peter</persName> lb., ed. Raabe, p. 67) = <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ταφοσίριον</foreign> (see Euseb.
               H. E. vi. 40). Clearly then <!--  Add Syriac  --> <foreign xml:lang="grc">τάφος</foreign>, and the name was taken to
               mean <quote>Tomb of <persName>Osiris</persName></quote> (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-4">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->.I cannot even guess what this word may
               mean.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, unleavened bread.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-3">Evag. ii. 8; Liberat. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n67-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσίας</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n69-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n69-2">Liberat. 15; Evag. ii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-1">Evag. ii. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-2">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">δέησις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71-1">Matt. xxviii. 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71-2">Migne, Patr. Graec. vi. p. 274.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n71-4">Matt. xxii. 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n72-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n72-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-1">Imperfectly written in MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->. <quote>Mich. has <quote>that
               they hold fast,</quote> reading <!--  Add Syriac  -->; but it is hard to explain the
               corruption in the text</quote> (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-3">See bk. 7, ch. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-5">Mansi, vol. vii. p. 539 ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-1">Leo, Ep. 156, ch. ii.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-2">Evag. ii. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηλάτης</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-5">Evag. ii. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-1">Mansi, vol. vii. p. 537.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπομνήματα</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-3">Prov. xviii. 3 (LXX).</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for<!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-5">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσταγμα</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-5">Liberat. 15 and 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-7">Perhaps we should read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and trans. <quote>more than
               ten thousand persons were killed there in the attempt to rescue,</quote> etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πάραλος</foreign>, the province of Phœnice
               Maritima.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, see note 1, p. 62.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-2">Liberat. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσταγμα</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">δημοτικός</foreign></note>
            <note xml:id="n78-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ὀρφανοτροφεῖον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-3">Evag. ii. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ὀρφανοτρόφος</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n81-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->; and for the
               defective word<!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-1"> Num. xx. 17; Prov. iv. 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-2">A free quotation from Eccles. vii. 16-18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-4">Ps. cxlii. (Syr. cxli.) 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-7"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  --> as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-8">John i. 42; Matt. xvi. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n83-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. μοχλοί.</note>
            <note xml:id="n83-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n83-3">Heb. ii. 14-18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n83-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n84-1">Orat. ii., contra Arian. 74.</note>
            <note xml:id="n84-2">The words <!--  Add Syriac  --> must have dropped out of the
               MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n84-3">1 Cor. iii. 11, 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n84-4">De Incarn. Dei Verbi (Migne, Patr. Graec. vol. xxviii. p.
               25).</note>
            <note xml:id="n85-1">Athan. ad Epict. 8, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n85-2"> Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n85-3">This is the best I can make of it, the text may be corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n85-4">Ibid. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n86-1">Migne, Patr. Lat. vol. viii. p. 874.</note>
            <note xml:id="n86-2">John xvii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n86-3">Migne, Patr. Lat. vol. viii. p. 929.</note>
            <note xml:id="n86-4">John i. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n86-5">1 Cor. vi. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-1">Migne, Patr. Græc. vol. x. p. 1128ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-3">0010, MS., which L. omits.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-4">Supplied from the Greek.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87-5">Heb. xiii. 8. This quotation is not in the Greek.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-1">Phil. ii. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-2">Luke xxiv. 36-43; John xx. 19-27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-3">MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->, which
               L. omits.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-4">Migne, Patr. Græc. vol. x. p. 1117. Here Mich. has "of the
               same."</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-5">This is only an attempt at translating the sentence; a comparison
               with the Greek shows that the text is corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n89-1">Migne, Patr. Graec. vol. xxix. pp. 673, 680, 681.</note>
            <note xml:id="n89-2">Ibid. vol. xlv. p. 601.</note>
            <note xml:id="n89-3">The source of this quotation we are not able to find.</note>
            <note xml:id="n90-1">Not in any of the extant works of Pseudo-Julius.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-2">De Capt. Eutrop. 8. Here, and at the beginning of the next
               quotation, Mich. has <quote>of the same,</quote> which must therefore have dropped out of our text
               (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-3">Ibid. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-4">This quotation does not occur in either of the extant sermons on
               the Nativity.</note>
            <note xml:id="n92-1"> Migne, Patr. Graec. vol. xxviii. p. 28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n92-2"> Probably for <!--  Add Syriac  --> we should read
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> (Gk. <foreign xml:lang="grc">υἱὸν Θεοῦ</foreign>), and transl. <quote>two dwelling together, One the
               Son of God, of the same nature,</quote> etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="n92-3"> Gal. i. 8, 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n92-4">Sixth Paschal Letter, Migne, Patr. Græc. vol. Ixv. p. 60.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-1">The Greek <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐρανίου λαβόμενος σώματος</foreign> shows that for
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> we should read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-2">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  --> (Gr. πηλῷ),
               and for <!--  Add Syriac  --> read<!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-3">This and the latter part of the preceding are probably from the
               lost part of the fifth Paschal Letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-4">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-1">Heb. ii. i6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-2">Migne, Pair. Grac. vol. Ixxvi. p. 372.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-3">The rest is not in the Greek. Mich, has <quote>OF THE SAME,</quote> which must
               therefore have dropped out of our text (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-1">Cyr. Ep. 46. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-2">We must insert <!--  Add Syriac  -->; the Greek is <foreign xml:lang="grc">ποῦ τὸ
               τέλειον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-3"> For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, Gk.
               εἰ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-4">Mark v. 41.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-5">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, L., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-7">Pusey's Libr. of the Fathers (Cyr. 5 Tomes, p. 368); cf. Migne,
               Patr. Græc. 76, p. 1429, where, however, the extract begins after this
               sentence.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-8">John vi. 48.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὕπαρχοι</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">φάλσον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-4">A word has been erased here from the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-1"><!--  Add Syriac  --> MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-2">1 <persName>John</persName> iv. 1-3; 2 John 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-3">2 <persName>John</persName> 10, 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-4">Gal. i. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-5">Tit. iii. 10, 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-1">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  --> (or
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-3">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-4"><!--  Add Syriac  --> i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στάσις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-1">The MS. here adds <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>Fourth Book.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n100-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
