<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb type="page" n="11"/>
         <head>A volume of records of events which have happened in the world</head>
         <div type="book" n="1">
            <head>Book 1</head>
            <list>
               <item>The first chapter, an apology, for undertaking the work.</item>
               <item>The second chapter, an epistle containing a request with regard to the table of
                  generations in the book of Genesis.</item>
               <item>The third chapter, a defence of the table of generations in the matter of the
                  chronological canons, which are set down below.</item>
               <item>The fourth chapter, an epistle containing a request with regard to the
                  translation of the Greek book of <persName>Asyath</persName>, which was found in the library of the
                  house of <persName>Beruya</persName>, the bishops from the <placeName>city of Rhesaina</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-1"/></item>
               <item>The fifth chapter, an answer to the epistle.</item>
               <item>The sixth chapter, a translation of the book of <persName>Asyath</persName>.</item>
               <item>The seventh chapter, a translation of <quote><persName>Silvester</persName>, Patriarch of Rome,</quote> relating
                  the conversion and baptism of <persName>Constantine</persName>, the believing king, and the
                  disputations of the Jewish doctors.</item>
               <item>The eighth chapter, the revelation of the repository of the bones of <persName>Stephen</persName>
                  and <persName>Nicodemus</persName> and <persName>Gamaliel</persName> and <persName>Habib</persName> his son.</item>
               <item>The ninth chapter, about <persName>Isaac</persName> and <persName>Dodo</persName>, the Syriac doctors.</item>
            </list>
            <pb type="page" n="12"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="1.1">
               <head>The First Chapter</head>
               <p>Men who were moved like irrational beasts (and they were merely animal<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-1"/>) by
                  foul habits and wicked customs and brutal instincts and earthly<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-2"/>
                  life<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-3"/> and evil tradition<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-4"/> handed down from one to another, in the
                  eager pursuit of passions, in the corruption of the flesh, and in the impure
                  desires of the body, men whom the Scripture named flesh, saying, <quote>My spirit shall
                  not dwell with men for ever, for that they are flesh</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-5"/> whom <persName>Solomon</persName> also
                  calls ungodly, saying, <quote>Ungodly men with their words and with their works called
                  upon death and thought it their friend; and they melted away and sware and made a
                  covenant with it, because they are worthy to be part of it. For they said in
                  themselves (and they did not reason aright), <quote>Our life is short and in
                  sorrow,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-6"/> and there is no further remedy at the death of a man, and no man
                  hath appeared who hath been released from <persName>Hades</persName>. For we were suddenly born, and
                  hereafter we shall return to be as though we had never been: for the breath in our
                  nostrils is as smoke,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-7"/> and reason as a spark stirred in our heart; which
                  being extinguished,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-8"/> our body shall be as ashes, and the breath shall be
                  scattered abroad as thin air, and our name shall be forgotten after a time, and no
                  man shall remember our works, and our life shall pass away as the trace of clouds,
                  and as a mist that<pb type="page" n="13"/> is driven away before the beams of the
                  sun, and its heat is heavy upon it. For our life is a shadow that passeth away,
                  and there is no remedy at our death: for it is sealed, and there is none that
                  returneth. Come on therefore, let us enjoy these good things: and let us speedily
                  use the creatures in our youth. Let us fill ourselves with choice wine and
                  ointments: and let no blossom<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-1"/> of the air pass by us: let us crown
                  ourselves with the flowers of the rose-tree before it be withered: and let none of
                  us be without voluptuousness until our old age; and in every place let us leave a
                  token<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-2"/> of our voluptuousness: for this is our portion and this is our
                     inheritance</quote></quote>; <ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-3"/> these did as<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-4"/> <persName>Moses</persName> bears witness: <quote>The whole earth
                  was of one language, and of one speech. And it came to pass, when they removed
                  from the east, that they found a plain in the land of <placeName>Sinʿar</placeName>; and they dwelt
                  there. And they said, each man to his fellow, <quote>Go to, let us cast bricks and burn
                  them with fire.</quote> And they had brick for stone, and slime had they for mortar. And
                  they said, <quote>Go to, let us build us a town and a tower whose top may reach unto
                  heaven; and let us make us a name, lest we be scattered abroad upon the
                  earth.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-5"/> And they toiled and built zealously,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-6"/> and laboured in vain
                  at the tower.</p>
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-7"/> yet again the tribes of <persName>Reuben</persName> and <persName>Gad</persName> and the half tribe of Manasseh,
                  when they turned back from the rest of the tribes of their brethren, who had taken
                  possession of the land of promise, and came to <placeName>Gilgal</placeName> by the side of <placeName>Jordan</placeName> in the
                  land of <persName>Khʾnaʿan</persName>, built there with stones which they <pb type="page" n="14"/>
                  collected a great altar to see to by the side of <placeName>Jordan</placeName>. And, when the rest of the
                  tribes heard of it, <persName>Phineas</persName> the son of <persName>Eliʿazar</persName> the priest and the chiefs of the
                  congregation, the captains of the hosts<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-1"/> of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, came to them and
                  inquired at their hands concerning this; and they returned them answer, <quote>It is
                  that it may be a witness between us and you, that your children may not say to our
                  children in time to come, <quote>What have ye to do with the Lord God of Israel, ye
                  children of Reuben and children of <persName>Gad</persName>? For behold! the Lord God hath set a border
                  between us and you, even this <placeName>Jordan</placeName>.</quote> And we said, <quote>Let us take us occasion and
                  build us an altar, not for sacrifice, nor for offering, but for a witness between
                  us and you, and between our generations after us.</quote></quote></p>
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-2"/> again <placeName>Gideon</placeName>, after he had overthrown the Midianites, spread a garment
                  and asked each man for the earrings of the prey which the men with him had
                  gathered; and the weight of the earrings that he asked was a thousand and seven
                  hundred<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-3"/> measures of weight: and <placeName>Gideon</placeName> took them and made thereof a
                  lufro,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-4"/> and put it in his village, even in ʿOfrah: and the children of
                  <placeName>Israel</placeName> went astray after it, and it became a snare to <persName>Gideon</persName> and to his house.</p>
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-5"/> again the mother of <persName>Micah</persName> of <placeName>Mount Ephraim</placeName>, she also received eleven
                  hundred measures of silver from her son, and made a graven image and a molten
                  image.</p>
               <p>And again <persName>Abshalom</persName> the son of <persName>David</persName> <quote>in his lifetime, reared up for himself an
                  image in the dale of the kings: for he said, <quote>I have no one to keep my name in
                     remembrance</quote>: and he called the image after his name: and it was called
                  <quote><persName>Abshalom</persName>'s hand,</quote> unto this day.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-6"/> And Methodius also, bishop of Olympus  <!-- abshalom or abshalom hand as a name? -->
                  and martyr, in the work which he addressed to <persName>Aglaophon</persName> concerning the
                  resurrection of the <pb type="page" n="15"/> dead, tells a story about
                  Phidias,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-1"/> a craftsman and sculptor, who wrought an ivory<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-2"/> statue,
                  beautiful to behold, and, in order that it might last a long time and not be
                  destroyed or spoilt, poured oil under its feet and anointed the rest of the
                  sculpture.</p>
               <p>And we see images of divers persons in divers places, and we find records<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-3"/>
                  written on papyrus concerning divers events which have happened in the world, and
                  statues set up to preserve the memory and extol the merits of those who are
                  dead.</p>
               <p>How just and right is it therefore for the discreet and earnest to see that the
                  rest of the events which have occurred from time to time after those chronicled in
                  the three Ecclesiastical Histories of <persName>Eusebius</persName>, <persName>Socrates</persName>, and <persName>Theodoret</persName>, which are
                  scattered about and not collected in one book, are, as far as is possible,
                  collected together from epistles or manuscripts or trustworthy reports and set
                  down for the benefit of the believers and of those who care for right instruction
                  and mental excellence! May the recording of them have the help of <persName>Christ</persName> our God,
                  to whom we pray that He will give us wisdom and eloquence, that without confusion
                  we may write the true account of the things which have happened!</p>  
               <p>Now, since in the Syriac manuscripts of the table of generations in Genesis there
                  is a certain variation and divergence<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-4"/> from the Greek,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-5"/> and no small
                  deficiency in the number of years, it is right for us and in harmony with our work
                  and reasonable<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-6"/> that it should begin with the book of Genesis, and after
                  this should continue with the book of <persName>Asyath</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-7"/> and after that with that of
                  <persName>Silvester</persName> and the conversion<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-8"/> of <persName>Constantine</persName> the king and his baptism, with
                  regard to which <persName>Eusebius</persName> has failed to give an accurate account and <persName>Socrates</persName> has
                  missed the truth (for the king was not baptized <pb type="page" n="16"/> at the
                  end of his life, as he<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-1"/> wrote, since the story of his conversion by
                  <persName>Silvester</persName> is also preserved in writing and in pictures at Rome in several places,
                  as those who have been there<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-2"/> and come to us have seen and tell), and
                  further concerning the revelation of the repository of the bones of <persName>Stephen</persName> and
                  his companions, and concerning <persName>Isaac</persName> and <persName>Dodo</persName>, the Syriac<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-3"/> doctors.</p>
               <p>And here we will end the first book; and afterwards, from such sources as we can
                  find, we will write about the succeeding events in books and in the chapters
                  contained in them severally, as written below, from the thirty-second year of
                  <persName>Theodosius</persName> the son of <persName>Arcadius</persName> to the year 880 of the Greeks.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-4"/></p>
               <p>Now<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-5"/> we beg<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-6"/> that the readers or hearers will not blame us, if we do
                  not call the kings victorious and mighty, and the generals<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-7"/> valiant and
                  astute,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-8"/> and the bishops pious and blessed, and the monks chaste and of
                  honourable character, because it is our object to relate<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-9"/> facts, following
                  in the footsteps of the Holy Scriptures, and it is not our intention on our own
                  account to praise and extol rulers with flattering words,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-10"/> or to revile
                  and insult with rebuke those who believe differently, provided only we do not find
                  something of the kind in the manuscripts and epistles which we are about to
                  translate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="1.9">
               <head>Chapter IX</head>
               <head>This chapter tells about the Syriac doctors, <persName><persName>Isaac</persName></persName> and <persName>Dodo</persName>, who lived in the
                  days of the believing kings <persName>Arcadius</persName> and <persName>Theodosius</persName></head>
               <p><persName>Isaac</persName> the teacher, a native of <placeName>Syria</placeName>, issued forth from one of the monastic
                  dwellings of the West; and he in his diligence went up to <placeName>Rome</placeName>, and he also
                  travelled to other cities. And he had books which were full of profitable
                  teaching, containing all kinds of comments upon the Sacred Scriptures, following
                  <persName>Ephraim</persName> and his disciples.</p>
               <p>And <persName>Dodo</persName> also was a worthy monk of <placeName>Samkè</placeName>, a town belonging to the district of
                  <placeName>Amida</placeName>. And on account of the captivity and famine which occurred in his days in
                  that country, he was sent by the chiefs of the people to the king; and he proved
                  himself very acceptable. And this man also had, as it appears to us, about three
                  hundred works, more or less, upon every matter taken from the Divine Scriptures,
                  and concerning holy men, and hymns.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n11-1"> Cf. ch. 4 (p. 15, l. 24, L.), <quote>in the library of the memorable
               bishops who were called the family of the house of <placeName>Beruya</placeName> from the city of <placeName>Rhesaina</placeName>,
               in the possession of a lad of their kin named <persName>Morʿabdo</persName>..., I found a little
               book...called the book of <persName>Asyath</persName>.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n12-1">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac -->, not <!--  Add Syriac -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac -->, not <!--  Add Syriac -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-3"><foreign xml:lang="grc">πολιτεία</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac --> for <!--  Add Syriac -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-5">Gen. vi. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac -->, not <!--  Add Syriac -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-7">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac -->, NOT <!--  Add Syriac -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-8">Before <!--  Add Syriac --> the MS. has <!--  Add Syriac -->, which
               L. does not print.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-1">The MS. reading is <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-2"><foreign xml:lang="grc">σύμβολον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-3">Wisd. i. 16-ii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-4">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-5">Gen. xi. 1-4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. This word occurs again in bk. 7, ch. 9 (p.
               224, I. 13, L.), where <persName>Payne Smith</persName> proposes to read <!--  Add Syriac  -->. The word,
               however, is found in both MSS. at that place, and occurs again here, where
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>frequently</quote>, does not suit the context. In both places the
               most suitable meaning is as above. The corresponding adjective occurs in ch. 7 (p.
               73, I. 5, L.), and in bk. 12, ch. 5 (p. 325, I. 23, L.), where the meaning seems to
               be <hi rend="doubleQuote">violent</hi> or <hi rend="doubleQuote">stormy</hi>; see note on 12. 5. The adverb also occurs in 7. 6 (p. 215,
               I. 2, L.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-7"><persName>Josh</persName>. xxii. 9-27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-2">Judg. viii. 24-27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-4">The Syriac corruption of the Heb.<foreign xml:lang="heb">אפוֹד</foreign> (efod) with the preposition
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> prefixed.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-5">Judg. xvii. 1-4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14-6">2 Sam. xviii. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-1">Method, ap. Epiph. Haer. Ixiv. 18, Phot. Bibl. Cod. 234.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> with Sachau
               {Academy, June 1871).</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-3"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπομνήματα</foreign></note>
            <note xml:id="n15-4">The MS has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-6">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-7">The Syriac form of the Hebrew <foreign xml:lang="heb">אסנח</foreign>, <hi rend="doubleQuote">Asnath</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n15-8"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κατήχησις.</foreign></note>
            <note xml:id="n16-1">I.e. <persName>Eusebius</persName>; but perhaps we should read <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               <quote>they wrote</quote>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> either is out of place or should be again
               inserted after <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-4">569. The same date is given in ch. 3 ad fin.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-5">Cf. Socr. bk. 6, praef.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-6">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-7">στρατηγός</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-8"><!--  Add Syriac  -->The dictionaries give only a bad sense to this
               word; but here and in bk 9, ch. 17 (p. 286, I. 3, L.) a good sense is imperatively
               required. It occurs again in bk. 3, ch. 11 (p. 131, I. 26), where either meaning
               would suit, and in 7. 13 (p. 230, I. 15), where the good sense is much the more
               probable.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-9">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-10">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
