<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book" n="10">
            <head>Book 10</head>
            <div type="section" n="10.0">
               <p>In this tenth Book also and in the sixteen chapters contained in it, which are set
                  forth below, are included the events which successively happened from the year
                  fifteen, the year eight hundred and forty-eight according to the era of the
                  Greeks,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n296-1"/> down to the end of the year thirteen, the year eight hundred and
                  fifty-nine of the Greeks,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n296-2"/> still in the time which is concerned with this
                  serene king of our day, Justinian.</p>
               <p>The first chapter, concerning Ephraim, who went down to the East.</p>
               <p>The second, concerning the doings of Bar Khili at Amida in the years fifteen and
                  two.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n296-3"/></p>
               <p>The third, concerning Cyrus, a presbyter of the town of Lʾgino,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n296-4"/> who was
                  burned in the tetrapylon of Amida.</p>
               <p>The fourth, concerning the epistle of Rabbulo of Edessa to Gemellinus of Perrhe
                  about those who eat the sacrament like ordinary bread.</p>
               <p>The fifth, concerning the dedication of the church at Antioch, and also the Synod
                  which was assembled by Ephraim.</p>
               <p>The sixth, concerning Khosru, king of Persia, who went up and took Sura and
                  Berhrœa and Antioch.</p>
               <p>The seventh, concerning Belisarius, who went down and took Sisaurana, a fortress
                  in Persian territory.</p>
               <p>The eighth, concerning Khosru, who went up and took Callinicus and the other
                  camps<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n296-5"/> on the frontier<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n296-6"/> of the Euphrates and the Chaboras.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="297"/>
               <p>The ninth, concerning the plague of tumours.</p>
               <p>The tenth, concerning Martin and Justus, who entered Persian Armenia and
                  returned.</p>
               <p>The eleventh, concerning Khosru, who went up to Edessa and did not take it, and
                  returned.</p>
               <p>The twelfth, concerning James and Theodore, the pious believing bishops, who were
                  consecrated and sent to the East and intrusted with the leadership.</p>
               <p>The thirteenth, concerning the country of Lazica, which was conquered by
                  Khosru.</p>
               <p>The fourteenth, concerning the lack of corn and the scarcity of vegetables which
                  occurred in the years nine and ten.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n297-1"/></p>
               <p>The fifteenth, concerning Rome, which the barbarians took and sacked.</p>
               <p>The sixteenth, concerning the decorations and buildings of Rome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="10.1">
               <head>Chapter 1</head>
               <head>The first chapter<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n297-2"/></head>
               <p>When<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n297-3"/> Severus and Anthimus, the believing chief priests, had been driven
                  out<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n297-4"/> by the king, as mentioned in the ninth Book above, and had withdrawn
                  from the royal city on the arrival of Agapetus of Rome, who soon after died at the
                  end of the month of March in the year fourteen,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n297-5"/> as also did Sergius the
                  archiatros, who brought him, then Ephraim, who held the see of Antioch in the
                  East, was strengthened and invigorated, and upon his sending a message [to the
                  king](?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n297-6"/> there was sent <pb type="page" n="298"/>[a force of
                  Romans](?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n298-1"/> and Clement[inus the tribune(?): and] he received orders in
                  the year fifteen<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n298-2"/> to traverse<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n298-3"/> the Eastern jurisdiction and to go
                  all round it, and himself to give admonition in words, while Clementinus was to
                  use force to make the inhabitants of the cities in the East accept the Synod, as
                  had been done by the natives of Italy, the land of Rome. And this same Ephraim,
                  accompanied by Clementinus, went [to] Berrhœa and Chalcis and Hierapolis and Batnæ
                  and Edessa, and to Sura and to Callinicus and the rest of the frontier,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n298-4"/>
                  and to Rhesaina and to Amida and to Constantia; and he induced many persons to
                  submit, some by words and by promising<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n298-5"/> them the friendship of the king,
                  and some by fear of threats and also exile and spoliation of goods and degradation
                  from their ranks<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n298-6"/> and exclusion from all trades; and others they hunted
                  and drove from country to country, among them the monks, who were found approved
                  in the faith and true believers in time of trial. And, as the winter was a severe
                  one, so much so that from the large and unwonted quantity of snow the birds
                  perished and…, there was distress… among men… from the evil things. And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n298-7"/>…
                  in various countries… From the hill of Singara [in the land] of the Persians they
                  took(?)… John, the <pb type="page" n="299"/>believing [bishop] of Constantia, [by
                  means of] a man named Cons[tantius(?)], and he was imprisoned in A[n]t[i]o[ch] and
                  afflicted and… he would not change but continued…until the beginning of the year
                  one<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-1"/> [in] prison [and there] ended [his life]… and they were expelled… and
                  lived in [various] countries… [until] the year three.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-2"/>… Khos[r]u … and
                  went up [to] S[ura] and Berrhœa and Anti[o]ch.</p>
               <p>Now Theodosius of Alexandria was summoned by the king to come to him, and went up
                  with a few bishops from his jurisdiction; and he would in no wise accept the Synod
                  of Chalcedon, until in the year one<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-3"/> Paul was appointed to the see. And,
                  when Theodosius and the bishops who were with him came before the king, their
                  [arrival] was announced by letter<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-4"/> to Ephraim… thence… But<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-5"/>
                  The[odosius and those who were] with him [appeared] before the king and…, and
                  without…, and they were removed…, and there they lived,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-6"/> and the queen was
                  studious in showing them honour, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-7"/> no one [of] their acquaintances or
                  other discreet men was prevented from seeing them [or] ministering to them…. Now
                  there went up… in [the year fif]teen,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-8"/> and also(?) … the king…
                  much<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-9"/>… he<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-10"/> told him about [a… man] named But<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-11"/>…, [who
                  plotted] a rising<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n299-12"/> in Dara in the summer of the year, who was put to
                  death. And he freed the king from distress of mind, but in what way I have not
                  sure enough information to state, and therefore keep silence.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="300"/>
               <p>And, because Paul who succeeded<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n300-1"/> Th[eo]d[osius](?) in the see…, he shut
                  up…<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n300-2"/> on account of zeal for the faith [in] a bath and suffocated him; and
                  this man's son he arrested and put in the guard-house, that he might not make his
                  father's death known. But it so happened that he escaped and made his way to the
                  queen, and through the believers who knew his father he told the news of his
                  fearful death. And on this account Ephraim of Antioch was sent to Alexandria, and
                  Abraham Bar Khili [accompanied him]; and, as they passed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n300-3"/> through
                  Palestine, they took with them a monk named Zoilus. And they went to Alex[andria
                  and] investigated the action of Paul; and they drove him from his see and
                  enthroned Zoilus, a Synodite,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n300-4"/> in the city: and in order to protect this
                  man from the violence [of] the people of the city they appointed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n300-5"/> Acacius
                  Bar Eshkhofo<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n300-6"/> of Amida<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n300-7"/> tribune<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n300-8"/> of the Romans there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="10.2">
               <head>Chapter 2</head>
               <p>The second chapter of the tenth Book, concerning the doings of Abraham<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n300-9"/>
                  [bar Khili at Amida]</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="301"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="10.4">
               <head>Chapter 4</head>
               <head>From the epistle written by Rabbulo to Gemellinus, bishop of Perrhe, about
                  those who insult the Mysteries and support themselves upon them like common
                  bread<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-1"/></head>
               <p>"I<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-2"/> have heard that in your country of Perrhe certain of the brethren,
                  whose cloisters<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-3"/> are not known,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-4"/> and others of the
                  distinguished<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-5"/> archimandrites of the place, have falsely given out
                  concerning themselves the vain report that they do not eat bread, and have lyingly
                  uttered of themselves the empty boast that they do not drink water, and have
                  asserted<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-6"/> of themselves that they abstain from wine. Accordingly I am
                  afraid<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-7"/> to mention that I have heard that they insult the body and blood
                  of Jesus, the Son of God; but, since necessity constrains me, I will, as is right,
                  be bold to say things which are what these men are not afraid to do, who madly and
                  without discrimination offer<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-8"/> the body and blood of Jesus Christ our Lord,
                  that is, the holy and hallowing body which they have received and the living and
                  life-giving blood which they have drunk. These men, whom I do not know how to
                  name,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-9"/> are said impiously to satisfy the constant wants of their natural
                  hunger and thirst upon it, and it is impossible for them of their own will to go
                     <pb type="page" n="302"/>even one day without the oblation, which is their
                  sustenance; but continually every day a large quantity of food is supplied by the
                  sacrament. And for this reason also they richly<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n302-1"/> leaven the particle which
                  they prepare, and diligently dress<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n302-2"/> it, and carefully seethe it, that it
                  may serve them for food, and it is not treated as the mystery of the body of
                  Christ, symbolised<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n302-3"/> in unleavened bread. And for the rest it is said that,
                  whenever hard pressed, they even offer common unconsecrated bread over one
                  another's hands and eat it. And it is said to be their practice, when walking from
                  one place to another or going on a long journey, to satisfy their natural hunger
                  and thirst on the same body of our Lord two or three times in one day, and, as
                  soon as they have reached<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n302-4"/> their destination, in the evening they are said
                  again to offer the oblation and partake of it as if fasting; nay, even in the holy
                  days of the fast of Lent they presume to act in this manner without fear of God
                  and without shame before men. And men who, as they say, refrain from<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n302-5"/>
                  bread and water every day are found to eat the holy bread and drink the blessed
                  wine on such glorious days, on which even the vile themselves abstain."</p>
               <p>"Now the Spirit that is in me, holy brother ours, bears witness for me that I
                  tremble to write to your reverence all that I have heard about them, because my
                  heart could not really believe it:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n302-6"/> and I would it had been possible for
                  you to have known what I wish to learn<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n302-7"/> without an epistle or a word from
                  me, and for these same men to have received correction from your uprightness,
                  because neither did I wish that either you, my lord, or they should know what is
                  rumoured about <pb type="page" n="303"/>them. Do not then think yourself or let
                  them suppose that it is because I believe the evil report about them that I write
                  these same things to you concerning them; but, being still in doubt, I say to
                  others also that it is impossible that such a great sin should be committed by men
                  who have ever been baptized in Christ. For they say that, as soon as they have
                  performed the sacrament in the paten, they lightly<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n303-1"/>(?) eat<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n303-2"/> as
                  much as they want of it, while the cup of the blood each of them tempers with hot
                  water, whenever they can, like mixed wine and drinks it, and again fills it and
                  gives it to his neighbour; so that owing to the quantity of wine which they drink
                  under the name of the sacrament they are often obliged actually to spit it out of
                  their mouth."</p>
               <p>"O what transcendent impiety, if it is the fact that these men, despising their
                  life, have converted the revered vessels of the sacrament, which on account of the
                  mysteries contained in them even for spiritual heavenly purposes men fear to
                  approach boldly, into vessels of service for their belly, and did not even so much
                  as remember the punishment which Beltʾshatstsar, the heathen king, received and
                  was reproved! For, because in the vessels of the service of God he purposed to
                  insult God like a rebel by using them in a carnal fashion, the likeness of a palm
                  of a hand that wrote was sent from on high to write on the wall of his house the
                  righteous sentence of condemnation for his presumption:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n303-3"/> though how indeed
                  can the vessels of service of the temple in Jerusalem be compared to the glorious
                  vessels of service of the body and blood of the Son of God? For neither is the
                  showbread of the priests of Israel in any way worthy to be compared to the glory
                  of the transcendent mystery; and, if so be any man likens the bread of the table,
                  which David ate when he was hungry, to the life- giving body of God the Word, we
                  ought to look upon him as <pb type="page" n="304"/>a foolish man who does not
                  distinguish the body and blood of the Lord from showbread: wherefore he is an
                  offender against the body and blood of our Lord. For the showbread scarcely
                  cleansed a bodily pollution, even when baptisms of various kinds were combined
                  with it and observance of this and that: but this life-giving body and blood of
                  our Lord Jesus not only purged and hallowed the sin of the soul and of the body in
                  those who received it with faith, but also caused God to be in us, and that by His
                  Spirit, as we are in Him by our body;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n304-1"/> for, 'Whoso eateth My body and
                  drinketh My blood,' says the Son of God, 'he is in Me and I in him, and I will
                  raise him up at the last day.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n304-2"/> In another way again we may understand the
                  greatness of this service, which is a new one, delivered to us by God the Word,
                  from the hard and severe punishment which Paul pronounced against those who have
                  enjoyed it, beyond that received<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n304-3"/> by those who offend against the old
                  service introduced by Moses; for he said, 'If so be he who transgressed against
                  Moses' law died without mercy at the mouth of two or three witnesses, of how much
                  sorer punishment will he be worthy who hath trodden under foot the Son of God, and
                  hath counted the blood of His covenant as that of an ordinary man, and hath done
                  despite unto the Spirit of His grace, wherewith we were sanctified.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n304-4"/> Who
                  is there, therefore, who is so mad as to compare this bread of life, which came
                  down from heaven by virtue of its union with God the Word and gives life to the
                  world, to the showbread with its earthly seasoning? But the opinion of anyone who
                  thinks or acts in this manner<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n304-5"/> is manifest and is, moreover, clearly
                  apparent, for he who thus madly receives it reckons it to be in fact common bread,
                  as he sees it, and does not believe the Son who says, 'The bread which I will give
                  is My body, which is given for the life of the world;'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n304-6"/> for it follows
                  that not only is the bread in the body of Christ, as is seen by them, but in the
                  bread is the body of the invisible God,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n304-7"/> as we believe and <pb type="page"
                     n="305"/>receive the body<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n305-1"/> not to satisfy our bellies but to heal our
                  souls. For<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n305-2"/> those who eat the holy bread in faith do in it and with it eat
                  the living body of God the Sanctifier, and those who eat it without faith receive
                  sustenance, as with other things necessary for the body. For, if the bread is
                  carried off and eaten by enemies by violence, they eat common bread, because those
                  that eat it have not faith, which perceives its sweetness:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n305-3"/> for the bread
                  is tasted by the palate, but the virtue which is hidden in the bread is tasted by
                  faith. For that which is eaten is not only the body of our Saviour, as we said a
                  little before, but whatever is mingled with it, as we believe: for the
                  virtue<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n305-4"/> which is not eaten is mingled with the edible bread, and to those
                  that partake of it becomes one with it, even as the hidden heavens mingle with the
                  visible water, and from them a new birth is born. For the Spirit secretly hovers
                  over the visible water, so that from it a likeness of the heavenly Adam is born
                  anew.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n305-5"/> And, just as in the visible water, in order that it may impart to
                  all who are outwardly baptized in it, there is invisible life, so also in the
                  external bread food is hidden and concealed, of which everyone who rightly
                  partakes obtains immortal life; and we believe the saying of Paul, that those who
                  receive it slightingly obtain from it injury to soul and body and are not
                  profited, even if they are reckoned among the believers. And would that they
                  obeyed the saying of the apostle, who says, 'And let a man examine himself, and
                  then let him eat of that bread and drink of that cup; and he that eateth of it
                  when he is not fit for it eateth and drinketh condemnation to himself!<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n305-6"/>
                  And the same proclaims by his words that it is on account of our enmity against
                  the body and blood that the various infirmities <pb type="page" n="306"/>and
                  unexpectedly sudden death have befallen us by a righteous judgment. "By reason of
                  this happen most of the diseases and sicknesses, and the fate of those who fall
                  asleep suddenly. But, if we judged ourselves, we should not be judged. But, when
                  our Lord judges us, He gives us a discipline, that we may not be condemned with
                  the world."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n306-1"/> And, if those who were in the fixed days of service were now
                  to partake, they would receive one substance only of the body of life. If it be
                  done without the sorrow of repentance, and men do not receive it in faith with
                  reverent fear, even if they do not also commit a deed contrary to their faith,
                  then they are guilty of the body and blood of the Lord, as Paul said, because they
                  do not discern the Lord's body. What punishment can be too severe for this, too
                  great even to be applied to the judgment of those who approach it without fear and
                  do not receive an aliment of faith, but a thing necessitated by their hunger? O,
                  what insolence is this, to which the divine retribution is not equal, if it slays
                  the man! Who does not fear even heaven, when men satisfy the needs of their bodies
                  on a coal of devouring fire, as if it were common bread? Who is not frightened at
                  this statement, that of the coal on which our life depends, that which the
                  seraph<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n306-2"/> revealed to us, grasping it with a fiery forceps in his hand, to
                  signify the sublimity of our mystery, and, while meditating upon it with
                  reverence, approached to take hold of it, of this these men eat to satiety and
                  without fear? And before the body which is given for the life of the world their
                  heart does not quake and they are not afraid, and their hands do not tremble or
                  shake, and their knees do not slip that they should fall, when they eat it for the
                  support of bodily life. And perhaps we ought to say that our Lord also in His full
                  knowledge of all times knew the deed of these men; and for this reason, after they
                  had eaten of the legal passover and were satisfied, then blessed the bread and
                  gave it to His disciples, in order that these men might not say that, after He had
                  blessed, they were satisfied (but, after they were satisfied. He blessed, when the
                  Master and His disciples took a small particle of it); and over the cup He said,
                     <pb type="page" n="307"/>'Take, drink ye all of it,' that they might understand
                  by this that it was of this small cup of which twelve persons drank."</p>
               <p>"And it must needs be said that they thought of themselves that they would attract
                  the admiration of simple persons(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-1"/>by their abstinence from bread and
                  wine, and did not understand that the laughter of the intelligent would defeat and
                  overcome them, and would fall upon their heads, prevailing over the praise of
                  ignorant persons like them. Those who are like them have in all this unpardonable
                  sin accepted for themselves glory from perishing men, even though it did not
                  result to them. It is not fit that they should be named men, but, in justice, they
                  should be named rabid dogs; for the sign of rabid dogs is this, that they suddenly
                  attack the body of their master to eat it."</p>
               <p>"And a man who has forbidden himself bread ought to be empty and not taste
                  anything until the time appointed for him. And this is well known that, when Saul
                  enacted that no one should taste anything on the day of battle until the evening,
                  then Jonathan, because he tasted some honey on the end of his rod, incurred the
                  penalty of death, if it had not been for the violence of the people until he was
                  safe. For 'the foundation of the life of man is bread and water,'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-2"/> says
                  Jesus Bar Asira,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-3"/> the son of Simeon. (Under the name of bread he extended
                  his saying to all food.) And they say of these men that, after they have received
                  the oblation in the morning, and partaken of it yet again in the evening, then
                  they lightly(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-4"/> eat other food and lightly(?) feed on dressed beet and
                  pulse.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-5"/> They are said to fill themselves<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-6"/> on cheese instead of
                  bread; they are, moreover, in the habit of eating fish with all their pleasant
                  taste; they sate themselves largely <pb type="page" n="308"/>on delicious fruit,
                  and they delight in it particularly when dry, besides honey-combs and
                  egg-cakes.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n308-1"/> And, because the heat of the wine which they drink under the
                  name of the Sacrament inflames them more with thirst, all through the summer
                  season they are said regularly to drink the milk of sheep and goats;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n308-2"/> and
                  this again they have done of set purpose, for they have also discovered that the
                  moisture and coolness of milk<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n308-3"/> are found to temper the perpetual burning
                  which results from the wine in their excess. Now, because of these things, and by
                  reason of them, there is in due season uttered, as it shall be spoken, against
                  them also the righteous reproof of God which He pronounced to Eli because of his
                  sons: 'Behold! I have given you all the good things of the earth, that ye might
                  use them without sin; even as for them I set apart all the offerings of the
                  children of Israel, that they might enjoy them without guilt. Wherefore have ye
                  also offended against My body and My blood, like those who wrought wickedness
                  against My sacrifices and against My offerings?' And, since the impiety of these
                  men against God has far surpassed the impiety of those others, which was committed
                  against the people, there has been fear and great trembling in case they should
                  suffer, lest also a punishment like that which went forth against those should be
                  pronounced against them. "'Wherefore,' thus said the Lord, the God of Israel, 'I
                  said indeed that thy house and the house of thy father should minister before Me
                  for ever'; but now the Lord saith, 'Be it far from Me! for them that honour Me I
                  will honour, and they that despise Me shall be lightly esteemed.'"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n308-4"/> You
                  see how He rejected them for ever from the priesthood, and made them outcasts and
                  aliens from His house."</p>
               <p>"Now, what shall I say<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n308-5"/> of men who are not in unison <pb type="page"
                     n="309"/>with the prophets of the Old Testament, nor yet resemble<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n309-1"/> the
                  apostles of the New? For they ought at least to have learned from the chief of the
                  apostles, Peter, what his food was; since he has plainly stated in what his bodily
                  life consisted. For, when his chosen disciple, Clement, asked him to allow him to
                  be his only minister, he spoke thus to him, praising his zeal and jesting at his
                  sustenance: 'Why! Who is strong enough for all this ministry? Are we not
                  continually eating bread and olives? or perhaps it may be that sometimes there may
                  also be a cabbage.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n309-2"/> Moreover, have they not also received a good
                  tradition from Paul, the preacher of truth? For, behold! he also out of the
                  greatness of his need sent and sold his tunic, and with the price of it it is
                  written that they bought bread only and brought it to him with a cabbage,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n309-3"/>
                  that by his action he might lay down a law for us also, as in his saying, 'If we
                  have food and raiment, that is enough for us.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n309-4"/> And, if it is a small
                  thing for them to liken themselves to the apostles, the baptizers of the world,
                  let them imitate even the Lord of the apostles, the Maker of the worlds, and of
                  all that is in them; unless, perhaps, even the human dispensation of our God is
                  contemptible and vile in their eyes. For, behold! as to our Lord, He has
                  everywhere shown us that He ate bread; and the bread too was not of wheat, but it
                  was of barley, and so were the seven other loaves, which were fruitful and
                  multiplied at His word, and 4000 men ate of them and left seven baskets
                  actually(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n309-5"/> full of bread. And, when He ate the passover with His
                  disciples, unleavened bread was set before Him. And also after His resurrection
                  from the dead He ate bread with His disciples for forty days, that the
                  dispensation of our Lord and His fleshly assumption of a body<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n309-6"/> might be
                  believed by them, as they themselves wrote:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n309-7"/> 'Jesus went in and out among
                  them.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n309-8"/> And the house of Cleopas, <pb type="page" n="310"/>because He did
                  not wish them to recognise Him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n310-1"/> while walking with them in the way, He
                  blessed over bread and brake it for them within the house, and then they knew
                  Him."</p>
               <p>"But these men, as I hear, do not follow in their deeds those that err, nor yet
                  are they in concord with the truth in their actions; for they are not circumcised
                  like the Marcionists, neither are they ascetic after the manner of Christians.
                  For, behold! they are not like those deniers of the truth who eat only pulse or
                  bread, but do not presume to commit a lie at their oblations, neither yet do they
                  resemble<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n310-2"/> us believers who eat common bread in moderation and receive the
                  support<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n310-3"/> of our true life separately."</p>
               <p>"Why have these gluttons not trained themselves, so that cheap things only might
                  be enough for them? And why have these guzzlers not accustomed themselves<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n310-4"/>
                  to repel the hunger of their belly with something mean and vile? And wherefore do
                  they not eat ordinary, simple, common bread only? But it is plain that it is in
                  order that they may not afflict themselves. But, if<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n310-5"/> they really wish to
                  afflict their bodies, let them not sate themselves, but eat bread only. And,
                  behold! they are wasted and shrunk and reduced to weakness. But it is plain and
                  manifest that these men do not struggle with their bodies, nor yet do they
                  wrestle<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n310-6"/> with Satan; but for the sake of vain glory they exercise
                  themselves in the tricks of their evil devices, and not in the afflictions of
                  asceticism."</p>
               <p>And further the rest of the epistle with proofs from the Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="311"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="10.5">
               <head>Chapter 5</head>
               <head>The fifth chapter, concerning the dedication of the church which Ephraim of
                  Antioch performed,and the synod of the bishops of his jurisdiction</head>
               <p>Ephraim,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n311-1"/> who was chief priest in Antioch, rebuilt from its foundations
                  the round-shaped church in Antioch and the four triklinia adjoining it. And, when
                  he performed the consecration of it, he assembled one hundred and thirty-two
                  bishops from his jurisdiction in the year one;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n311-2"/> and on the occasion of the
                  dedication<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n311-3"/> of the church he received a contribution from each one of
                  them, such as he pleased, on a lavish<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n311-4"/> scale. And he confirmed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n311-5"/>
                  the Synod of Chalcedon in a document which the bishops whom he had assembled were
                  required to sign; and they anathematised the holy Severus, the believing
                  patriarch, and everyone who agrees with him and does not accept the Synod.</p>
               <p>But God, who makes judgment for the oppressed, after a short time roused up the
                  Assyrian against him and against the city, according to the words of the prophet,
                  who said, "The Assyrian is the rod of Mine anger and the whip wherewith I scourge:
                  against a profane people will I send him, and against a peevish people will I give
                  him a charge, to lead away captives and to take<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n311-6"/> the prey."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n311-7"/> And
                  two years afterwards, in the year three,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n311-8"/> Khosru went up against Antioch,
                  as described in the following chapter.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n311-9"/></p>
               <p>The rest of the tenth Book is wanting in Add. 17,202. The sixteenth chapter and a
                  fragment of the fifteenth are, however, contained in Cod. Rom., and the former
                  exists also in a shortened form in Brit. Mus. Add. MS. 12,154 (fol. 158), from
                  which it is published by Land. Part of the contents of <pb type="page" n="312"
                  />chapters 6-15 may also be recovered from the fragments of James of Edessa (Brit.
                  Mus. Add. MS. 14,685, fol. 22), and from Michael and Gregory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="10.6">
               <head>Fragments of chs. 6-8 from Mich. fol. 173 R; Greg. p. 79, and Jac. Edess.
                  L.C.</head>
               <head/>
               <p>In the eleventh year of Justinian, which is the year eight hundred and fifty of
                  the Greeks,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n312-2"/> in the month of December(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n312-3"/> a great and terrible
                  comet appeared in the sky<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n312-4"/> at evening-time for one hundred days.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n312-5"/>
                  And that year the peace between the kingdoms was broken, and Khosru, king of the
                  Persians, went up and carried off captives from the cities of Sura and Antioch and
                  Berrhœa and Apamea and the districts belonging to them, a bitter captivity. And
                  the Romans also went down to Persia and carried off captives from the countries of
                  Kurdistan and Arzanene and Arabia.</p>
               <p>Then Khosru went up against Callinicus with a great army, and carried off captives
                  from it and from the whole of the southern part<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n312-6"/> of the land between the
                  Rivers.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n312-7"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="10.9">
               <head>Fragment of ch. 9 from Mich. fol. 184 R<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n312-8"/></head>
               <p>[Moreover Zachariah the Rhetor also writes concerning this scourge as
                  follows.]</p>
               <pb type="page" n="313"/>
               <p>In the Greek version of the prophecy of Ezekiel is a passage referring to the
                  plague of tumours; and instead of what is stated in the Syriac language, "All
                  knees shall flow with water,"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n313-1"/> he says, "All thighs shall be befouled with
                  pus."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n313-2"/> And this plague, which is the rising of a swelling on the groins
                  and in the arm-pits of men, began in Egypt and Ethiopia and Alexandria and
                  Nubia<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n313-3"/> and Palestine and Phoenicia and Arabia and Byzantium(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n313-4"/>
                  and Italy and Africa and Sicily and Gaul, and it penetrated to Galatia and
                  Cappadocia and Armenia and Antioch and Arzanene and Mesopotamia, and gradually to
                  the land of the Persians and to the peoples of the North-East, and it slew. And
                  those who were afflicted(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n313-5"/> with the scourge and happened to recover and
                  not die trembled and shook: and it was known that it was a scourge from Satan, who
                  was ordered by God to destroy men.</p>
               <p>In the city of Emesa was the head of John the Baptist, and many sought refuge with
                  it and escaped : and the demons were disturbed before men, being
                  scattered(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n313-6"/> by the saint.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="10.10">
               <head>Fragments of chs. 10, 11, from Jac. Edess., L.C.,Mich. fol. 173 R; Greg. P.
                  79<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n313-7"/></head>
               <p>The Romans went down and did much destruction in the country of
                  Armenia.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n313-8"/></p>
               <pb type="page" n="314"/>
               <p>And again Khosru went up and made an attack<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n314-1"/> upon Edessa, and, not being
                  able to take it, he carried off captives from Batnæ and departed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="10.12">
               <head>Fragment of ch. 12 from Mich. fol. 186 v,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n314-2"/> and Greg. Hist. Eccl. 215,
                  217.</head>
               <p>And on account of the distress and scanty numbers of the pastors among the
                  Persians there was a man named Cyrus, a believing bishop,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n314-3"/> who consecrated
                  and ordained priests, and that from the year one down to this year eight.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n314-4"/>
                  And, lest the heads of the communities of believers should be blamed, or because
                  the priests who were among the Persians belonged to the opposite party(?), and
                  they were assailed by affliction and trouble, they procured
                  provisions(?);<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n314-5"/> and then after due deliberation they consecrated and
                  appointed chief priests in Arabia; and these were Theodore the monk, a strenuous
                  man, and James, the laborious and industrious, the very strenuous,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n314-6"/> who
                  was then in the royal city.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n314-7"/> And he was to be found everywhere, visiting
                  and exhorting with readiness. And he was a practiser of poverty and an ascetic,
                  and swift on his feet, and travelled like ʿAsahel.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n314-8"/> And he was a presbyter
                  in the monastery of the Quarry in the village of Gamuwa, which is on the mountain
                  of Izlo.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n314-9"/> And by the treaty which he concluded he rescued many from among
                  the Persians.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="315"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="10.13">
               <head>Fragments of chs. 13, 14 from Jac. Edess. L.C.;Mich. fol. 185 v; Greg. p.
                  81<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n315-1"/></head>
               <p>Khosru, king of the Persians, again went up and carried off captives from<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n315-2"/>
                  Petra, a city in Lazica, and placed a garrison there.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n315-3"/> And from that time
                  the Romans continued making attacks upon it for seven years, and then the Persians
                  were defeated and the Romans took it from them.</p>
               <p>And at that time there was a scarcity of produce and a lack of the fruit of trees,
                  in the year nine,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n315-4"/> and there was a famine which destroyed soul and body,
                  and it was followed by emaciation such that a man ate 10 lbs. of bread at one time
                  and whatever other kinds of food he could get with it through greediness and
                  hunger. And he became swollen and inflated from the food, but was not satisfied,
                  but was hungry and greedy for food, and asked for bread to fill his belly, and so
                  he died.</p>
               <p>After this there was a plague among oxen in all countries, especially in the East,
                  and it lasted two years, until the lands remained untilled for lack of oxen.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="316"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="10.15">
               <head>About the sack of Rome, which in the days of Justinian the barbarians took and
                  sacked<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n316-1"/></head>
               <p>[In the eighteenth year of Justinian, which is the year eight hundred and
                  fifty-seven of the Greeks,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n316-2"/> the barbarians<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n316-3"/> took Rome, the chief
                  city of Italy; and since they could not guard it, they established themselves in
                  the camp<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n316-4"/> by the side of it, while they left the city deserted and
                  empty.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n316-5"/>]</p>
               <p>In<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n316-6"/> the third year after the sack of the city of Ilium, which was sacked
                  in the days of Samson and Eli the priest in Jerusalem, kings began to be set up in
                  the city of Rome, which was at first called Italy, and the kings who reigned in it
                  were called<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n316-7"/> kings of the Latins. And in the days of Yotham and Ahaz,
                  kings of Judah, Romulus became king there, and he built up the city with great and
                  noble buildings, and it was called Rome after his name; and the kingdom of its
                  inhabitants was called the kingdom of the Romans from the time of Hezekiah the
                  king.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="317"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="10.16">
               <head>[From the Ecclesiastical History of Zachariah, fromthe sixteenth chapter of the
                  tenth Book], about the objects<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n317-1"/> and buildings in the city of
                  Rome<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n317-2"/></head>
               <p>Now the description of the decorations of the city, given shortly, is as follows,
                  with respect to the wealth of its inhabitants, and their great and pre-eminent
                  prosperity, and their grand and glorious objects of luxury and pleasure, as in a
                  great city of wonderful beauty.</p>
               <p>Now its pre-eminent decorations are as follows, not to speak of the splendour
                  inside the houses and the beautiful formation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n317-3"/> of the columns in their
                  halls and of their colonnades(?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n317-4"/> and of their staircases, and their lofty
                  height,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n317-5"/> as in the city of wonderful beauty.</p>
               <p>It<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n317-6"/> contains 24 churches of the blessed apostles, Catholic churches. It
                  contains 2 great basilicæ, where the king sits and the senators are assembled
                  before him every day. It contains 324 great spacious streets. It contains 2 great
                  capitols. It contains 80 golden gods.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n317-7"/> It contains 64 ivory gods. It
                  contains 46,603 dwelling-houses. It contains 1797 houses of magnates. It contains
                  1352 reservoirs<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n317-8"/> pouring <pb type="page" n="318"/>forth water. It contains
                  274 bakers, who are constantly making and distributing annonce to the inhabitants
                  of the city, besides those who make and sell in the city. It contains 5000
                  cemeteries, where they lay out and bury. It contains 31 great marble
                  pedestals.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-1"/> It contains<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-2"/> 3785 bronze statues of kings and
                  magistrates. It contains, moreover, 25 bronze statues of Abraham, Sarah, and
                  Hagar, and of the kings of the house of David, which Vespasian the king brought up
                  when he sacked Jerusalem, and the gates of Jerusalem and other bronze
                  objects.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-3"/> It contains 2 colossal<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-4"/> statues. It contains 2 columns of
                  shells.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-5"/> It contains 2 circuses. It contains 2 theatres and one.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-6"/>
                  It contains 2 amphitheatres.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-7"/> It contains 4 beth ulde.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-8"/> It
                  contains 11 imfiya.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-9"/> It contains 22 great and mighty bronze
                  horses.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-10"/> It contains<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-11"/> 926<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-12"/> baths. It contains 4
                  orbilikon.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-13"/> It contains 14 tinon enkofitoriyon.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n318-14"/> It contains <pb
                     type="page" n="319"/>2 parenamabole<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n319-1"/> of special bronze horses.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n319-2"/>
                  It contains 45 sistre.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n319-3"/> It contains 2300 public oil-warehouses.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n319-4"/>
                  It contains 291 prisons or aspoke.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n319-5"/> It contains in the regions 254 public
                  places<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n319-6"/> or privies. It contains 673 emparkhe,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n319-7"/> who guard the city,
                  and the men who command them all are 7. The gates of the city are 37. Now the
                  circumference of the whole city is 216,036 feet, which is 40 miles; the diameter
                  of the city from east to west is 12 miles, and from north to south 12
                  miles.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n319-8"/></p>
               <p>But God is faithful, who will make its second prosperity greater than its first,
                  because great is the glory of all the might of the dominion of the Romans.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript" n="10.17">
               <p>The eleventh Book, the first three chapters of the twelfth Book, and the beginning
                  of the fourth chapter are missing.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n296-1">537.</note>
            <note xml:id="n296-2">One of these numbers must be erroneous, for the thirteenth year of
               the indiction ends with Aug. 31, 550, while the year 859 of the Seleucids ends with
               Sept. 30, 548. The latter is probably right, as the fall of Rome, with which the Book
               ends, was on Dec. 17, 546.</note>
            <note xml:id="n296-3">537 and 539.</note>
            <note xml:id="n296-4">Text "Lʾgin."</note>
            <note xml:id="n296-5">κάστρα.</note>
            <note xml:id="n296-6">λίμιτον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n297-1">546 and 547.</note>
            <note xml:id="n297-2">The words <!--  Add Syriac  --> and <!--  Add Syriac  --> seem to
               have been transposed, the text reading "book 1, chapter 10."</note>
            <note xml:id="n297-3">Mich. fol. 173 v.</note>
            <note xml:id="n297-4">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not<!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n297-5">536.</note>
            <note xml:id="n297-6">In this chapter the MS. is very much torn and obliterated. The
               words in brackets are conjectural supplements.</note>
            <note xml:id="n298-1">This supplement is made probable by the account in Elijah's life
               of John of Constantia (ed. Kleyn, p. 47).</note>
            <note xml:id="n298-2">536-7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n298-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n298-4">λίμιτον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n298-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n298-6">ἀξίας.</note>
            <note xml:id="n298-7">The MS. is here very indistinct, and, as Land's text is very
               incomplete, I give the text which I follow, conjectural supplements being enclosed in
               square brackets: <!--  Add Syriac  --></note>
            <note xml:id="n299-1">537-8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n299-2">540.</note>
            <note xml:id="n299-3">537-8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n299-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n299-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n299-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n299-7"><!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n299-8">537. A year ending with — καιδέκατον can hardly in this place be
               other than fifteen.</note>
            <note xml:id="n299-9"><!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n299-10"><!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n299-11">Or possibly Kut…</note>
            <note xml:id="n299-12">ἀνταρσία</note>
            <note xml:id="n300-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n300-2">Mich.: "he suffocated his archdeacon"; but I cannot get this from
               the letters remaining in our text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n300-3">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n300-4">συνοδικός.</note>
            <note xml:id="n300-5">Only <!--  Add Syriac  --> is visible. Read
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n300-6">I.e. son of a cobbler.</note>
            <note xml:id="n300-7">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n300-8">χιλίαρχος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n300-9">Here the MS. breaks off. The words in brackets I supply from the
               headings in the introduction to this Book. The whole of this chapter and the
               following are missing.</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-1">This letter is also published by Overbeck in his edition of
               Ephraim (p. 231 ff.) from our MS. The beginning of it is quoted by Assemani (B. O.
               vol. i. p. 409), as from John of Ephesus ap. "Dion." This extract bears no indication
               that it is part of a letter, and varies considerably from our author.</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-2">Jo. Eph. ap. "Dion." (Assem., B. O. i. p. 409); Mich. fol. 179
               ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Jo.
               Eph.</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-4">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-5">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich.
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> (so Overbeck), not
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-7">Only <!--  Add Syriac  --> is visible. Read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.
               Mich. <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-8">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-9">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich.
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n302-1">Instead of <!--  Add Syriac  -->, Jo. Eph. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "for a long time." Our text is supported by Mich.
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n302-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Jo.
               Eph.; so Mich. <!--  Add Syriac  -->. If the MS. reading be retained, the meaning is
               "cleanse."</note>
            <note xml:id="n302-3"> Instead of <!--  Add Syriac  -->, Jo. Eph. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "eaten." Mich, omits the clause.</note>
            <note xml:id="n302-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Jo.
               Eph.; so Mich. <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n302-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> (Hamilton).
               Mich. <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n302-6">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n302-7">We rather require "to state.''</note>
            <note xml:id="n303-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, "easily." This word occurs three times in
               this chapter with reference to eating, and it is difficult to see the meaning of it.
               Mich, has here <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "sufficiently," and perhaps, therefore, read
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->; in the other places he omits it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n303-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  -->. So Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n303-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich.
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n304-1">Mich, "his body.</note>
            <note xml:id="n304-2"> John vi. 54, 56.</note>
            <note xml:id="n304-3">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  -->; so Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n304-4">Heb. x. 28, 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n304-5">Insert <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n304-6">John vi. 52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n304-7">Mich. "Son of God."</note>
            <note xml:id="n305-1">A comparison with Mich, shows that at this point a leaf has been
               lost in our MS., which I supply from Mich. An extract from this portion is also
               contained in Add. MS. 14,532, fol. 67, from which it has been edited by Overbeck (op.
               cit. p. 230). The translation of the part which exists only in Arabic I submit with
               great diffidence, having but a very superficial knowledge of that language.</note>
            <note xml:id="n305-2">Here the extract in 14,532 begins.</note>
            <note xml:id="n305-3">Mich, has "its life," and therefore read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n305-4">Mich. "the body."</note>
            <note xml:id="n305-5">Here the extract in 14,532 ends.</note>
            <note xml:id="n305-6">1 Cor. xi. 28, 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n306-1">1 Cor. ii. 30-32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n306-2">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->; cf. Isa. vi. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->(<!--  Add Syriac  -->)). Neither the reading
               nor the translation is clear.</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-2">Sir. xxix. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-3">Arabic <!--  Add Arabic  -->; but the Syriac must have been
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. See p. 303, note 1. Here the Syriac text
               begins again.</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-5">I insert "beet and" from Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-6">Read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Payne Smith. There seems to be
               some further error in this sentence, but the sense is clear.</note>
            <note xml:id="n308-1">Or "round eggs"; lit. "rounds (σφαῖραι) of eggs."</note>
            <note xml:id="n308-2">Mich, omits "sheep," and adds "instead of water."</note>
            <note xml:id="n308-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "bread," which gives no
               intelligible sense. I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->. So Mich., who, however, has "the
               moisture of the wine and the coolness of the milk."</note>
            <note xml:id="n308-4">1 Sam. ii. 30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n308-5">Mich., apparently reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "thus he says."</note>
            <note xml:id="n309-1">Mich, "listen to."</note>
            <note xml:id="n309-2">Clem. Hom. xii. 5, 6; id. Recog. vii. 5, 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n309-3">Act. Paul. et Thecl. xxiii. (Syriac, Wright, pp. 147, 148;
               translation, pp. 129. 130).</note>
            <note xml:id="n309-4">1 Tim. vi. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n309-5"><!--  Add Syriac  --> is probably corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n309-6">The MS. inserts <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               (so Overbeck), which L. does not print.</note>
            <note xml:id="n309-7">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n309-8">Acts i. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n310-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n310-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n310-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> (so Overbeck), not
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n310-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as Overbeck.
               The MS. has a dot both above and below the letter.</note>
            <note xml:id="n310-5">The word <!--  Add Syriac  --> is accidentally repeated in the
               MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n310-6">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n311-1">Mich. fol. 173 v.</note>
            <note xml:id="n311-2">537-8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n311-3">ἐγκαίνια.</note>
            <note xml:id="n311-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n311-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n311-6">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n311-7">Isa. x. 5, 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n311-8">540.</note>
            <note xml:id="n311-9">There follow in the MS. the words <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "the
               sixth chapter,"</note>
            <note xml:id="n312-1">The order and contents of these passages agree so well with the
               headings at the beginning of this Book, that I make no doubt that they are taken from
               our author. In general I follow Michael, whose account is the longest.</note>
            <note xml:id="n312-2">538-9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n312-3">Or January, it not being stated whether it was the 1st or the 2nd
               Khonun. The month is only in Jac. Edess.</note>
            <note xml:id="n312-4">"In the sky " is only in Jac. Edess.</note>
            <note xml:id="n312-5">So Jac. Edess. Mich, has "several days."</note>
            <note xml:id="n312-6">"The southern part " is only in Jac. Edess.</note>
            <note xml:id="n312-7">Mich, and Greg, afterwards relate the capture of Antioch and
               Callinicus over again. As this second account occurs in similar words in "Dionysius "
               (Cod. Syr. Vat. 162, fol. 71), who writes out John of Ephesus, and is absent in Jac.
               Edess., it is almost certainly derived from John, a fact which strongly confirms the
               previous conclusion that the account in the text is derived from our author.</note>
            <note xml:id="n312-8">Greg. (p. 80) also quotes a passage relating to the plague as from
               Zachariah; but only the last sentence of this is identical with Mich.'s quotation,
               the rest being identical with a passage quoted by Mich. from Jo. Eph. It is clear,
               therefore, that either Gregory has erred or his text is corrupted.</note>
            <note xml:id="n313-1">Ezek. vii. 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n313-2">This passage is written in the margin of 9. 13 in Cod. Rom., where
               it is printed by Mai (p. 358) as part of the text (see p. 242, note 1).</note>
            <note xml:id="n313-3">Greg. "Libya."</note>
            <note xml:id="n313-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. If Byzantium is meant, the spelling is
               strange. Moreover, the Syrians always call it ""Constantinople, or "the royal city."
               Greg. omits.</note>
            <note xml:id="n313-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, "ate" ; perhaps we should read
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "took."</note>
            <note xml:id="n313-6">I take <!--  Add Syriac  --> to be an error for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n313-7">The close correspondence of this account of the expedition against
               Edessa with the heading of ch. 9 seems to show that it is derived from our author.
               Jac. Edess., indeed, inserts the capture of Petra between the Armenian campaign and
               the expedition to Edessa, but only by a slip, for the following sentence, "and from
               that time the Romans were attacking it" etc. (see ch. 13), must refer to Petra, not
               to Edessa, as is proved by the sense and by a comparison with Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n313-8">In Jac. Edess. only.</note>
            <note xml:id="n314-1">"And made an attack" is in Jac. Edess. only.</note>
            <note xml:id="n314-2">That this passage is derived from our author is shown by the use
               of the indictional years, which is not found in Jo. Eph. Moreover, according to our
               author's own peculiar fashion the numerals are given in Greek.</note>
            <note xml:id="n314-3">"Of Singara" is added by Greg.</note>
            <note xml:id="n314-4">538-545.</note>
            <note xml:id="n314-5">This sentence (not in Greg.) is extremely obscure and probably
               corrupt. The real meaning seems to be that many Monophysites had been carried off by
               the Persians.</note>
            <note xml:id="n314-6">Greg. adds "a simple man."</note>
            <note xml:id="n314-7">In Mich, this clause is applied to Theodore, but is followed by
               the words "This is my lord James Burdʾʿoyo," which seem to be a gloss intended to
               point out that they really belong to James. After this Greg, inserts "and they
               ordained him œcumenical metropolitan."</note>
            <note xml:id="n314-8">Mich. "Active in his journeying, and travelled like a
               courier."</note>
            <note xml:id="n314-9">Greg, adds, "and he began to go round the countries of the East
               and to give ordination to the orthodox, showing himself in the dress of a beggar, and
               chiefly on the roads from fear of the persecution."</note>
            <note xml:id="n315-1">That this passage comes from our author appears from the
               juxtaposition of these two events, the campaign in Lazica and the famine, as in the
               headings above, and from the use of the indictional reckoning with the numeral in
               Greek; see note below.</note>
            <note xml:id="n315-2">So Mich. Jac. Edess. has "took."</note>
            <note xml:id="n315-3">Here Jac. Edess. interpolates the attack on Edessa (see ch. 11,
               note).</note>
            <note xml:id="n315-4">546. The translator of Mich., who alone records the date, has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "in the district of Hanata"; but no such place is known, and I
               have no doubt that it is a misunderstanding of ἔνατον, which our author
               transliterates as <!--  Add Syriac  --> at p. 249, l. 7, 12; p. 258, l. 9, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n316-1">The heading and the latter portion of the chapter are in Cod. Rom.
               The first paragraph, which seems to be derived from the same source, I supply from
               Mich. and Greg. (pp. 80, Si). A portion of the Syriac Michael containing this
               paragraph and the description of Rome in the next chapter has been edited by Prof.
               Guidi (Bull. della Commiss. Arch. di Roma, xix. p. 61 ff.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n316-2">546. This was the twentieth of Justinian, and the fact that the
               same misreckoning is found twice in 12. 4 and once in 12. 5 tends to show that this
               sentence is derived from our author.</note>
            <note xml:id="n316-3">Mich. "the Romans."</note>
            <note xml:id="n316-4">κάστρα.</note>
            <note xml:id="n316-5">Mich, adds, "of its people. And that you may know what loss to the
               empire of the Romans was wrought at its capture, behold! I will write out an account,
               though only in a summary, composed by one that knew and saw its buildings."</note>
            <note xml:id="n316-6">Mich. fol. 185 r.</note>
            <note xml:id="n316-7">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               Mai prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n317-1"><!--  Add Syriac  --> is probably an error for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "decoration,'' as in Cod. Rom. and in the introduction to this
               book.</note>
            <note xml:id="n317-2">This is the heading in 12,154 (see p. 311). Cod. Rom. has "a
               description of the decoration of Rome." The chapter has been edited with an
               introduction, notes, and translation by Prof. Guidi (Bull. della Commiss. Arch, ai
               Roma, xii. p. 218 ff.; cf. xix. p. 61 ff.), from whose work I have derived much
               assistance.</note>
            <note xml:id="n317-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n317-4"><!--  Add Syriac  --> = περίστυλα (Guidi), or possibly προστάδες,
               vestibules.</note>
            <note xml:id="n317-5">Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n317-6">Mich. (ed. Guidi); Notitia ap. Jordan Top. der Stadt Rom, 2.
               571.</note>
            <note xml:id="n317-7">The word <!--  Add Syriac  -->, "great," has been corrected to
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> in the margin of the MS., though Mai prints both (Guidi, p.
               227).</note>
            <note xml:id="n317-8"><!--  Add Syriac  --> = κάναλος. Notit. “lacos.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-1">βάσεις. Notit. “arci marmorei XXXVI.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-2">Before <!--  Add Syriac  --> Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               which Mai does not print. It is correctly given by Guidi.</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-3">Mich. “And took the bronze gates and other objects.</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-5">A misunderstanding of “columnæ coclides.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-6">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as Mai
               prints. 12,154 has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, “3,” and so Mich. Notit. “theatra
               III.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-7">12,154, <!--  Add Syriac  --> = κυνήγια. Cod. Rom.
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> (Mich. <!--  Add Syriac  -->), which Guidi takes to be a
               corruption of <!--  Add Syriac  --> = θεώρια. Notit. “amphitheatra II.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-8"><!--  Add Syriac  --> = λοῦδοι (Guidi). Notit. “ludi IIII.” Mich.
               Arab. adds <!--  Add Syriac  -->, “granaries.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-9">νυμφεῖα (Guidi). Notit. “nymfea XV” (MS. B “XI). Mich. Syr.
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> (Ὁλύμπια), Arab. <!--  Add Arabic  -->, “places of
               amusement.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-10">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, “feeble,” not
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, “bronze,” as Mai; but we must read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and
               so Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-11">The words <!--  Add Syriac  -->, omitted by Mai, are in the MS.
               So Guidi.</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-12">Mich. Syr. 56, Arab. “956,” and so MS. B of Notitia: cet.
               “856.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-13"><!--  Add Syriac  --> = κούρτης βιγίλων (Guidi). Notit. “Cohortes
               vigilum VII.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n318-14"><!--  Add Syriac  --> (Mich. Syr. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, Arab.
               <!--  Add Arabic  -->) = Notit. “quorum excubitoria XIII,” “quorum” having been
               translated ὦντινων, and ὦν omitted by the Syrian (Guidi).</note>
            <note xml:id="n319-1"><!--  Add Syriac  --> (Mich. <!--  Add Syriac  -->) = παρεμβολαί.
               Notit. "castra" (Guidi).</note>
            <note xml:id="n319-2">A mistranslation of "equitum singularium" (Guidi).</note>
            <note xml:id="n319-3">μαστρυλλεῖα (Guidi). Notit. "lupanaria XLV." MS. "46." Read "45"
               with Mich.</note>
            <note xml:id="n319-4">ἀποθηκάρια.</note>
            <note xml:id="n319-5">Notit. "horrea CCXC" (MS. B "CCXCI"), so that
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> is probably a corruption of <!--  Add Syriac  --> (Duval in
               Guidi); but, as Mich, also has "prisons," the corruption may have existed in our
               author's original text, and I therefore do not emend. <!--  Add Syriac  --> Guidi
               takes to be a corruption of "ἀποθῆκαι."</note>
            <note xml:id="n319-6">This word (δημόσια) generally means "public baths"; but the
               translation in the text accords with Notit. "latrinæ publicæ" (the Curiosum printed
               opposite adds "quod est sicessos") "CCXLIIII."</note>
            <note xml:id="n319-7">ἔπαρχοι (Guidi). Mich. Arab. <!--  Add Arabic  -->, "custodians";
               Notit. "vicomagistri DCLXXII" (MS. B DCLXXIII).</note>
            <note xml:id="n319-8">Here 12,154 adds, "These are exclusive of many things which we
               have not set down here. And these things the author set down while weeping for the
               city, because in his time the barbarians entered it and sacked it." This MS. omits
               the sentences containing corrupt or difficult words, as well as the introductory and
               concluding sentences. Mich. (Arab. fol. 185 r) has, in place of the concluding
               sentence, "Verily for the sack of this great city, which was completely burnt at this
               time by a barbarian people, Justinian the king sorrowed exceedingly, and all the
               magnates of the kingdom clothed themselves in mourning. And in those days the king's
               sorrow was increased by the death of the queen, the blessed Theodora, who departed in
               the twentieth year of the reign of Justinian, which is the year eight hundred and
               fifty-nine of the Greeks, and he gave a large quantity of gold on behalf of her
               soul." Greg. (p. 81) has the same in a shorter form.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
