<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb type="page" n="18"/>
         <div type="book" n="2">
            <head>Book 2</head>
            <div type="chapter" n="2.1">
               <head>The Beginning of the Second Book</head>
               <p>After the Ecclesiastical History of <persName>Eusebius</persName> of <placeName>Cæsarea</placeName>, both <persName>Socrates</persName> and
                  <persName>Theodoret</persName>, in the treatises which they successively composed, reaching down to the
                  thirty-second year of the reign of <placeName>Theodosius</placeName> the Less, wrote for the memory and
                  profit of the prudent, as best they were able, accounts of the transactions and
                  matters that occurred in various places, which they were diligent in learning from
                  the volumes, and letters, and records,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18-1"/> and words of living speakers, that
                  they examined.</p>
               <p>And accordingly I also, insignificant though I be, am beginning to write, as you
                  asked me, for the instruction of the brethren, and for the gratification of the
                  lovers of doctrine, and for the confirmation of believers, <persName>Christ</persName> our Lord and God
                  consenting and aiding and giving the word of power — by your great advice,
                  diligent brother, and while you pray that I may write the truth with eloquence
                  without confusion or cause for blame.</p>
               <p>For when, making a commencement of this treatise of the second Book, I am
                  relating, as concisely as possible, without prolonging the discourse or being
                  wearisome to the reader or tedious to the hearer, what I was able<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18-2"/> to
                  discover from records and Acts<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18-3"/> or from letters, — truth that was carefully
                  examined, — I shall set down here the truth of the resurrection, which took place
                  in the days of <persName>Theodosius</persName> the king, of the bodies of the seven youths who were in
                  a cave in the district <pb type="page" n="19"/>of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, and the Syriac records;
                  both to keep them in the memory of the saints and for the glory of God, Who is
                  able to do all things.</p>
               <p>And then I shall set down briefly in the form of chapters, so that the account may
                  not be enlarged of the events of one period which we write in detail in the Acts
                  that are found in every place, what happened during the ten remaining years of the
                  life of <persName>Theodosius</persName>, but in this Book I am writing them so to speak — what happened
                  in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> respecting <persName>Eutyches</persName> the archimandrite and <persName>Flavian</persName> the chief
                  priest, and the Synod of thirty-one bishops and twenty-two archimandrites who met
                  together and who brought about the deprivation of <persName>Eutyches</persName>; and also respecting
                  the second Synod which was held in <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> concerning <persName>Flavian</persName> in the days of
                  <persName>Dioscorus</persName> and <persName>Juvenalis</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19-1"/> and <persName>Domnus</persName>, and the one hundred and twenty- eight
                  bishops who were with them.</p>
               <p>And then I begin with the third Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="2.2">
               <head>The Second Chapter Tells about the Heresy of <persName>Eutyches</persName> the Presbyter, and his
                  Deprivation</head>
               <p>There was, in the days of king <persName>Theodosius</persName>, one <persName>Eutyches</persName>, a presbyter and
                  archimandrite, a recluse belonging to those who dwell in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. This man
                  was visited by many (who resorted to him ostensibly on account of his chastity and
                  piety) who happened to be in the city, and especially by the soldiers of the
                  palace, who were lovers of doctrine. For at that time Nestorius, who was ejected,
                  was being justly reviled because of his filthy doctrine. This Nestorius it was who
                  held and taught base opinions respecting the Incarnation of God the Word; and he
                  imagined that the two Natures existed separately in <persName>Christ</persName> our God after the
                  union; and he held the precedence of the infant who was conceived and formed in
                  the Virgin, whom he also called [n19-1]<!--  Add Syriac  --> on . MS., an evident
                  mistake for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. <pb type="page" n="20"/><persName>Jesus</persName> and <persName>Christ</persName>; and
                  he thought that God the Word at length descended upon Him, views scarcely
                  differing from those of <persName>Paul</persName> of <placeName>Samosata</placeName>, and much the same as the teaching of the
                  school of <persName>Diodorus</persName>, which he studied, accepted, and loved; but he lightly and
                  without compunction refused to call the ever-virgin, holy <persName>Mary</persName>, by the title 
                  <quote>Theotokos,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-1"/> even though the true doctors who were before him, <persName>Athanasius</persName>
                  and <persName>Gregory</persName> and <persName>Basil</persName> and <persName>Julius</persName>, and the others, had so called her; and,
                  moreover, he also censured them, as the letter testifies which he wrote from <placeName>Oasis</placeName>
                  to the clergy and citizens. Whereupon, many being disturbed by his doctrine, a
                  Synod, consisting of one hundred and ninety-three bishops, was assembled at
                  <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>; and it carefully examined his teaching; and it called upon him three
                  times, according to the canonical rule of the Church, to apologise and to censure
                  his own interpretations, and at length to confess <persName>Jesus</persName> to be God the Word Who
                  became incarnate, one Person and one Nature, as the doctors of the holy Church
                  teach. But he would not consent, as also <persName>Socrates</persName> relates in the short account
                  which he wrote of him, and which is fully told in the original Acts.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-2"/>
                  Consequently his deprivation took place in the days of <persName>Celestine</persName>, <persName>Cyril</persName>, and
                  <persName>Juvenalis</persName>, before the arrival of <persName>John</persName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> and his attendant bishops, who
                  were delayed.</p>
               <p>It<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-3"/> was somewhere about this time that <persName>Eutyches</persName>, wishing to affirm the one
                  Nature in <persName>Christ</persName>, rejected the truth of the body derived from the Virgin, which
                  God the Word took in her and from her. And in the conversation which he held with
                  those who came together to him, this same <persName>Eutyches</persName> affirmed an inaccurate
                  dogma,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-4"/> not having been well instructed.</p>
               <p>But he taught many that (the Word became flesh)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-5"/> as <pb type="page" n="21"
                  />the atmosphere assumes bodily form and becomes rain or snow under the influence
                  of the wind, or as water by reason of the cold air becomes ice.</p>
               <p>And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-1"/> when the report of his vile teaching was published abroad it was
                  investigated by <persName>Eusebius</persName> of <placeName>Dorylaeum</placeName>, who happened to be in the city; and he
                  informed <persName>Flavian</persName>, the chief priest, concerning it, and he gave him an
                  indictment.</p>
               <p>And he was called upon three times by thirty-one bishops who were there and
                  twenty-two archimandrites, to come forward and apologise for his opinions, and
                  abjure them, and make a written statement of the true confession. And at first,
                  indeed, he would not do so, at one time saying that it was<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-2"/> his fixed
                  determination<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-3"/> to remain in perpetual seclusion, and again, that he was
                  sick, and had a cough, and was old; (and he made these excuses relying upon the
                  aid of the soldiers of the palace, who were his friends. Now the king heard of
                  these matters. But at last, when his deprivation was decreed to take place, he was
                  compelled to appear before the council of bishops; however, he did not recant his
                  doctrine with whole-hearted sincerity, but kept on saying, <quote>Just as you teach two
                  Natures in <persName>Christ</persName>, so do I say.</quote></p>
               <p>And, behold! all these things are written expressly, one after another, in
                  lengthened discourse in the Acts of that Council. However, that we may not make
                  our narrative too long, but may compress much into small compass, as the wise man
                  says,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-4"/> we refrain from relating them again in detail and writing them down
                  here. Then his deprivation took place. Now in the accusations against him and in
                  the interlocutions,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-5"/> and more especially in what was said by <persName>Eusebius</persName> of
                  Dorylæum when contending with him, the two Natures after the union were expressly
                  taught in conformity with the doctrine of Nestorius.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-6"/> And the interlocution
                  of <persName>Flavian</persName> set forth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-7"/> the same views. And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-8"/> <persName>Eutyches</persName>, rejecting the
                  party of <persName>Flavian</persName> <pb type="page" n="22"/>and <persName>Eusebius</persName>, who deposed him, sent a
                  libel<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-1"/> to <placeName>Rome</placeName> to <persName>Leo</persName>, who was the chief priest there, begging that these
                  matters should be investigated in another Synod; with regard to which libel he
                  received a reply. And when the party of <persName>Flavian</persName> heard it they also wrote,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-2"/>
                  and sent the Acts of the Council concerning <persName>Eutyches</persName> to <persName>Leo</persName>. And the latter wrote
                  to <persName>Flavian</persName> the letter called the <persName>Tome</persName>, in which there are many heads that have  <!-- is the tome a personal name? -->
                  been condemned by the dogmatic<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-3"/> doctors; which also were censured at that
                  time by <persName>Dioscorus</persName> and his followers, and again by <persName>Timothy</persName> the Great, who was with
                  him, and by many treatises of others, which we omit to mention again here and to
                  write down.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="2.3">
               <head>The<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-4"/> Third Chapter Gives an Account in Concise Terms of the Second Synod
                  which was Held in <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, about the Matter of <persName>Flavian</persName> the Chief Priest and
                  <persName>Eutyches</persName> the Monk</head>
               <p>Accordingly a Synod was convened, the second in <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, about the matter of
                  <persName>Flavian</persName> and <persName>Eutyches</persName>; and it was held in the presence of the legates of <persName>Leo</persName>, who
                  were sent with his letter. And the bishops came together there to the number of
                  one hundred and eighty-eight, the chief rulers among them being <persName>Dioscorus</persName> of
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and <persName>Juvenalis</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, and <persName>Domnus</persName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. And the contents of
                  the Acts of the Constantinopolitan Council concerning <persName>Eutyches</persName> were
                  examined;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-5"/> and <persName>Flavian</persName> and <persName>Eusebius</persName> were ejected. And an outcry was raised
                  by the bishops who were there; and they anathematised every one who would say,
                  <quote>There are two <pb type="page" n="23"/>Natures in Christ after the union.</quote> But a
                  question<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23-1"/> was also raised again there about what <persName>Theodoret</persName> of <placeName>Cyrrhus</placeName> wrote
                  censuring the twelve Heads which <persName>Cyril</persName> drew up against <persName>Nestorius</persName>, who was
                  previously banished; and about the letter of <persName>Hibo</persName> of <placeName>Edessa</placeName> which he wrote to
                  <persName>Moris</persName> of <placeName>Nisibis</placeName> in opposition to <persName>Cyril</persName> and in favour of <persName>Nestorius</persName>; and about what
                  he said in his interpretations concerning <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> and <persName>Mary</persName>, as his own
                  deacons, who were his accusers, testified. And besides these the partisans of <persName>John</persName>
                  of <placeName>Gaios</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23-2"/> and others were deposed. But <persName>Eutyches</persName> the archimandrite was
                  received, because he presented a libel of recantation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23-3"/> to the Synod, which
                  was held there in <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, and confessed the true faith. But the Synod appointed
                  <persName>Anatolius</persName> as bishop of Constantinople in the room of <persName>Flavian</persName>, and then
                  dispersed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="2.4">
               <head>The Fourth Chapter Discusses the Regular Succession<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23-4"/> of the Chief
                  Priests who Held Office From the First Synod of <persName>Ephesus</persName> to the Death of King
                  <persName>Theodosius</persName>, in the Days of <persName>Valentinus</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23-5"/> who was Succeeded by <persName>Marcian</persName>, the
                  Convener of the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon in Bithynia</placeName>, which Met in the Year Seven <!-- include both as place name or separate them?-->
                  Hundred and Sixty-four of the Greek Era of <persName>Alexander</persName></head>
               <p>With respect to the regular succession of the chief priests from the first Synod
                  of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> to the death of <persName>Theodosius</persName>, it is pertinent to our subject to relate
                  who they were. In <pb type="page" n="24"/><placeName>Rome</placeName>, after <persName>Celestine</persName>, <persName>Leo</persName> was bishop
                  for twenty-one years and forty-three days; and in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, after <persName>Cyril</persName>,
                  <persName>Dioscorus</persName> was bishop for eight years and three months. And in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>,
                  <persName>Maximus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-1"/> for two years and two months; and after him, <persName>Proclus</persName> for two years
                  and two months; and after him, <persName>Flavian</persName> for six years; and after him, <persName>Anatolius</persName> for
                  eight years. In <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, <persName>Domnus</persName> was bishop after <persName>John</persName>; and after him <persName>Maximus</persName>. And
                  in <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, <persName>Juvenalis</persName> was bishop for thirty-six years, who, holding the same
                  position, was present at the three Synods, because the time of his years was
                  protracted. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="2.5"> 
               <head>The Fifth Chapter Contains the Letter of <persName>Proclus</persName>, Chief Priest of
                  <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, to the Armenians. It is a Very Excellent Letter, Showing the Faith
                  of the Man; and to Preserve it in Memory we have Transcribed it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-2"/> here for
                  the Benefit of Believing Brothers</head>
               <head>The Letter of <persName>Proclus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-3"/></head>
               <p><quote>Beloved, the mystery of the true faith is true love, and the pure undoubting
                  confession of the Trinity equal, undivided, and susceptible of no addition; and a
                  mind not varying in its state, but steadfast in its faith towards God. That is the
                  faith which we do not possess on tables of stone, as in the type, but receive on
                  the tables of our hearts, as in a mystery; tables (I say) which are nailed to the
                  cross, and are inscribed with the sprinkling of the blood of God. And it is right
                  for us not only to believe, but also to follow earnestly after virtues and morals
                  worthy of the faith.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-4"/> For virtue is to be chosen by everyone, especially by
                  those whose beauty of soul has not been corrupted by a hateful life of lusts.
                  There are indeed <pb type="page" n="25"/>many kinds of virtue. For even the
                  heathen, drowned in error and lost in mind, wrote memorable things<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-1"/>
                  concerning this virtue. But as for this nature which is visible and flows on
                  without cessation, they only felt<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-2"/> after it in their written teaching. But
                  either their sight was dim from length of time, or they were blinded by error, so
                  as to hinder them from the perception of the truth and from real virtue. For they
                  say in their teaching that there are four kinds of virtue, namely, justice,
                  self-restraint, wisdom, and fortitude; which things, though they are to be highly
                  accounted, yet are exercised here below and have their sphere upon the earth. They
                  say, indeed, that fortitude is the contest with fierce nature, and self-restraint
                  the triumph over the passions, and wisdom the distinguished government of
                  cities,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-3"/> and justice right division. And thus they ordered and arranged the
                  world, according to that which is in the law,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-4"/> and they defined wickedness
                  on both sides. However, anything superior to and transcending this visible scene
                  they did not understand, nor were they able to describe it in writing. But with
                  the blindness of their mind they have contracted virtue itself, and have
                  shut<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-5"/> it up within what is visible alone. The Christians, however, by whose
                  own faith the eyes of their heart have been enlightened, whose master and teacher
                  is the blessed <persName>Paul</persName>, have declared that to be<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-6"/> virtue which lifts us up to
                  God, and which governs in orderly fashion the things that are on earth. This most
                  illustrious <persName>Paul</persName>, then, considered that there were many kinds of virtue; but he
                  especially preached about these three, namely, faith, hope, and love. For faith
                  gives to men something which transcends human nature, and causes that fleshly
                  nature, as yet encompassed by many passions, to hold converse with spiritual
                  beings. <pb type="page" n="26"/>For the knowledge of that which angels and
                  spiritual hosts did not know on account of its sublimity, faith imparts to men,
                  who walk upon the earth and wallow in the dust, and it brings them near to the
                  Throne of the Kingdom, and it tells them of that Nature which is without beginning
                  and without end; and by the rays of light which it diffuses, it drives away
                  darkness of thought<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n26-1"/> from the soul; and when it has cleared off all gloom
                  and denseness from the heart, then it causes that to be clearly seen which is
                  comprehended in its invisibility, and also is seen in its incomprehensibility. But
                  hope shows things to come in the present, not as in a dream, one can say, but
                  forcibly; and, without a doubt, confirms in the mind that which is future as if it
                  were actually seen; and it forms before a man's eyes, so to speak, what he is
                  still expecting. For this hope is superior to every restraint, and brings near,
                  without delay, the thing expected to him who is expecting it.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>But love is the chief of all our mysteries, for it persuaded God the Word, though
                  He is always on the earth, near to all and with all (heaven and earth being filled
                  by Him), to become incarnate and come by means of the flesh. And, being God, He
                  became also man; He retained that which properly belonged to Himself on His own
                  part, and He became like us on our part. These two then agree together, for faith
                  is the mirror of love, and love is the completion of faith. We believe, therefore,
                  that God the Word became incarnate without undergoing any change; and we rightly
                  so believe, for this is the foundation of our salvation. For His nature receives
                  no change, nor does it cause any addition to the Trinity. Thus indeed do we also
                  ourselves believe.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>Every Christian, therefore, who is not rich in faith, hope, and love, is not what
                  he is named; but even though he seem to have subdued his flesh and to have
                  delivered himself from the passions of his soul, he is not meet for the crown of
                  victory, inasmuch as he maintains the outward appearance<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n26-2"/> of virtue, but he
                  is not united to Him who crowns the conquerors that have resolutely contended on
                  behalf of virtue in faith and <pb type="page" n="27"/>hope and love. Faith, then,
                  according to what we have said,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-1"/> is the chief of all blessings; let it
                  therefore be kept without guile, and let us not tarnish it by the falsehood of
                  human thoughts, neither let us toss it about in the midst of confusing voices, nor
                  by the explanations of those who are reputed to be wise: for faith is not to be
                  explained; faith is a mystery. Let it then remain within the limits of the Gospel
                  of the apostles; and let no man dare to contend in his explanation with this faith
                  by which he is saved, and which he confessed in baptism by the signature of his
                  tongue. For this lofty height of faith has repelled every attack and all vaunting
                  and rashness, not of man only, but also of every spiritual nature. And the blessed
                  <persName>Paul</persName> testifies, crying out, <quote>If we or an angel from heaven should preach anything
                  beside what ye have received, let him be accursed.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-2"/> For the angel has been
                  appointed to minister and not to preach doctrine, and he brings punishment<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-3"/>
                  upon any who does not remain<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-4"/> in his allotted station, but seeks after what
                  is too high for his nature; but even though<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-5"/> he displays the exaltation of
                  his nature, let not the novelty of his preaching be received. Let us then guard
                  what we have received with sleepless care; and by the bright shining of our faith
                  let the eye of our soul be always open. But what have we received<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-6"/> from the
                  Divine Scriptures except this, that God by His word created the world out of
                  nothing and brought the creation, which had no previous existence, into being; and
                  made man in His own image and likeness, and honoured him by the law of nature; and
                  gave him the commandment when he was in a state of freedom; and showed him how to
                  help himself,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-7"/> that by the choice of the good he should flee from the evil;
                  and the propensity of man being biassed towards the evil expelled disobedience <pb
                     type="page" n="28"/>from Paradise? And again, by the fathers and patriarchs,
                  and by the Law, the judges, and the prophets, our Creator instructed our nature,
                  that we should keep far away from sin, and should concern ourselves about the good
                  and do it. And at last when sin established its kingdom over us by our own will,
                  because the law of nature had been corrupted on its part,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-1"/> and the written
                  law had been despised, and the prophets, after the manner of men, brought deeds to
                  remembrance but did not raise up our fleshly humanity from the depth of the evils,
                  God the Word Himself, even He who is without beginning and without end,
                  incomprehensible, invisible, and almighty, God the Word (I say) came and became
                  incarnate; for He could be whatsoever He willed. God the Word then, Who is one of
                  the Trinity, became incarnate; but He became incarnate because He so willed. And
                  wishing to show<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-2"/> everywhere that He was really man, He was born from the
                  Virgin. For the evangelist did not say that He entered into a perfect man, but
                  that He <quote>became flesh,</quote> meaning thereby His natural beginning and referring to the
                  origin of His birth. For just as a man who is naturally born does not come forth
                  complete in the perfection of active power all at once, but the seed of the nature
                  at first becomes a body, and afterwards, little by little, at length attains the
                  strength of the passions and of the whole active power; so God the Word went to
                  meet the origin and root of the birth. God the Word then became perfect man, and
                  He did not take away anything from His own unchangeable nature by the miracle
                  which He wrought — a miracle which did not enter into the heart of man to
                  conceive, but which we learn by faith and have not comprehended by investigation.
                  And having become man. He saved by His flesh the whole human race, and He paid the
                  debt of sin, in that He died as man for all men; but as God the hater of evil. He
                  destroyed him that had the evil power of death, that is, <persName>Satan</persName>. But He showed the
                  capability of the Law by fulfilling all righteousness. And He gave to our nature
                  its pristine beauty; and by becoming man He honoured the nature <pb type="page"
                     n="29"/>which was derived from the earth, and showed Himself to be its Creator.
                  There is therefore one Son, for we worship the Trinity in unity, and we do not
                  introduce a fourth into this number; but there is one Son, begotten from the
                  Father, without beginning and without end, through whom we believe that the worlds
                  were made, He Who was from that root. He Who without flux sprang from the Father;
                  that same God the Word Who, without change of place, issues from the Father; yet
                  remaining as He is. For although <ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29-1"/> He became man and appeared on the <placeName>earth</placeName>,
                  yet He did not depart from Him who begat Him.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>God the Word therefore wished to save the being whom He created; and He dwelt in
                  the womb which is the gate of the universal nature of all, and He revived and
                  blessed the womb, and by issuing forth from it He sealed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29-2"/> it. And by His
                  supernatural birth He showed that He became incarnate in a manner transcending
                  reason; for there are none among the beings above and beneath who know how He
                  became incarnate. There is not, then, one who is <persName>Christ</persName> and another who is God the
                  Word (away with such a thought!), for the divine nature does not know two sons; He
                  therefore was begotten the only One from One; for where there is not copulation of
                  parents, there duality of the offspring is not possible. <quote>In the name of <persName>Jesus
                  Christ</persName>,</quote> indeed, <quote>every knee shall bow, of things in heaven and on earth, and of
                  things under the earth.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29-3"/> For if <persName>Christ</persName> is another and not God the Word,
                  then of necessity <persName>Christ</persName> must be mere man; and how can the exalted nature of
                  heavenly beings bow the knee and worship His Name, if He be not God of God? or how
                  shall we receive the voices of prophets, crying, <quote>God appeared upon earth and held
                     converse with men?</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29-4"/> For concerning His Incarnation it is said, <quote>He
                  appeared,</quote> and the expression, <quote>He held converse,</quote> is used concerning His converse
                  which He displayed with men in the end of the ages. For thus He that is exalted in
                  greatness showed His almighty power; and as the universal Ruler to Whom everything
                  is easy. He remained what He was on His own part, and became what He willed for
                  us.</quote></p>
               <pb type="page" n="30"/>
               <p><quote>But if the swaddling clothes, and the lying in the manger, and the growth of the
                  body, and the sleeping<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-1"/> in the ship, and the weariness on the journey, and
                  the occasional hunger, and all those things which happened to Him Who was truly
                  man, be a cause of stumbling to some persons, let them know that if they be in
                  doubt concerning His sufferings, they deny the dispensation; but when they deny
                  the dispensation they do not believe in the Incarnation, but when they do not
                  believe in the Incarnation they lose their own lives. For if from the foundation
                  of the world a man was not born who trod a way of birth like this,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-2"/> let
                  these new Jewish wranglers<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-3"/> show it, and then indeed their troublesome
                  contention<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-4"/> will be disclosed. But if this is the universal beginning of
                  nature, and God the Word truly became man, how then, while confessing with us the
                  dispensation, do they deny the sufferings? Let them therefore choose for
                  themselves one of two things: either let them by denying the sufferings deny also
                  the dispensation and be reckoned among the ungodly; or, if they accept the benefit
                  which is derived from the dispensation, let them not be ashamed of the sufferings.
                  I am amazed indeed at the blindness of their heart, who by a newly invented way
                  have trodden the path that leads to error. For I myself know and have rightly
                  learned from the Holy Scriptures only one Son; and I believe in one nature<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-5"/>
                  of God the Word Who became man, and the same endured the sufferings and wrought
                  the miracles, Who was begotten from His Father before all things, and became
                  incarnate in the end of the ages, and was born from <persName>Mary</persName>, the Theotokos. And we
                  confess that He is God over all, and we introduce no foreign element into the
                  nature of the Deity, for no addition is possible to the Trinity in Unity; but the
                  same Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, by Whom were all things, also endured our sufferings and
                  carried our infirmities, <pb type="page" n="31"/>as the prophet<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-1"/> says; and
                  He, being the same, wrought the miracles and suffered in our stead.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>But perhaps in their contention these new Jews will strive with us, inventing
                  thoughts weaker than a spider's web, and say that if indeed the Trinity be one
                  essence then the Trinity is without suffering; and our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is
                  reckoned in the Trinity, and He is God the Word, therefore He is without
                  suffering; consequently He Who was crucified must be another, and not God the Word
                  Who is without suffering. Truly they who speak in this fashion are weaving the
                  texture of a spider's web, and they who excogitate these new definitions are
                  writing upon water; and <quote>thinking themselves to be wise they have become foolish,
                  and their silly heart is darkened.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-2"/> For the eye, which has been dazzled by
                  the brilliant light of the sun, cannot see clearly; and the mind that is sick
                  cannot receive the sublimity of the faith.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>What then do we say? That, so far as the Godhead is concerned, the Trinity is one
                  essence, and is exalted above all sufferings. And when we say that the Son
                  suffered, we do not mean that He suffered according to Nature, for His Nature is
                  above sufferings. But in confessing that God the Word, one of the Trinity, became
                  incarnate, we give a reason for the understanding of those who in faith ask us why
                  He became incarnate. Because man who was formed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-3"/> in the image of God, and
                  to whom imperial freedom was given, erred in this freedom, and was led by the
                  counsel of the deceiver; and he gave himself up to error, and he became the slave
                  of lustful passions — passions all of which exercise dominion over a composite
                  being — passions whose end is death — passions which none among the created beings
                  is able to destroy. God the Word willed to destroy those passions whose end is
                  death. He willed, indeed, to become incarnate and to be a composite being; that
                  is, a perfect man in all points like us, sin only excepted; because it was not
                  possible for that Nature, which is incorruptible, intangible, and invisible, to
                  receive passions, for all passions are struggles of all composite <pb type="page"
                     n="32"/>beings. For with that exalted Nature of the Godhead, which alone is
                  uplifted high above all things, there is no composition; passion therefore was
                  unable to enter where composition could not be. God the Word then willed to
                  destroy the passions which reign over nature subject to passions (as we said
                  before) whose citadel was death; and He became flesh from the Virgin, in a manner
                  that He, God the Word, knew; and He became man perfectly, being at the same time
                  God over all. For He did not abandon what properly belonged to Him when He became
                  like us; but being God, He became man, for such was His will. He emptied Himself,
                  therefore, by His own will by taking the likeness of a slave, and He became man,
                  and suffered in our stead, by His own will, though His Godhead was not in any
                  respect limited; and thus He saved the whole human race. Wherefore <persName>Gabriel</persName> also,
                  when announcing the might and dominion of Him that should be born, said to <persName>Mary</persName>,
                  <quote>He shall save His people from their sins.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n32-1"/></p>
               <p><quote>But the people are not the people of a man but of God, and a man cannot deliver
                  the world from sins, because he also entered into the world in a state of
                  corruption. But necessarily He is the same; He is not divided into two (away with
                  such a thought!); but being one, by being born from a woman, He shows that He
                  is<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n32-2"/> truly man; but by becoming man without copulation, and preserving His
                  mother's virginity, He declared Himself to be God. The Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>,
                  therefore, Who came into the world and held converse with men, as the Holy
                  Scriptures testify, saved the world. Now, if <persName>Christ</persName> be man, and not God the Word,
                  how did He create everything in the beginning, when He Himself had no existence?
                  For if man was later than the (other) created things, it is evident that this
                  <persName>Christ</persName> also did not bring into being what had existence before Him. How then does
                  <persName>Paul</persName> cry, saying, <quote>There is one Lord <persName>Christ</persName>, through Whom were all
                  things</quote>?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n32-3"/> For if all things were through <persName>Christ</persName>, it is evident that <persName>Christ</persName>
                  is God the Word. The evangelist also testifies, saying, <quote>In the beginning was the
                  Word, and <pb type="page" n="33"/>the Word was with God, and the Word was God. He
                  was in the beginning with God, and all things were by Him.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-1"/> If, therefore,
                  the evangelist cries that all things were by the Word, and Paul, interpreting this
                  expression, says, There is one Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, by Whom were all things, it is
                  evident that <persName>Christ</persName> is God over all. But if the objectors bring forward to us the
                  voices of the Scriptures, in which He is called man, namely, that of Peter, who
                  says, <quote><persName>Jesus</persName> of <placeName>Nazareth</placeName>, a man</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-2"/> and of <persName>Paul</persName>, who says, <quote>By that man in
                  Whom God has ordained that we should believe</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-3"/> and of our Lord Himself,
                  Who says respecting Himself, <quote>Why do ye seek to kill Me, a man?</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-4"/> let them
                  know that either through their dulness they have been hindered from the
                  understanding of Scripture, or through their wickedness they are perverting what
                  is well written,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-5"/> according to their own deceitfulness. For also <persName>Christ</persName> is
                  truly man; but He became man, not having been so before, but only God; for just as
                  He is uncreated God, so also He, the same, is man, truly, personally,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-6"/> and
                  certainly, without change and without any kind<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-7"/> of phantasy. And we do not
                  confess that the body of our Lord is from heaven; indeed we excommunicate everyone
                  who says so; but we confess that it is by the Holy Ghost and the power of the
                  Highest which overshadowed the holy Virgin <persName>Mary</persName>, the Theotokos. But if the Virgin
                  did not bear God, then she who remained undefiled is not deserving of admiration.
                  But if the voices of the prophets foretelling the incomprehensible nature of our
                  mystery, cried out, <quote>Behold a virgin shall conceive, and bear a son, and they
                  shall call His name <persName>Immanuel</persName>, which is, God with us,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-8"/> why <pb type="page"
                     n="34"/>do they take away from the glory of His mother, seeing that He Who was
                  born in lowly fashion is God over all ?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-1"/> But perhaps the objectors will
                  raise this objection, that truly every one who is born is of the same nature as
                  the mother who bore him; if, then, she who bore him was human, it necessarily
                  follows that he who was born was human also. Ye say well, O vain babblers! but
                  then the child is of the same nature as she whom the birth-pangs smite when he who
                  is born comes according to the natural course; however, the naturally-born child
                  is corrupt from the beginning, because copulation precedes corruption. But where
                  this reproach did not even enter the mind, but there was an ineffable miracle, the
                  birth having been supernatural, there He that was born was God. We confess Him to
                  be the same who created the world, and gave the Law, and put the Spirit in the
                  prophets, and in the end of the times for the sake of the life and salvation of
                  men became incarnate and was made man; and He inspired the apostles, and sent them
                  forth for the salvation of people and nations. Let us flee, then, my brothers,
                  from these troubled streams of error; I mean the doctrines that fight against God
                  — namely, from the mad folly of <persName>Arius</persName>, who was dividing the indivisible Trinity;
                  and from the rashness of <persName>Eunomius</persName>, who limited beneath his science the
                  incomprehensible nature; and from the frenzy of <persName>Macedonius</persName>, who would sever from
                  the Godhead the Spirit proceeding not departing;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-2"/> along with all the other
                  heretics lost in their error; but especially from this new doctrine and blasphemy
                  formulated by <persName>Nestorius</persName>, who far surpasses the Jews in his blasphemy. For those
                  former heretics were despising the everlasting Son, Who is from all eternity with
                  the Father, and depriving the root of its fruit; but these teachers of our day by
                  their doctrine are bringing in another in addition to Him Who is from all
                  eternity, Who became man for our salvation, so that they make a plurality of sons
                  in that one and incorruptible Nature which is from one essence. <pb type="page"
                     n="35"/>Let us say, then, with <persName>Paul</persName>, that <persName>Christ</persName> is He Who <quote>made both
                  one</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35-1"/> for of Jews and heathen through baptism, He has created one new man,
                  and by His power He made that one, which, through the exercise of its freedom was
                  divided. Let these impious teachers, then, dread the sentence of judgment if what
                  was divided has been brought into unity, but that one Person Who made both one is,
                  after their manner of reasoning, divided.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>But now we shall leave the multitude of words and come to the concise statement
                  of true doctrine. Whoever desires to know that the alone and only-begotten Son,
                  Who was before the life of <persName>Abraham</persName> — that the same became incarnate in the end of
                  the times, let him ask <persName>Paul</persName>, who thunders with his voice, declaring rightly that
                  He Who was born from the Jews in the flesh is the everlasting God; for, while
                  telling and declaring the contempt of the Jews and the contention of the people
                  with God, and the root which is the Father,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35-2"/> and the seed which is <persName>Christ</persName>
                  our Lord, he says thus, <quote>Whose is the adoption</quote> <ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35-3"/> — for God cried through
                  His prophets, <quote><placeName>Israel</placeName> is My son. My firstborn and My glory</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35-4"/> and indeed
                  they reaped immeasurable glories from the constant miracles and the covenants with
                  <persName>Abraham</persName>, which told of the multitude of the people and the blessings — <quote>and the
                  giving of the law,</quote> — that of <placeName>Mount Sinai</placeName>, which was written by the finger of God,
                  — <quote>and the promises,</quote> — both the land of <placeName>Palestine</placeName> and that in the seed of <persName>Abraham</persName>
                  the nations should be blessed, — <quote>whose are the fathers,</quote> — for in the night of
                  error they arose and as stars of the faith — <quote>from whom <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> appeared in
                  the flesh, Who is God over all.</quote> And he does not say this only and deem it
                  sufficient; for also indeed the beginning of God the Word, Who is without
                  beginning and without end, is not from the time of His birth by <persName>Mary</persName>. Who then is
                  this <persName>Christ</persName>? He Who was begotten of the Father before the worlds in a manner which
                  the mind of created beings cannot comprehend, and in the end of the times took
                  flesh and became <pb type="page" n="36"/>man from the Virgin <persName>Mary</persName>, the Theotokos;
                  He Who was shut up in the womb and in the cave, in a manner which He Himself
                  knows; He Who was laid in the manger; He Who grew in the flesh; He Who came down
                  to the lower parts of the earth, and by His own will endured all the sufferings of
                  men, that He might be believed to be man, and to be no other than the One Who came
                  down; but He Who came down and He Who went up is the same; however, He did not go
                  up first, but came down. For He did not become God by addition (away with such a
                  thought!), but He became man by the dispensation, for the race of men was in need
                  of this. And you shall not hear this from me or from any other, but from <persName>Peter</persName> and
                  from <persName>Paul</persName> — <persName>Peter</persName> when he says, <quote>Thou art <persName>Christ</persName>, the Son of the living
                  God</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-1"/> and <persName>Paul</persName> also, who learned by revelation from the Father concerning
                  the Son, and says, <quote>When God Who separated me from my mother's womb and called me
                  by His grace, was pleased to reveal His Son by my means.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-2"/> This <persName>Paul</persName> has
                  truly taught you who <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is when he cries and says, <quote>Of whom is <persName>Christ</persName> in
                  the flesh, Who is God over all, blessed for ever.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-3"/> What occasion of
                  calumny does not the word of <persName>Peter</persName> and <persName>Paul</persName> drive away from those who love
                  calumny! for he called Him <quote><persName>Christ</persName></quote> to show that He truly became man; he said of
                  Him, <quote>Who is of the Jews in the flesh,</quote> to show that His existence does not date
                  only from the time when He became incarnate;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-4"/> he said of Him, <quote>He is,</quote> to
                  tell us by his mode of expression that He is without beginning; he said of Him,
                  <quote>Who is over all,</quote> to proclaim Him Lord of created things; he said of Him, <quote>Who is
                  God,</quote> that we should not be drawn aside by the outward appearance and sufferings
                  so as to deny his incorruptible Nature; he said of Him, <quote>blessed</quote>, that we should
                  worship Him as the Ruler<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36-5"/> of all, and not regard Him as a fellow-<pb
                     type="page" n="37"/>slave; he said of Him, 'Who is for ever,' to show that it
                  is He Who by His word created all things, visible and invisible, whereby His
                  Godhead is glorified. We have, then, <persName>Christ</persName> Who is God over all, Whom we shall
                  worship, and we shall say to the heretics, <quote>In whomsoever the Spirit of <persName>Christ</persName> is
                  not, he is none of His.</quote> For we have the mind of <persName>Christ</persName>, and therefore we look for
                  the revelation of God our Saviour, the Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, Who Himself shall reward
                  the well-doers with the crown of victory, but the despisers with the
                  recompense<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-1"/> of their rashness. See, then, my brothers, that no man rob you
                  by impious words, or turn you aside by false science from the simplicity and
                  unadorned modesty of the pure beauty of the faith. But again, I repeat to you the
                  word of <persName>Paul</persName>, <quote>Beware lest any man rob you by the vain philosophy of the
                  traditions of men</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-2"/> — men who are inventors of vain things, who have not
                  taught us as the prophets and apostles teach, but have gone astray by their own
                  wisdom and followed the interpretation of their own mind; wherefore their teaching
                  is a stumbling-block to the Church of God, which He purchased with His precious
                  blood. For other foundation of the true faith can no man lay except that which is
                  laid, that there is one God, the Father, Ruler of all, and one Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>,
                  by Whom were all things, Who is from all eternity with the Father, from Him and of
                  the same Nature with Him; and one<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-3"/> Holy Spirit, the Lord and Life-giver,
                  Who proceeds from the Father, and together with the Father and the Son is
                  worshipped and glorified. Stand, then, in one spirit and one mind, and fight for
                  the faith, and be not in anything troubled by the adversaries, but keep the
                  tradition which you have received from the blessed Fathers, who,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37-4"/> out of
                  the whole creation, met together by the operation of the Holy Spirit, and preached
                  to us the true and undefiled faith, which we have from one end of the earth to the
                  other.</quote></p>
               <p>The end of the letter which the blessed <persName>Proclus</persName>, bishop of <pb type="page" n="38"
                  /><placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, wrote to Great <placeName>Armenia</placeName> of the Persians, concerning the true
                  faith.</p>                                                                                  
               <p>But<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38-1"/> <persName>Theodosius</persName> lived, as the Chronicle informs us, fifty years; of these
                  he reigned forty-two years, for he was eight years old when he began to reign. And
                  the acts of thirty-two years of his reign are related in the ecclesiastical
                  history of <persName>Socrates</persName>, and those of the other ten years more are written concisely
                  above in this second Book. He died then in the three hundred and eighth <placeName>Olympiad</placeName>;
                  and <persName>Marcian</persName> succeeded him in the kingdom. And in the year seven hundred and
                  sixty-four by the reckoning of the Greek era of <persName>Alexander</persName>, he gathered to
                  <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> a Synod of five hundred and sixty- seven bishops, whose acts we shall
                  describe as concisely as possible in this third Book which is written below, and
                  in its chapters, which have been taken for the most part from the history of
                  <persName>Zachariah</persName> the Rhetorician, which he wrote in Greek to a man called <persName>Eupraxius</persName>, who
                  lived in the royal palace and was engaged in the service of kings. But the body of
                  the holy <persName>John</persName> the bishop, who is called <persName>Chrysostom</persName>, had been brought back from the
                  place of his banishment, and it was honoured with a procession in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>.
                  And <persName>Eudocia</persName> the queen, the wife of <persName>Theodosius</persName>, went to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> for prayer, and
                  returned, and then died. But <persName>Geiseric</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38-2"/> subdued <persName>Carthage</persName> of <placeName>Africa</placeName> and
                  reigned over it. And <persName>John</persName> the general<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38-3"/> was killed by the servants of
                  <persName>Arbindus</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38-4"/> and there were earthquakes in various places. And then
                  <persName>Theodosius</persName> died.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n18-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. ὑπομνήματα</note>
            <note xml:id="n18-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. πεπραγμένα.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-1">It is impossible to give in English the exact equivalent of this
               theological term; neither <quote>God-bearer</quote> nor <quote>mother of God</quote> quite meet the
               case.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πεπραγμένα</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-3">Mich. fol. iii. v; Greg. H. E. i. p. 159 ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-4">The text <!--  Add Syriac  --> is corrupt. Possibly for
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> we should read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-5">Some such words must have dropped out of the text; both <persName>Michael</persName> and
               Barhebʳ- supply the omission as above.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-1">Liberat. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-2">Liberat. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-4">Sir. xxxii. (LXX. xxxv.) 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">διαλαλιαῖς</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-6">This seems to be the sense of the passage, but the text is
               evidently corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-7">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-8">Liberat. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-1">Or petitions <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">λίβελλοι</foreign>. For this letter
               see <persName>Leo</persName>, Ep. 21 (Migne, Patr. Lat. vol. liv.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-2">Leo, Ep. 22, 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">δογματικοί</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-4">Liberat. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-5">An exact translation of the text as it stands is impossible.
               Perhaps for <!--  Add Syriac  --> we should read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and render
               it, <quote>And they searched in the Acts for what was done in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> concerning
               <persName>Eutyches</persName>.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n23-1"> For <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>question,</quote> it would perhaps be better
               to substitute <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>outcry.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n23-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. No doubt <persName>John</persName> of <placeName>Aegae</placeName> is meant
               (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n23-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. It may stand either for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>consent</quote>, <quote>agreement</quote>, etc.; or for <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               <quote>recantation.</quote> This libel is given in <placeName>Mansi</placeName>, vol. vi. p. 629. As there is no
               recantation in it, perhaps the former meaning may be the one intended by our
               author.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23-4"><!--  Add Syriac  --> = <foreign xml:lang="grc">καταστασις</foreign></note>
            <note xml:id="n23-5">I.e. <persName>Valentinian</persName>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-1">I.e. <persName>Maximian</persName>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-3">Migne, Patr. Graec. vol. Ixv. p. 856, and Patr. Lat. vol. Ixvii. p.
               409.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-4">Down to this point the Syriac text is quite different from the
               Greek.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.; <!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS. I suggest
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and translate accordingly. The Greek is <foreign xml:lang="grc">διαφόρως</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS.; it should be <!--  Add Syriac  -->; the
               Greek is <foreign xml:lang="grc">ψηλαφῶντες</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->; the original is <foreign xml:lang="grc">τὴν ἐν ταῖς πόλεσιν
               ἀριστοκρατείαν.</foreign></note>
            <note xml:id="n25-4">Or, as by law.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-5">By reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> we
               obtain the sense of the original <foreign xml:lang="grc">περιέκλεισαν.</foreign></note>
            <note xml:id="n25-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26-1"> I venture to read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->;
               the Greek is <foreign xml:lang="grc">τὴν ἀχλὺν τῶν αἰσθησέων.</foreign></note>
            <note xml:id="n26-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS. (i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">σχῆμα</foreign>), not <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints
               it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-2">Gal. i. 9. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-3">Or, and punishment comes.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints
               it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-5"><persName>Mr. Brooks</persName> suggests that this is the correct reading
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, Gk. <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἰ καί</foreign>, not <!--  Add Syriac  --> as in the text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-6"><!--  Add Syriac  --> MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-7"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, his own help or profit.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-1">Or, had become obsolete.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-2">By reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> we get
               the sense of the original <foreign xml:lang="grc">δεῖξαι</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29-1">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->; the Greek is
               <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἰ καί</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29-3">Phil. ii. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29-4">Bar. iii. 37.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-2">By transposition of the word <!--  Add Syriac  --> the Syriac would
               give the same sense as the Greek, i.e. <quote>a man was born who trod a way of birth unlike
               this.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n30-3">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-4">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, so (tempted by theological bias) the
               Monophysite translator rendered the <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπόστασις</foreign> of the original.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-1">Isa. liii. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-2">Rom. i. 21, 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints
               it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32-1">There seems to be a confusion between <persName>Matt</persName>. i. 21 and <persName>Luke</persName> i.
               31-33.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32-2">I venture to read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32-3">I Cor. viii. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-1"><persName>John</persName> i. 1-3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-2">Acts ii. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-3">Acts xvii. 31. It is interesting to notice that the Syriac version
               (<!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>through the man whom He has ordained, and has converted
               everyone to the faith of Him</quote>) forms a connecting link between the Greek original and
               the rendering given above.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-4"><persName>John</persName> viii. 40.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-5">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-7">Read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->; the latter
               would convey a positively wrong meaning. Of course <!--  Add Syriac  --> must also be
               omitted.  <quote>Nullam suspicionem phantasiae,</quote> Lat. (<persName>Brooks</persName>).</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-8"><persName>Isa</persName>. vii. 14; <persName>Matt</persName>. i. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34-1">This is a troublesome passage for the translator. <persName>Mr. Brooks</persName>
               supposes that the word <!--  Add Syriac  --> has dropped out of the text through
               homoioteleuton, and he renders <quote>because He that was born was born through
               condescension, Who is God over all.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n34-2">Or, proceeding immutably.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35-1">Eph. ii. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35-2">The Greek is <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἀβράαμ</foreign>; it may be that we should read
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35-3">Rom. ix. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35-4">Ex. iv. 22 and <persName>Isa</persName>. xlvi. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-1"><persName>Matt</persName>. xvi. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-2"><persName>Gal</persName>. i. 15, 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-3"><persName>Rom</persName>. ix. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-4">In the translation above I adopt <persName>Mr. Brooks</persName>' suggestion, that we
               should read <!--  Add Syriac  --> instead of <!--  Add Syriac  -->. The rendering of
               the text as it stands would be, <quote>that He did not become incarnate from the Gentiles,
               but was from thence alone.</quote> This change brings the text into harmony with the Greek
               and Latin.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as in L.'s
               text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-2">Col. ii. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., an evident mistake for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37-4">From this point the Greek and Latin are different from our
               text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n38-1"><persName>Mich</persName>. fol. 115 v.</note>
            <note xml:id="n38-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ζινζήριχος</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n38-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηλάτης</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n38-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <persName>Areobindus</persName> (<persName>Brooks</persName>).</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
