<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Syriac Chronicle</title>
            <author><persName>Zachariah</persName> of <placeName>Mitylene</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book" n="7">
            <head>Book 7</head>
            <div type="section" n="7.0">
               <p>This seventh Book, in the fifteen chapters which are contained in it as given
                  below, tells about the events that occurred in the reign of <persName>Anastasius</persName>; in the
                  first chapter, about the beginning of his reign, and how <persName>Epiphanius</persName> the bishop was
                  ejected; and in the second chapter, about the Isaurians who rebelled and were
                  subdued, and the tyrants at the head of them were killed; and in the third
                  chapter, about <persName>Theodosiopolis</persName> and <persName>Amida</persName>, the cities which were subdued; and in the
                  fourth, about the manner in which the city of <placeName>Amida</placeName> was subdued; and the fifth,
                  about the famine that was in it, and how the Persians departed from it; the sixth,
                  about <placeName>Dara</placeName>, how the city was built; the seventh, about the expulsion of
                  <persName>Macedonius</persName>, who was ejected from <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>; the eighth, containing the letter
                  of <persName>Simeon</persName> the presbyter, giving information concerning his expulsion; the ninth,
                  about his successor <persName>Timothy</persName>, and how the expression, <quote>Who was crucified for us,</quote>
                  was proclaimed in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> in his days; the tenth, about the Synod which was
                  held in <placeName>Sidon</placeName> in the days of <persName>Flavian</persName> and <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName> the bishops, in the fifth
                  year,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n147-1"/> the eight hundred and twenty-third year of the Greeks; the
                  eleventh, about the petition which was framed by the monks of the East and <persName>Cosmas</persName>
                  of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, and presented to the Synod; the twelfth chapter, about the Synod that
                  was held in <placeName>Tyre</placeName> in the days of <persName>Severus</persName> and <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName>, which anathematised the
                  Council of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and the Tome of <persName>Leo</persName> with great freedom of speech; the
                  thirteenth chapter, about <persName>Ariadne</persName> the queen, who died, and about <persName>Vitalian</persName> the
                  tyrant, who took <persName>Hypatius</persName> prisoner in war; the fourteenth chapter, about <persName>Timothy</persName>,
                  who died, and his <pb type="page" n="148"/>successor was <persName>John</persName>; and about demons
                  that entered into the Egyptians, and Alexandrians, and Arabians who came to the
                  dedication festival at <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, and barked at the Cross and then ceased;[n148-1] <!-- [numbers in parethesis? ] -->
                  the fifteenth, telling who were chief priests in the days of <persName>Anastasius</persName> the king.
                  <persName>Anastasius</persName>, then, died in the eight hundred and twenty-ninth year of the Greeks,
                  in the three hundred and twenty-fourth Olympiad.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.1">
               <head>Chapter 1</head>
               <head>The first chapter of this seventh Book treats ofthe reign of Emperor <persName>Anastasius</persName>
                  who received the kingdom after <persName>Zeno</persName>, and of <persName>Euphemius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n148-2"/> the bishop there,
                  who was ejected</head>
               <p><persName>Zeno</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n148-3"/> having reigned seventeen years, as is recorded above in the sixth
                  Book and its chapters, died in the three hundred and seventeenth Olympiad, in the
                  eight hundred and second year by the reckoning of the Greeks, the fourteenth
                  Indiction, on the fourth day of the Great Week. And <persName>Anastasius</persName>, who was silentiary
                  decurion, received the kingdom. This man was from the city of <placeName>Dyrrhachium</placeName>, and was
                  powerful in aspect, vigorous in mind, and a believer. When he was a soldier he had
                  confidential friendship with <persName>Ariadne</persName> the queen, who desired and agreed to make him
                  king.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n148-4"/> To this man a few days before he became king [it happened as
                  follows].<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n148-5"/> There was a certain person named <persName>John</persName> the Scholastic, brother
                  of <persName>Dith</persName>, a native of <placeName>Amida</placeName>, a valiant man, and just and upright, fearing God and
                  forsaking evil; but by his own accord and freewill <pb type="page" n="149"/>he was
                  constant in the ministry, being a scholastic of the Church. And when he was in
                  <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> on a confidential mission<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n149-1"/> on behalf of his city, he saw a
                  vision once, and again a second time, showing that <persName>Anastasius</persName> the silentiary
                  should be made king. And he called him, and said to him, <quote>In accordance with the
                  rectitude and the virtues and the honour of thy soul, that thou mayest fulfil the
                  goodwill of God, do thou be peaceable and gentle and modest and upright, and show
                  thyself towards everyone quiet and kind for the benefit of all men, who are thy
                  kindred. It is not because I want anything from thee, or because I would flatter
                  thee, that I reveal to thee that thou shalt be made king very soon.</quote> And because
                  this <persName>John</persName> was celebrated and honoured for his merits, and was known also to many,
                  and, moreover, because he was a learned man,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n149-2"/> <persName>Anastasius</persName> believed him, and
                  took it as true; and he was constant with him there in the vigil of the church.
                  But it happened that when he received the kingdom, and he was desirous of
                  rewarding his friend with gifts of gratitude such as are sought after by<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n149-3"/>
                  and visible to men, this <persName>John</persName> would not take anything at all from him; but he soon
                  left the city and returned to his own country: being content with the
                  documents<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n149-4"/> which <persName>Zeno</persName> had drawn up, he only took assurance from <persName>Anastasius</persName>
                  that they should be received.</p>
               <p>But <persName>Euphemius</persName> the bishop there had been threatening <persName>Peter</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> that he
                  would decree his deprivation, because he wrote expressly a reply to <persName>Fravitta</persName> the
                  predecessor of <persName>Euphemius</persName>, and also because in his synodical letter which was sent
                  by some clergy, <persName>Longinus</persName> the presbyter and <persName>Andrew</persName> the deacon, he had anathematised
                  the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and the Tome. But at that time <persName>Euphemius</persName> was prevented from
                  doing this by the advice of <persName>Archelaus</persName>, bishop of <placeName>Caesarea</placeName>, <pb type="page" n="150"
                  />a wise man who happened to be there. And when <persName>Peter</persName> died, <persName>Euphemius</persName> maintained
                  the same hatred against <persName>Athanasius</persName>, <persName>Peter</persName>'s successor in the bishopric of
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, who more openly and authoritatively anathematised the Synod and the
                  Tome; against him <persName>Euphemius</persName> was making preparations to depose him, and called in
                  <persName>Felix</persName> of <placeName>Rome</placeName> to his aid. And when his machination became known to <persName>Athanasius</persName>
                  through his Apokrisiarioi there, who wrote and also sent to him a copy of the
                  letter which had been sent by him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n150-1"/> to <persName>Felix</persName>, then <persName>Athanasius</persName> made
                  preparation, and wrote to <persName>Sallust</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, and received a reply from him
                  concerning the agreement of the faith. And they both informed <persName>Anastasius</persName> the king
                  respecting <persName>Euphemius</persName> that he was a heretic, and showed a copy of his letter in
                  confirmation (of their charge). And when his deeds were examined by certain
                  bishops who happened to be in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and also by believing monks from
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> and the East, he was banished and ejected from his see; and <persName>Macedonius</persName>,
                  who also was ejected fifteen years later, as is recorded below, became bishop in
                  his stead.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.2">
               <head>Chapter 2</head>
               <head>The second chapter of this Book tells us how <placeName>Isauria</placeName> revolted</head>
               <p>Now the Isaurians prospered in the days of <persName>Zeno</persName> (who withdrew before <persName>Basiliscus</persName>
                  and <persName>Marcus</persName> the tyrants, and dwelt<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n150-2"/> as a refugee in the strongholds there
                  called <persName>Salmon</persName>); and they also had free intercourse<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n150-3"/> in the kingdom in his
                  days, and he was their rewarder, and he counted them worthy to receive good things
                  of all kinds from him; and on that account they could not bear their good fortune,
                  but were proud<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n150-4"/> and insolent when <persName>Anastasius</persName> became king. And they raised
                  a rebellion against him, and they appointed a <pb type="page" n="151"/>tyrant for
                  themselves, and they refused the gifts which were sent to them by <persName>Anastasius</persName>, and
                  they would not consent to give him tribute, but they even raided the
                  provinces<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n151-1"/> round about them. And when an outcry<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n151-2"/> and
                  accusation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n151-3"/> against them was brought to the king, he sent an army and made
                  preparations against them. And the Isaurians were defeated in battle; and they
                  showed themselves to be weak, and were subdued, and the tyrants were killed.</p>
               <p>But an earthquake occurred. And locusts invaded ʿArab<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n151-4"/> of <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>. And
                  there was a famine in the year nine,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n151-5"/> of which James the doctor of Batnas
                  wrote an account, in the eleventh (year) of the reign of <persName>Anastasius</persName>. And many of
                  the Arabs died, both in Amida, whither they retired, and in various other
                  places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.3">
               <head>Chapter 3<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n151-6"/></head>
               <head>The third chapter of this seventh Book makes known how <persName>Theodosiopolis</persName> of
                  <placeName>Armenia</placeName> was subdued, and concerning the city <placeName>Amida</placeName> of <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName></head>
               <p>When<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n151-7"/> <persName>Piroz</persName>, king of the Persians, was reigning in his own country, in the
                  thirteenth (year) of <persName>Anastasius</persName>, the Huns issued forth from the gates that were
                  guarded by the Persians, and from the mountainous region there, and invaded the
                  territory of the Persians. And <persName>Piroz</persName> became alarmed, and he gathered an army and
                  went to meet them. And when he inquired from them the reason of their preparation
                  and invasion of his country, they said to him, <quote>What the kingdom of the Persians
                  gives to us by way of tribute is <pb type="page" n="152"/>not sufficient for us
                  Barbarians, who, like rapacious wild beasts, reject God in the North-West region;
                  and we live by our weapons, our bow and our sword; and we support ourselves by
                  flesh-food of all kinds; and the king of the Romans has promised by his
                  ambassadors to give us twice as much tribute whenever we shall dissolve our
                  friendship with you Persians; and accordingly we made our preparations,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n152-1"/>
                  and we have come here, that either you shall give us as much as the Romans, and we
                  will ratify our treaty with you, or else if you do not give it to us, take war.</quote>
                  And when <persName>Piroz</persName> perceived the determination of the Huns, although they were much
                  fewer in number than his own army, he thought it well to play them false and
                  deceive them; and he promised them to give it. And four hundred of the chief men
                  of the Huns assembled, and they had with them <persName>Eustace</persName>, a merchant of <placeName>Apamea</placeName>, a
                  clever man, by whose advice they were guided. But <persName>Piroz</persName> also and four hundred men
                  with him met together. And they went up into a mountain; and they made a treaty,
                  and they ate together, and they swore, lifting up their hands to heaven. And when
                  few remained along with the four hundred men who were to receive<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n152-2"/> the
                  tribute money which was being collected, and the rest of the Huns had dispersed to
                  return to their own country; after ten days <persName>Piroz</persName> broke faith with them, and
                  prepared war, both against the Huns who had dispersed, and against the four
                  hundred who remained and those with them. But <persName>Eustace</persName> the merchant encouraged the
                  Huns that they should not be alarmed even though they were very much fewer.
                  And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n152-3"/> in the place where the oaths were made, they cast musk and spices
                  upon coals of fire, and made an offering to God according to the advice of
                  <persName>Eustace</persName>, that he might overthrow the liars. And they joined battle with <persName>Piroz</persName>, and
                  killed him and a great number of his army; and they pillaged the Persian
                  territory, and returned to their own country. And the body of <persName>Piroz</persName> was not found;
                  and in his country they call him the liar.</p>
               <p>But <persName>Kawad</persName>, who succeeded him in the kingdom, and his <pb type="page" n="153"
                  />nobles cherished hatred against the Romans, saying that they had caused the
                  incursion of the Huns, and the pillage and the devastation of their country. And
                  <persName>Kawad</persName> gathered an army, and went out against <persName>Theodosiopolis</persName> in <placeName>Armenia</placeName> of the
                  Romans, and subdued the city; and he treated its inhabitants mercifully, because
                  he had not been insulted by them; but he took <persName>Constantine</persName>, the ruler of their
                  city, prisoner.</p>
               <p>And in the month of October<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n153-1"/> he reached <persName>Amida</persName> of <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>. (But though
                  he assailed it) with fierce assaults of sharp arrows and with
                  battering-rams,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n153-2"/> which thrust the wall to overthrow it, and
                  pent-houses,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n153-3"/> which protected those who brought together the materials for
                  the besiegers' mound<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n153-4"/> and raised it up and made it equal in height with
                  the wall, for three months, day after day, yet he could not take the city by
                  storm; while his own people were suffering much hardship through work and
                  fighting, and he was constantly hearing in his ears the insults of disorderly men
                  on the wall, and their ridicule and mockery, and he was reduced to great straits.
                  And indignation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n153-5"/> and regret took possession of him, because the winter
                  came upon him in its severity, and because the Persians, being clad in their loose
                  garments,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n153-6"/> showed themselves inefficient; and their bows were greatly
                  relaxed by the moisture of the atmosphere; and their battering-rams did not hurt
                  the wall or make any breaches in it, for (the defenders) were binding
                  bundles<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n153-7"/> of rushes<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n153-8"/> from the beds<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n153-9"/> with chains, and
                  receiving upon them the violence of the battering-rams, and thus preventing them
                  from breaking the wall. But they themselves made a breach in the wall from inside,
                  and they carried the material of the mound from without into <pb type="page"
                     n="154"/>the fortress within, and they gradually propped up the cavity with
                  beams from beneath. And when chosen Persian warriors ascended the mound and laid
                  beams upon the wall to effect an entrance (now they were clad in armour, and the
                  king was near with his army outside, and was supporting them with display of
                  strength<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n154-1"/> and shooting of arrows, and encouraging them with shouting, and
                  stimulating them and urging them forward by his presence and appearance, they
                  being about five hundred men), the defenders threw strings of skin just flayed
                  from an ox, and soaked vetch mixed with myrrh-oil from the wall upon the beams,
                  and poured the liquid from the vetch upon the skins to make them slippery, and
                  they placed fire among the props which were beneath the mound. And when they had
                  engaged in a conflict with each other for about six hours, and (the besiegers) had
                  failed to effect an entrance, the fire blazed up and consumed the wood of the
                  props, and immediately also the rest of the material<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n154-2"/> was reduced to ashes
                  by the violence of the fire, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n154-3"/> the mound was destroyed and
                  fell.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n154-4"/> And the Persians who were on the top of it were burned, and they
                  were also bruised, being struck with stones by those on the wall. And the king
                  retired with shame and grief, being more than ever mocked and insulted by those
                  daring, proud, and boastful men. For there was no bishop in that city to be their
                  teacher and to keep them in order. For <persName>John</persName> the bishop, a chaste and noble man of
                  honoured character, had died a few days before. This man was called from the
                  monastery of <placeName>Karthamin</placeName>, and he, having been elected, came, and he became their
                  bishop. However, he did not change his asceticism and self-mortification and habit
                  of life, but was constant (in them)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n154-5"/> by day and by night. And he <pb
                     type="page" n="155"/>warned<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n155-1"/> and rebuked the rich men of the city at
                  the time of the famine and the incursion of the Arabs<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n155-2"/> and the pestilence,
                  saying that they should not keep back the corn in the time of distress, but should
                  sell it and give to the poor; lest if they kept it back, they might be only
                  hoarding it for the enemy, according to the word of Scripture. And so, in fact, it
                  happened. To him an angel appeared openly, standing beside the
                  altar<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n155-3"/>-table, and he foretold to him the incursion of the enemy, and that
                  he should be taken away as a righteous man from the face of the enemy; and he
                  revealed the saying, and published it in the presence of the people of the city,
                  that they might turn and be saved from the wrath.</p>
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter" n="7.4">
               <head>Chapter 4</head>
               <head>The fourth chapter of this seventh Book tells how the city of <placeName>Amida</placeName> was
                  subdued, and what befell its inhabitants</head>
               <p>When <persName>Kawad</persName> and his army had been defeated in the various assaults which they made
                  upon the city, and a large number of his soldiers had perished, his hands were
                  weakened; and he asked that a small gift of silver should be given to him, and he
                  would withdraw from the city. But <persName>Leontius</persName>, the son of <persName>Pappus</persName>, the chief
                  councillor, and <persName>Cyrus</persName> the governor,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n155-4"/> and <persName>   </persName> the steward, by
                  the messengers whom they sent to <persName>Kawad</persName>, demanded from him the price of the garden
                  vegetables which his army had eaten, as well as for the corn and wine which they
                  gathered and brought away from the villages. And when he was greatly grieved at
                  this, and was preparing to withdraw in disgrace, <persName>Christ</persName> appeared to him in a
                  vision of the night, as he himself after- <pb type="page" n="156"/>wards<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n156-1"/>
                  related it, and said to him, that within three days He would deliver up to him the
                  inhabitants of the city, because they had sinned against Him; and this took place
                  as follows:— On the western side of the city by the <placeName>Tripyrgion</placeName> was a guard of
                  monks who were told off from the monastery of <persName>John</persName> of <placeName>Anzetene</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n156-2"/> and their
                  archimandrite was a Persian. And on the outside, right opposite this watch-tower,
                  a certain Marzban,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n156-3"/> named <persName>Kanarak</persName> the Lame, was encamped. And day after
                  day, vigilantly watching by night and by day, he was diligent and clever in
                  devising plans for the subjugation of the city. For there was one whom they called
                  in the city <persName>Kutrigo</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n156-4"/> a turbulent and thievish fellow; this man was very
                  daring in all kinds of attacks upon the Persians, and he used to make raids and
                  snatch away from them cattle and goods; so that they also, being accustomed to
                  hear the men on the wall crying out, used to call him <persName>Kutrigo</persName>. <persName>Kanarak</persName> observed
                  this man, and perceived that he went out by the aqueducts adjoining the
                  Tripyrgion, and snatched up spoil, and went in again. And for a time the Persians
                  let him accomplish his will, marking and examining his actions, and they ran after
                  him and saw the place from which he came out and where he went in.</p>
               <p>But it happened on that night on which the city was subdued, that there was
                  darkness, and a dense cloud sending down soft rain; and a certain man gave a
                  friendly entertainment to the monks who guarded the Tripyrgion, and he gave them
                  wine to drink late in the night, and consequently sleep overtook them, and they
                  did not watch diligently upon their guard, according to their usual custom. And
                  when<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n156-5"/> <persName>Kanarak</persName> and a few soldiers came up, pursuing <persName>Kutrigo</persName>, and drew near
                     <pb type="page" n="157"/>to the wall, the monks did not cry out nor cast
                  stones; and the man perceived that they were asleep, and he sent for scaling-
                  ladders and for his troops; and his followers went in by the aqueducts, and
                  climbed the tower of the monks, and killed them. And they took the tower and also
                  the battlement<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n157-1"/>; and they set up the scaling-ladders against the wall, and
                  sent to the king.</p>
               <p>But when those who were in charge of another tower, their neighbours, heard it,
                  they cried out, and tried to come to the monks who were being killed, and were not
                  able; but some of them were wounded by arrows from the Persians, and died. And
                  when the report reached <persName>Cyrus</persName> the governor, and he came up and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n157-2"/> torches
                  were held close to him, he was easily struck by an arrow from the Persians, who
                  stood in the darkness and were themselves unhurt by the archers; and he withdrew
                  wounded. But when it was morning, and the king and his army reached the place,
                  they set scaling-ladders against the wall ; and he ordered his troops to go up;
                  and many of those who went up perished, being<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n157-3"/> wounded by arrows and by
                  stones, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n157-4"/> driven back by spears. And those who through fear turned and
                  fled down the scaling-ladders were killed by the king's command, as cowards and
                  fugitives from the battle. Whereupon the Persians took courage and set themselves
                  either to gain the victory by conquering and subduing the city, or being smitten
                  in the actual conflict to escape reproach and slaughter from their king; for he
                  was near, and was a spectator of their struggle. But the citizens tried to loose
                  from beneath the keystone of the arch of the tower in which the Persians were, and
                  they were engaged in loosening the supports; and while this was taking place,
                  another tower was subdued, and another and another in succession, and the guards
                  of the wall were killed.</p>
               <p>But <persName>Peter</persName>, a man of huge stature, a native of <placeName>ʿAmkhoro</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n157-5"/> <pb type="page"
                     n="158"/>being clad in an iron coat of mail, held the battlement of one side
                  alone by himself; and did not allow the Persians to pass, and repelled and hurled
                  back with a spear those who assailed him from without and within, holding his
                  ground and standing like a hero: until at length, when five or six towers on
                  another side were subdued, he also fled and was not killed. And the Persians first
                  got possession of the whole wall and held it; and they spent a night and a day and
                  the following night in killing and driving back the guards. And at last they
                  descended and opened the gates, and the army entered, having received the king's
                  command to destroy the men and women of all classes and ages for three days and
                  three nights. But a certain Christian prince of the country of <placeName>Arran</placeName> pleaded with
                  the king on behalf of a church called the Great Church of the Forty Martyrs; and
                  he spared it, being full of people. And after three days and three nights the
                  slaughter ceased by the king's command. And men went in to guard the treasures of
                  the Church and of the great men of the city, that the king might have whatever was
                  found in them. But the order also was given that the corpses of those who were
                  slain in the streets and of those whom they had crucified should be collected and
                  brought round to the northern side of the city, so that the king, who was on the
                  south side, might enter in. And they were collected, and they were numbered as
                  they were brought out, eighty thousand; besides those that were heaped up in the
                  taverns, and were thrown into the aqueducts, and were left in the houses. And then
                  the king entered the treasury of the Church, and seeing there an image of the Lord
                  <persName>Jesus</persName>, depicted in the likeness of a Galilean, he asked who it was. And they
                  answered him, <quote>It is God</quote> ;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n158-1"/> and he bowed his head before it, and said,
                  <quote>He it was Who said to me, <quote>Stay, and receive from Me the city and its 
                  inhabitants, for they have sinned against Me.</quote></quote> But he took away a quantity of
                  silver and gold of the holy vessels, and costly garments formerly belonging to
                  <persName>Isaac Bar Barʿai</persName>, a consul<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n158-2"/> and a rich man of the city, which came to the
                  Church by inheritance a few years before. But he found there also good wine dried
                  into its dregs, which <pb type="page" n="159"/>used to be brought out and placed
                  in the sun for seven years together, and at last it became dry; from this the
                  stewards, when on their journeys, were accustomed to take some, ground to dust, in
                  clean<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n159-1"/> linen pouches. And they would put a little of it into water so as
                  to make a mixture, which, when they drank it, afforded the sweetness and flavour
                  of wine. And they told the ignorant that it was <quote>hʾnono.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n159-2"/> And the king
                  admired it greatly, and took it away. And the art of making this agreeable
                  beverage was lost to the sons of the Church from that time.</p>
               <p>But the gold and silver belonging to the great men's houses, and the beautiful
                  garments, were collected together and given to the king's treasurers. But they
                  also took down all the statues of the city, and the sun-dials, and the marble; and
                  they collected the bronze and everything that pleased them, and they placed them
                  upon wooden rafts that they made, and sent them by the river <placeName>Tigris</placeName>, which flows
                  past the east of the city and penetrates into their country. But the king sought
                  for the chiefs and great men of the city; and <persName>Leontius</persName>, and <persName>Cyrus</persName> the governor,
                  who was wounded by the arrow, and the rest of the great men, were brought to him;
                  but the Persians had killed <persName>Paul Bar Zainab </persName>the steward, lest he should make known
                  to the king that they had found a quantity of gold in his possession. But they
                  clothed <persName>Leontius</persName> and <persName>Cyrus</persName> in filthy garments, and put swine-ropes on their necks,
                  and made them carry pigs, and led them about proclaiming and exposing them, and
                  saying, <quote>Rulers who do not rule their city well nor restrain its people from
                  insulting the king, deserve such insult as this.</quote> But at last the great men, and
                  all the chief craftsmen,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n159-3"/> were bound and brought together, and set apart
                  as the king's captives; and they were sent to his country with the military escort
                  which brought them down. But influential men of the king's army drew near and said
                  to him, <quote>Our kinsmen and brethren were killed in battle by the inhabitants of the
                  city,</quote> and they asked him that one-tenth <pb type="page" n="160"/>of the men
                  should be given to them for the exaction of vengeance. And they brought them
                  together and counted them, and gave to them in proportion from the men; and they
                  put them to death, killing them in all sorts of ways.</p>
               <p>But the king bathed himself in the bath of <persName>Paul Bar Zainab</persName>, and after winter he
                  departed from the city. And he left in it <persName>Glon</persName> the general as governor, and two
                  Marzbans, and about three thousand soldiers to guard the city, and <persName>John Bar
                  Habloho</persName>, one of the rich men, and <persName>Sergius Bar Zabduni</persName>, to rule the people.</p>
               <p>And then in the summer the Romans came, and their leaders were <persName>Patrick</persName> the
                  commander-in-chief, an old man, upright and a believer, but deficient in mental
                  power, and <persName>Hypatius</persName>, and <persName>Celer</persName> the master of the offices, and at length also
                  <persName>Areobindus</persName>; moreover, Count <persName>Justin</persName>, who received the kingdom after <persName>Anastasius</persName>,
                  accompanied them. And they met together, and they attacked<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n160-1"/> the city with
                  wooden towers and excavations, and all kinds of engines; and they set fire also to
                  the gate of the city, which was called the gate of <placeName>Mâr Zʾʿuro</placeName>, to effect an
                  entrance upon the Persians; however, they were hindered because they were resting,
                  and they did not rush in, for the Persians shut the gate. And the Romans did not
                  subdue it nor take it from them by assault; although the inhabitants were reduced
                  to misery from famine, day after day, until at last the people there were eating
                  one another. But how this happened, although the story is horrible and wretched,
                  yet because it is true, I shall relate how<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n160-2"/> in the following fifth chapter
                  of this seventh Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.5">
               <head>Chapter 5</head>
               <head>The fifth chapter of the seventh Book tells about the famine which occurred
                  when <placeName>Amida</placeName> was being subdued, and how the Persians went out from it and departed
                  to their own country</head>
               <p>King <persName>Kawad</persName>, as stated above, on his departure with his army from <placeName>Amida</placeName> to his own
                  country, left in it <persName>Glon</persName>, a <pb type="page" n="161"/>general, and two Marzbans,
                  and about three thousand soldiers to guard the city; and also two or three rich
                  men and some private inhabitants. These the Roman generals did not overcome, nor
                  did they subdue and take the city. But at last Patrick went down to
                  <placeName>Arzanene</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n161-1"/> of the Persians, and carried off captives, and subdued
                  fortresses there. And <persName>Areobindus</persName> and <persName>Hypatius</persName> went down to <placeName>Nisibis</placeName> and did not
                  subdue it, although the citizens were favourably inclined towards the Romans, and
                  showed themselves lazy<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n161-2"/> in the fight. However, the king of the Persians
                  hearing of it, came with an army against the Romans; and they fled before him, and
                  they left their tents and the heavy baggage which they had with them. Areobindus
                  fled from Arzamena and Aphphadana,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n161-3"/> and <persName>Hypatius</persName> and <persName>Patrick</persName> and others
                  from <placeName>Thelkatsro</placeName>. And they lost many horses and their riders, who fell from the
                  cliffs of the mountains, and were bruised, and perished, and were mangled.</p>
               <p>But<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n161-4"/> <placeName>Farzman</placeName> alone, a warlike man, prospered in battle several times; and
                  he was celebrated and dreaded amongst the Persians, and his very name terrified
                  them, and his exploits wasted and weakened them; and they proved themselves to be
                  cowards in his presence, and fell before him. This man at last came to <placeName>Amida</placeName> with
                  five hundred horsemen, and he watched the Persians who went out to the villages,
                  and he killed some of them, and he took the animals<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n161-5"/> which they had with
                  them, and also their horses.</p>
               <p>Now a certain crafty fellow, <persName>Gadono</persName> by name, of the town of <placeName>Akhorè</placeName>, whom I myself
                  know, introduced himself to him, and made a compact with him, that he would
                  beguile and bring out to him, on some pretext, <persName>Glon</persName>, the Persian general, and
                  three or four hundred horsemen. And because this aforesaid <persName>Gadono</persName> was a hunter of
                  wild animals, and partridge, and fish,[#161-6] he used to go in freely to <persName>Glon</persName>,
                  carrying in his hands a <pb type="page" n="162"/>present of game for him; and he
                  ate bread in his presence, and received from him out of the property of the city
                  what was equal in value to the game.</p>
               <p>And at last he told him that there were about one hundred Romans and five hundred
                  horses nearly seven miles away from the city, at a place called <quote>ʿAfotho
                  Roʾʿen</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n162-1"/> and as a friend he advised him to go out and take possession of
                  the beasts, to kill the Romans, and make a name for himself.</p>
               <p>And he sent scouts, who saw a few Romans and the horses, and returned and gave him
                  the information. Then he made preparation and took with him four hundred horsemen,
                  and this <persName>Gadono</persName> upon a mule; and he led him and set him in the midst of the ambush
                  of the Romans, who were on the watch for him. So the Romans cut the Persians to
                  pieces, and they brought away the head of <persName>Glon</persName> to <placeName>Constantia</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n162-2"/></p>
               <p>Upon this, distress and rage seized the son of <persName>Glon</persName> and the Marzbans, who used to
                  allow<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n162-3"/> the inhabitants who happened to be shut up in the city to go out to
                  the market, which was held beside the wall by peasants from the villages. These
                  peasants brought wine and wheat and other produce, and sold them both to the
                  Persians and to the citizens, while horsemen were stationed close to them, and
                  escorted them, a certain number at a time, and conducted them in. And by an
                  excellent law of the Persians, no one dared to take anything from the villagers,
                  who sold what they liked and received the price in money and kind from the city;
                  consequently they attended the market diligently. However, in consequence of the
                  slaughter of <persName>Glon</persName> and the horsemen, the market was held no more. And the great men
                  who were left in the city, and about ten thousand persons besides, were arrested
                  and shut up in the Stadium, and they were kept there without food; and they ate
                  their shoes, and they also ate and drank their excrements. And at last they
                  attacked one another; and now when they were almost perishing, those who were left
                  in the Stadium <pb type="page" n="163"/>were let loose like the dead from their
                  graves in the midst of the city. And famishing women, who were found there in
                  troops, laid hold of some of the men by means of blandishments and guile and
                  artifices, and overcame them, and killed and ate them; and more than five hundred
                  men were eaten by women. And the famine which was in this city being so grievous,
                  the distress surpassed the blockade of Samaria and the destruction of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>,
                  which is recorded in Scripture and <persName>Josephus</persName> relates.</p>
               <p>But at last <persName>Farzman</persName> came to the city, and he made a treaty with the Persians
                  there, for they, too, were weak. And the chiefs of the Romans and the Persians sat
                  by the gate of the city, while the Persians went out carrying as much as they
                  could, and they were not searched.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n163-1"/> And if any of the citizens accompanied
                  them they were asked whether they desired to remain or would like to go with the
                  Persians. So the evacuation of the city took place.</p>
               <p>But eleven hundred pounds of gold were given to <persName>Kawad</persName> by <persName>Celer</persName>, the master of the
                  offices, for the ransom of the city and for peace.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n163-2"/> And when the documents
                  were drawn up they brought the drafts<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n163-3"/> to the king for his signature. And
                  the king fell asleep, and it was told him in a vision that he should not make
                  peace; and when he awoke he tore up the paper, and departed to his own country,
                  taking the gold with him.</p>
               <p>But <persName>Farzman</persName> remained in the city to govern its inhabitants and the country. (Now a
                  remission of tribute was granted by the king for seven years.) And he dealt kindly
                  with the inhabitants of the city. And he bestowed gifts lavishly on those who
                  returned from captivity, and he received them peaceably, every man according to
                  his rank. And the city was at peace and was inhabited.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n163-4"/> And building was
                  added to the wall. And, by the advice of Dith, a merciful bishop was sent again to
                  the city, a quiet and affable man, a monk, and a councillor,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n163-5"/> <persName>Thomas</persName> <pb
                     type="page" n="164"/>by name. And, besides, the providence of God summoned and
                  conveyed thither <persName>Samuel</persName> the Just, from the monastery of the <placeName>Katharoi</placeName>, a
                  miracle-worker and a <quote>dissolver of doubts</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n164-1"/> and he also sustained the
                  city by his prayers, and aided its inhabitants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.6">
               <head>Chapter 6</head>
               <head>The sixth chapter of this seventh Book tells about the town of <placeName>Dara</placeName> of
                  <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>, how it was built on the border of the Roman and Persian territories in
                  the days of <persName>Anastasius</persName> the king, and <persName>Thomas</persName> the bishop of the city of <placeName>Amida</placeName></head>
               <p>Anastasius<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n164-2"/> the king brought severe censures<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n164-3"/> against the Roman
                  generals<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n164-4"/> and commanders who betook themselves to the royal city after the
                  conflict with the Persians, because they did not, according to his will, under the
                  Lord, prosper and succeed in the war, and conquer the Persians or drive them out
                  from <placeName>Amida</placeName>, except by the gifts and the gold that were sent from him. And they
                  alleged in their defence to him, that it was hard for generals to contend with a
                  king who according to the word of God, although he was an Assyrian and an enemy,
                  was sent by the Lord to the country of the Romans for the punishment of sins, and,
                  moreover, on account of the greatness of the army which he had with him; and that
                  it was no easy matter for them in his absence also to subdue <persName>Nisibis</persName>; because they
                  had no engines ready, nor any refuge in which to rest. For the fortresses were far
                  away and were too small to receive the army, and neither the supply of water in
                  them nor the vegetables were sufficient. And they begged of him that a city should
                  be built by his command beside the mountain, as a refuge for the army in which
                  they might rest, and for the preparation of weapons, and to guard the country of
                  the Arabs from the inroads of the <pb type="page" n="165"/>Persians and Saracens.
                  And some of them spoke to him in favour of <persName>Dara</persName>, and some in favour of <persName>Ammodis</persName>.
                  Then he sent a message to <persName>Thomas</persName> the bishop of <placeName>Amida</placeName>, and he despatched
                  engineers<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n165-1"/> who drew up a plan<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n165-2"/> and this holy <persName>Thomas</persName> brought it up
                  with him to the king. And the king and the great men agreed that Dara should be
                  built as a city. And at that time <persName>Felicissimus</persName> was commander,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n165-3"/> an
                  energetic and wise man; and he was not at all covetous, but was upright, and a
                  friend of the peasants and the poor. Now King <persName>Kawad</persName> was fighting with the Tamuroye
                  and other enemies of his country. And the king gave gold to <persName>Thomas</persName> the bishop as
                  the price of the village which belonged to the Church; and he bought<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n165-4"/> it
                  for the treasury. And he liberated all the serfs who were in it, and granted to
                  each of them his land and his house. And for the building of the church of the
                  city he gave several hundred pounds of gold. And he promised with an oath that he
                  would give with liberal hand whatever the bishop might expend, and that he would
                  not disown the obligation. And at last he issued a royal decree,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n165-5"/> and in
                  full detail,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n165-6"/> providing that the work of building the city should be
                  carried out according to the direction of the bishop without delay, gain and
                  profit thereby accruing to the craftsmen and slaves and peasants who were required
                  for the collection of material there.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n165-7"/> And he sent a number of
                  stonecutters and masons; and he commanded that no man should be deprived of the
                  wages he earned, because he rightly perceived and cleverly understood that by that
                  means a city could quickly be built upon the frontier. And when they began by the
                  help of the Lord and commenced the work, there were there as overseers and
                  commissaries over it <persName>Cyrus</persName> <persName>ʿAdon</persName> and <persName>Eutychian</persName> the presbyters, and <persName>Paphnout</persName>
                  and</p>
               <p><persName>Sergius</persName> and <persName>John</persName> the deacons, and others from the clergy of <persName>Amida</persName>. And the bishop
                  himself paid frequent personal visits <pb type="page" n="166"/>to the
                  place.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n166-1"/> And gold was given in abundance without any stint to the craftsmen
                  and for work of every kind, at the following rate, the regular sum of four
                  keratin<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n166-2"/> a day for each workman, and if he had an ass with him, of eight.
                  And consequently many grew rich and wealthy. And since the report was published
                  abroad that the work was honest and that the wages were given, from the <placeName>East</placeName> to
                  the <placeName>West</placeName> workmen and craftsmen flocked together. And the overseers who were over
                  the work also received a liberal allowance,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n166-3"/> and their wallets were
                  filled; for they found the man generous, gentle, and kind; and, moreover, he
                  believed in the just king, and in his promises which he made to him. And in two or
                  three years the city was built, and, as we may say, suddenly sprang up on the
                  frontier. And when <persName>Kawad</persName> heard of it, and sought to put a stop to the work, he was
                  unable, for the wall was raised, and built high enough to be a protection for
                  those who took refuge behind it. And a large public bath<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n166-4"/> and a spacious
                  storehouse were built. And a conduit was constructed which passed along the lower
                  part of the mountain, and wonderful cisterns within the city to receive the water.
                  And persons to hasten the work were frequently sent from the king to the bishop,
                  and they all brought back excellent reports of his integrity and justice to the
                  king; and he was greatly pleased with the man, and sent gold in answer to the
                  man's requests, and fulfilled them without delay. And at last the number of
                  hundred pounds which he sent was counted, and the bishop forwarded a written
                  statement to the king, that, speaking in the presence of God, the money had been
                  expended upon the work, and that no part of it remained in his hand or had been
                  given to his Church. And he readily sent him a royal decree containing a receipt
                  of the exchequer<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n166-5"/> <pb type="page" n="167"/>to the effect that all the gold
                  which had been sent by him had been expended upon the building in the city. And
                  <placeName>Dara</placeName> was completed, and it was named <placeName>Anastasiopolis</placeName>, after the name of the just
                  king. And he swore by his crown that no statement of accounts<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n167-1"/> should be
                  required from <persName>Thomas</persName> or from his Church, either by himself or by any of his
                  successors in the kingdom. And he<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n167-2"/> appointed there and consecrated as
                  first bishop <persName>Eutychian</persName> the presbyter, a zealous man, and accustomed to the
                  transaction of business; and he gave the privilege of certain rights to his
                  Church, taken from the jurisdiction of the Church of <placeName>Amida</placeName>. And attached to him
                  was <persName>John</persName>, one of the Roman soldiers from <placeName>Amida</placeName>. Him <persName>Eutychian</persName> tonsured, and made
                  him a presbyter and master of the hostelry;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n167-3"/> and when he went up to the
                  royal city this <persName>John</persName> accompanied him. And the king, upon his being presented to
                  him, gave him an endowment<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n167-4"/> for his church. But <persName>Abraham Bar Kili</persName> of
                  <placeName>Thel-midè</placeName> was notary at that time, who was the son of <persName>Ephraim</persName> of <placeName>Constantia</placeName>, and
                  he also attached himself to <persName>Eutychian</persName> the bishop, who made him a presbyter. And he
                  was sent as overseer of the work and the building of the bath; and at last he
                  became steward of the Church.</p>
               <p>But the king gave <persName>Eutychian</persName> gifts of holy vessels and gold for the
                  building<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n167-4"/> of the great church,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n167-5"/> and sent him away. And the bishop
                  having lived but a little longer, died. And his successor there was <persName>Thomas Bar
                  ʿAbdiyo</persName> of <placeName>Resaina</placeName>, who had been a Roman soldier, and had been appointed steward
                  of the Church of <placeName>Amida</placeName>; and he also was vigilant and well versed in business. And
                  <persName>John</persName> the master of the hostelry, being an honourable and chaste man, was faithful
                  to him and beloved by him. And when this holy <persName>Thomas</persName> withdrew from his see on
                  account of his zeal for the faith, this believing <persName>John</persName> <pb type="page" n="168"
                  />joined him, and he appointed him as his suffragan;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n168-1"/> and for about
                  seventeen years he lived in exile in different places. And he sent him (<persName>John</persName>) to
                  <placeName>Berroea</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n168-2"/> where he died in the year three<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n168-3"/> (when <persName>Khosrun</persName> went up
                  to <placeName>Antioch</placeName>), having joined the monks who had withdrawn from Marde before the
                  enemy; and he was buried in the monastery of <placeName>Beth-Thiri</placeName>; and he was laid beside
                  his bishop, who entered into rest before him.</p>
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter" n="7.7">
               <head>Chapter 7</head>
               <head>The seventh chapter of the seventh Book concerning the expulsion of <persName>Macedonius</persName>
                  the heretic from the royal city</head>
               <p><persName>Macedonius</persName>, who was bishop of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, omitted no intrigue of heart to
                  conceal his opinions. But, like the fruit which bursts open in its day, according
                  to the saying of Job,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n168-4"/> and <quote>what is covered shall be revealed, and what is
                  done in the secret chamber shall be proclaimed upon the house-tops,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n168-5"/> as
                  is said, again, in the Gospel. This man (was attached) to the monks of the
                  monastery of the Akoimetoi, of whom there were about one thousand, and who lived
                  luxuriously in baths and in other bodily indulgences, and outwardly appeared to
                  men honourable, and were adorned with the semblance of chastity, but were inwardly
                  like whited sepulchres, full of all uncleanness. And they agreed to the mind of
                  <persName>Macedonius</persName>; and he used to celebrate the memory of <persName>Nestorius</persName> every year, and they
                  used to celebrate it with him in their monastery and in the other monastic
                  dwellings where the same opinions were held. And consequently they had great
                  freedom of intercourse with this <persName>Macedonius</persName>. And they were continually reading the
                  writings of the school of <persName>Diodorus</persName> and <persName>Theodore</persName>; and <persName>Macedonius</persName> himself com- <pb
                     type="page" n="169"/>piled a book of quotations from them, and from the work
                  which was drawn up by <persName>Theodoret</persName> concerning the Acts of the Synod (not the one that
                  is translated into the Syriac language); and he ornamented it with gold; and he
                  said, <quote>It is from the holy fathers and the doctors of the Church.</quote> And when he
                  showed it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n169-1"/> to the king, he would not receive it; and he said to him, <quote>You
                  have no need of such things, go rather and burn this.</quote> And when he saw the mind of
                  the king he formed a plan<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n169-2"/> for actually raising a rebellion against him;
                  and he was in the habit of calling him a heretic and a Manichaean. And the Master
                  of the Offices, because he was lavishly supplied with gifts by him, was favourably
                  inclined towards him. And the report was brought to the king by some true men who
                  were no framers of flattering words. And he held a Council;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n169-3"/> and in the
                  presence of his patricians he told of the insult which had been offered to him by
                  <persName>Macedonius</persName>; and he was distressed, and wept, and adjured them not to be influenced
                  by fear; but if, in truth, their king was displeasing to them, or if they knew
                  that he was infected with the deceit of heresy, they should take his dominion from
                  him, and he should be cast out as an unbeliever. And they fell upon their faces
                  before him, weeping.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n169-4"/> And they inveighed against the audacity of
                  <persName>Macedonius</persName>, crying out and reviling him; and they praised the king; and they
                  decreed the bishop's banishment. And in order that the Master of the
                  Offices,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n169-5"/> who aided him, might be humiliated, he was commanded to expel
                  him, so that he should be sent to Oasis. And also <persName>Pascasius</persName> the deacon, who was
                  attached to and beloved by <persName>Macedonius</persName>, was arrested (and he wrote, in the presence
                  of the prefect, in the records<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n169-6"/> of the Acts,[#169-7] all his deeds), he
                  and certain monks and others who caused a tumult in the city to prevent the words,
                  <quote>God Who was crucified for us,</quote> being proclaimed there, as they had been
                  proclaimed in the whole jurisdiction of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> from the days of <persName>Eustace</persName> the
                  bishop.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="170"/>
               <p>And to show when and how these things were done, behold I have written down
                  accurately, for the instruction of the readers, the letter of <persName>Simeon</persName> the presbyter
                  and his brethren the monks who were with him, who happened to be at that time in
                  the royal city having come from the East, and who wrote to <persName>Samuel</persName> their
                  archimandrite concerning the expulsion of <persName>Macedonius</persName>, as follows:—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.8">
               <head>Chapter 8</head>
               <head>The eighth chapter of this seventh book tells about the letter that was sent
                  from <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> concerning the expulsion of <persName>Macedonius</persName></head>
               <p><quote>To the virtuous, elect, and God-loving presbyter and archimandrite <persName>Samuel</persName>, and to
                  the presbyters and deacons, together with all the other brethren, from <persName>Simeon</persName> the
                  presbyter, in the royal city, and the brethren who are with him, greeting. After
                  we wrote the former letter to your Holiness concerning all that <persName>Macedonius</persName> did in
                  the monastery of <placeName>Dalmatus</placeName> against the whole truth, God stirred up the spirit of
                  the believing king like a lion to the prey, and he roared, and made the whole
                  faction of the enemies of the truth to tremble; for it is said, <quote>As a watercourse
                  in the hands of the gardener, so is the heart of the king in the hands of the
                  Lord.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n170-1"/> May He Who has not turned away from the prayer of His elect, and
                  Who has not suffered the desire of those who worship man instead of God to come to
                  pass, grant that the matter may receive a righteous fulfilment through your
                  prayers; yea and amen! We testify to you that after Macedonius did that of which
                  we sent<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n170-2"/> information to your Piety, and anathematised those reprobate
                  persons and the accursed Council on the 20th of July, there was on the 22nd (the
                  sixth day of the week)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n170-3"/> a dedication festival at <pb type="page" n="171"
                  />the Martyr Church in the <placeName>Hebdomon</placeName>; and the king himself was present. And neither
                  he nor the queen would receive the oblation from him; on the contrary, he even
                  addressed him in severe terms. But on the 24th (the first day of the week) the
                  monks of this place went in and communicated in the church with <persName>Macedonius</persName>, and
                  the king was vexed with them for going in. And on the 25th (the second day of the
                  week) a few brethren, who seceded from these monks, entered in and went to <persName>Mâr
                  Patrick</persName> the general,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n171-1"/> and gave him a libel to present to the king, saying,
                  <quote>We declare that he celebrated the memory of Nestorius, and that he used to send
                  orders to us, and we also did the same in our monasteries every year.</quote> And they
                  wrote other things against him, testifying that transactions such as these took
                  place in their monasteries. On that same day the king commanded, and the water
                  which supplied the baths was cut off from their monasteries, and only that which
                  they drank was left to them. And also he took away the denarii<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n171-2"/> which they
                  used to receive from the treasury.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n171-3"/> And on the 26th, one of the senators
                  called Romanus went in to the king and gave him a written statement of all the
                  things which were done at the bishop's house; and he said to the king that
                  <persName>Pascasius</persName> the deacon, along with <persName>Macedonius</persName>, was the author of all the mischief;
                  and he said besides, <quote>They have made a certain large book containing extracts from
                  all the heresies, and it is overlaid with gold.</quote> And the king sent for it, and
                  took it to himself, that he might see all its blasphemies. But on the 27th the
                  king convened a Council; and when the patricians went in the king said to them,
                  <quote>Have you not seen what this Jew who is amongst us did, for in my presence and
                  that of your excellencies he did what he did, and he anathematised the accursed
                  Synod and those reprobate persons; and when, to avoid great trouble, we accepted
                  his act, he then went off, and in the monastery of <placeName>Dalmatus</placeName> reversed everything
                  which <pb type="page" n="172"/>he himself had done, and he contradicted the whole
                  truth, and lied unto God and before me and unto you. Is this a fair statement?</quote>
                  And at once <persName>Clementinus</persName> the patrician said before them all, <quote>May God Himself cast
                  him out from his priesthood who has lied unto God!</quote> And forthwith the king
                  commanded the great prefect to go out into the city and bring together all the
                  orthodox who were wounded when they cried out, <quote>Who was crucified for
                  us,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n172-1"/> that he might learn who their assailants were. And the prefect went
                  out and did as he was commanded. And on the 28th he took the names of all the
                  Nestorians who were the life of <persName>Macedonius</persName>, and brought them in to the king; and
                  the king commanded that they should be arrested.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And on the 29th the king assembled all the commanders of the forces and all the
                  officers of the Scholarians<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n172-2"/> and the patricians, and he said to them,
                  <quote>According to my regular custom I wish to give a donative!</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n172-3"/> For so it had
                  been his practice to give it once in five years ever since he became king, at the
                  same time requiring oaths from all the Romans to the effect that they would not
                  act treacherously against the kingdom. But on this occasion he required them to
                  take the oath in the following manner: A copy of the gospel being placed for them,
                  they went in and received five denarii each, and they swore as follows, <quote>By this
                  law of God and by the words which are written in it, we will contend<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n172-4"/> with
                  all our might for the true faith and for the kingdom, and we will not act
                  treacherously either against the truth or the king.</quote> In this manner, indeed, he
                  required them to take the oath, because he heard that <persName>Macedonius</persName> was trying to
                  raise a rebellion against him.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>On the 30th of July the king gave a largess<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n172-5"/> to the whole army. On the
                  same day the presbyters and deacons, who separated from his clergy lest they
                  should be implicated <pb type="page" n="173"/>in his wickedness, presented a
                  libel<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n173-1"/> against <persName>Macedonius</persName> to the king, charging him, in addition to all
                  his other wickedness, with calling his Majesty a Manichaean and a Eutychianist. And
                  on the 31st of July (the first day of the week) they went in to the king's
                  presence with great fear, and found him filled with rage and agitation. And when
                  they had waited a long time, and everyone was watching in fear to see what
                  commands would issue from him, he opened his mouth and began to speak thus, <quote>Do
                  you not know that from my childhood I have been brought up in the faith; have any
                  of you ever seen in me any departure from the truth?</quote> And they said, <quote>Far be it
                  from us, lord.</quote> And at once he rejoined to them,<quote>Since <persName>Macedonius</persName> calls me a
                  Manichaean and a Eutychianist, behold! before God the Judge of all I make my
                  defence, affirming that I neither have held nor do hold any opinion foreign to the
                  faith of the three hundred and eighteen holy fathers, and of the one hundred and
                  fifty; and I confess that One of the Persons of the Trinity, God the Word, came
                  down from heaven, and became incarnate from <persName>Mary</persName> the Theotokos and ever virgin;
                  and He was crucified for us, and He suffered and died; and He rose again in three
                  days, according to His own will; and He is the Judge of the dead and of the
                  living. I adjure you by the Holy Trinity, that if you know anything else in me, or
                  if you are not persuaded of the truth of what I have said, you take this
                  robe<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n173-2"/> and crown off me and burn them in the midst of this city.</quote> And when
                  he said this there was great weeping; and all the patricians cast themselves down
                  before him, and <persName>Patrick</persName> the general<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n173-3"/> said, <quote>God will not forgive, nor will
                  your Majesty and the canons of the Church have mercy on him who has done this.</quote>
                  And the king said, <quote>Everyone, then, who goes to confer with<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n173-4"/> <persName>Macedonius</persName> or
                  to hold communion with him, is thereby alienated from me.</quote> And while they stood
                  before him, he spoke against the Master of the Offices, saying, <quote>The riches and
                  the honour which God gave us were not sufficient, <pb type="page" n="174"/>but we
                  must needs take a bribe in a matter of the life of all men, and we shall lose our
                  own life.</quote> And while he was speaking he looked at the Master of the Offices, who
                  had inflicted many evils upon the believers; and the Lord, forasmuch as He is the
                  Judge of the dead and the living, rewarded him according to his works. And on the
                  same day the king set guards of Romans at the gates of the city and the harbours,
                  lest any of those monks here should come in to the city. And on the first of
                  August <persName>Pascasius</persName> the deacon was arrested, and he went in before the prefect and
                  confessed everything which was done in the bishop's house, saying that <persName>Macedonius</persName>
                  was even trying to raise a rebellion against the king. And on the day after some
                  Nestorians were arrested, and they affirmed that they had some forged<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n174-1"/>
                  books of this heresy; and the prefect sent and brought them to the Praetorium, and
                  he showed them to the king and to the Senate.</quote></p>
               <p><quote>And on the sixth day of the month there was a General Council,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n174-2"/> and the
                  orthodox and the Nestorians who undertook the defence of <persName>Macedonius</persName> came in before
                  them. And they found the king standing, because some bishops belonging to our
                  party had entered. And the king said to these clergy of <persName>Macedonius</persName>, <quote>Why have you
                  come?</quote> and they replied, <quote>If your Majesty commands, your servant will come to your
                     Clemency.</quote> And he said, '<quote></quote>Let him go to those before whom he proclaimed his <!-- [Quote starts but no end] -->
                  wickedness, and who obeyed him; for, at one time, he had a certain ornamented
                  book, and he affirmed it was taken from the fathers, and that they taught two
                  Natures after the Incarnation; and I said to him, <quote>There is no need for you to use
                  this, go and burn it.</quote> And he said to the clergy, <quote>What are the two Natures and
                  the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> which God has overturned from its very foundations? Ye are
                  accursed Jews, I declare to you that there is not one God-fearing man among you
                  who is grieved for what has been done in His Church.</quote> And they went out from his
                  presence in great fear and distress. And the orthodox were <pb type="page" n="175"
                  />loud in his praises. And when the clergy returned to Macedonius they said to
                  him, <quote>The lord of the world has, in the presence of the Senate, anathematised the
                  Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and everyone who says two Natures.</quote> And he replied to them, <quote>I,
                  in my turn, anathematise everyone who does not receive the Synod, and say two
                  Natures.</quote> And his archdeacon cried out, <quote>Far be it from us, then, ever to have any
                  more part or communion with you.</quote></quote></p>
               <p><quote>And on the first day of the week, which was the seventh of the month, the
                  believers came and entered the church, and it was filled from end to end. And when
                  the passage from the apostle was read, all the people began to cry out together,
                  <quote>Let not him who has taken away from the Trinity enter the church; let not him who
                  has blasphemed against the Son of God come in hither; no one wants the Jewish
                  bishop; where <persName>Nestorius</persName> went, there let his disciples also go. Long live the king,
                  the second <persName>Constantine</persName>, the upholder of the faith; the gospel to the throne!</quote> And
                  at that instant the clergy took the gospel and placed it on the throne. And when
                  the clergy saw the whole congregation of the church crying out together, they also
                  showed themselves, and cried out, shaking their stoles,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n175-1"/> and saying, <quote>The
                  victorious king has gained the victory for our Church.</quote> And as soon as they
                  ceased, the great prefect delivered an address<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n175-2"/> to them in the following
                  terms: <quote>We accept your goodwill and your zeal on behalf of the truth; and the lord
                  of the world is, as you know, very solicitous for the preservation of orthodoxy
                  and the peace of all the Churches; and your acclamations on behalf of the true
                  faith we will bring to his hearing.</quote> And when the deacon made the proclamation and
                  did not mention his name, and it was not read in the Diptych, the mysteries were
                  celebrated: and as<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n175-3"/> our Lord willed that he should go out, the king
                  commanded, and his banishment was decreed. And, with the object of
                  humiliating<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n175-4"/> the Master of the Offices, he sent him to expel <pb
                     type="page" n="176"/>him; and he found him in the church, whither he had fled,
                  sitting down, with his head between his knees; and he said to him, <quote>The lord of
                  the world has decreed your banishment</quote>; and the other asked, <quote>Whither?</quote> and he
                  replied, <quote>Where your comrade<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n176-1"/> went.</quote> And the stewards of the Church
                  interposed, saying to him, <quote>We entreat your Lordship, have pity on his old age,
                  and let him not depart in the daytime, lest the people of the city strike him and
                  stone him, but in the evening time let him go.</quote> And when they swore that they
                  would keep him, then he (the Master of the Offices) also left an auxiliary
                  force<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n176-2"/> with them. And they said to him, <quote>The king has commanded you to
                  give up that book of the Synod which you have with you</quote>; and he replied, <quote>I will
                  not give it.</quote> But, being forced to do so, he laid it on the table; and the clergy
                  took it up and gave it to the Master's officer,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n176-3"/> and he brought it to the
                  king. And in the evening of the seventh day of the month the Master of the Offices
                  arrived with a military force<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n176-4"/> and expelled him, and gave him up to those
                  who were appointed to carry him away. And all the orthodox were in great
                  fear.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n176-5"/></p>
               <p><quote>Now, my lord, we have truly informed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n176-6"/> your Holiness of what has
                  occurred,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n176-7"/> and we shall declare to you hereafter whatever the Lord may
                  bring to pass. Pray for us, O elect of God!</quote></p> 
               <p>But the former defence made by the king proves to us that <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName>, the believing
                  doctor, the bishop of <placeName>Hierapolis</placeName>, <pb type="page" n="177"/>who was a zealous man,
                  having learned that <persName>Macedonius</persName> was a heretic, sent a written statement of the true
                  faith to the king (as he had done also in the days of <persName>Zeno</persName>),<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n177-1"/> and it was
                  read before the Senate; and he showed that opinions in opposition to it were held
                  by the school of <persName>Diodorus</persName> and <persName>Theodore</persName>, and by <persName>Nestorius</persName>, their disciple, who was
                  ejected, and by <persName>Theodoret</persName>, and <persName>Hibo</persName>, and <persName>Andrew</persName>, and <persName>John</persName>, and <persName>Aetheric</persName>—the men who
                  set up the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and received the Tome, and cleft asunder the unity
                  of God the Word, Who became incarnate, dividing it into two natures with their
                  properties, by what they taught concerning <persName>Christ</persName> after His Incarnation. And at
                  the same time he (<persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName>) urged the king, saying, <quote>It is right that they should
                  be anathematised by all who make a public boast of their own orthodoxy,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n177-2"/>
                  and of agreeing to the faith of your Majesty.</quote> And when <persName>Macedonius</persName> was required to
                  do this, he anathematised them under compulsion; but after that he used secretly
                  to celebrate their memory in the monastery of <persName>Dalmatus</persName>, as has been written
                  above.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.9">
               <head>Chapter 9</head>
               <head>The ninth chapter of this seventh Book tells about <persName>Timothy</persName> the successor of
                  <persName>Macedonius</persName>, and how in the days of <persName>Anastasius</persName> the king, the words,<quote>Who was
                  crucified for us,</quote> were proclaimedin the royal city<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n177-3"/></head>
               <p>After<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n177-4"/> <persName>Macedonius</persName>, <persName>Timothy</persName> became bishop in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>; and he was a
                  believing man, and his deeds were in conformity with his name, for it means
                  <quote>God-honouring.</quote> And in his days there was one <persName>Marinus</persName> of <placeName>Apamea</placeName>, a vigilant and
                  clever man, well-versed in business, wise and learned, who was, moreover, true in
                  the faith, the friend and confidant of the king, and a chartularius and his
                  counsellor. And when he was <pb type="page" n="178"/>walking in the street or
                  sitting anywhere, he would tell his secretaries<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n178-1"/> to commit in concise form
                  whatever thought he had to writing. And at night also, he had a pen-and-ink
                  stand<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n178-2"/> hanging by his bedside, and a lamp burning by his pillow, so that
                  he could write down his thoughts on a roll; and in the daytime he would tell them
                  to the king, and advise him as to how he should act. And accordingly, as he was
                  from the district of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, all of which ever since the days of <persName>Eustace</persName> the
                  bishop had been so full of zeal that it was the first to proclaim, <quote>Who was
                  crucified for us,</quote> he also vehemently<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n178-3"/> urged and advised King <persName>Anastasius</persName>
                  to do the same. And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n178-4"/> when some heretics heard of his ardour, they went to
                  him together, and said to him, "<quote>You desire and incite men on earth to go beyond
                  the holy hymn of praise which the angels offer to the Trinity, saying, <quote>Holy,
                  Holy, Holy, mighty Lord, of whose praises heaven and earth are full.</quote></quote>
                  Immediately, God the Word Himself, Who in the flesh was crucified for us men,
                  prepared a defence in his mouth to this effect, <quote>The angels, indeed, offer the
                  hymn of praise, which contains their confession to the adorable and co-equal
                  Trinity, rightly, and do not proclaim that He was crucified for them; but we, on
                  the other hand, in the hymn of praise, which contains our confession, rightly say
                  that He was crucified for us men, for He became incarnate from us, and did not
                  invest Himself with the nature of angels.</quote> And so he put them to silence, and he
                  instructed the king, who thereupon commanded that the words, <quote>Who was crucified
                  for us,</quote> should be proclaimed in the royal city as in the district of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. And
                  at the same time a wonderful sign occurred, proving to wise men that <persName>Christ</persName>, Who
                  was crucified in the flesh at <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, was God; namely, an eclipse<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n178-5"/> of
                  the sun, which took place in those days,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n178-6"/> and produced darkness from the
                  sixth hour unto the ninth hour.</p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="179"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.10">
               <head>Chapter 10</head>
               <head>The tenth chapter of this seventh Book gives information respecting the synod
                  which was held at <placeName>Zidon</placeName> in the year five, the eighth hundred and twenty-third year
                  of the Greeks, and of the Antiochenes the five hundred and sixtieth</head>
               <p><persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n179-1"/> a learned man and a Syriac doctor, and zealous in the faith,
                  the bishop of <placeName>Hierapolis</placeName>, in the days of <persName>Zeno</persName> sent a written statement of the
                  faith, and asked <persName>Zeno</persName> some questions about his faith, and received a reply. And it
                  was he who exposed <persName>Calandion</persName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, and ejected him from his See. But he had
                  his suspicions also about <persName>Flavian</persName>, that he was a heretic; and he sent a letter and
                  urgent messengers to King <persName>Anastasius</persName>, begging that a Synod should be held at
                  <placeName>Sidon</placeName>. And the king gave the order, and the Synod assembled in the five hundred
                  and sixtieth year of the Antiochene era.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n179-2"/> And he urged the believing and
                  zealous monks of the East, and <persName>Cosmas</persName> a learned man from the monastery of <persName>Mâr
                  ʿAkiba</persName> at <placeName>Chalcis</placeName>, who was residing in <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, and they drew up a petition and
                  presented it to <persName>Flavian</persName> and to the Council of bishops who were with him at <placeName>Sidon</placeName>.
                  And they wrote, in an able and logical manner, a list of censures in seventy-seven
                  Heads, with many quotations from the holy doctors confirming the censure upon the
                  Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and the Tome of <persName>Leo</persName>, and they presented this also to the Synod,
                  at the same time begging and adjuring the priests to effect reforms, and take
                  stumbling-blocks out of the way of the Church and purge it, by openly
                  anathematising the Synod. But <persName>Flavian</persName> the chief priest and some of the priests who
                  were with him deferred the matter, saying, <quote>We are content with a document
                  anathematising the school of <persName>Diodorus</persName>, the censures of certain persons upon the
                  twelve Heads of <persName>Cyril</persName>, and <persName>Nestorius</persName>, lest we should arouse the sleeping
                  dragon<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n179-3"/> and corrupt many with his poison.</quote> And so the Synod was
                  dissolved.</p>
               <pb type="page" n="180"/>
               <p>But the zeal of <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName> urged the monks again, and they went up to <persName>Anastasius</persName>
                  and informed him of what had occurred in the Synod, and concerning <persName>Flavian</persName>, that
                  he was a heretic; and having received an order for his ejection, and returned to
                  the East, they assembled at <placeName>Antioch</placeName> against him. And some of them were wounded,
                  and others were killed; but nevertheless <persName>Flavian</persName> was ejected from his See. And his
                  successor was <persName>Severus</persName>, a learned and well-tried monk from the monastery of
                  <persName>Theodore</persName> the ex-pleader<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n180-1"/> at <placeName>Gaza</placeName>, who was apokrisiarios at the royal city,
                  and was a confidant and friend of <persName>Probus</persName>, and his kinsmen. This man had previously
                  written the Philalethes, and also he had made a solution of the seven questions of
                  the Diphysites. And he was ready in dispute with the heretics, and he was well
                  known to the king by means of <persName>Probus</persName>; and he was appointed chief priest of
                  <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. And afterwards, when there was a Synod in <placeName>Tyre</placeName>, he joined with <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName>,
                  and the priests of his district, and those of <placeName>Phoenice Libani</placeName>, and <placeName>Arabia</placeName>, and
                  <placeName>Euphratesia</placeName>, and <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName> in expounding the Henotikon of <persName>Zeno</persName>, showing that its
                  effect was to abrogate the Council of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>. And the bishops assembled at <placeName>Tyre</placeName>
                  openly anathematised the Synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> and the Tome. And they wrote to <persName>John</persName>
                  of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> and to <persName>Timothy</persName> of the royal city; and received replies from them and
                  from <persName>Elijah</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, who was eventually ejected, and was succeeded by <persName>John</persName>.
                  And because <persName>Sergius</persName>, a grammarian there, composed shortly afterwards a book of
                  censure upon that Synod, and gave it to the monks from <placeName>Palestine</placeName> who were of his
                  way of thinking, this holy Severus, hearing about it, wrote a refutation of it at
                  great length, and by quotations and proofs derived from the true doctors of the
                  Church he confirmed his doctrine in three volumes, entitled, Against the
                  Grammarian. But the other treatises of this doctor <persName>Severus</persName>, and his commentaries,
                  and his Catechism, and his work, Against <persName>Julian</persName> the Phantasiast, and his wonderful
                  Dogmatic Letter, afford great profit and instruction to the lovers of
                  doctrine.</p> 
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="181"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.11">
               <head>Chapter 11</head>
               <head>The eleventh chapter of this seventh Book tells about the petition which was
                  drawn up by monks of the east and <persName>Cosmas</persName> of <placeName>Chalcis</placeName>, and was presented to the
                  council which met at <placeName>Zidon</placeName> in the days of <persName>Flavian</persName> and <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName> the bishops, in
                  the five hundred and sixtieth year of the Antiochene era</head>
               <p><quote>"</quote>Before all things we give thanks to <persName>Christ</persName>, Who is God over all, and we also <!-- [Quote starts but no end] -->
                  thank our merciful <persName>Christ</persName>-loving king, who has aroused you all to zeal for
                  religion, and called this your holy Council to one meeting place, in the name of
                  one only <persName>Christ</persName> the Son of God, that in Him you may bring all men together to the
                  one faith, which the Holy Scriptures have delivered and the fathers have ever
                  kept, standing steadfastly in one mind, and being united and agreeing together in
                  one good man,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n181-1"/> and teaching all men the divine doctrine through the Holy
                  Spirit, Who spoke by them. For our Lord has accounted you to be worthy,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n181-2"/>
                  and chosen you at this time for the sake of the unity of his holy Churches, not
                  that you should make a new faith for them; because that written definition, which
                  was made by the three hundred and eighteen holy fathers who assembled at <placeName>Nicea</placeName>, is
                  sufficient for the affirmation of the Holy Scriptures; but that you should build
                  up<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n181-3"/> the faith which has always existed, and which many persons have rashly
                  sought to destroy, speaking <quote>not from the mouth of the Lord,</quote> as the
                  prophet<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n181-4"/> says, but <quote>from their own belly,</quote> and by their wicked artifices
                  they have severed from one another those who in the simplicity of their hearts
                  kept the tradition of the holy fathers and were united together in the true faith.
                  For <persName>Christ</persName> is He, O holy men! Who is divided by them; and, therefore, as long as
                  He is denied, it is not possible for the Church ever to come to any <pb
                     type="page" n="182"/>agreement; seeing that it is rent asunder by these persons
                  through the inventions of different words. For it is written, <quote>No kingdom that is
                  divided against itself shall stand</quote>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-1"/> and again, <quote>If ye bite and devour
                  one another, take heed lest ye be consumed one of another.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-2"/> Since, then,
                  we are one body in <persName>Christ</persName>, and we are members of His members, according to the
                  word of the divine apostle,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-3"/> we draw near to your Holinesses with
                  confidence as to pastors, entreating you to keep the true faith for the whole
                  world, without spot, like the fair dove spoken of in the Song of Songs; and that
                  you separate it from all heresies which have the outward appearance of religion,
                  and stand around it like queens and concubines and damsels, and are anxious to
                  associate and to be one and the same with it, and through it to be received as
                  true. But by doing this you shall receive a reward, and you shall hear the Lord
                  saying, <quote>Him that confesses Me before men, will I confess before My Father Who is
                  in heaven.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-4"/> Separate, then, as stewards of the divine words, between the
                  pure and the corrupt, as He says;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-5"/> and cast out those who mingle<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-6"/>
                  the tares with the pure wheat, and their evil doctrine along with them, for He
                  says, <quote>Put away the evil-doer from the congregation, and victory shall go forth
                  with it.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-7"/></p>
               <p><quote>Now, though what has been said is manifest and well known,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-8"/> it was
                  necessary to explain it above and prove it clearly, even as the holy fathers
                  agreeing in one true faith bound all men together in one concord. But the heretics
                  have mingled lawless wranglings with the words of the holy fathers, and
                  confound<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-9"/> with them schismatical<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-10"/> impieties, and have separated
                  the holy Churches; whom the prophet rebuked, saying, <quote>Thy tavern-keepers<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-11"/>
                  mingle water with wine.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182-12"/></p>
               <pb type="page" n="183"/>
               <p>And so the petition goes on, and has many quotations from the fathers in proof of
                  the seventy-seven censures upon the Council of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.12">
               <head>Chapter 12</head>
               <head>The twelfth chapter, which tells about the synodthat was held in <placeName>Tyre</placeName>, in the
                  days of <persName>Severus</persName> and <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName> the doctors, and the bishops who were with them, who
                  expressly and openly anathematised the synod and tome</head>
               <p>The twelfth chapter, which tells about the synod that was held in <placeName>Tyre</placeName>, in the days
                  of <persName>Severus</persName> and <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName> the doctors, and the bishops who were with them, who
                  expressly and openly anathematised the synod and tome</p>
               <p>Now <persName>Severus</persName>, who succeeded <persName>Flavian</persName> in <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, was a learned man by reading the
                  wisdom of the Greeks, and he was an ascetic and a well-tried monk, and he was also
                  zealous for the true faith and well-versed in it, and he had read the Holy
                  Scriptures with understanding and the expositions made by the ancient authors who
                  were disciples of the apostles, namely, <persName>Hierotheus</persName>, and <persName>Dionysius</persName>, and <persName>Titus</persName>, and
                  also <persName>Timothy</persName>; and after them <persName>Ignatius</persName>, and <persName>Clement</persName>, and <persName>Irenaeus</persName>, and such writers
                  as <persName>Gregory</persName>, and <persName>Basil</persName>, and <persName>Athanasius</persName>, and <persName>Julius</persName>, and the other chief priests and
                  true doctors of the holy Church. And like a <quote>scribe who is instructed for the
                  kingdom of heaven, who brings from his treasures things old and new,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n183-1"/> so
                  also he had thoroughly studied many histories, and they were rooted in his mind
                  clearly to be seen.</p>
               <p>And this <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName>, also, was a Syriac doctor, and he had diligently studied the
                  works existing in that language, and besides these he was well-versed in the
                  doctrine of the school of <persName>Diodorus</persName> and <persName>Theodore</persName> and the others; but, nevertheless,
                  as his actions proved to the wise, this old and zealous man was truly a
                  believer.</p>
               <p>These men gave full and clear information to King <persName>Anastasius</persName>, who rejected the
                  Council of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> with all his heart; and he commanded that, for the purpose of
                  effecting needed reforms, a Synod of Orientals should be assembled at <pb
                     type="page" n="184"/><placeName>Tyre</placeName>. And it was assembled, consisting of the bishops of
                  the districts of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, and <placeName>Apamea</placeName>, and <placeName>Euphratesia</placeName>, and <placeName>Osrhoene</placeName>, and
                  <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>, and <placeName>Arabia</placeName>, and <placeName>Phoenice Libani</placeName>. And, making the true faith clear, he
                  (i.e. <persName>Severus</persName>) expounded the Henotikon of <persName>Zeno</persName> as meaning the abrogation of the
                  transactions of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName>; and he openly there anathematised the addition which it
                  had made to the faith. And the bishops in Council assembled, along with <persName>Severus</persName>
                  and <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName> the believers and doctors who zealously stood at their head,
                  proclaimed the whole truth; and they wrote letters of agreement both to <persName>John</persName> of
                  <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and to <persName>Timothy</persName> of the royal city, and also <persName>Elijah</persName> of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> at that
                  time assented to the letters, although shortly after he was ejected, and was
                  succeeded by <persName>John</persName>. Consequently the priests were again united in this concord of
                  the faith, with the exception of the see of <placeName>Rome</placeName>. (And the reason of this
                  exception was) that <persName>Alimeric</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n184-1"/> was the anti-Caesar there, and he had
                  rebelled against <persName>Anastasius</persName> in the Western region, and he held the kingdom in
                  <placeName>Rome</placeName>. And he was a warlike man; and in his day he rendered great service to the
                  people of <placeName>Italy</placeName>, by delivering them from the barbarians and Goths. And he also
                  conferred many benefits upon his city, <placeName>Rome</placeName>, erecting buildings and granting
                  privileges.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n184-2"/> However, he was a Diphysite, having been converted from the
                  heresy of <persName>Arius</persName>. Consequently there could not be any assent on the part of
                  Symmachus and his successor <persName>Hormisda</persName>, the chief priests of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, to what was done
                  in the East. And zealous persons can gain information respecting these matters
                  from the letter which <persName>Akhsʾnoyo</persName> wrote after his expulsion.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n184-3"/></p>
            </div>
            <pb type="page" n="185"/>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.13">
               <head>Chapter 13</head>
               <head>The thirteenth chapter of this Book tells about <persName>Ariadne</persName> the queen, who died, and
                  how the tyrant <persName>Vitalian</persName> came upon the scene, whotook<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n185-1"/> <persName>Hypatius</persName> prisoner in
                  war</head>
               <p><persName>Ariadne</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n185-2"/> the queen, the wife of <persName>Zeno</persName>, was allied to this <persName>Anastasius</persName> after
                  the death of her husband, and she made him king; and she held the kingdom for many
                  years, as many as forty, in the state of first and second marriage; and she died
                  in the year eight hundred and twenty-four of the Greeks. And her husband remained
                  on, keeping the holy truth; even though he was advanced in years, and he was
                  occupied with the business of his kingdom.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n185-3"/> And he had anxiety and
                  trouble, because of one <persName>Vitalian</persName> a Goth, who was a general,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n185-4"/> and warlike,
                  and courageous and daring, and cunning in war. To this man many savage people
                  attached themselves; and he gave them gold with a liberal hand, and, besides, they
                  enriched themselves with the spoil which they took from the dominions of
                  <persName>Anastasius</persName>. And when he had been for a long time at peace, <persName>Vitalian</persName> broke his
                  word; and he rebelled and injured the Roman dominions, and oppressed the kingdom,
                  and treated it with contempt; and he haughtily advanced to the very suburbs of
                  <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> without any fear. And at one time troops, with <persName>Hypatius</persName> at their
                  head, were sent against him by <persName>Anastasius</persName>; and they were routed by him, and
                  <persName>Hypatius</persName> was taken prisoner; and he treated him with great indignity, and to
                  insult him he even shut him up in a pig-sty.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n185-5"/> And upon one occasion he put
                  him to open shame, carrying him about through the army in the most humiliating
                  fashion, because <persName>Hypatius</persName> once took the wife of this <persName>Vitalian</persName> prisoner and treated
                  her insultingly. And in consequence of this <persName>Vitalian</persName>'s indignation against him was
                  very strong. For in the impetuosity of his youth this <persName>Hypatius</persName> was carnal and
                  wanton in lust after women. And at last he was ransomed by a large <pb type="page"
                     n="186"/>sum of gold that was sent for him, and he returned from captivity with
                  <persName>Vitalian</persName>, possessing the wisdom that results from punishment.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186-1"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="7.14">
               <head>Chapter 14</head>
               <head>The fourteenth chapter of the seventh Book tells about <persName>Timothy</persName>, who died, and
                  whose successor was <persName>John</persName>; and of some people who came to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> for the
                  festival, and they were possessed by demons, who barked at the Cross during the
                  dedication<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186-2"/></head>
               <p><persName>Timothy</persName>, having lived six or seven years, died<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186-3"/> in the year
                  eleven.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186-4"/> And <persName>John</persName> succeeded him. And in the year in which <persName>Anastasius</persName> the
                  king died, there were some Egyptians and Alexandrians and men from beyond the
                  <placeName>Jordan</placeName>, Edomites and Arabians, who came to the festival of the dedication<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186-5"/>
                  which is the making of the Cross at <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, which was held on the fourteenth of
                  September; and demons took possession of many of them, and they barked at the
                  Cross, and then ceased and went out. And this caused anxiety and distress to the
                  prudent; they did not, however, accurately<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186-6"/> understand the reason, until
                  the event occurred, and it signified the wrangling about the faith, and the
                  stumbling-block afterwards caused thereby. This God made known beforehand, that we
                  might consider the temptation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186-7"/> and be proved by it;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186-8"/> and by our
                  enduring it and persevering in the faith we might have joy; as <persName>James</persName> the apostle
                  says, <quote>Let it be all joy to you, my brethren, when you enter into divers and many
                  temptations; for you know that the trial of faith procures patience for you. But
                  let patience have its perfect work, that you may be complete and perfect, wanting
                  nothing.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186-9"/></p>
               <pb type="page" n="187"/>
               <p>Now <persName>Anastasius</persName> died on the ninth day of July. And his successor was <persName>Justin</persName>, who
                  went down with the army<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n187-1"/> in company with the generals,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n187-2"/> at the
                  time that <persName>Kawad</persName>, king of the Persians, came to <placeName>Amida</placeName>. And he was a handsome old
                  man with white hair, but he was unlearned;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n187-3"/> and he shared<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n187-4"/> in the
                  opinions of the people of Rome respecting the faith, because he belonged to that
                  jurisdiction, being from the camp<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n187-5"/> called <placeName>Mauriana</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n187-6"/> the
                  water<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n187-7"/> of which is bad, and turns to blood when it is boiled.</p>
               <p>There is in this Book a period of twenty-seven years, three months and a half, the
                  lifetime of <persName>Anastasius</persName>.</p>
            </div> 
            <div type="chapter" n="7.15">
               <head>Chapter 15</head>
               <head>The fifteenth chapter of the seventh Book, stating who were the chief priests in
                  the days of <persName>Anastasius</persName> the king</head>
               <p>Now the following were the chief priests in the days of <persName>Anastasius</persName>. Of the
                  Diphysites:—Of <placeName>Rome</placeName>—<persName>Felix</persName>, and <persName>Symmachus</persName> his successor, and <persName>Hormisda</persName> who is still
                  living.</p>
               <p>Of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, the believers—<persName>Athanasius</persName>, and <persName>John</persName> his successor, and again another
                  <persName>John</persName>, and Dioscorus who now occupies the See.</p>
               <p>In <placeName>Antioch</placeName>—<persName>Flavian</persName> who was ejected, and <persName>Severus</persName> the believer.</p>
               <p>In <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>—<persName>Euphemius</persName>, and <persName>Macedonius</persName> who was ejected, and <persName>Timothy</persName> the
                  believer, and <persName>John</persName> his successor, who received the Synod in the beginning of the
                  reign of <persName>Justin</persName> and died shortly after, and <persName>Epiphanius</persName> was his successor.</p>
               <p>Of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>—<persName>Sallust</persName>, and <persName>Elijah</persName> his successor who was ejected, and <persName>John</persName> who
                  received the Synod in the days of <persName>Justin</persName>, and <persName>Peter</persName> his successor.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n147-1">I.e. of the Indiction = A.D. 512.</note>
            <note xml:id="n148-1">The text has<!--  Add Syriac  -->, which cannot be translated; for 
               it I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, which is almost identical in meaning with the word
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->. See ch. 14, where the full expression is
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>and then were silent and went out.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n148-2">Called <persName>Epiphanius</persName> in the Introduction to this Book.</note>
            <note xml:id="n148-3">Here begins an extract in Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n148-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->; the reading of the Cod. Rom. is
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> which may be rendered <quote>his accession.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n148-4">The words in brackets are not in the Syriac, but they must be
               understood.</note>
            <note xml:id="n149-1"> Or, <quote>with liberty to treat on behalf of his city</quote>; the Syriac is
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐν παῤῥησία</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n149-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>skilled in dialectics.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n149-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n149-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">χάρτης</foreign>, perhaps the Henotikon. Cod.
               Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, and Mai translates, <quote>quae Zeno pro Christianis
               constituerat. </quote> Here the extract in Cod. Rom. ends.</note>
            <note xml:id="n150-1">I.e. by <persName>Euphemius</persName>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n150-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., <!--  Add Syriac  -->, L., read
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n150-3">Or, <quote>great influence</quote>  ; the word is <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e.
               <foreign xml:lang="grc">παῤῥησία</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n150-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->; see p. 199, note 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n151-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i,e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπαρχίας</foreign> (meaning <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπαρχίας</foreign>).</note>
            <note xml:id="n151-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐκβόησις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n151-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, (<!--  Add Syriac  -->), i.e.
               ἀναφορά.</note>
            <note xml:id="n151-4"><quote>Arab,</quote> a name applied to certain districts in
               Mesopotamia.</note>
            <note xml:id="n151-5">501.</note>
            <note xml:id="n151-6">This and the three following chapters are contained in Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n151-7">Mich. fol. 156 v ff.; Greg. p. 75 ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n152-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n152-2">Cod. Rom. has<!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n152-3">There is a <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  --> in
               the MS., which L. does not print.</note>
            <note xml:id="n153-1">The text has merely <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not stating whether it
               was the first or the second Theshri; but from <persName>Josh</persName>. Styl. 50 we know that it was the
               first, i.e. October.</note>
            <note xml:id="n153-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, rams' heads.</note>
            <note xml:id="n153-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, roofs of skin, testudines.</note>
            <note xml:id="n153-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, lit. <quote>mule.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n153-5">Read <!--  Add Syriac  -->] for <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n153-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, perhaps from <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               (σαράβαλλα), <quote>loose trousers</quote>; but see p. 229, note 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n153-7"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">κόδρα</foreign>, quadra.</note>
            <note xml:id="n153-8"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n153-9"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀκκούβιτον</foreign>, accubitum.</note>
            <note xml:id="n154-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>pomp</quote>. Cod. Rom. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>arms.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n154-2">So Cod. Rom. <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> of
               MS. and L.'s text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n154-3">Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n154-4">There appears to be some confusion in both texts; by a few slight
               alterations it might be made to yield this meaning, <quote>and consumed the wood of the
               props, and immediately it was reduced to ashes; and the rest of the mound which
               escaped the violence of the fire was loosened and fell.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n154-5">Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>in the service.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n155-1">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n155-2">So the text; but it may be corrupt, and the reference be to the
               invasion of <quote>ʿArab</quote> by locusts (see ch. 2).</note>
            <note xml:id="n155-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  --> (east), as
               L. prints it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n155-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἡγεμών</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n156-1">So Cod. Rom. The other text has <!--  Add Syriac  --> for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, meaning, <quote>as he himself related the sight.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n156-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mr. Brooks points out that in Jo. Eph., de
               Beat. Orient, 58 (Land, Anecd. Syr. ii. p. 279), this word is definitely identified
               with <quote>Anzetenian</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n156-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. See <persName>Payne Smith</persName>’s <persName>John</persName> of <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, 121,
               note.</note>
            <note xml:id="n156-4">I.e. <quote>the accused,</quote> from <foreign xml:lang="grc">κατηγορέω</foreign>; after <persName>Kutrigo</persName> Cod. Rom. has
               the words <!--  Add Syriac  -->. The meaning of <!--  Add Syriac  --> is uncertain;
               <persName>Dean Payne Smith</persName> suggests <foreign xml:lang="grc">λῃστρικός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n156-5">For <!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., Cod. Rom. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n157-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πεδατοῦρα</foreign>, the walking space in a
               fortification.</note>
            <note xml:id="n157-2">Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n157-3">Inserting <!--  Add Syriac  --> with Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n157-4">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               which L. omits.</note>
            <note xml:id="n157-5">This translation is conjectural. From the text it would rather
               seem as if <!--  Add Syriac  --> was an adjective qualifying <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               and meaning <quote>formidable</quote>; but the Lexicons give no such word.</note>
            <note xml:id="n158-1">Cod. Rom. and Mich. add <quote>of the Nazarenes.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n158-2"><!--  Add Syriac  --> i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὕπατος</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n159-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n159-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>mercy.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n159-3">For <!--  Add Syriac  -->, which cannot be translated, I adopt Mr.
               <persName>Brooks</persName>' suggestion, and read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n160-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with
               Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n160-2">Read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod. Rom., for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n161-1">Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <quote>the country of the
               Persians.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n161-2">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> of L.'s text (<!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               MS.) read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, with Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n161-3">For <!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., Cod. Rom. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n161-4">Mich. fol. 158 v.</note>
            <note xml:id="n161-5">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>butter</quote>; for it I read
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n161-6">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               <quote>pigeons</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n162-1"><!--  Add Syriac  --> perhaps means <quote>the fold of the
               shepherds.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n162-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS. and Cod. Rom., not
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n162-3">After <!--  Add Syriac  --> Cod. Rom. inserts the words
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>the Marzbans who were there became cautious, and would not
               allow.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n163-1">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               <quote>decorated</quote> or <quote>armed</quote>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n163-2">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> read <!--  Add Syriac  --> with Cod.
               Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n163-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπογραφάς</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀπογραφάς</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n163-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n163-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">βουλευτής</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n164-1">Dan. v. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n164-2">Mich. fol. 158 r.</note>
            <note xml:id="n164-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, Cod. Rom., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n164-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n165-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">μηχανικούς</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n165-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">σκάριφος</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n165-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. dux.</note>
            <note xml:id="n165-4">Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n165-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">σάρκα εἱμαρμένη</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n165-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, without synopsis.</note>
            <note xml:id="n165-7"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, Cod. Rom. for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n166-1">So Cod. Rom. The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> (see p. 13, note
               6), <quote>showed himself diligent in attendance there.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n166-2"> 1⅓ obols.</note>
            <note xml:id="n166-3">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               which might perhaps be rendered <quote>were very active.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n166-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. δημόσιον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n166-5">So the MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n167-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. λογοθεσίαι.</note>
            <note xml:id="n167-2"><persName>Thomas</persName>, bishop of <placeName>Amida</placeName>, seems to be the subject of this sentence,
               not the king.</note>
            <note xml:id="n167-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ξενοδοχάριος</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n167-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n167-5">Reading <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n167-6">Here Cod. Rom. inserts the words <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>which was
               to be built in the city.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n168-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">χωρεπίσκοπος</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n168-2">540.</note>
            <note xml:id="n168-3">I read <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  -->. However,
               as both MSS. have the latter, it may be that we should render it <quote>Ahlaf.</quote> </note>
            <note xml:id="n168-4">Job xxxii. 19 (Syr.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n168-5">St. Luke xii. 2, 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n169-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not<!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n169-2">See p. 245, note 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n169-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">σιλέντιον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n169-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n169-5">Text, <quote>Magisterian.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n169-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπομνήματα</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n169-7"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρᾶξις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n170-1">Prov. xxi. 1. The words <!--  Add Syriac  --> are not in the
               Peshitto.</note>
            <note xml:id="n170-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n170-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>the preparation.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n171-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηλάτης</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n171-2">The word <!--  Add Syriac  --> in the text is manifestly wrong; it
               should be written <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">δηνάριον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n171-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ταμιεῖον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n172-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, <foreign xml:lang="grc">σταυρώθεις δι’ ἡμᾶς</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n172-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., for <!--  Add Syriac  --> L. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">σχολάριος</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n172-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. donativum. <persName>Payne Smith</persName>’s <persName>John</persName> of
               <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, p. 185, note.</note>
            <note xml:id="n172-4">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, which is
               most probably the reading of the MS., here somewhat rubbed.</note>
            <note xml:id="n172-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ῥόγας</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n173-1"><!--  Add Syriac  --> here is an evident mistake for
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">λίβελλον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n173-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">χλαμύς</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n173-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηλάτης</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n173-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">συντυχία</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n174-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πλαστά</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n174-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">σιλέντιον</foreign> κομβέντον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n175-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὠράρια αὐτῶν, ὠράριον</foreign> =
               orarium.</note>
            <note xml:id="n175-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">προσφώνησις</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n175-3">Jo. Eph. ap. <quote>Dion</quote>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n175-4">So the MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->; there is a mistake in L.'s
               text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n176-1">Probably <persName>Euphemius</persName>, who was also banished to <placeName>Euchaita</placeName>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n176-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">βοήθεια</foreign>. <quote>Dion</quote>.
               <!--  Add Syriac  --></note>
            <note xml:id="n176-3"><quote>Magistrian</quote> an attendant upon the Master of the Offices. The
               whole passage is a troublesome one, and I am much indebted to <persName>M. Nau</persName>, who has
               published an analysis of the unedited parts of the Chronicle attributed to <persName>Dionysius</persName>
               of <placeName>Tellmahrè</placeName>, and who, through Mr. <persName>Brooks</persName>, kindly supplied a MS. extract from fol.
               147 of the account of the expulsion of <persName>Macedonius</persName>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n176-4">The corresponding expression in the Chronicle of <quote><persName>Dionysius</persName></quote> is
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>a large auxiliary force.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n176-5">In Chron. <quote>Dion</quote>. <!--  Add Syriac  --> (sic)
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>and it (or he) caused great trouble in the whole Church of
               the orthodox.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n176-6"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n176-7"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n177-1">Assem., B. O. vol. ii. p. 34.</note>
            <note xml:id="n177-2">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> before <!--  Add Syriac  -->,
               which L. omits.</note>
            <note xml:id="n177-3">This chap. is in Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n177-4">Mich. fol. 156 r.</note>
            <note xml:id="n178-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">νοτάριος</foreign>. Cod. Rom. has
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>to preserve it.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n178-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">καλαμάριον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n178-3"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, see p. 13, notee 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n178-4">Greg. H. E. i. p. 185.</note>
            <note xml:id="n178-5">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> we must read <!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e.
               ἔκλειψις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n178-6">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->. Omit <!--  Add Syriac  --> with Cod.
               Rom. and L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n179-1">Mich. fol. 160 r ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n179-2">512.</note>
            <note xml:id="n179-3">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->; there is a mistake in L.'s
               text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n180-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. I have taken it as the Syriacised form of
               <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀπὸ δικανικῶν</foreign>; but I give this explanation with diffidence. The word
               <!--  Add Syriac  --> = <foreign xml:lang="grc">δικανικός</foreign>, is found in <placeName>Leben</placeName> des Severus, p. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n181-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->. Mich. has <quote>in one good work,</quote> reading
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n181-2">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n181-3">For <!--  Add Syriac  --> I read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n181-4">Jer. xxiii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-1">St. Mark iii. 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-2">Gal. v. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-3">Rom. xii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-4">St. Matt. X. 32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-5">Mal. iii. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-6">The MS. has <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L. prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-7">This is probably a general reference to <persName>Josh</persName>. vii. rather than an
               exact quotation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-8"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-9"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.
               prints.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-10">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-11"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182-12">Isa. i. 22. The rendering in the Peshitto is remarkable, and no
               doubt suggested the above: it is <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n183-1">Matt. xiii. 52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n184-1"><quote>Theodoric, called <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁ Οὐαλαμήρον</foreign>, hence the form above</quote>
               (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n184-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. προνόμια.</note>
            <note xml:id="n184-3">Cf. p. 207, and note 4 there.</note>
            <note xml:id="n185-1">MS. <!--  Add Syriac  -->, not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as L.</note>
            <note xml:id="n185-2">Here begins an extract in Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n185-3">Here an extract in Cod. Rom. ends.</note>
            <note xml:id="n185-4"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>. For <!--  Add Syriac  -->
               read <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n186-1">Or literally, <quote>And punishment is wisdom.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n186-2">This chap. is in Cod. Rom.</note>
            <note xml:id="n186-3">Cod. Rom. has the word <!--  Add Syriac  -->; it is omitted in the
               MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n186-4">518.</note>
            <note xml:id="n186-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐγκαινία</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n186-6">Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> here. The other reading,
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>recently,</quote> could hardly be made to give sense.</note>
            <note xml:id="n186-7">So Cod. Rom. The MS. has <quote>the event.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n186-8">So Cod. Rom. <!--  Add Syriac  -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n186-9">Jas. i. 2-4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n187-1"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐξέρκετον</foreign>, or exercitus.</note>
            <note xml:id="n187-2"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n187-3">Mai takes <!--  Add Syriac  --> as part. from
               <!--  Add Syriac  -->, <quote>to shave,</quote> and translates <quote>prolixo capillo</quote>; but Jo. Mal. p.
               410, has <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁλοπόλιος, εὔμορφο… ἀγράμματος</foreign> (Brooks).</note>
            <note xml:id="n187-4">Cod. Rom. has <!--  Add Syriac  --> for <!--  Add Syriac  --> of
               MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n187-5"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">κάστρα</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n187-6">Or Bederiana, as Mai writes here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n187-7"><!--  Add Syriac  -->, MS., not <!--  Add Syriac  -->, as
               L.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
