<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Epistle to Polycarp</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Epistles of Ignatius after the Syriac Version</title>
            <author>Ignatius of Antioch</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Epistles of Ignatius after the Syriac Version.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 11/12/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Ante-Nicene_Christian_Library/Epistle_to_Polycarp_(Syriac_version)"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Ante-Nicene_Christian_Library/Epistle_to_Polycarp_(Syriac_version)
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The Epistle of <persName>Ignatius</persName> to <persName>Polycarp</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/></head>
         <salute><persName>Ignatius</persName>, who is [also called] <persName>Theophorus</persName>, to <persName>Polycarp</persName>, bishop of <placeName>Smyrna</placeName>, or
            rather, who has as his own bishop God the Father, and our Lord Jesus Christ: [wishes]
            abundance of happiness.</salute>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <head>Chapter 1</head> 
            <p>Because thy mind is acceptable to me, inasmuch as it is established in God, as on a
               rock which is immoveable, I glorify God the more exceedingly that I have been counted
               worthy of [seeing] thy face, which I longed after in God. Now I beseech thee, by the
               grace with which thou art clothed, to add [speed] to thy course, and that thou ever
               pray for all men that they may be saved, and that thou demand<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> things which are
               befitting, with all assiduity both of the flesh and spirit. Be studious of unity,
               than which nothing is more precious. Bear with all men, even as our Lord beareth with
               thee. Show patience<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> with all men in love, as [indeed] thou doest. Be stedfast in
               prayer. Ask for more understanding than that which thou [already] hast. Be watchful,
               as possessing a ​spirit which sleepeth not. Speak with every man according to the
               will of God. Bear the infirmities of all men as a perfect athlete; for where the
               labour is great, the gain is also great.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <head>Chapter 2</head>
            <p>If thou lovest the good disciples only, thou hast no grace; [but] rather subdue those
               that are evil by gentleness. All [sorts of] wounds are not healed by the same
               medicine. Mitigate [the pain of] cutting<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> by tenderness. Be wise as the serpent in
               everything, and innocent, with respect to those things which are requisite, even as
               the dove. For this reason thou art [composed] of both flesh and spirit, that thou
               mayest entice<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> those things which are visible before thy face, and mayest ask, as
               to those which are concealed from thee, that they [too] may be revealed to thee, in
               order that thou be deficient in nothing, and mayest abound in all gifts. The time
               demands, even as a pilot does a ship, and as one who stands exposed to the tempest
               does a haven, that thou shouldst be worthy of God. Be thou watchful as an athlete of
               God. That which is promised to us is life eternal, which cannot be corrupted, of
               which things thou art also persuaded. In everything I will be instead<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> of thy soul,
               and my bonds which thou hast loved.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <head>Chapter 3</head>
            <p>Let not those who seem to be somewhat, and teach strange doctrines, strike thee with
               apprehension; but stand thou in the truth, as an athlete<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> who is smitten, for it is
               [the part] of a great athlete to be smitten, and [yet] conquer. More especially is it
               fitting that we should bear everything for the ​sake of God, that He also may bear
               us. Be [still] more diligent than thou yet art. Be discerning of the times. Look for
               Him that is above the times, Him who has no times, Him who is invisible, Him who for
               our sakes became visible, Him who is impalpable, Him who is impassible, Him who for
               our sakes suffered, Him who endured everything in every form for our sakes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <head>Chapter 4</head>
            <p>Let not the widows be overlooked; on account of<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> our Lord be thou their guardian,
               and let nothing be done without thy will; also do thou nothing without the will of
               God, as indeed thou doest not. Stand rightly. Let there be frequent<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/> assemblies:
               ask every man [to them] by his name. Despise not slaves, either male or female; but
               neither let them be contemptuous, but let them labour the more as for the glory of 
               <pb n="100"/>God, that they may be counted worthy of a more precious freedom, which is of God. Let <!-- [page goes from page 99 to 100 is the n a 100 or a 99?] -->
               them not desire to be set free out of the common [fund], lest they be found the
               slaves of lusts.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <head>Chapter 5</head>
            <p>Flee wicked arts; but all the more discourse regarding them. Speak to my sisters,
               that they love in our Lord, and that their husbands be sufficient for them in the
               flesh and spirit. Then, again, charge my brethren in the name of our Lord <persName>Jesus
               Christ</persName>, that they love their wives, as our Lord His church. If any man is able in
               power to continue in purity,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/> to the honour of the flesh of our Lord, let him
               continue so without boasting; if he boasts, he is undone; if he become known apart
               from the bishop, he has destroyed himself.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> It is becoming, therefore, to men and
               women who marry, that they marry with the counsel of the bishop, that ​the marriage
               may be in our Lord, and not in lust. Let everything, therefore, be [done] for the
               honour of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <head>Chapter 6</head>
            <p>Look ye to the bishop, that God also may look upon you. I will be instead of the
               souls of those who are subject to the bishop, and the presbyters, and the deacons;
               with them may I have a portion in the presence of God! Labour together with one
               another, act as athletes<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12"/> together, run together, suffer together, sleep together,
               rise together. As stewards of God, and of His household,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> and His servants, please
               Him and serve Him, that ye may receive from Him the wages [promised]. Let none of you
               be rebellious. Let your baptism be to you as armour, and faith as a spear, and love
               as a helmet, and patience as a panoply. Let your treasures be your good works, that
               ye may receive the gift of God, as is just. Let your spirit be long-suffering towards
               each other with meekness, even as God [is] towards you. As for me, I rejoice in you
               at all times.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <head>Chapter 7</head>
            <p>The Christian has not power over himself, but is [ever] ready to be subject to
               God.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/></p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <head>Chapter 8</head>
            <p>I salute him who is reckoned worthy to go to Antioch in my stead, as I commanded
               thee.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/></p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n1">The inscription varies in each of the three Syriac
               mss., being in the first, <title>The Epistle of my lord <persName>Ignatius</persName> the bishop</title>;
               in the second, <title>The Epistle of <persName>Ignatius</persName></title>; and in the third, <title>The
                  Epistle of <persName>Ignatius</persName>, bishop of Antioch</title>.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n2">For <quote>vindicate thy place</quote> in the Greek.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n3">Literally, <quote>draw out thy spirit.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n4">Cureton observes, as one alternative here, that <quote>the
               Syrian translator seems to have read <foreign xml:lang="grc">παράξυσμα</foreign>, for <foreign xml:lang="grc">παροξυσμοὺς</foreign>.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n5">Or, <quote>flatter,</quote> probably meaning to <quote>deal gently
               with.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n6">Thus the Syriac renders <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀντίψυχον</foreign> in the Greek.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n7">The Greek has <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄκμων</foreign>, <quote>an anvil.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n8">The Greek has <foreign xml:lang="grc">μετά</foreign>, <quote>after.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n9">Or, <quote>constant,</quote> <quote>regular.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n10">i.e. <quote>in celibacy.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n11">Or, <quote>corrupted himself.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n12">Literally, <quote>make the contest.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n13">Literally, <quote>sons of His house.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n14">These are the only parts of chaps, vii. and viii. in
               the Greek that are represented in the Syriac.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

