<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Epistle to the Ephesians</title> 
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Epistles of Ignatius after the Syriac Version</title>
            <author><persName>Ignatius</persName> of <placeName>Antioch</placeName></author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
            <p><ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Ante-Nicene_Christian_Library/Epistle_to_the_Ephesians_(Syriac_version)"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Ante-Nicene_Christian_Library/Epistle_to_the_Ephesians_(Syriac_version)
                  </ref><ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative
                  Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The Second Epistle of <persName>Ignatius</persName>: To the Ephesians<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/></head> 
         <salute><persName>Ignaitus</persName>, who is [also called] <persName>Theophorus</persName>, to the church which is blessed in the
            greatness of God the Father, and perfected; to her who was selected<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> from eternity,
            that she might be at all times for glory, which abideth, and is unchangeable, and is
            perfected and chosen in the purpose of truth by the will of the Father of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>
            our God; to her who is worthy of happiness; to her who is at Ephesus, in <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>,
            in joy which is unblameable: [wishes] abundance of happiness.</salute>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <head>Chapter 1</head>
            <p>Inasmuch as your name, which is greatly beloved, is acceptable to me in God, [your
               name] which ye have acquired by nature, through a right and just will, and also by
               the faith and love of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> our Saviour, and ye are imitators of God, and are
               fervent in the blood of God, and have speedily completed a work congenial to you;
               [for] when ye heard that I was bound,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> so as to be able to do nothing for the sake
               of the common name and hope (and I hope, through your prayers, that I may be devoured
               by beasts at Rome, so that by means of this of which I have been accounted worthy, I
               may be endowed with strength to be a disciple of God), ye were diligent to come and
               see me. Seeing, then, that we ​have become acquainted with your multitude<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> in the
               name of God, by Onesimus, who is your bishop, in love which is unutterable, whom I
               pray that ye love in <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> our Lord, and that all of you imitate his
               example;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> for blessed is He who has given you such a bishop, even as ye deserve [to
               have].<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/></p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <head>Chapter 3<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/></head>
            <p>But inasmuch as love does not permit me to be silent in regard to you, on this
               account I have been forward to entreat of you that ye would be diligent in the will
               of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <head>Chapter 8<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/></head>
            <p>For, so long as there is not implanted in you any one lust which is able to torment
               you, behold, ye live in God. I rejoice in you, and offer supplication<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/> on account
               of you, <placeName>Ephesians</placeName>, a church which is renowned in all ages. For those who are carnal
               are not able to do spiritual things, nor those that are spiritual carnal things; in
               like manner as neither can faith [do] those things which are foreign to faith, nor
               want of faith [do] what belongs to faith. For those things which ye have done in the
               flesh, even these are spiritual, because ye have done everything in <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <head>Chapter 9</head>
            <p>And ye are prepared for the building of God the Father, and ye are raised up on high
               by the instrument of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, which is the cross; and ye are drawn by the rope,
               ​which is the Holy Spirit; and your pulley is your faith, and your love is the way
               which leadeth up on high to God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <head>Chapter 10</head>
            <p>Pray for all men; for there is hope of repentance for them, that they may be counted
               worthy of God. By your works especially let them be instructed. Against their harsh
               words be ye conciliatory, by meekness of mind and gentleness. Against their
               blasphemies do ye give yourselves to prayer; and against their error be ye armed with
               faith. Against their fierceness be ye peaceful and quiet, and be ye not astounded by
               them. Let us, then, be imitators of our Lord in meekness, and strive who shall more
               especially be injured, and oppressed, and defrauded.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="102"/>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <head>Chapter 14<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/></head>
            <p>The work is not of promise,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> unless a man be found in the power of faith, even to
               the end.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <head>Chapter 15</head>
            <p>It is better that a man should be silent while he is something, than that he should
               be talking when he is not; that by those things which he speaks he should act, and by
               those things of which he is silent he should be known.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <head>Chapter 18<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12"/></head>
            <p>My spirit bows in adoration to the cross, which is a stumbling-block to those who do
               not believe, but is to you for salvation and eternal life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <head>Chapter 19</head>
            <p>There was concealed from the ruler of this world the virginity of Mary and the birth
               of our Lord, and the three renowned mysteries<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> which were done in the tranquillity
               of God from the star. And here, at the manifestation of the Son, magic began to be
               destroyed, and all bonds were loosed; and the ancient kingdom and the error of evil
               was destroyed. Henceforward all things were moved together, and the destruction of
               death was devised, and there was the commencement of that which was perfected in
               God.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p>.....<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/></p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">Another inscription is, <title>Epistle the second,
                  which is to the <persName>Ephesians</persName></title>.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">Literally, <quote>separated.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">Literally, <quote>bound from actions.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">Cureton renders, <quote>have received your abundance,</quote>
               probably referring the words to gifts sent by the <persName>Ephesians</persName> to <persName>Ignatius</persName>.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">Literally, <quote>be in his image.</quote></note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">There is no apodosis, unless it be found in what
               follows.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">The following clause is the whole of chap. iii. in the
               Greek, which is represented in the Syriac.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">Chaps. iv. v. vi. vii. of the Greek are totally omitted
               in the Syriac.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">Thus Cureton renders the words, referring in
               confirmation to the Peshito version of Phil. i. 4, but the meaning is
               doubtful.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">Chaps. xi. xii. xiii. of the Greek are totally wanting
               in the Syriac, and only these few words of chaps, xiv. and xv. are
               represented.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">The meaning seems to be that mere profession, without
               continuous practice, is nothing.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">Chaps. xvi. and xvii. of the Greek are totally wanting
               in the Syriac.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">Literally, <quote>the mysteries of the shout.</quote> The meaning is
               here confused and obscure. See the Greek.</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="n">Chaps. xx. and xxi. of the Greek are altogether wanting
               in the Syriac.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
