<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Timothy I, Apology for Christianity</title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial transcription by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreading of the transcription and initial markup of persons, places, and
                  titles by </resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#anorth">Adelaide North</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p><!-- Complete with bibliographic information on the Mingana translation. --></p>
            <p>Initial transcription of the text by Roger Pearse, downloaded from Tertullian.org on
               06/22/2025: <ref
                  target="https://www.tertullian.org/fathers/timothy_i_apology_01_text.htm">
                  https://www.tertullian.org/fathers/timothy_i_apology_01_text.htm</ref>. The
               present transcription has followed Roger Pearse.</p>
            <p>Both the original translation by Alphonse Mingana and the transcription by Pearse are
               in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>With the assistance of <persName>God</persName> we will write the debate held by the <persName>Patriarch Mar Timothy</persName>
            before <persName>Mahdi, the Commander of the Faithful</persName>, by way of question and answer, on the
            subject of the Christian religion.</p>
         <p>On the one hand I feel repugnance to write to your Lordship,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> and on the other I am
            anxious to do so. I feel repugnance, on account <pb n="16"/> of the futility of the outcome of
            the work. It is true that I could not have acquired a mature experience of such a
            futility from the single discussion herein mentioned, but I may state that I have
            acquired such an experience from discussions that took place before the one involved in
            the present lucubration.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> I am anxious, in order to confirm and corroborate a
            traditional habit, inasmuch as the habit of friendly correspondence has acquired the
            right of prescription from very early times, and has thereby received an additional
            title to existence; as a matter of fact it is born and grows in us from our childhood,
            nay even babyhood, and it is very difficult to shake a habit of such a duration. For the
            reason, however, stated at the beginning I sometimes infringe this law, especially when
            I am reminded by a wise man who says that it is useless to draw upon that which is
            difficult to inherit. This is also due to the fact that the subject is to me difficult
            and is even against my nature, but we know that habit conquers inclination, as a
            powerful thought conquers a weak one.</p>
         <p>We often see that a strong and well rooted branch goes spontaneously back to its former
            and congenial state after it has been violently twisted, and we do find that when
            powerful torrents are diverted from their natural channels with violence, they return
            immediately to their natural and customary course, without the need of any violence.
            This happens to me in relation to your great wisdom; to put a stop to our correspondence
            we must needs make use of violence, but after the cessation of this violence, we go back
            to our natural state, while love conquers all between us and covers the weaknesses of
            the flesh which are full of shame and confusion, and also many other human proclivities
            which are known to the mind, but which the speech conceals and hides under the veil of
            silence. Such weaknesses are well known to your great wisdom, as if you were their
            father and originator, and are also known to all the members of the Orthodox Church.
            Love covers and hides all these weaknesses as the water covers and hides the rocks that
            are under it. But let us now embark on our main subject in the way sanctioned by our old
            habit and ancient custom.</p>
         <p>Let it be known to your wisdom, O <persName>God-loving Lord</persName>, that before these days I had an
            audience of our victorious <persName>King</persName>, and according to usage I praised <persName>God</persName> and <persName>his Majesty</persName>.
            When, in the limited space <pb n="17"/> allowed to me, I had finished the words of my
            complimentary address, in which I spake of the nature of <persName>God</persName> and His Eternity, he did
            something to me, which he had never done before; he said to me: <quote>O <persName>Catholicos</persName>, a man
               like you who possesses all this knowledge and utters such sublime words concerning <persName>God</persName>,
               is not justified in saying about <persName>God</persName> that He married a woman from whom He begat a son.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> 
            —And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>And who is, O <persName>God-loving King</persName>, who has ever uttered
               such a blasphemy concerning <persName>God</persName>?</quote>—And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said to me: <quote>What then do you
                  say that <persName>Christ</persName> is?</quote> —And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>O <persName>King</persName>, <persName>Christ</persName> is the <persName>Word-God</persName>,
                     who appeared in the flesh for the salvation of the world.</quote>—And our victorious <persName>King</persName>
            questioned me: <quote>Do you not say that <persName>Christ</persName> is the <persName>Son of God</persName>?</quote>—And I replied to <persName>his
               Majesty</persName>: <quote>O <persName>King</persName>, <persName>Christ</persName> is the <persName>Son of God</persName>, and I confess Him and worship Him as such.
                  This I learned from <persName>Christ</persName> Himself in the Gospel and from the Books of the <title>Torah</title> and of
                  the Prophets, which know Him and call Him by the name of <hi rend="doubleQuote">Son of God</hi> but not a son in
                  the flesh as children are born in the carnal way, but an admirable and wonderful Son,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/>
                  more sublime and higher than mind and words, as it fits a divine Son to be.</quote></p>
         <p><persName>Our King</persName> asked then: <quote>How?</quote>—And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>O <persName>our King</persName>, that He is a Son
            and one that is born, we learn it and believe in it, but we dare not investigate how He
            was born before the times, and we are not able to understand the fact at all, as <persName>God</persName> is
            incomprehensible and inexplicable in all things; but we may say in an imperfect simile
            that as light is born of the sun and word of the soul, so also <persName>Christ</persName> who is <persName>Word</persName>, is
            born of <persName>God</persName>, high above the times and before all the worlds.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said to me:
            <quote>Do you not say that He was born of the <persName>Virgin Mary</persName>?</quote>—And I said to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>We say
               it and confess it. The very same <persName>Christ</persName> is the <persName>Word</persName> born of <persName>the Father</persName>, and a man born
               of <persName>Mary</persName>. From the fact that He is <persName>Word-God</persName>, He is born of <persName>the Father</persName> before the times,
               as light from the sun and word from the soul; and from the fact that He is man He is
               born of the <persName>Virgin Mary</persName>, in time; from <persName>the Father</persName> He is, therefore, born eternally, and
               from <persName>the Mother</persName> He is born in time, without <pb n="18"/> a Father, without any marital contact,
               and without any break in the seals of the virginity of <persName>His Mother</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>Then <persName>our God-loving King</persName> said to me: <quote>That He was born of <persName>Mary</persName> without marital
            intercourse is found in the Book,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> and is well known, but is it possible that He was
            born without breaking the seals of the virginity of His mother?</quote>—And I replied to him:
            <quote>O <persName>King</persName>, if we consider both facts in the light of natural law, they are impossible,
               because it is impossible that a man should be born without breaking the seals of his
               mother's virginity, and is equally impossible that He should be conceived without a
               man's intercourse. But if we consider not nature but <persName>God</persName>, the <persName>Lord of nature</persName>, as <persName>the
                  Virgin</persName> was able to conceive without marital relations, so was she able to be delivered
               of her child without any break in her virginal seals. There is nothing impossible with
               <persName>God</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> who can do everything.</quote>—Then the <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>That a man can be born without
                  marital intercourse is borne out by the example of <persName>Adam</persName>, who was fashioned by <persName>God</persName> from
                  earth without any marital intercourse, but that a man can be born without breaking his
                  mother's virginal seals we have no proof, either from Book nor from nature.</quote></p>
         <p>And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName> in the following manner: <quote>That He was born without breaking
            the virginal seals of His mother we have evidence from Book and nature. From Book there
            is the example of <persName>Eve</persName> who was born from the side of <persName>Adam</persName> without having rent it or
            fractured it, and the example of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> who ascended to <placeName>Heaven</placeName> without having torn
            and breached the firmament. In this way He was born of <persName>Mary</persName> without having broken her
            virginal seals or fractured them. This can also be illustrated from nature: all fruits
            are born of trees without breaking or tearing them, and sight is born of the eye while
            the latter is not broken or torn, and the perfume of apples and all aromatic substances
            is born of their respective trees or plants without breaking and tearing them, and the
            rays are born of the sun without tearing or breaking its spheric form. As all these are
            born of their generators without tearing them or rending them, so also <persName>Christ</persName> was born
            of <persName>Mary</persName> without breaking her virginal seals; as His eternal birth from <persName>the Father</persName> is
            wonderful, so also is His temporal birth from <persName>Mary</persName>.</quote> <pb n="19"/> </p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>How was that <persName>Eternal One</persName> born in time?</quote>—And I answered: <quote>It is
            not in His eternity that He was born of <persName>Mary</persName>, O <persName>our King</persName>, but in His temporalness and
            humanity.</quote> —And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>There are, therefore, two distinct beings: if one
               is eternal and <persName>God</persName> from <persName>God</persName> as you said, and the other temporal, the latter is therefore
               a pure man from <persName>Mary</persName>.</quote>—And I retorted: <quote><persName>Christ</persName> is not two beings, O <persName>King</persName>, nor two Sons,
                  but Son and <persName>Christ</persName> are one; there are in Him two natures, one of which belongs to the
                  Word and the other one which is from <persName>Mary</persName>, clothed itself<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> with the <persName>Word-God</persName>.</quote>—And the
            <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>They are, therefore, two, one of whom created and fashioned, and the other
               uncreated and unfashioned.</quote>—And I said to him: <quote>We do not deny the duality of natures, O
                  <persName>King</persName>, nor their mutual relations, but we profess that both of them constitute one <persName>Christ</persName>
                  and Son.</quote></p>
         <p>And the <persName>King</persName> retorted: <quote>If He is one He is not two; and if He is two, He is not
            one.</quote>—And I replied to him: <quote>A man is one, while in reality he is two: one in his
               composition and individuality, and two in the distinction found between his soul and his
               body; the former is invisible and spiritual, and the latter visible and corporeal <persName>Our
                  King</persName>, together with the insignia of his Kingdom is also one King and not two, however
               great may be the difference that separates him from his dresses. In the same way the
               Word of God, together with the clothings of humanity which He put on from <persName>Mary</persName>, is one
               and the same <persName>Christ</persName>, and not two, although there is in Him the natural difference
               between the <persName>Word-God</persName> and His humanity; and the fact that He is one does not preclude the
               fact that He is also two. The very same <persName>Christ</persName> and Son is indeed known and confessed as
               one, and the fact that He is also two does not imply confusion or mixture, because the
               known attributes of His natures are kept in one person<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> of the Son and <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> retorted to me: <quote>Even in this you cannot save yourself from duality in
            <persName>Christ</persName></quote>—And I demonstrated the fact to him through another illustration and said: <quote>The
               tongue and the word are <pb n="20"/> one with the voice in which they are clothed, in a way that
               the two are not two words nor two tongues, but one word, together with the tongue and
               the voice, so that they are called by all one tongue with the word and the voice, and in
               them one does not expel two. This is also the case with the <persName>Word-God</persName>; He is one with His
               humanity, while preserving the distinction between His invisibility and His visibility,
               and between His Divinity and His humanity. <persName>Christ</persName> is one in His son-ship, and two in the
               attributes of His natures.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Did not <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> say, I am going to <persName>My God</persName> and to your
            <persName>God</persName>?</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/>—And I said: <quote>It is true that this sentence has been said by <persName>our Saviour</persName>, but
               there is another sentence which precedes it and which is worthy of mention.</quote>—And the
            <persName>King</persName> asked: <quote>Which is it?</quote>—And I said: <quote><persName>Our Lord</persName> said to His Disciples <quote>I am going to My
               Father and to your Father, and to <persName>My God</persName> and your <persName>God</persName>.</quote></quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>How can
                  this be? If He says that He is <persName>His Father</persName>, He is not <persName>His God</persName>, and if He is <persName>His God</persName>, He
                  is not <persName>His Father</persName>; what is this contradiction?</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/>—And I replied to him: <quote>There is no
                     contradiction here, O <persName>God-loving King</persName>. The fact that He is <persName>His Father</persName> by nature does not
                     carry with it that He is also <persName>His God</persName> by nature, and the fact that He is <persName>His God</persName> by
                     nature does not imply that He is <persName>His Father</persName> by nature. He is, however, from <persName>His Father</persName>
                     by the nature of the Word, born of Him from eternity, as light from the sun and word
                     from the soul; and <persName>God</persName> is <persName>His God</persName> by the nature of the humanity of the Word born of
                     <persName>Mary</persName>. Man is living and rational only by the nature of his soul, which has indeed
                     received from <persName>God</persName> a living and rational nature, but he is said to be living and rational
                     in his body also, through its association with this living and rational soul. In reality
                     what be is by nature when his body and soul are separated, is not what he is in its
                     composite state when his body and soul are united. In spite of all this however, he is
                     called one living and rational man and not two. In the same way <persName>God</persName> is called, and is,
                     the <persName>Christ's Father</persName> by the nature of the union of <persName>Word-God</persName> with our human nature, and on
                     the other hand He is called <persName>His God</persName> by the nature of His humanity that He took from us
                     in union with the <persName>Word-God</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>In this way He is then one Son and <persName>Christ</persName>, and not two. He <pb n="21"/> was not born of <persName>Mary</persName> in
            the same way as He was born of <persName>God</persName>, nor was He born of <persName>God</persName> in the same way as He was
            born of <persName>Mary</persName>. So the Son and the <persName>Christ</persName> are really one, in spite of His births being
            two, and the same <persName>Christ</persName> has <persName>God</persName> as Father by nature, and as <persName>God</persName>: Father by the fact
            that He is <persName>Word-God</persName>, and <persName>God</persName> by the fact of His birth from <persName>Mary</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p><persName>Our King</persName> showed here marks of doubt as to the possibility of all the above explanations,
            and I removed his doubt through another illustration, and said: <quote>The letter of the
               <persName>Commander of the Faithful</persName> is one, both in the words that are written in it and in the
               papyrus on which the words are written, and <persName>our King</persName>, the <persName>King of Kings</persName>, is called both
               the father and the owner of his letter. He is called its father through the words born
               of his soul, which have been impressed on the papyrus, and he is called its owner
               through his being the owner of the papyrus on which the words have been written. Neither
               the papyrus, however, is, by nature, from the soul of <persName>the King</persName>, nor the words are by
               nature from the papyrus-reed, but the words are by nature born of the soul of <persName>the King</persName>,
               and the papyrus is by nature made of the papyrus-reed, i.e., from <foreign xml:lang="grc">πάπυρος</foreign>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> In this
               same way <persName>Christ</persName> is one, both in His being <persName>Word-God</persName> and in His humanity taken from us,
               but the very same <persName>God of Christ</persName> is both <persName>His Father</persName> and <persName>His God</persName>: <persName>His Father</persName>, from the
               fact that He was born before the times of <persName>the Father</persName>, and <persName>His God</persName> from the fact that He
               was born in time of Mary. By nature, however, He is not a man from the Father, nor is
               the Word by nature from <persName>Mary</persName>, but He is the very same <persName>Christ</persName> both from <persName>the Father</persName> and
               from <persName>Mary</persName>, in the first case as <persName>God</persName>, and in the second case as man.</quote>"</p>
         <p>Then <persName>our God-loving King</persName> said to me: <persName>How can the spirit who has no genital organs
            beget?</persName>—And I replied to him: <quote>O <persName>God-loving King</persName>, how can the spirit then do things and
               create without possessing organs of creation. As He created the worlds without
               instruments of creation, so He was born without the medium of the genital organs. If He
               could not be born without the intermediary of the genital organs, He could not by
               inference have created without the <pb n="22"/> intermediary of the instruments of creation. If
               He created without any instruments of creation, He was, therefore, born without the
               genital organs. Lo, the sun also begets the rays of light without any genital organs.
               <persName>God</persName> is therefore able to beget and create, although He is a simple and not a composite
               spirit; and without any genital organs and instruments of creation He begets <persName>the Son</persName> and
               makes <persName>the Spirit</persName> proceed from the essence of His person as the sun does for the light
               and the heat.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Do you believe in <persName>Father</persName>, <persName>Son</persName> and <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>?</quote>—And I
            answered: <quote>I worship them and believe in them.</quote>—Then <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>You, therefore,
               believe in three Gods?</quote>—And I replied to <persName>our King</persName>: <quote>The belief in the above three names,
                  consists in the belief in three Persons, and the belief in these three Persons consists
                  in the belief in one God. The belief in the above three names, consists therefore in the
                  belief in one God. We believe in <persName>Father</persName>, <persName>Son</persName> and <persName>Holy Spirit</persName> as one God. So <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>
                  taught us, and so we have learnt from the revelation of the books of the prophets. As
                  <persName>our God-loving King</persName> is one King with his word and his spirit, and not three Kings, and
                  as no one is able to distinguish him, his word and his spirit from himself and no one
                  calls him <persName>King</persName> independently of his word and his spirit, so also <persName>God</persName> is one God with <persName>His
                     Word</persName> and <quote>His Spirit</quote>, and not three Gods, because <persName>the Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit of God</persName> are
                  inseparable from Him. And as the sun with its light and its heat is not called three
                  suns but one sun, so also <persName>God</persName> with <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName> is not three Gods but is and
                  is called one God.</quote></p>
         <p>Then <persName>the King</persName> said to me: <quote>What is my word? It is something that vanishes and
            disappears.</quote>—And I replied to him: <quote>As <persName>God</persName> does not resemble in His nature <persName>the Commander
               of the Faithful</persName>, so also <persName>the Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit of God</persName> do not resemble those of <persName>the
                  Commander of the Faithful</persName>. We men sometimes exist and sometimes do not exist because we
               have a beginning and an end, as we are created. This is the case also with our word and
               our spirit, which at one time exist, and at another cease to exist, and have a beginning
               and an end. <persName>God</persName>, however, who is higher and more exalted than all is not like us in this
               respect, but He exists divinely and eternally, and there was no time in which He was
               not, nor will there be a time in which He will not be. He has no beginning and no end,
               because He is not created. <pb n="23"/> In the same way are <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>, who exist
               divinely and eternally, that is to say without beginning and without end, as <persName>God</persName> with
               <persName>God</persName>, without any separation.</quote></p>
         <p>Then <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Are <persName>the Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> not separable from <persName>God</persName>?</quote>—And I
            replied: <quote>No: never. As light and heat are not separable from the sun, so also (<persName>the
               Word</persName>) and <persName>the Spirit of God</persName> are not separable from Him. If one separates from the sun
               its light and its heat, it will immediately become neither light-giver nor
               heat-producer, and consequently it will cease to be sun, so also if one separates from
               <persName>God</persName> <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>, He will cease to be a rational and living God, because the
               one who has no reason is called irrational,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12"/> 
               and the one who has no spirit<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> is dead.
               If one, therefore, ventures to say about <persName>God</persName> that there was a time in which He had no
               Word and no Spirit, such a one would blaspheme against <persName>God</persName>, because his saying would be
               equivalent to asserting that there was a time in which <persName>God</persName> had no reason and no life. If
               such adjectives are considered as blasphemy and abomination when said of <persName>God</persName>, it follows
               that <persName>God</persName> begat <persName>the Word</persName> in a divine and eternal way, as a source of wisdom, and had <persName>the
                  Spirit</persName> proceeding from Him eternally and without any beginning, as a source of life. <persName>God</persName>
               is indeed the eternal source of life and wisdom; as a source of wisdom He imparts by <persName>His
                  Word</persName> wisdom to all the rational beings, and as a source of life He causes life to flow
               to all the living beings, celestial and terrestrial alike, because <persName>God</persName> is the creator of
               everything by means of <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our powerful King</persName> said to me: <quote>Tell me from which books you can show me that <persName>the
            Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> are eternally with <persName>God</persName>.</quote>—And I replied: <quote>We can demonstrate this
               first from the Books of the Prophets, and afterwards from the Gospel. As to the
               prophets, <persName>David</persName> said first thus: <quote>By the Word of the <persName>Lord</persName> were the heavens made, and all
                  His hosts by the Spirit of His mouth.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/> In another passage he glorifies the Word of
               <persName>God</persName> as if it were <persName>God</persName>, in the following terms: <quote>I shall glorify the Word of <persName>God</persName></quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15"/>
               Further, in speaking of the resurrection of the dead he said of <persName>God</persName>, <quote>Thou sendest <pb n="24"/>
                  forth <persName>Thy Spirit</persName> and they are created, and Thou renewest the face of the earth.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16"/> The
               prophet <persName>David</persName> would not have glorified a created being, nor would he have called creator
               and renewer some one who was created and fashioned. In another passage he speaks of the
               Word of <persName>God</persName> as itself <persName>God</persName>, without a beginning and without an end, because he writes:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17"/>
               <quote>Thou art for ever, O <persName>Lord</persName>, and <persName>Thy Word</persName> standeth in <placeName>Heaven</placeName>;</quote> he teaches here that as
               <persName>God</persName> is for ever in heaven, so also the Word of <persName>God</persName> is in heaven for ever and without an
               end, because he who is without an end is also without a beginning, and he who has no
               beginning has no end.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Afterwards comes the prophet <persName>Isaiah</persName> who speaks of the Word of <persName>God</persName> in a way similar to
            that of <persName>David</persName>, in saying thus: <quote>The grass withereth and the flower fadeth, but the Word
               of <persName>our God</persName> standeth for ever.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18"/> Other prophets also speak of this point in several
            passages. So far as the Gospel is concerned we gather the same conclusion from the
            following passage: <quote>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with <persName>God</persName>, and the
               Word was <persName>God</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19"/> We are taught here two things: that the Word is eternal, and that the
            same Word is <persName>God</persName> by nature. All these the Gospel teaches about the Word, and it teaches
            us also the same thing concerning the Spirit in the very same chapter, <quote>In Him was
               life,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20"/> i.e., in the same <persName>Word—God</persName> was <hi rend="singleQuote">life</hi> which means <hi rend="doubleQuote">(in Him) was Spirit</hi> or <hi rend="doubleQuote">He
                  was it.</hi> In saying of <persName>the Word</persName> in the first passage that He <hi rend="doubleQuote">was,</hi> does not refer to any
            beginning, and so is the case with regard to the second passage referring to <persName>the Spirit</persName>.
            Indeed the Gospel in using this <hi rend="doubleQuote">was</hi> is not speaking of His creation but of His
            eternity. If <persName>Spirit</persName> is life and life is eternally in <persName>God</persName>, <persName>the Spirit</persName> is consequently
            eternally in <persName>God</persName>. And <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> (<persName>Holy Ghost</persName>?) is <persName>the Spirit of God</persName>, and the life and
            light of men.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>In one passage <persName>Christ</persName> said to <persName>His Father</persName>, <quote>And now, O <persName>Father</persName>, glorify Thou Me with
            Thine own Self with the glory which I had with Thee before the world was.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21"/> He said
            here, <quote>with the glory which He had before the world was, and not which came to Him;</quote> if
            He had said, <quote>With the glory which had come to me with Thee before the world was,</quote> He
            would have taught us that He was a created and made being, but since He said <persName>with the
               glory which I had with Thee before the world was</persName> He clearly taught us that while <pb n="25"/>
            all the world was created He alone was without a beginning, as the <persName>Word of God</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>In another passage while He was about to ascend to <placeName>Heaven</placeName> He said to His disciples, <quote>Go
            and teach all nations and baptise them in the name of <persName>the Father</persName>, and of <persName>the Son</persName>, and of
            <persName>the Holy Ghost</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22"/> <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> would not have allowed Himself to count created and
            made beings with the One who is uncreated and unmade, and temporal beings with the One
            who has no beginning and no end. As the wise men do not mix promiscuously with one
            another in one count sun, stone and horse, nor pearl, gold and brass, but say, for
            instance, in a separate way: three pearls, or three stars, as these are similar in
            nature and resemble one another in everything, so also would the case be with <persName>Jesus
               Christ</persName>, who would have never allowed himself to count with <persName>God</persName> <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>,
            if He did not know that they were equal to <persName>God</persName> in nature. How could He have made equal
            in honour and royal power the one who was not <persName>God</persName> in nature with the one who was, or the
            one who was temporal with the one who was eternal? It is not the servants who
            participate in royal honour but the children.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23"/></p>
         <p>Then <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>What is the difference between <persName>the Son</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName>, and
            how is it that <persName>the Son</persName> is not <persName>the Spirit</persName> nor <persName>the Spirit</persName> <persName>the Son</persName>? Since you said that <persName>God</persName>
            is not composite there should not be any difference with <persName>God</persName> in the fact that He begets
            and makes proceed from Himself.</quote>—And I replied to <persName>our King</persName> as follows: <quote>There is no
               difference, O <persName>King</persName>, between the persons in their relation to one another, except that
               the first is not begotten, and the second is begotten, and the third proceeds; and <persName>God</persName>
               consists in <persName>Father</persName>, <persName>Son</persName>, and <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>; and He begat the former and made the latter
               proceed from Him from eternity without any bodily cleavage and separation in the organs
               and places that are fit for generation and procession. <persName>God</persName> is not composite and has no
               body, and since the terms <hi rend="singleQuote">cleavage</hi> and <hi rend="singleQuote">organs</hi> imply a body—because all bodies are
               composite—it follows that <hi rend="singleQuote">cleavage</hi> and <hi rend="singleQuote">organs</hi> do not apply to <persName>God</persName>; indeed <persName>God</persName> being
               without body and not being composite, is thought of without any notion of <hi rend="singleQuote">cleavage</hi> and
               <hi rend="singleQuote">separation.</hi> <pb n="26"/> Reason comes out of the soul—because mind comes out of the soul— but
               it comes out of it without any suffering, without any cleavage, and without the
               instrumentality of organs. The very same sun begets light and makes heat come out of it,
               without any cleavage or bodily separation, and in a way that all the light is from all
               the sun and all the heat from all its spheric globe.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>All the reason and all the mind are from all the soul, the former by process of birth
            and the second by that of procession, as all the heat and all the mind are with the sun
            and with the soul respectively, and all the heat and all the reason are with the soul,
            with the sun, and with ourselves, while light does not become heat nor heat light. This
            very method applies to <persName>the Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName>: the former is begotten, and the latter
            proceeds from <persName>God</persName> and <persName>the Father</persName>, not through any material cleavage, and any suffering,
            nor from a special organ, but as from an uncircumscribed being: an uncircumscribed one
            in an uncircumscribed fashion, and one who is all in all without space and time, in a
            way that <persName>the Son</persName> is not <persName>the Spirit</persName>, nor <persName>the Spirit</persName> <persName>the Son</persName>, in qualifications and
            attributes.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>From the whole of an apple the whole of the scent and the whole of the taste are
            begotten and proceed in a way that the apple does not make the scent proceed from one
            part of it and beget the taste from another, but scent and taste come out of all the
            apple. While scent and taste are mixed with each other and with the apple, they are
            nevertheless separate in a way that taste is not scent and scent is not taste, and are
            not confused with each other, nor separated from each other, but are so to speak mixed
            together in a separate way, and separated from each other in a mixed way, by a process
            that is as amazing as it is incomprehensible. In this very way from the uncircumscribed
            <persName>Father</persName> <persName>the Son</persName> is begotten and <persName>the Spirit</persName> proceeds, in an uncircumscribed way: the
            eternal from the eternal, the uncreated from the uncreated, the spiritual from the
            spiritual. Since they are uncircumscribed they are not separated from one another, and
            since they are not bodies they are not mixed and confused with one another, but are
            separated in their persons in a united way, so to speak, and are united in their nature
            in a separate way. <persName>God</persName> is, therefore, one in nature with three personal attributes.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>If they are not separated by remoteness and nearness as they
            are uncircumscribed, <persName>the Father</persName> therefore, <pb n="27"/> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> clothed also themselves
            with the human body, together with <persName>the Son</persName>; if <persName>the Father</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> did not put on
            human body with <persName>the Son</persName>, how is it that they are not separated by distance and
            space?</quote>—And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>As the word of <persName>the King</persName> clothes itself with the
               papyrus on which it is written, while his soul and his mind cannot be said to do the
               same, and as his soul and his mind while not separated from his word, cannot
               nevertheless be said that they clothe themselves with the papyrus, so also is the case
               with the Word of <persName>God</persName>; because although He put on our human body without having been
               separated from <persName>the Father</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName>, yet <persName>the Father</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> cannot be said
               to have put on our human body.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Further, the word that is begotten of the soul clothes itself with the voice that is
            caused by the vibration of the air, and yet it is not separated from the soul and the
            mind, and the soul and the mind are not said that they clothe themselves with the voice,
            and no man ever says that he heard the mind and the soul of so-and-so, but he does say
            that he heard the word of so-and-so, and this in spite of the fact that the word is not
            remote from the mind, nor the mind from the soul, and are not separated from one
            another. In this very way the <persName>Word-God</persName> clothed Himself with a body from ourselves,
            without having been separated in the least from <persName>the Father</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName>, and in this
            way also <persName>the Father</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> are not said to have put on human body with <persName>the
               Word</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Finally, the body is believed to be and actually is the temple and the clothing of the
            soul, but it is not believed and actually is not the temple and the clothing of the word
            and of the mind, in spite of the fact that neither the word nor the mind are remote from
            the soul, nor is the soul itself remote from the word and the mind. In this way <persName>the Word</persName>
            alone is spoken of as having put on our human body, while <persName>the Father</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> are
            not said to have put it on, in spite of the fact that they are not remote from <persName>the Word</persName>
            in distance and locality.</quote> The objections and the difficulties raised by <persName>our Sovereign</persName>
            have been rebutted and explained in the above way.</p>
         <p>After these <persName>the King</persName> said to me: <quote>Who is your head and your leader?</quote>—And I replied: <quote><persName>Our
            Lord Jesus Christ</persName>.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> asked me: <quote>Was <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> circumcised or not?</quote>—And I
            answered: <quote>He was.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> asked me: <quote>Why do you <pb n="28"/> not then circumcise yourself?
               If your head and leader is <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, and <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> was circumcised, you should
               also by necessity circumcise yourself.</quote>—And I spoke thus: <quote>O <persName>King</persName>, <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> was both
                  circumcised and baptised. He was circumcised eight days after His birth according to the
                  injunction of the Law, and He was baptised while He was about thirty years of age, and
                  by His baptism He annulled circumcision. I do not follow the Law as the <persName>Christ</persName> followed
                  all the Law;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24"/> I follow the Gospel, and that is why I do not circumcise myself in spite
                  of the fact that <persName>Christ</persName> circumcised Himself, but I baptise myself with water and spirit
                  like Him. I believe in <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, and since <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> was baptised I consider
                  baptism as an urgent necessity for me.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25"/> I leave the image and cleave to the
                  reality.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> asked me: <quote>How did <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> abolish circumcision and what is the
            meaning of the <hi rend="singleQuote">image</hi> you have spoken of?</quote>—And I replied: <quote>All the <title>Torah</title>, was, O <persName>King</persName>,
               the image of the Gospel. The sacrifices that are in the Law are the image of the
               sacrifice of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, and the priesthood and high-priesthood of the Law are the
               image of the high-priesthood of <persName>Christ</persName>, and the carnal circumcision is the image of His
               spiritual circumcision. As He abolished the Law by the Gospel, and the sacrifices by His
               sacrifice, and the priesthood of the Law by His priesthood, so also He abolished and
               annulled the carnal circumcision which is performed by the work of the hands of men by
               means of His circumcision which is not performed by the work of the hands of men but by
               the power of <persName>the Spirit</persName>, and it is the sacrament<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n26"/> of the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName> and of the
               resurrection from death.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>If <persName>Christ</persName> abolished the Law and all its requirements, He is,
            therefore, its enemy and its adversary. We call enemies those who destroy and contradict
            one another.</quote>—And I replied to him: <quote>The light of the stars is abolished by the light of
               the sun, and the light of the latter is not for that the enemy of that of <pb n="29"/> the
               former; the functions of childhood are also abolished by those of manhood, and man is
               not for that the enemy of himself; an earthly kingdom is also abolished by the heavenly
               Kingdom, and the Kingdom of God is not for that the enemy of men. In this very way <persName>Jesus
                  Christ</persName> abolished and destroyed the Law by the Gospel, while He is not for that the enemy
               and the adversary of the Law.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Where did <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> worship and pray in the years that
            elapsed between His birth and His ascension to <placeName>Heaven</placeName>? Was it not in the house of
            holiness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27"/> and in <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>?</quote>—And I replied: <quote>Yes.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> asked: <quote>Why then do
               you worship <persName>God</persName> and pray in the direction of the East?</quote>—And I replied: <quote>The true worship
                  of the <persName>Omnipotent God</persName>, O <persName>King</persName>, will be performed by mankind in the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName>,
                  and the image of the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName> in the earth is the paradise of <placeName>Eden</placeName>; now as the
                  paradise of <placeName>Eden</placeName> is in the east, we therefore worship <persName>God</persName> and pray rightly in the
                  direction of the east in which is the <placeName>Paradise</placeName> which is the image of the <placeName>Kingdom of
                     Heaven</placeName>. There is also another reason for our conduct: <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> walked in the flesh
                  thirty-three years on the earth, O <persName>King</persName>. In the thirtieth year he repaid to <persName>God</persName> all the
                  debt that the human kind and angels owed to Him. It was a debt that no man and no angel
                  was able to pay, because there has never been a created being that was free from sin,
                  except the Man with whom <persName>God</persName> clothed Himself and became one with Him in a wonderful
                  unity.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28"/></p>
         <p><quote>After having then paid to <persName>God</persName> the debt of all the creatures and abrogated, annulled,
            and torn the contract containing it, He went to the <!-- Does this mean the Jordan River? --><placeName>Jordan</placeName>, to <persName>John the Baptist</persName>, and was
            baptised by him, and thus the One who was the image of the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName> placed this
            baptism of His in the forefront of the Christian life. From the day of His baptism to
            that of His ascension to heaven there are three years, and it is in these three years
            that He has taught us all the economy of the Christian religion: baptism, laws,
            ordinances, prayers, worship in the direction of the east, and the sacrifice that we
            offer. All these things He practised in His person and taught us to practise ourselves.
            Because He wished to proclaim to the world through His disciples: the Gospel, the
            baptism, the sacrifice and the worship <pb n="30"/> and prayer to <persName>God</persName>, He performed and fulfilled
            them all in His own person, in order that His disciples might fulfil themselves what
            they had seen Him practising Himself, and that they might teach others to do the
            same.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Further, the worship of <persName>God</persName> started at the beginning in the East; it is indeed in that
            direction that <persName>Adam</persName> and his children worshipped <persName>God</persName>, because the <placeName>Paradise</placeName> is in the
            direction of the east.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29"/> Moreover, <persName>Noah</persName>, <persName>Abraham</persName>, <persName>Isaac</persName>, <persName>Jacob</persName> and <persName>Moses</persName> used to worship
            <persName>God</persName> and to pray while turning towards the east and <placeName>Paradise</placeName>, that is towards the
            direction and the place in which <persName>God</persName> had been worshipped from the beginning by <persName>Adam</persName> and
            his children, as we have just now said. It is for this reason that <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> taught
            His disciples to worship <persName>God</persName> and pray towards the east. Because <persName>Adam</persName> transgressed the
            commandment of <persName>God</persName>, he was driven out of <placeName>Paradise</placeName>, and when he went out of <placeName>Paradise</placeName> he
            was thrown on this accursed earth. Having been thrown on this accursed earth, he turned
            his face away from <persName>God</persName>, and his children worshipped demons, stars, sun, moon and graven
            and molten images. <persName>The Word of God</persName> came then to the children of men in a human body, and
            in His person paid to <persName>God</persName> the debt that they were owing Him. To remind them, however, of
            the place from which their father was driven because of his transgression of the
            commandment, He made them turn their faces towards <placeName>Paradise</placeName> in their worship and prayer,
            because it is in it that <persName>God</persName> was first worshipped.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Because <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> saved men from the deportation of <persName>Satan</persName>, and <persName>the Word of God</persName> freed
            them from the worship of idols, He rightly turned also the direction of their sight and
            their mind towards <persName>God</persName> and towards <placeName>Paradise</placeName> where He was first worshipped. He simply
            brought back the one who was going astray to the house of his father. This is also the
            reason why the angel <persName>Gabriel</persName>, when announcing to <persName>Mary</persName> the conception of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>,
            appeared to her from the direction of the east as it is written in your book.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30"/> Finally,
            we worship <persName>God</persName> in the direction of the east, because being light He is more congruously
            worshipped in the direction of the light.</quote> <pb n="31"/> </p>
         <p><persName>Our King</persName> then said to me: <quote>Did <persName>Christ</persName> then worship and pray?</quote>—And I answered <persName>his
            Majesty</persName>: <quote>He did worship and pray.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> retorted saying: <quote>By the fact that you
               say that He worshipped and prayed, you deny His divinity, because if He worshipped and
               prayed He is not <persName>God</persName>; if He was <persName>God</persName>, he would not have worshipped and prayed.</quote>—And I
            replied: <quote>He did not worship and pray as <persName>God</persName>, because as such He is the receiver of the
               worship and prayer of both the celestial and the terrestrial beings, in conjunction with
               <persName>the Father</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName>, but He worshipped and prayed as a man, son of our human kind.
               It has been made manifest by our previous words that the very same <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is
               <persName>Word-God</persName> and man, as <persName>God</persName> He is born of <persName>the Father</persName>, and as man of <persName>Mary</persName>. He further
               worshipped and prayed for our sake, because He Himself was in no need of worship and
               prayer.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>There is no creature that has no need of worship and
            prayer.</quote>—And I replied: <quote>Has <persName>Jesus Christ, the Word of God</persName>, sinned or not?</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName>
            said: <quote>May <persName>God</persName> preserve me from saying such a thing!</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31"/> —And I then asked: <quote>Has <persName>God</persName>
               created the worlds with His Word or not?</quote> And <persName>our King</persName> replied in the affirmative and
            said <quote>Yes.</quote>—And I then asked: <quote>Is the one who is neither a sinner nor in need of
               anything, in need of worship and prayer?</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> answered <quote>No.</quote> —And I then said
            to him: <quote>If the <persName>Christ</persName> is a Word from <persName>God</persName>, and a man from <persName>Mary</persName>, and if as a <persName>Word of God</persName>
               He is the Lord of everything, and as a man He did not commit any sin as the Book and <persName>our
                  King</persName> testify, and if he who is the Lord of everything and a creator is not in need, and
               he who is not a sinner is pure, it follows that <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> worshipped and prayed to
               <persName>God</persName> neither as one in need nor as a sinner, but He worshipped and prayed in order to
               teach worship and prayer to His disciples, and through them to every human being.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>The disciples would not have yielded to His teaching, if He had not put it into
            practice in His own person. There is no creature that has not sinned except <persName>Jesus
               Christ, the Word of God</persName>, and He is the only created being who in His own humanity
            appeared above the dirt of sin. As He was baptised without having any need of baptism,
            and as He died on the Cross but not because of His own sin, so also <pb n="32"/> He gave Himself
            to worship and prayer not for His own sake but in order to impart their knowledge to His
            disciples.</quote></p>
         <p><persName>Our God-loving King</persName> ended the above subject here, and embarked on another theme and said
            to me: <quote>How is it that you accept <persName>Christ</persName> and the Gospel from the testimony of the <title>Torah</title>
               and of the prophets, and you do not accept <persName>Muḥammad</persName> from the testimony of <persName>Christ</persName> and the
               Gospel?</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n32"/> And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>O <persName>our King</persName>, we have received concerning
                  <persName>Christ</persName> numerous and distinct testimonies from the <title>Torah</title> and the prophets. All of the
                  latter prophesied in one accord and harmony in one place about His mother: <quote>Behold a
                     virgin shall conceive and bear a son,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33"/> and taught us that He shall be conceived and
                  born without marital intercourse like <persName>the Word of God</persName>. It is inded fit that the One who
                  was born of <persName>the Father</persName> without a mother should have been born in the flesh from a virgin
                  mother without a father, in order that His second birth may be a witness to His first
                  birth. In another place they reveal to us His name: <quote>And His name shall be called
                     <quote>Emmanuel, Wonderful, Counsellor, and Mighty God</quote> of the worlds.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34"/></p>
         <p><quote>In another place the prophets reveal to us the miracles that He will work at His coming
            in saying, <quote>Behold your <persName>God</persName> will come. . . . He will come and save you. Then the eyes of
               the blind shall be opened, and the ears of the deaf shall hear. Then shall the lame man
               leap as an hart, and the tongue of the dumb shall be loosened.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35"/> Yet in another place
            they disclose to us His passion and His death, <quote>He shall be killed for our
               transgressions, and humbled for our iniquities.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36"/> Sometimes they speak to us about His
            resurrection, <quote>For Thou hast not left my soul in <placeName>Sheol</placeName>, nor hast Thou suffered <persName>Thy Holy
               One</persName> to see corruption,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37"/> and <quote><persName>The Lord</persName> hath said unto me, Thou art my Son; this day
                  have I begotten Thee.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38"/> Some other times they teach us concerning His Ascension to
            <placeName>Heaven</placeName>, <quote>Thou hast ascended on high, Thou hast led captivity captive, and Thou hast made
               gifts to men,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n39"/> and <quote><persName>God</persName> went up in glory, and <persName>the Lord</persName> with the sound of a 
                  trumpet.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n40"/> <pb n="33"/></p>
         <p><quote>Some other times they reveal to us His coining down from heaven in saying, <quote>I am one
            like the son of men coming on the clouds of heaven, and they brought Him near before the
            Ancient of days, and there was given Him dominion, and glory and a kingdom that all
            peoples of the earth should serve Him and worship Him. His dominion is an everlasting
            dominion, and His kingdom shall not pass away nor be destroyed.</quote>'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41"/> These and scores of
            other passages of the prophets show us <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> in a clear mirror and point to Him.
            So far as <persName>Muḥammad</persName> is concerned I have not received a single testimony either from <persName>Jesus
               Christ</persName> or from the Gospel which would refer to his name or to his works.</quote></p>
         <p>And our benevolent and gracious <persName>King</persName> made a sign to mean that he was not convinced, then
            he repeated twice to me the question: <quote>Have you not received any?</quote>—And I replied to him:
            <quote>No, O <persName>God-loving King</persName>, I have not received any.</quote>—And <persName>the King</persName> asked me: <quote>Who is then the
               <persName>Paraclete</persName>?</quote> —And I answered: <quote><persName>The Spirit of God</persName>.</quote>—And <persName>the King</persName> asked: <quote>What is the Spirit
                  of God?</quote>—And I replied: <quote><persName>God</persName>, by nature; and one who proceeds, by attribute; as <persName>Jesus
                     Christ</persName> taught about Him.</quote>—And <persName>our glorious King</persName> said: <quote>And what did <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> teach
                        about Him?</quote>—And I answered: <quote>He spoke to His disciples as follows: <quote>When I go away to <placeName>Heaven</placeName>, I will
                           send unto you <persName>the Spirit-Paraclete</persName> who proceeded from <persName>the Father</persName>, whom the world cannot
                           receive, who dwelleth with you and is among you, who searcheth all things, even the deep
                           things of <persName>God</persName>, who will bring to your remembrance all the truth that I have said unto
                           you, and who will take of mine and show unto you.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42"/> </p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>All these refer to <persName>Muḥammad</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43"/> —And I replied to him: <quote>If
            <persName>Muḥammad</persName> were <persName>the Paraclete</persName>, since <persName>the Paraclete</persName> is <persName>the Spirit of God</persName>, <persName>Muḥammad</persName>, would,
            therefore, be <persName>the Spirit of God</persName>; and <persName>the Spirit of God</persName> being uncircumscribed like <persName>God</persName>,
            <persName>Muḥammad</persName> would also be uncircumscribed like <persName>God</persName>; and he <pb n="34"/> who is uncircumscribed being
            invisible, <persName>Muḥammad</persName> would also be invisible and without a human body; and he who is
            without a body being uncomposed, <persName>Muḥammad</persName> would also be uncomposed. Indeed he who is a
            spirit has no body, and he who has no body is also invisible, and he who is invisible is
            also uncircumscribed; but he who is circumscribed is not <persName>the Spirit of God</persName>, and he who
            is not <persName>the Spirit of God</persName> is not <persName>the Paraclete</persName>. It follows from all this that <persName>Muḥammad</persName> is
            not <persName>the Paraclete</persName>. <persName>The Paraclete</persName> is from heaven and of the nature of <persName>the Father</persName>, and
            <persName>Muḥammad</persName> is from the earth and of the nature of <persName>Adam</persName>. Since heaven is not the same thing
            as earth, nor is <persName>God the Father</persName> identical with <persName>Adam</persName>, <persName>the Paraclete</persName> is not, therefore,
            <persName>Muḥammad</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Further, <persName>the Paraclete</persName> searches the deep things of <persName>God</persName>, but <persName>Muḥammad</persName> owns that he does
            not know what might befall him and those who accept him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44"/> He who searches all things
            even the deep things of <persName>God</persName> is not identical with the one who does not know what might
            happen to him and to those who acknowledge him. <persName>Muḥammad</persName> is therefore not <persName>the Paraclete</persName>.
            Again, <persName>the Paraclete</persName>, as <persName>Jesus</persName> told His disciples, was with them and among them while He
            was speaking to them, and since <persName>Muḥammad</persName> was not with them and among them, he cannot,
            therefore, have been <persName>the Paraclete</persName>. Finally, <persName>the Paraclete</persName> descended on the disciples
            ten days after the ascension of <persName>Jesus</persName> to heaven, while <persName>Muḥammad</persName> was born more than six
            hundred years later, and this impedes <persName>Muḥammad</persName> from being <persName>the Paraclete</persName>. And <persName>Jesus</persName>
            taught the disciples that <persName>the Paraclete</persName> is one God in three persons, and since <persName>Muḥammad</persName>
            does not believe in the doctrine of three persons in one Godhead, he cannot be <persName>the
               Paraclete</persName>. And <persName>the Paraclete</persName> wrought all sorts of prodigies and miracles through the
            disciples, and since <persName>Muḥammad</persName> did not work a single miracle through his followers and
            his disciples, he is not <persName>the Paraclete</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>That <persName>the Spirit-Paraclete</persName> is consubstantial with <persName>the Father</persName> and <persName>the Son</persName> is borne out by
            the fact that He is the maker of the heavenly powers and of everything, and since he who
            is the maker and creator of everything is <persName>God</persName>, <persName>the Spirit-Paraclete</persName> is therefore <persName>God</persName>;
            but the world is not able to receive <persName>God</persName>, as <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> said,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n45"/> because <persName>God</persName> is
            uncircumscribed. Now if <persName>Muḥammad</persName> were <persName>the Paraclete</persName>, since <pb n="35"/> this same <persName>Paraclete</persName> is
            <persName>the Spirit of God</persName>, <persName>Muhḥammad</persName> would therefore be <persName>the Spirit of God</persName>. Further, since <persName>David</persName>
            said, <quote>By <persName>the Spirit of God</persName> all the powers have been created,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46"/> celestial and
            terrestrial, <persName>Muḥammad</persName> would be the creator of the celestial and terrestrial beings. Now
            since <persName>Muḥammad</persName> is not the creator of heaven and earth, and since he who is not creator
            is not <persName>the Spirit of God</persName>, <persName>Muḥammad</persName> is, therefore, not <persName>the Spirit of God</persName>; and since the
            one who is not <persName>the Spirit of God</persName> is by inference not <persName>the Paraclete</persName>, <persName>Muḥammad</persName> is not <persName>the
               Paraclete</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>If he were mentioned in the Gospel, this mention would have been marked by a distinct
            portraiture characterising his coming, his name, his mother, and his people as the true
            portraiture of the coming of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is found in the <title>Torah</title> and in the prophets.
            Since nothing resembling this is found in the Gospel concerning <persName>Muḥammad</persName>, it is evident
            that there is no mention of him in it at all, and that is the reason why I have not
            received a single testimony from the Gospel about him.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47"/> </p>
         <p>And <persName>the God-loving King</persName> said to me: <quote>As the Jews behaved towards <persName>Jesus</persName> whom they did not
            accept, so the Christians behaved towards <persName>Muḥammad</persName> whom they did not accept.</quote>—And I
            replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>The Jews did not accept <persName>Jesus</persName> in spite of the fact that the
               <title>Torah</title> and the prophets were full of testimonies about Him, and this renders them worthy
               of condemnation. As to us we have not accepted <persName>Muḥammad</persName> because we have not a single
               testimony about him in our Books.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>There were many testimonies but
                  the Books have been corrupted, and you have removed them.</quote>—And I replied to him thus:
            <quote>Where is it known, O <persName>King</persName>, that the Books have been corrupted by us, and where is that
               uncorrupted Book from which you have learned that the Books which we use have been
               corrupted? If there is such a book let it be placed in the middle in order that we may
               learn from it which is the corrupted <pb n="36"/> Gospel and hold to that which is not corrupted.
               If there is no such a Gospel, how do you know that the Gospel of which we make use is
               corrupted?</quote></p>
         <p><quote>What possible gain could we have gathered from corrupting the Gospel? Even if there was
            mention of <persName>Muḥammad</persName> made in the Gospel, we would not have deleted his name from it; we
            would have simply said that <persName>Muḥammad</persName> has not come yet, and that he was not the one whom
            you follow, and that he was going to come in the future. Take the example of the Jews:
            they cannot delete the name of <persName>Jesus</persName> from the <title>Torah</title> and the Prophets, they only contend
            against Him in saying openly that He was going to come in the future, and that He has
            not come yet into the world. They resemble a blind man<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48"/> without eyes who stands in
            plain daylight and contends that the sun has not yet risen. We also would have done
            likewise; we would not have dared to remove the name of <persName>Muḥammad</persName> from our Book if it
            were found anywhere in it; we would have simply quibbled concerning his right name and
            person like the Jews do in the case of <persName>Jesus</persName>. To tell the truth, if I had found in the
            Gospel a prophecy concerning the coming of <persName>Muḥammad</persName>, I would have left the Gospel for
            the <title>Ḳur'ān</title>, as I have left the <title>Torah</title> and the Prophets for the Gospel.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Do you not believe that our Book was given by <persName>God</persName>?</quote>—And I
            replied to him: <quote>It is not my business to decide whether it is from <persName>God</persName> or not. But I
               will say something of which <persName>your Majesty</persName> is well aware, and that is all the words of <persName>God</persName>
               found in the <title>Torah</title> and in the Prophets, and those of them found in the Gospel and in the
               writings of the Apostles, have been confirmed by signs and miracles; as to the words of
               your Book they have not been corroborated by a single sign or miracle. It is imperative
               that signs and miracles should be annulled by other signs and miracles. When <persName>God</persName> wished
               to abrogate<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49"/> the Mosaic law, He confirmed by the signs and miracles wrought by the
               <persName>Christ</persName> and the Apostles that the words of the Gospel were from <persName>God</persName>, and by this He
               abrogated the words of the <title>Torah</title> and the first miracles.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50"/> Similarly, as He abrogated
               <pb n="37"/> the first signs and miracles by second ones, He ought to have abrogated the second
               signs and miracles by third ones. If <persName>God</persName> had wished to abrogate the Gospel and introduce
               another Book in its place He would have done this, because signs and miracles are
               witnesses of His will; but your Book has not been confirmed by a single sign and
               miracle. Since signs and miracles are proofs of the will of <persName>God</persName>, the conclusion drawn
               from their absence in your Book is well known to <persName>your Majesty</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> asked: <quote>Who is then the rider on an ass, and the rider on a camel?</quote>—And I
            replied: <quote>The rider on an ass is <persName>Darius the Mede</persName>, son of <persName>Assuerus</persName>, and the rider on a
               camel is <persName>Cyrus the Persian</persName>, who was from <placeName>Elam</placeName>. <persName>The King of <placeName>Elam</placeName></persName> destroyed the kingdom of
               the Medes, and passed it to the Persians,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51"/> as <persName>Darius the Mede</persName> had destroyed the kingdom
               of the Babylonians and passed it to the Medes.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>From where is this known?</quote>— And I replied: <quote>From the context.
            In the preceding passage the prophet said, <quote>Go up, O <placeName>Elam</placeName>, and mountains of <placeName>Media</placeName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n52"/> 
            By the words <hi rend="singleQuote">Mountains of Media</hi> <persName>Darius the Mede</persName> is meant, and by the word <hi rend="singleQuote">Elam</hi> the
            kingdom of the Persians is designated. The Book says also in the words that follow, <quote>And
               one of the horsemen came and said, <placeName>Babylon</placeName> is fallen, is fallen,</quote> and shows clearly that
            the passage refers to <persName>Darius</persName> and <persName>Cyrus</persName>, because it is they who destroyed the kingdom of
            the Babylonians.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>Why did he say that the first was riding on an ass, and the second
            on a camel?</quote>—And I replied: <quote>The reason is that asses are generally more in use in the
               country of the Medes, while in the country of the Persians and Elamites camels are more
               in evidence. Through animals the prophet referred to countries, and through countries to
               the powers and kingdoms which were to rise in them. Further, because the kingdom of the
               Medes was to be weak and indolent while that of the Persians or Elamites was to be <pb n="38"/>
               strong and valiant, <persName>God</persName> alluded to the kingdom of the Medes through the weak ass, and to
               that of Elamite and Persians through the valiant camel. In the <title>Book of Daniel</title> also <persName>God</persName>
               alluded to the kingdom of the Medes through the indolent bear, and to that of the
               Elamites and Persians through the valiant leopard.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n53"/> Again, in the vision of the <persName>King
                  Nebuchadnezzar</persName> <persName>God</persName> symbolised the kingdom of the Medes in the malleable silver, while
               that of the Persians and Elamites in the strong brass.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54"/> In this same way the prophet
               alluded to the kingdom of <placeName>Media</placeName> through the ass, and to that of <placeName>Elam</placeName> through the
               camel.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>The rider on the ass is <persName>Jesus</persName> and the rider on the camel is
            <persName>Muḥammad</persName>.</quote>—And I answered <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>O <persName>our God-loving King</persName>, neither the order of
               times nor the succession of events will allow us to refer in this passage the riding on
               the ass to <persName>Christ</persName> and the riding on the camel to <persName>Muḥammad</persName>. It is known with accuracy
               from, the order and succession of the revelations to the prophets that the ass refers to
               the Medes and the camel to the Elamites, and this order of the revelations and this
               succession of events impede us from ascribing the words of the scripture to other
               persons. Even if one, through similarity between adjectives and names, does violence to
               the context and refers the passage dealing with the ass to <persName>Jesus</persName> on account of a
               different passage: <quote>Lowly, and riding upon an ass, and upon a colt, the foal of an ass,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55"/> 
               yet it is not possible to refer the passage dealing with the camel to <persName>Muḥammad</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n56"/></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>For what reason?</quote>—And I replied: <quote>Because the prophet <persName>Jacob</persName> said,
            <quote>The sceptre of the kingdom shall not depart from <persName>Judah</persName>, nor an utterer of prophecy from
               his seed, until <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> come, because kingdom is His, and He is the expectation of
               the peoples.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n57"/> In this he shows that after the coming of the <persName>Christ</persName> <pb n="39"/> there will be
            neither prophet nor prophecy. And <persName>Daniel</persName> also concurs in saying that for putting an end
            to all vision and prophecy, and for the coming of <persName>Christ</persName>, the King, seven weeks and
            threescore and two weeks will elapse, and then the <persName>Christ</persName> will be killed, and there will
            not be any more kingdom and prophecy in <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n58"/> In this he showed that visions and
            prophecies will come to an end with the <persName>Christ</persName>. And the <persName>Christ</persName> Himself said: <quote>The
               prophets and the <title>Torah</title> prophesied until <persName>John</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n59"/> Every prophecy, therefore, ended with
            the time of <persName>Christ</persName>, and after <persName>Christ</persName> there was no prophecy nor did any prophet rise.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n60"/>
            All the prophets prophesied about <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, and the <persName>Christ</persName> directed us to the
            <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName>, and it is superfluous that after the knowledge that we have of <persName>God</persName>
            and the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName> we should be brought down to the knowledge of the human and
            earthly things.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>As to the prophets they prophesied sometimes concerning the earthly affairs and
            kingdoms, and some other times concerning the adorable Epiphany and Incarnation of the
            <persName>Word-God</persName>. As to <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> He did not reveal to us things dealing with the law and
            earthly affairs, but He solely taught us things dealing with the knowledge of <persName>God</persName> and
            the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName>. We have already said that all prophecy extended as far as <persName>Christ</persName>
            only, as <persName>Christ</persName> Himself and the prophets asserted, and since from the time of <persName>Christ</persName>
            downwards only the <placeName>Kingdom of God</placeName> is being preached, as <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> taught, it is
            superfluous that after the adorable Incarnation of <persName>Christ</persName> we should accept and
            acknowledge another prophecy and another prophet A good and praiseworthy order of things
            is that which takes us up from the bottom to the top, from the human to the divine
            things, and from the earthly to the heavenly things; but an order which would lower us
            from top to bottom, from divine to worldly, and from heavenly to earthly, things, is bad
            and blameworthy.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our victorious King</persName> said to me: <quote>Why do you worship the Cross?</quote>—And I replied:
            <quote>First because it is the cause of life.</quote>— <pb n="40"/> And <persName>our glorious King</persName> said to me: <quote>A cross
               is not the cause of life but rather of death.</quote>—And I replied to him: <quote>The cross, is as
                  you say, O <persName>King</persName>, the cause of death; but death is also the cause of resurrection, and
                  resurrection is the cause of life and immortality. In this sense the cross is the cause
                  of life and immortality, and this is the reason why through it, as a symbol of life and
                  immortality, we worship one and indivisible <persName>God</persName>. It is through it that <persName>God</persName> opened to us
                  the source of life and immortality, and <persName>God</persName> who at the beginning ordered light to come
                  out of darkness, who sweetened bitter water in bitter wood, who through the sight of a
                  deadly serpent granted life to the children of <placeName>Israel</placeName>—handed to us the fruit of life
                  from the wood of the Cross, and caused rays of immortality to shine upon us from the
                  branches of the Cross.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>As we honour the roots because of the fruits that come out of them, so also we honour
            the Cross as the root of which the fruit of life was born to us, and from which the ray
            of immortality shone<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n61"/> upon us. As a decisive proof of the love of <persName>God</persName> for all,
            luminous rays of His love shine from all His creatures visible and invisible, but the
            most luminous rays of the love of <persName>God</persName> are those that shine from the rational beings.
            This love of <persName>God</persName> can then be demonstrated from all creatures, and from the ordinary
            Divine Providence that is manifest in them, but the great wealth of His love for all
            humanity is more strikingly in evidence in the fact that He delivered to death in the
            flesh His beloved Son for the life, salvation, and resurrection of all. It is only just,
            therefore, O <persName>our victorious King</persName>, that the medium through which <persName>God</persName> showed His love to
            all, should also be the medium through which all should show their love to <persName>God</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62"/> </p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Can <persName>God</persName> then Himself die?</quote>—And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>The
            <persName>Son of God</persName> died in our nature, but not in His Divinity. When the royal purple and the
            insignia of the kingdom are torn, the dishonour redounds to the King: so also is die
            case with the death of the body of the <persName>Son-God</persName>.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>May <persName>God</persName>
               preserve me from saying such a thing.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n63"/> They did not kill Him and they did not crucify
               Him, but He made a <pb n="41"/> similitude for them in this way.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64"/> —And I said to him: <quote>It is
                  written in the Sūrat `Īsa, <quote>Peace be upon me the day I was born, and the day I die, and
                     the day I shall be sent again alive.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65"/> This passage shows that He died and rose up.
            Further, <persName>God</persName> said to <persName>`Īsa (Jesus)</persName> <quote>I will make Thee die and take Thee up again to me.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66"/> </p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>He did not die then, but He will die afterwards.</quote>—And I replied to
            him: <quote>Therefore He did not go up to heaven either, nor was He sent again alive, but He
               will go up to heaven afterwards and will be sent again alive in the future. No, <persName>our
                  King</persName>, <persName>Jesus</persName> did go up to heaven a long time ago, and has been sent again alive, as your
               Book also testifies. If He went up it is obvious that He had died previously, and if He
               had died, it is known that He had died by crucifixion, as the Prophets had stated before
               His coming.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Which prophet said that He died by crucifixion?</quote>—And I replied
            to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>First the prophet <persName>David</persName>, who said, <quote>They pierced my hands and my feet,
               and my bones cried; and they looked and stared upon me; they parted my garments among
               them and cast lots upon my vesture.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n67"/> The Gospel testifies that all these were
               fulfilled. And <persName>Isaiah</persName> said, <quote>He shall be killed for our sins and humbled for our
                  iniquity.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n68"/> And the prophet <persName>Jeremiah</persName> said, <quote>Wood will eat into His flesh and will
                     destroy Him from the land of the living. I gave my body to wounds and my cheeks to
                     blows, and I did not turn my face from shame and spittle.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n69"/> And the prophet <persName>Daniel</persName>
               said, <quote>And <persName>the Messiah</persName> shall be killed but not for Himself.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n70"/> And the prophet
               <persName>Ẓechariah</persName> said, <quote>And smite the shepherd of <placeName>Israel</placeName> on his cheeks,</quote> and <quote>O sword, awake
                  against my shepherd.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n71"/> Indeed numerous are the passages in which the prophets spoke of
               His death, murder, and crucifixion.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>He made a similitude only for them in this way.</quote>—And I replied to
            him: <quote>And who made a similitude for them in this way, O <persName>our King</persName>? How did <persName>God</persName> deceive
               them and <pb n="42"/> show them something which was not true? It is incongruous to <persName>God</persName> that He
               should deceive and show something for another thing. If <persName>God</persName> deceived them and made a
               similitude for them, the Apostles who simply wrote what <persName>God</persName> had shown to them, would be
               innocent of the deception, and the real cause of it would be <persName>God</persName>. If on the other hand,
               we say that it is <persName>Satan</persName> who made such a similitude for the Apostles, what has <persName>Satan</persName> to
               do in the Economy of <persName>God</persName>? And who dares to say about the ḥawārīyūn<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n72"/> that <persName>Satan</persName> was
               able to deceive them? The Apostles drove and cast away the demons, who shouted and run
               away from them on account of the Divine power that was accompanying them. If crucifixion
               was only an unreal similitude, and if from it death took place, even death would be an
               unreal similitude; we further assert that from this death there has been resurrection,
               which in this case would also be an unreal similitude; then out of this resurrection
               there has been ascension to heaven, which would also be unreal and untrue. Now since the
               resurrection precedes the ascension, this resurrection is also a reality and not a
               similitude; and since death was a reality and not a similitude, and since death is
               preceded by crucifixion, this crucifixion is consequently a reality also, and not an
               illusion or a similitude.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>It was not honourable to <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> that <persName>God</persName> should have allowed
            Him to be delivered to Jews in order that they might kill Him.</quote>—And I answered <persName>his
               Majesty</persName>: <quote>The prophets have been killed by the Jews, but that not all those who have
                  been killed by the Jews are despicable and devoid of honour<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n73"/> is borne out by the fact
                  that none of the true prophets is despicable and devoid of honour in the sight of <persName>God</persName>.
                  Since it is true that the prophets have generally been killed by the Jews, it follows
                  that not all those who have been killed by the Jews are despicable and devoid of honour.
                  This we assert for the prophets. So far as <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is concerned we say that the
                  Jews crucified only the <persName>Christ</persName> in the flesh, which He delivered to them voluntarily, and
                  His murder was not imposed forcibly upon Him by them. Because He, <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, said, <quote>I
                     have power upon my soul to lay it down, and I have power to take <pb n="43"/> it again; and no
                     man taketh it from me</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74"/> In this He showed that He would suffer out of His own free
                  will, and not out of His own weakness or from the omnipotence of the Jews. He who when
                  hanging on the wood of the Cross moved the heavens, shook the earth, changed the
                  dazzling sun into darkness and the shining moon into blood-redness, and He who rent the
                  stones and the graves, raised and resuscitated the dead, could not be so weak as not to
                  be able to save Himself from the hands of the Jews. It is, therefore, out of His own
                  free will that He approached the suffering on the cross and death, and He did not bear
                  the death of crucifixion at the hands of the Jews out of abjection and weakness on His
                  part, but He bore both crucifixion and death at the hands of the Jews out of His own
                  free will.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>No blame attaches, therefore, to the Jews from His death, if they
            simply fulfilled and satisfied His wish.</quote>—And I answered <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>If the Jews had
               solely crucified Him in order that He might raise the dead and ascend to heaven, they
               would naturally have been not only free from blame, but worthy of thousands of crowns
               and of encomia of all kinds, but if these same Jews crucified Him in order not that He
               might rise up again from the dead and ascend to heaven, but in order that they might
               intensify His death and obliterate Him from the surface of the earth, they would with
               great justice be worthy of blame and death. Indeed they crucified Him not in order that
               He might go up to heaven but go down to <placeName>Sheol</placeName>; <persName>God</persName>, however, raised Him up from the dead
               and took Him up to heaven.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our God-loving King</persName> said to me; <quote>Which of the two things would you be willing to
            admit? Was the <persName>Christ</persName> willing to be crucified or not? If He was willing to be crucified,
            the Jews who simply accomplished His will should not be cursed and despised. If,
            however, He was not willing to be crucified and He was crucified, He was weak and the
            Jews were strong. In this case, how can He be <persName>God</persName>, He who found Himself unable to
            deliver Himself from the hands of His crucifiers whose will appeared to be stronger than
            His?</quote></p>
         <p>And I answered these objections by other questions as follows: <quote>What would our King,
            endowed with high acumen and great wisdom, say to this: When <persName>God</persName> created <persName>Satan</persName> as one of
            the angels, did He wish this <persName>Satan</persName> to be an angel or not? If <persName>God</persName> wished Him <pb n="44"/> to be
            Satan instead of an angel, the wicked Satan would, therefore, simply be accomplishing
            the will of <persName>God</persName>; but if <persName>God</persName> did not wish <persName>Satan</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n75"/> to be <persName>Satan</persName> but an angel, and in spite
            of that he became <persName>Satan</persName>, the will of <persName>Satan</persName> became stronger than the will of <persName>God</persName>. How can
            we then call <persName>God</persName> one whose will was overcome by the will of <persName>Satan</persName>, and one against whom
            <persName>Satan</persName> prevailed?</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Another question: Did <persName>God</persName> wish <persName>Adam</persName> to go out of <placeName>Paradise</placeName> or not? If He wished to drive
            him out of <placeName>Paradise</placeName>, why should <persName>Satan</persName> be blamed, who simply helped to do the will of <persName>God</persName>
            in his driving <persName>Adam</persName> from <placeName>Paradise</placeName>. On the other hand, if <persName>God</persName> did not wish <persName>Adam</persName> to go out
            of <placeName>Paradise</placeName>, how is it that the will of <persName>God</persName> became weak and was overcome, while the will
            of <persName>Satan</persName> became strong and prevailed? How can He be <persName>God</persName>, if His will has been completely
            overcome? The fact that <persName>Satan</persName> and <persName>Adam</persName> sinned against the will of <persName>God</persName> does not affect
            the divinity of <persName>God</persName> and does not show Him to be weak and deficient, and the fact that
            <persName>God</persName> had willed <persName>Satan</persName> to fall from heaven and <persName>Adam</persName> to go out of <placeName>Paradise</placeName> does not absolve
            <persName>Satan</persName> and <persName>Adam</persName> from blame and censure, and the fact that they did not sin to accomplish
            the will of <persName>God</persName> but to accomplish their own will are a good analogy to the case of <persName>Jesus</persName>
            <persName>Christ</persName>. He should not indeed be precluded from being <persName>God</persName>, nor should He be rendered weak
            and deficient in strength by the fact that the Jews sinned but not by His will, and that
            in their insolence they crucified Him; and the fact that the <persName>Christ</persName> wished to be
            crucified and die for the life, resurrection and salvation of all should not exempt the
            Jews from hell and curse.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>The Jews did not crucify the <persName>Christ</persName> because He willed it, but they crucified Him
            because of their hatred and malice both to Himself and to the One who sent Him. They
            crucified Him in order that they might destroy Him completely, and He willed to be
            crucified so that He might live again and rise from the dead, and be to all men the sign
            and proof of the resurrection of the dead.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Another question: What would our victorious and powerful King say about those who fight
            for the sake of <persName>God</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76"/> Do they wish to be killed or not? If they do not wish to be
            killed and are killed, their death has no merit, and they will not go to heaven;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77"/> and
            if they <pb n="45"/> wish to be killed, are their murderers blameworthy or not? If they are not
            blameworthy, how is it that unbelievers who killed Muslims and believers are not
            blameworthy, and if they are blameworthy, why should they be so when what they did was
            simply to fulfil the wish of the victims? The fact is that the murderers of the men who
            fight for the sake of <persName>God</persName> are not exempted from fire and hell; indeed, the murderers do
            not slay them so that they may go to heaven, but they do it out of their wickedness and
            in order to destroy them. In this way also the Jews will not be exempted from the
            eternal fire by the fact that <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> wished to be crucified and die for all. They
            did not crucify Him because He wished to be crucified, but because they wished to
            crucify Him. They did not crucify Him in order that He might live again and rise up from
            the dead, but they crucified Him in order that He might be destroyed once for all. Let
            this suffice for this subject.</quote></p>
         <p><quote><persName>Jesus</persName> was also able to save Himself from the Jews, if He had wished to do so. This is
            known first from the fact that on several occasions they ventured to seize Him, but
            because He did not wish to be seized by them, no one laid hands on Him. It is also known
            by the fact that while He was hanging on the cross, He moved the heavens, shook the
            earth, darkened the sun, blood-reddened the moon, rent the stones, opened the graves,
            and gave life to the dead that were in them. He who was able to do all these things in
            such a divine way, was surely able to save Himself from the Jews. And He who rescued
            from the mouth of <placeName>Sheol</placeName> in such a wonderful way the temple of His humanity after it had
            lain therein for three days and three nights, was surely able to save and rescue the
            very same temple from the unjust Jews, but if He had saved it He would not have been
            crucified, and if He had not been crucified He would not have died, and if He had not
            died He would not have risen up to immortal life, and if He had not risen up to immortal
            life, the children of men would have remained without a sign and a decisive proof of the
            immortal life.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>To-day because of the resurrection of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> from the dead the eyes of all the
            children of men look towards an immortal life, and consequently in order that this
            expectation of the immortal life and of the world to come might be indelibly impressed
            upon mankind, it was right that <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> should rise from the dead; but in order
            that He might rise from the dead, it was right that He should first die, and in <pb n="46"/>
            order that He might truly die it was imperative that His death should have been first
            witnessed by all, as His resurrection was witnessed by all. This is why He died by
            crucifixion. If He were to suffer, to be crucified and die before all, when He had to
            rise from the dead His resurrection would also be believed by all. Immortal life is thus
            the fruit of the crucifixion, and the resurrection of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> from the dead—a
            resurrection which all believers expect—is the outcome of the death on the cross.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>If He had delivered Himself from the hands of His crucifiers, He would have brought
            profit to Himself alone, and would have been of no use to the rest of mankind, like
            <persName>Enoch</persName> and <persName>Elijah</persName> who are kept in <placeName>Paradise</placeName> beyond the reach of death for their exclusive
            benefit, but now that He delivered Himself into the hands of crucifiers, and they dared
            to kill Him on their own account, He conquered death after three days and three nights,
            rose up to immortal life and brought profit first to His own self and then to all
            creatures, and He became the sign and proof of resuscitation and resurrection to all
            rational beings. He put His wish into practice in an Economy full of wisdom, and His
            crucifiers cannot be absolved from blame any more than the brothers of <persName>Joseph</persName> can be
            absolved from blame.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>When <persName>Joseph</persName> was sold by his brothers as a slave to some men, and he afterwards rose up
            from slavery to the government of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, it was not the aim of those who sold him that
            he should govern <placeName>Egypt</placeName>. If they had dreamed of this they would never have sold him into
            slavery. Indeed, those who were unable to bear the recital of <persName>Joseph</persName>'s dreams on account
            of their intense jealousy and violent envy, how could they have borne seeing him at the
            head of a Government. They sold him into slavery but <persName>God</persName>, because of the injustice done
            to him by his brothers, raised him from slavery to power. This analogy applies to the
            Jews and to <persName>Satan</persName> their teacher: if they had known that <persName>Christ</persName> would rise again to life
            from the dead and ascend from earth to heaven after His crucifixion, they would never
            have induced themselves to crucify Him, but they crucified Him out of their own wicked
            will.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>What would you say to this, O <persName>King of Kings</persName>: If <persName>your Majesty</persName> had a house and wanted to
            pull it down in order to rebuild it again, if an enemy came and pulled it down and
            burned it with fire, would you give thanks to that enemy for his action in pulling down
            the house, or <pb n="47"/> would you not rather inflict punishment on him, as on one who had
            demolished and burned a house belonging to <persName>your Majesty</persName>?</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> replied: <quote>The one
               who would do such a thing would deserve a painful death.</quote>—And I then answered: <quote>So also
                  the Jews deserve all kinds of woes, because they wished to demolish and destroy the
                  temple of the <persName>Word of God</persName>, which was anointed and confirmed by the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>, which
                  was divinely fashioned without the intervention of man from a holy virgin, and which <persName>God</persName>
                  raised afterwards to heaven. <persName>God</persName> showed in all this its thorough distinction from, and
                  its high superiority over, all else. As the heaven is high above the earth, the temple
                  of the <persName>Word of God</persName> is greater and more distinguished than all angels and children of
                  men. If <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is in heaven and heaven is the throne of <persName>God</persName>, it follows that <persName>Jesus
                     Christ</persName> sat on the throne of <persName>God</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Who gave you the Gospel?</quote>— And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote><persName>Our
            Lord Jesus Christ</persName></quote>—And <persName>our victorious King</persName> asked: <quote>Was it before or after His ascension
               to heaven?</quote>—And I replied to him: <quote>Before His ascension to heaven. As the Gospel is the
                  narrative of the Economy of the works and words of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, and as the works of
                  <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> were done and His concrete words were uttered before His ascension to
                  heaven, it follows that the Gospel was delivered to us before His ascension to heaven.
                  Further, if the Gospel is the proclamation of the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName>, and this
                  proclamation of the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName> has been delivered to us by the mouth of <persName>our Lord</persName>,
                  it follows that the Gospel was also delivered to us by the mouth of <persName>our Lord</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName>, invested with power, said to me: <quote>Was not a part of the Gospel written by
            <persName>Matthew</persName>, another part by <persName>Mark</persName>, a third part by <persName>Luke</persName>, and a fourth part by <persName>John</persName>?</quote>—And I
            replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>It is true, O <persName>our King</persName>, that these four men wrote the Gospel.
               They did not write it, however, out of their own head nor from the fancies of their
               mind. Indeed they had no literary attainments of any kind, and by profession they were
               generally fishermen, shoemakers or tentmakers. They wrote and transmitted to us what
               they had heard and learned from <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, who had taught them in actions and words
               during all the time He was walking with them in the flesh on the earth, and what the
               <persName>Spirit-Paraclete</persName> had reminded them of.</quote><pb n="48"/> </p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Why are they different from one another and contradict one
            another?</quote>—And I answered <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>It is true that there is difference between their
               words, as to contradiction there is not any between them, not even in a single case.
               Different people write differently even on the creation of <persName>God</persName>, the <persName>Lord</persName> of all: some of
               them speak of the great height of heaven, some others of the brilliant rays of the sun,
               some others of the wonderful phases of the moon, some others of the fine beauty of the
               stars, some others of the atmosphere, some others of the land and sea, and some others
               of some other topics. Further, among the people who write on heaven alone some speak of
               its immense height and some others of the swiftness of its movement, and among those who
               speak of the sun alone, some write on the high and dazzling resplendence of its light,
               some others on its heat, some others on the roundness of its sphere, some others on its
               purity and clearness, and some others on its multitudinous powers and effects.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Let <persName>your Majesty</persName> order some men to write on the topic of the resplendent glory of <persName>your
            Majesty</persName>, and some others on the great quantity of your gold and silver, and some others
            on the lustre of your pearls and precious stones, and some others on the beauty and fine
            features of the face of <persName>your Majesty</persName>, and some others on the power, might and strength
            of your Kingdom, and some others on the wisdom and intelligence of <persName>your Majesty</persName>, and yet
            some others on your gentleness, virtue, and piety. In what they will write there might
            be differences of words in their statements of facts, but there will not be any
            contradiction between them, not even in a single item. They will all be right in all
            that they will write, although some of them might omit some items, because there is no
            one who is able to speak with accuracy of everything dealing with the works of <persName>God</persName> nor
            with the greatness of the glory of <persName>your Majesty</persName>. The above applies to what the
            evangelists wrote concerning the words, deeds, and natures of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>. There are
            here and there differences in their statements, but as to contradictions there are none
            whatever. The four of them write in the same way and without discrepancies and
            differences on the main topics of His conception, birth, baptism, teaching, passion on
            the cross, death, burial, resurrection, and ascension to heaven.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our powerful King</persName> said to me: <quote>You should know, O <persName>Catholicos</persName>, that as <persName>God</persName> gave the
            law through the prophet <persName>Moses</persName> and <pb n="49"/> the Gospel through the <persName>Christ</persName>, so He gave the
            furḳān<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78"/> through <persName>Muḥammad</persName></quote>—And I replied: <quote>O my victorious <persName>King</persName>, the changes that were
               to take place in the law given through <persName>Moses</persName>, <persName>God</persName> had clearly predicted previously
               through the prophets whom we have mentioned. <persName>God</persName> said thus through the prophet <persName>Jeremiah</persName>
               and showed the dissolution of the law of <persName>Moses</persName> and the setting up of the Gospel, <quote>Behold
                  the days come, saith the <persName>Lord</persName>, that I will make a new covenant with the house of <placeName>Israel</placeName>
                  and with the house of <placeName>Judah</placeName>: not according to the covenant that I made with their
                  fathers in the day that I took them by the hand to bring them out of the land of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>,
                  which covenant they nullified, and I also despised them, saith the <persName>Lord</persName>: but this shall
                  be the covenant that I will make with the house of <placeName>Israel</placeName>: After those days, saith the
                  <persName>Lord</persName>, I will put my law in their minds and write it in their hearts, and will be their
                  God, and they shall be my people. And they shall teach no more every man his neighbour
                  nor his brother, saying. <hi rend="doubleQuote">Know the Lord,</hi> for they shall all know me from the least of
                  them unto the greatest of them.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n79"/> In the above words <persName>God</persName> demonstrated both the
               dissolution of the law of <persName>Moses</persName> and the setting up of the Gospel.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Through another prophet, called <persName>Joel</persName>, <persName>God</persName> disclosed the signs which would occur at the
            time of the dissolution of the <title>Torah</title> and the setting up of the Gospel, and the signs
            concerning the <persName>Spirit-Paraclete</persName> which the Apostles, the commanders of the army of the
            Gospel, were to receive, because He said through him, <quote>And afterwards I will pour out my
               spirit upon all flesh, and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy, and your old men
               shall dream dreams, and your young men shall see visions. And on my servants and on my
               handmaidens I will pour my spirit in those days.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n80"/> This is said of the
            <persName>Spirit-Paraclete</persName> who descended on the Apostles after the ascension of <persName>Jesus</persName> to heaven,
            according to the promise that He had previously given. And the prophet adds, <quote>And I will
               show wonders in the <pb n="50"/> heavens and the earth, blood and fire, and pillars of smoke. The
               sun shall be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n81"/> All this took place at
            the Passion of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> on the Cross. And he further adds, <quote>Before the great and the
               terrible day of the <persName>Lord</persName>;</quote> he calls the <quote>great and terrible day of the <persName>Lord</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n82"/> the day
                  on which the <persName>Word-God</persName> will appear in our flesh with great power and glory of angels, and
                  the day on which the stars will fall from heaven, as <persName>Jesus</persName> Himself said in the Gospel.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n83"/> 
            And the prophet further adds, <quote>Whosoever shall call on the name of the <persName>Lord</persName> shall be
               saved,</quote> that is to say whosoever shall receive the Gospel of <persName>God</persName> shall live an
            everlasting life.</quote></p>
         <p><quote><persName>God</persName>, therefore, pointed clearly to the transition from the Law to the Gospel when He
            showed us a new covenant, and signs, witnessed by men, that appeared in heaven and
            earth, in sun, moon, and stars, and when He showed us the gifts of the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName> which
            He imparted to the Apostles: wonders, signs, and miracles. <persName>God</persName> nowhere showed such
            irrefragable signs for the transition from the Gospel to something else. The Law that
            was given by <persName>Moses</persName> was the symbol of the Gospel, and the Gospel is the symbol of the
            <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName>, and there is nothing higher than the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our powerful King</persName> said to me: <quote>Did not <persName>God</persName> say clearly to the children of <placeName>Israel</placeName>, <quote>I
            will raise you up a prophet from among your brethren like unto me.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n84"/> Who are the
            brethren of the children of <placeName>Israel</placeName> besides the Arabs,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n85"/> and who is the prophet like unto
            <persName>Moses</persName> besides <persName>Muḥammad</persName>?</quote>—And I answered <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>The Israelites have many other
               brethren besides the Arabs, O <persName>our Sovereign</persName>. First of all the six sons of <persName>Abraham</persName> by
               <persName>Keturah</persName> are nearer to the Arabs than the Israelites, then the Edomites composed of three
               hundred clans are also nearer to the Israelites than the Arabs. <persName>Jacob</persName> from whom
               descended the Israelites, and <persName>Esau</persName> from whom sprang the Edomites are indeed brothers and
               sons of <persName>Isaac</persName>, and <persName>Isaac</persName> from whom the Jews descend and <persName>Ishmael</persName> from whom the Arabs
               spring, together with <persName>Zimran</persName> and <persName>Jokshan</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n86"/> and their brothers, the sons of <persName>Keturah</persName>, are
               children of <persName>Abraham</persName>. If the sentence of the <pb n="51"/> prophet <persName>Moses</persName> refers to the brethren of
               the children of <placeName>Israel</placeName> and not to their own twelve tribes, it would be more appropriate
               to apply it to the Edomites, because it has been shown that they are nearer to the
               Israelites than the Arabs. It is not only the Arabs who are the brethren of the
               Israelites but also the Ammonites and the Moabites.</quote></p>
         <p>"Further, Moses said to the children of Israel that God will raise up from among their
            brethren a prophet to themselves and not to the Arabs, because he says that the prophet
            whom the Lord your God will raise up will be from among yourselves and not from outside
            yourselves, from your brethren and not from strangers, and then that prophet will be
            similar and not dissimilar to him in doctrine. This Biblical passage resembles that
            other passage in which God said to them concerning a king, 'I will raise up for thee a
            king from thy brethren.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n87"/> As in the subject of a king God does not refer to the
            children of Ishmael by the word 'their brethren,' so also in the subject of a prophet He
            does not refer to them through the same word.</p>
         <p><quote>Further, you assert that <persName>Muḥammad</persName> has been sent as a prophet to his own people.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n88"/> We
            must examine in this respect the construction of the words. It is said: a prophet from
            yourselves, from among your brethren, and like unto me. If <persName>Muḥammad</persName> be a prophet like
            <persName>Moses</persName>, <persName>Moses</persName> wrought miracles and prodigies; and <persName>Muḥammad</persName>, who would in this case be a
            prophet like <persName>Moses</persName>, should have wrought many miracles and prodigies. And then, if
            <persName>Muḥammad</persName> be a prophet like <persName>Moses</persName>, since <persName>Moses</persName> practised and taught the Law that was
            given to him on <placeName>Mount Sinai</placeName>, <persName>Muḥammad</persName> should similarly have taught the <title>Torah</title> and
            practised the circumcision, and observed the Jewish Sabbath and festivals. <persName>Muḥammad</persName> did
            not teach the <title>Torah</title>, and <persName>Moses</persName> taught the <title>Torah</title>, the prophet <persName>Muḥammad</persName> is not, therefore,
            like unto <persName>Moses</persName>, because the one who was to be a prophet like unto <persName>Moses</persName>, would not have
            changed anything from <persName>Moses</persName>, and the one who is different in one thing from <persName>Moses</persName> is not
            a prophet like unto <persName>Moses</persName>. The prophet <persName>Moses</persName> spoke the above words concerning the
            prophets who from time to time rose after him from this or that Jewish tribe, such as
            <persName>Joshua</persName> son of <persName>Nun</persName>, <persName>David</persName>, <persName>Samuel</persName>, and others <pb n="52"/> after them, who from generation to
            generation were sent to the Israelites.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n89"/> </p>
         <p>And <persName>our victorious King</persName> said to me: <quote>What is the punishment of the man who kills his
            mother?</quote>—And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>And what is the punishment of the man who does
               not respect the honour of his mother?</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Strokes, fetters, and
                  death.</quote>—And I said to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>The decision of <persName>your Majesty</persName> is just. And the man
                     who kills his mother is also liable to the same punishment.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said to me:
            <quote><persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is, therefore, liable to the same punishment, because He let His mother
               die and so killed her.</quote>—And I asked the <persName>King</persName>: <quote>Which is the highest, this world or the
                  world to come?</quote> And <persName>our King</persName> answered: <quote>The world to come.</quote>—And I then replied to <persName>his
                     Majesty</persName>: <quote>If <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> let His mother die, and through death He transferred her to
                        the next world, which as <persName>your Majesty</persName> asserts is better than this one, He therefore
                        invested His mother with a higher dignity and more sublime honour; and since the one who
                        honours his mother is worthy of all blessings, <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> who transferred His mother
                        from the mortal life to the immortal one and from the land of troubles to the <placeName>Kingdom of
                           Heaven</placeName>, is, therefore, Worthy of all blessings.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>What should ?<persName>Jesus Christ</persName> have done? While He takes up everybody from earth to heaven,
            and while, as <persName>God</persName> said, He causes them to be immortal after having been mortal, should
            He only have <pb n="53"/> left His own mother in this mortal life? This would have been a great
            disgrace; but her death which took place like that of every other human being, was only
            natural and did not bring the smallest disgrace to her. As it was not a dishonour to her
            to have been born from a womb, so also it was not a dishonour to her to have been born
            again to eternal life from death and earth.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n90"/> If <persName>Mary</persName> had not died, she would not have
            risen; and if she had not risen, she would have been far from the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName>, and
            it is fair that <persName>Mary</persName>, the mother of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> through whom the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName> was
            revealed, should have been raised up first to heaven. It was, therefore, imperative that
            she should have died. He who demolishes a house in order to renew it and ornament it, is
            not blameworthy but praiseworthy.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Is Jesus Christ good or not?</quote>— And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>:
            <quote>If <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is the <persName>Word of God</persName>, and <persName>God</persName> is good, <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is, therefore, good.
               He is one nature with <persName>God</persName>, like light is one with the sun.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>How then
                  did <persName>Jesus</persName> say, <quote>There is none good but one, that is one God?</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n91"/> —And I replied to him:
            <quote>Was the <persName>Prophet David</persName> just or not?</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>He was just and head of the
               just.</quote>— And I said then: <quote>How then did the prophet <persName>David</persName> say, <quote>There is no one that is
                  just, no, not one,</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n92"/> —And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>This saying does not include <persName>David</persName>. It has
                     been said of the wicked ones.</quote>— And I said: <quote>So also the sentence, <quote>There is none good
                        but one</quote> cannot possibly include the <persName>Christ</persName>. As the sentence, <quote>There is no one that is
                           just</quote> embraces many others to the exclusion of <persName>David</persName>, so also the sentence, <quote>There is
                              none good</quote> embraces many others to the exclusion of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, and as <persName>David</persName> did not
                        include himself when he said, <quote>There is no just man, no, not even one,</quote> so also the
                        <persName>Christ</persName> did not include Himself when he said, <quote>There is none good but one, and that is
                           one God.</quote></quote></p>
         <p><quote>The very same <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> who said about Himself, <quote>I am the good shepherd,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n93"/> could
            not have said the above sentence, <hi rend="singleQuote">There is none good</hi> about Himself. Indeed, He said
            this sentence about the one whom He was addressing. The latter was thinking this in his
            <pb n="54"/> heart: how difficult are the laws that <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is establishing! There is none
            good but one God who gave us all the good things found in the land of promise. As to
            <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, He disclosed to him his hidden thoughts and showed to him that his words
            were in flagrant contradiction with his thoughts, in calling Him in his words <hi rend="singleQuote">good
               master</hi> while in his thoughts he was saying <quote>This one was no good</quote>, and wishing to
            rebuke him He disclosed to him his thoughts and said to him, <quote>Why callest thou me good
               with thy tongue while in thy thoughts thou sayest about me, <quote>This one is no good,
                  because He orders me to squander my fortune; there is none good but one that is <persName>God</persName>?</quote></quote>
            <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> makes mention both of a good man and a good tree.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n94"/> How is it possible that
            there is a good man and a good tree, and <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> alone is not good? How can this be
            possible?</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>If you accepted <persName>Muḥammad</persName> as a prophet your words would be
            beautiful and your meanings fine</quote>— And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>We find that there is
               only one prophet who would come to the world after the ascension of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> to
               heaven and His descent from heaven.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95"/> This we know from the prophet <persName>Malachi</persName> and from the
               angel <persName>Gabriel</persName> when he announced the birth of <persName>John</persName> to <persName>Zechariah</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>And who is that prophet?</quote>—And I replied: <quote>The prophet <persName>Elijah</persName>. The
            prophet <persName>Malachi</persName> who is the last of the prophets of the Law, said, <quote>Remember ye the law
               of <persName>Moses</persName>, my servant, which I commanded unto him in <placeName>Horeb</placeName> for all <placeName>Israel</placeName>, with the
               statutes and judgments. Behold I will send you <persName>Elijah</persName> the prophet, before the coming of
               the great and dreadful day of the <persName>Lord</persName>. And he shall turn the heart of the fathers to
               the children, and the heart of the children to their fathers, lest I come and smite the
               earth with a curse.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n96"/> And the angel <persName>Gabriel</persName> when announcing to <persName>Zechariah</persName> the <pb n="55"/> birth
            of <persName>John</persName> reminded him of these very words, because he said to him, <quote>Fear not, <persName>Zechariah</persName>,
               for thy prayer is heard, and thy wife <persName>Elizabeth</persName> shall bear thee a son, and thou shalt
               call his name <persName>John</persName>. And thou shalt have joy and gladness, and many shall rejoice at his
               birth. For he shall be great in the sight of the <persName>Lord</persName>, and shall be filled with the <persName>Holy
                  Ghost</persName> even from his mother's womb. And many of the children of <placeName>Israel</placeName> shall he turn to
               the Lord their God. And he shall go before him in the spirit and power of the prophet
               <persName>Elijah</persName>, to turn<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n97"/> the hearts of the fathers to the children and the disobedient to the
               wisdom of the just, and to make ready a people prepared for the <persName>Lord</persName>.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n98"/> </p>
         <p><quote>Think, O <persName>our victorious Sovereign</persName>, how the angel called <persName>Jesus</persName> <hi rend="singleQuote">the Lord their God.</hi> It
            is this prophet <persName>Elijah</persName> who, as we have learned, will come into the world after the
            ascension of <persName>Jesus</persName> to heaven. He will come to rebuke the <persName>Antichrist</persName>, and to teach and
            preach to everybody concerning the second apparition of <persName>Jesus</persName> from heaven. As John, son
            of <persName>Zechariah</persName>, came before His apparition in the flesh, and announced Him to everybody in
            saying, <quote>Behold the <persName>Lamb of God</persName>, which taketh away the sin of the world</quote>'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n99"/> <quote>He is that
               shall baptise with <persName>Holy Ghost</persName> and fire,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n100"/> <quote>He is the one the latchet of whose shoes I
                  am not worthy to unloosen</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n101"/> —so also the prophet <persName>Elijah</persName> is going to come before the
            divine apparition of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> from heaven in order to announce beforehand to all His
            glorious apparition, and to make them ready for His presence.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Both messsengers, <persName>John</persName> and <persName>Elijah</persName>, are from one power of <persName>the Spirit</persName>, with the
            difference that one already came before <persName>Christ</persName> and the other is going to come before
            Him, and their coming is similar and to the same effect. In the second coming He will
            appear from heaven in a great glory of angels, to effect the resurrection of all the
            children of <persName>Adam</persName> from the graves. As the <persName>Word of God</persName>, He created everything from the
            beginning and He is going to renew everything at the end. He is the <persName>King of Kings</persName> and
            <persName>Lord of Lords</persName>, and there is no end and no limit to His Kingdom.</quote></p>
         <p>And our highly intelligent <persName>Sovereign</persName> said: <quote>If you had not corrupted the <title>Torah</title> and the
            Gospel, you would have found in them <persName>Muḥammad</persName> also with the other prophets.</quote>—And to set
            his mind at <pb n="56"/> rest on this subject I replied to him: <quote>To the mind of <persName>your Majesty</persName>, O
               my illustrious <persName>Sovereign</persName>—you to whom <persName>God</persName> has granted that intelligence and
               broad-mindedness which are so useful for the administration of public and private
               affairs of the people, and you who speak and act is a way that is congruous with the
               dignity of <persName>your Majesty</persName>—it is due to inquire why and for what purpose we might have
               corrupted the Books. Both the <title>Torah</title> and the prophets proclaim as with the voice of
               thunder and teach us collectively the divinity and humanity of <persName>Christ</persName>; His wonderful
               birth from <persName>His Father</persName> before the times, a birth which no man will ever be able to
               describe and to comprehend. It is written, <quote>Who shall declare his generation,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n102"/> and,
               <quote>His coming out is in the beginning, from the days of the worlds</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n103"/> and, <persName>From the
                  womb before the morning-star I have begotten Thee</persName> and, <quote>His name is before the sun.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n104"/></p>
         <p><quote>So far as His temporal birth is concerned it is written, <quote>Behold a virgin shall
            conceive and bear a son and shall call his name <persName>Emmanuel</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n105"/> <persName>David</persName> and <persName>Isaiah</persName> and all
            the other prophets reveal to us clearly and distinctly the signs and miracles that He
            was going to perform in His appearance in the flesh, and the accurate knowledge of <persName>God</persName>
            with which the earth was going to be filled through this appearance. They tell us about
            His passion, His crucifixion, and His death in the flesh, as we have demonstrated above.
            They tell us about His resurrection from the dwelling of the dead and His ascension to
            heaven. Finally they enlighten us concerning His second appearance from heaven and
            concerning the resurrection of the dead which He is going to effect, and the judgment
            which He is going to hold for all, as one who is <persName>God</persName> and the <persName>Word of God</persName>. O <persName>our
               Sovereign</persName>, while all the corpus of the Christian doctrine is embodied in the <title>Torah</title> and
            the Gospel like a clear symbol and mirror, for what reason could we have dared to
            corrupt these living witnesses of our faith? They are indeed the witnesses of our truth,
            O <persName>our Sovereign</persName>, and from them shines on us the resplendent light of the duality of the
            natures of the divinity and humanity of <persName>Christ</persName>, and that of His death, resurrection, and
            ascension to heaven. It could <pb n="57"/> never have been possible for us to stir ourselves
            against ourselves, and tamper with the testimony of the <title>Torah</title> and the gospel to <persName>our
               Saviour</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Even if we were able to corrupt the Books of the <title>Torah</title> and the Gospel that we have with
            us, how could we have tampered with those that are with the Jews? If one says here that
            we have corrupted those that are in our hands while the Jews themselves corrupted those
            that are in theirs, how is it that the Jews have not corrupted those passages through
            which the Christian religion is established? The Christians never have had and will
            never have such deadly enemies as the Jews; if the Jews had, therefore, tampered with
            their Book, how could we Christians induce ourselves to accept a text which had been
            corrupted and changed, a text which would have shaken the very foundations of the truth
            of our religion? No; the truth is that neither we nor the Jews have ever tampered with
            the Books. Our mutual hostility is the best guarantee to our statement.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n106"/> </p>
         <p><quote>If the Christians and the Jews are enemies, and if there is no possibility that enemies
            should have a common agreement on the line that divides them, it was therefore
            impossible for the Christians and the Jews to agree on the corruption of the Books.
            Indeed the Jews disagree with us on the meaning of some verbs and nouns, tenses and
            persons, but concerning the words themselves they have never had any disagreement with
            us. The very same words are found with us and with them without any changes. Since the
            <title>Torah</title> and the Prophets teach the truth of Christianity, we would have never allowed
            ourselves to corrupt them, and that is the reason why, O <persName>our victorious Sovereign</persName>, we
            could have never tampered with the <title>Torah</title> and the Prophets.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>The very same reason holds good with regard to the Gospel, which we could not and would
            not have corrupted under any circumstances. What the ancient prophets prophesied about
            the <persName>Christ</persName> is written in the Gospel about the <persName>Christ</persName>. The ray of light that shines on
            the eyes of our souls is the same from the <title>Torah</title>, from the prophets, and from the
            Gospel. The only difference is that in the first two Books the light is in words uttered
            in advance of the facts, while in the last Book it is in the facts themselves. What the
            prophets had taught us about the divinity and humanity of <persName>Christ</persName>, and about all the
            Economy <pb n="58"/> of the <persName>Word-God</persName> in the flesh, the Gospel proclaimed to us without corruption
            in a glorious manner. Further, <persName>God</persName>, the giver of both the <title>Torah</title> and the Gospel is one,
            and if we had changed them in any way, we would have changed those things which
            according to some people are somewhat undignified in our faith.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our victorious King</persName> asked me: <quote>And what are those things which you call undignified
            in our faith?</quote>—And I replied to his benevolence: <quote>Things such as the growth of <persName>Christ</persName> in
               stature and wisdom; His food, drink, and fatigue; His ire and lack of omniscience; His
               prayer, passion, crucifixion, and burial, and all such things which are believed by some
               people to be mean and debasing. We might have changed these and similar things held by
               some people to be mean and undignified; we might have also changed things that are
               believed by some other people to be contradictory, such as the questions dealing with
               the times, days, verbs, pronouns, and facts, questions which appear to some people to
               furnish a handle for objections that tend to some extent to weaken our statement I
               submit that we might have been tempted to alter these, but since we did not induce
               ourselves to alter them, how could we have dared to tamper with whole passages revealed
               by <persName>God</persName>? Not only could we not dream of tampering with them, but we are proud of them and
               consider them as higher and more sublime than others. From such higher and more sublime
               passages we learn that <persName>Jesus</persName> is an eternal God, and believe that He is consubstantial
               with <persName>the Father</persName>, and from the passages that are believed by some to be mean and
               undignified we learn that this same <persName>Jesus</persName> is a true man and having the same human nature
               as ourselves.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>No, O <persName>our victorious Sovereign</persName>, we have not changed, not even one iota, in the Divine
            Book, and if the name of <persName>Muḥammad</persName> were in the Book, how we would have expected his
            coming and longed for it, as we expected with an eager desire to meet those about whom
            the prophets wrote, when they actually came or they were about to come. Further, what
            closer relationship have we with the Jews than with the Arabs that we should have
            accepted the <persName>Christ</persName> who appeared from the Jews while rejecting the Prophet that appeared
            from the Arabs? Our natural relationship with the Jews and with the Arabs is on the same
            footing. Truth to tell, the Jews, before the appearance of <persName>Christ</persName>, were honoured more
            than all other nations by <persName>God</persName> and by men, but after the sublime appearance of the
            <persName>Word-God</persName> from them, <pb n="59"/> since they shut their eyes in order not to rejoice in the light
            that came to enlighten the world, they have been despised and dejected, and they thought
            of <persName>God</persName> as other people did.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>A shell is kept in the royal treasuries as long as it contains a pearl, but when the
            pearl has been extracted from it, it is thrown outside and trodden under the feet of
            everyone. In this same way are the Jews: as long as the <persName>Christ</persName> had not appeared from
            them, but was hidden in them as a pearl is hidden in a shell, they were respected by all
            men, and <persName>God</persName> showed them to others, as a glorious and enlightened people, by means of
            the numerous signs and wonders that He performed among them; but after the appearance
            from them of the <persName>Christ-God</persName> in the flesh, and their rejection of His revelation and
            their turning away from Him, they were delivered to slavery among all other peoples.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>The Jews are, therefore, despised to-day and rejected by all, but the contrary is the
            case with the Arabs, who are to-day held in great honour and esteem by <persName>God</persName> and men,
            because they forsook idolatry and polytheism, and worshipped and honoured one God; in
            this they deserve the love and the praise of all; if, therefore, there was an allusion
            to their Prophet in the Books, not only we would not have introduced any changes in it,
            but we would have accepted him with great joy and pleasure, in the same way as we are
            expecting the one of whom we spoke, and who is going to appear at the end of the world.
            We are not the correctors but the observers of the commandments of <persName>God</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our Sovereign</persName> said with a jocular smile: <quote>We shall hear you about these at some
            other time, when business affairs give us a better opportunity for such an intimate
            exchange of words.</quote></p>
         <p>And I praised <persName>God</persName>, <persName>King of Kings</persName> and <persName>Lord of Lords</persName>, who grants to earthly Kings such a
            wisdom and understanding in order that through them they may administer their Empire
            without hindrance. And I blessed also <persName>his Majesty</persName> and prayed that <persName>God</persName> may preserve him
            to the world for many years and establish his throne in piety and righteousness for ever
            and ever. And in this way I left him on the first day.</p>
         <p>Here End the Questions and Answers of the First Day. <pb n="60"/> </p>
         <p>The Questions and Answers of the Second Day.</p>
         <p>The next day<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n107"/> I had an audience of <persName>his Majesty</persName>. Such audiences had contantly taken
            place previously, sometimes for the affairs of the State, and some other times for the
            love of wisdom and learning which was burning in the soul of <persName>his Majesty</persName>. He is a
            lovable man, and loves also learning when he finds it in other people, and on this
            account he directed against me the weight of his objections, whenever necessary.</p>
         <p>After I had paid to him my usual respects as <persName>King of Kings</persName>, he began to address me and
            converse with me not in a harsh and haughty tone, since harshness and haughtiness are
            remote from his soul, but in a sweet and benevolent way.</p>
         <p>And <persName>our King of Kings</persName> said to me: <quote>O <persName>Catholicos</persName>, did you bring a Gospel with you, as I
            had asked you?</quote>—And I replied to his exalted <persName>Majesty</persName>: <quote>I have brought one, O our
               victorious and <persName>God-loving King</persName>.</quote>—And our victorious <persName>Sovereign</persName> said to me: <quote>Who gave you
                  this Book?</quote>—And I replied to him: <quote>It is the <persName>Word of God</persName> that gave us the Gospel, O <persName>our
                     God-loving King</persName>.</quote>— And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>Was it not written by four Apostles?</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108"/> And I
            replied to him: <quote>It was written by four Apostles, as <persName>our King</persName> has said, but not out of
               their own heads, but out of what they heard and learned from the <persName>Word-God</persName>. If then the
               Gospel was written by the Apostles, and if the Apostles simply wrote what they heard and
               learned from the <persName>Word-God</persName>, the Gospel has, therefore, been given in reality by the
               <persName>Word-God</persName>. Similarly, the <title>Torah</title> was written by <persName>Moses</persName>, but since <persName>Moses</persName> heard and learned
               it from an angel, and the angel heard and learned it from <persName>God</persName>, we assert that the <title>Torah</title>
               was given by <persName>God</persName> and not by <persName>Moses</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>In the same way also the Muslims say that they have received the <title>Ḳur'ān</title> from <persName>Muḥammad</persName>,
            but since <persName>Muḥammad</persName> received knowledge and writing from an angel, they, therefore, affirm
            that the Book that was divulged through him was not <persName>Muḥammad</persName>'s or the angel's but <persName>God</persName>'s.
            So also we Christians believe that although the Gospel was given to us by the Apostles,
            it was not given as from them but as from <persName>God</persName>, <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>. Further, the
            letters <pb n="61"/> and official documents<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n109"/> of your Majesty are written by the hands of
            scribes and clerks, but they are not said to be those of scribes, but those of <persName>your
               Majesty</persName>, and of the <persName>Commander of the Faithful</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And our gracious and wise <persName>King</persName> said to me: <quote>What do you say about Muḥammad?</quote>—And I
            replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote><persName>Muḥammad</persName> is worthy of all praise, by all reasonable people, O
               my <persName>Sovereign</persName>. He walked in the path of the prophets, and trod in the track of the lovers
               of <persName>God</persName>. All the prophets taught the doctrine of one God, and since <persName>Muḥammad</persName> taught the
               doctrine of the unity of <persName>God</persName>, he walked, therefore, in the path of the prophets.
               Further, all the prophets drove men away from bad works, and brought them nearer to good
               works, and since <persName>Muḥammad</persName> drove his people away from bad works and brought them nearer
               to the good ones, he walked, therefore, in the path of the prophets. Again, all the
               prophets separated men from idolatry and polytheism, and attached them to <persName>God</persName> and to His
               cult, and since <persName>Muḥammad</persName> separated his people from idolatry and polytheism, and attached
               them to the cult and the knowledge of one God, beside whom there is no other God, it is
               obvious that he walked in the path of the prophets. Finally <persName>Muḥammad</persName> taught about <persName>God</persName>,
               <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>, and since all the prophets had prophesied about <persName>God</persName>, <persName>His Word</persName>
               and <persName>His Spirit</persName>, <persName>Muḥammad</persName> walked, therefore, in the path of all the prophets.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Who will not praise, honour and exalt the one who not only fought for <persName>God</persName> in words, but
            showed also his zeal for Him in the sword? As <persName>Moses</persName> did with the Children of <placeName>Israel</placeName> when
            he saw that they had fashioned a golden calf which they worshipped, and killed all of
            those who were worshipping it, so also <persName>Muḥammad</persName> evinced an ardent zeal towards <persName>God</persName>, and
            loved and honoured Him more than his own soul, his people and his relatives. He praised,
            honoured and exalted those who worshipped <persName>God</persName> with him, and promised them kingdom,
            praise and honour from <persName>God</persName>, both in this world and in the world to come in <placeName>the
               Garden</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n110"/> But those who worshipped idols and not <persName>God</persName> he fought and opposed, and showed
            to them the torments of hell and of the fire which is never quenched and in which all
            evildoers burn eternally.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>And what <persName>Abraham</persName>, that friend and beloved of <persName>God</persName>, did in <pb n="62"/> turning his face from
            idols and from his kinsmen, and looking only towards one God and becoming the preacher
            of one God to other peoples, this also <persName>Muḥammad</persName> did. He turned his face from idols and
            their worshippers, whether those idols were those of his own kinsmen or of strangers,
            and he honoured and worshipped only one God. Because of this God honoured him
            exceedingly and brought low<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n111"/> before his feet two powerful kingdoms which roared in
            the world like a lion and made the voice of their authority heard in all the earth that
            is below heaven like thunder, viz: the Kingdom of the Persians and that of the Romans.
            The former kingdom, that is to say the Kingdom of the Persians, worshipped the creatures
            instead of <persName>the Creator</persName>, and the latter, that is to say the Kingdom of the Romans,
            attributed suffering and death in the flesh to the one who cannot suffer and die in any
            way and through any process.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n112"/> He further extended the power of his authority through
            the <persName>Commander of the Faithful</persName> and his children from east to west, and from north to
            south. Who will not praise, O <quote>our victorious King</quote>, the one whom <persName>God</persName> has praised, and
            will not weave a crown of glory and majesty to the one whom <persName>God</persName> has glorified and
            exalted? These and similar things I and all God-lovers utter about <persName>Muḥammad</persName>, O my
            sovereign.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>You should, therefore, accept the words of <persName>the Prophet</persName>.</quote>—And I
            replied to his gracious <persName>Majesty</persName>: <quote>Which words of his our victorious <persName>King</persName> believes that I
               must accept?</quote> —And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>That <persName>God</persName> is one and that there is no other one
                  besides Him.</quote>—And I replied: <quote>This belief in one God, O <persName>my Sovereign</persName>, I have learned from the <title>Torah</title>, from the Prophets and from the Gospel. I
                     stand by it and shall die in it.</quote>—And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said to me: <quote>You believe in
                        one God, as you said, but one in three.</quote>—And I answered his sentence: <quote>I do not deny
                           that I believe in one God in three, and three in one, but not in three different Godheads,
                           however, but in the persons of <persName>God's Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>. I believe that these three
                           constitute one God, not in their person but in their nature. I have shown how in my
                           previous words.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> asked: <quote>How is it that these three persons whom you mention do not
            constitute three Gods?</quote> And I answered his <pb n="63"/> <persName>Majesty</persName>: <quote>Because the three of them
               constitute one God, O our victorious King, and the fact that He is only one God
               precludes the hypothesis that there are three Gods.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> retorted: <quote>The fact
                  that there are three precludes the statement that there is only one God. If there are
                  three, how can they be one?</quote>—And I replied: <quote>We believe that they are three, O <persName>our
                     Sovereign</persName>, not in Godhead, but in persons, and that they are one not in persons but in
                     Godhead.</quote> —And <persName>our King</persName> retorted: <quote>The fact that they are three precludes the statement
                        that they are one, and the fact that they are one precludes the statement that they are
                        three. This everybody will admit.</quote>—And I said to him: <quote>The three in Him are the cause of
                           one, and the one that of three, O <persName>our King</persName>. Those three have always been the cause of
                           one, and that one of three.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>How can one be the cause of three
                              and three of one? What is this?</quote>—And I answered his question: <quote>One is the cause of
                                 three, O <persName>our King</persName>, because this number one is the cause of the number two, and the
                                 number two that of the number three. This is, how, one is the cause of three, as I said,
                                 O <persName>King</persName>. On the other hand the number three is also the cause of the number one because
                                 since the number three is caused by the number two and this number two by the number
                                 one, the number three is therefore the cause of number one.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>In this process the number four would also be the cause of
            number five and so on, and the question of one Godhead would resolve itself into many
            Godheads, which, as you say, is the doctrine not of the Christians but of the
            Magians.</quote>—And I replied to <persName>our King</persName>: <quote>In every comparison there is a time at which one
               must stop, because it does not resemble reality in everything. We should remember that
               all numbers are included in number three. Indeed the number three is both complete and
               perfect<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n113"/> and all numbers are included in a complete and perfect number. In this
               number three all other numbers are included, O our victorious <persName>King</persName>. Above three all
               other numbers are simply numbers added to themselves, by means of that complete and
               perfect number, as it is said. It follows from all this that one is the cause of three
               and three of one, as we suggested.</quote> —And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Neither three nor two can
                  possibly be said of <persName>God</persName>.</quote>—And I replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>Neither, therefore, <pb n="64"/>
                     one.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> asked: <quote>How?</quote>—And I answered: <quote>If the cause of three is two, the
                        cause of two would be one, and in this case the cause of three would also be one. If
                        then <persName>God</persName> cannot he said to be three, and the cause of three is two and that of two one,
                        <persName>God</persName> cannot, therefore be called one either. Indeed this number one being the cause and
                        the beginning of all numbers, and there being no number in <persName>God</persName>, we should not have
                        applied it to Him. As, however, we do apply this number to <persName>God</persName> without any reference to
                        the beginning of an arithmetical number, we apply to Him also the number three without
                        any implication of multiplication or division of Gods, but with a particular reference
                        to <persName>the Word</persName> and the <persName>Spirit of God</persName>, through which heaven and earth have been created, as
                        we have demonstrated in our previous colloquy.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n114"/> If the number three cannot be applied
                        to <persName>God</persName>, since it is caused by the number one, the latter could not by inference be
                        applied to <persName>God</persName> either, but if the number one can be applied to <persName>God</persName>, since this number
                        one is the cause of the number three, the last number can therefore be applied also to
                        <persName>God</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>The number three denotes plurality, and since there
            cannot be plurality in Godhead, this number three has no room at all in Godhead.</quote>—And I
            replied to <persName>his Majesty</persName>: <quote>The number one is also the cause and the beginning of all
               number, O <persName>our King</persName>, and number is the cause of plurality. Since there cannot be any kind
               of plurality in <persName>God</persName>, even the number one would have no room in Him.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said:
            <quote>the number one as applied to <persName>God</persName> is attested in the Book.</quote>—And I said: <quote>So also is the
               case, O <persName>our King</persName>, with a number implying plurality. We find often such a number in the
               <title>Torah</title>, in the Prophets and in the Gospel, and as I hear, in your Book also, not,
               however, in connection with Godhead but in relation to humanity.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>So far as the <title>Torah</title> is concerned it is written in it, <quote>Let us make man in our image,
            after our likeness;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n115"/> and <quote>The man is become as <pb n="65"/> one of us;</quote>'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n116"/> 
            and, <quote>Let us go down, and there confound their language.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n117"/> As to the Prophets, it is witten in them,
            <quote>Holy, holy, holy, is the <persName>Lord of Hosts</persName>;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n118"/> and <quote>The <persName>Lord God</persName> and his <persName>Spirit</persName> hath sent
               me;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n119"/> and <quote>By the Word of the <persName>Lord</persName> were the heavens made, and all His hosts by <persName>the
                  Spirit</persName> of His mouth.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n120"/> As to the Gospel, it is written in it, <quote>Go ye and teach all
                     nations, baptising them in the name of <persName>the Father</persName>, and of <persName>the Son</persName> and of <persName>the Holy
                        Ghost</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n121"/> As to your Book, it is written in it, <quote>And we sent to her our Spirit,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n122"/> and <quote>We breathed into her from our Spirit,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n123"/> and <quote>We fashioned,</quote> <quote>We said,</quote> <quote>We did,</quote>
            and all such expressions which are said of <persName>God</persName> in a plural form. If the Holy Books refer
            these words to <persName>God</persName> in a plural form, what the Books say concerning <persName>God</persName> we have to say
            and admit Since we had to preserve without change the number one as applied to <persName>God</persName>, we
            had also by inference to preserve without modification the number three, that is to say
            plurality, as applied to Him. The number one refers to nature and Godhead, and the
            number three to <persName>God</persName>, <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>, because <persName>God</persName> has never been, is not, and
            will never be, without <persName>Word</persName> and <quote>Spirit</quote>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n124"/> </p>
         <p>And our wise <persName>Sovereign</persName> said: <quote>The plural form in connection with <persName>God</persName>, in the expressions
            <quote>We sent,</quote> <quote>We breathed,</quote> <quote>We said,</quote> etc, has been used in the Books not as a sign of
            persons or of Trinity, but as a mark of Divine majesty and power. It is even the habit
            of the kings and governors of the earth to use such a mode of speech.</quote> —And I replied to
            the wealth of his intelligence: <quote>What your glorious <persName>>Majesty</persName> has said is true. To you <persName>God</persName>
               gave knowledge and understanding along with power and greatness, more than to all other
               countries and kings. The community of all mankind, whether composed of freemen or of
               subjected races is personified in the kings, and the <pb n="66"/> community of mankind being
               composed of innumerable persons, the kings rightly make use of the plural form in
               expressions such as, <quote>We ordered,</quote> <quote>We said,</quote> <quote>We did,</quote> etc. Indeed the kings represent
               collectively all the community of mankind individually. If all men are one with the
               king, and the king orders, says and does, all men order, say and do in the king, and he
               says and does in the name of all.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Further, the kings are human beings, and human beings are composed of body and soul,
            and the body is in its turn composed of the power of the four elements. Because a human
            being is composed of many elements, the kings make use not unjustly of the plural form
            of speech, such as <quote>We did,</quote> <quote>We ordered,</quote> etc.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n125"/> As to <persName>God</persName> who is simple in His nature
            and one in His essence and remote from all division and bodily composition, what
            greatness and honour can possibly come to Him when He, who is one and undivided against
            Himself, says in the plural form, <quote>We ordered,</quote> and, <quote>We did?</quote> The greatest honour that
            can be offered to <persName>God</persName> is that He should be believed in by all as He is. In His essence
            He is one, but He is three because of <quote>His Word</quote> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>. This <persName>Word</persName> and this <persName>Spirit</persName>
            are living beings and are of His nature, as the word and the spirit of our victorious
            <persName>King</persName> are of his nature, and he is one King with his word and spirit, which are
            constantly with him without cessation, without division and without displacement.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>When, therefore, expressions such as, <persName>We spoke,</persName> <quote>We said,</quote> <quote>We did,</quote> and <quote>Our image
            and likeness,</quote> are said to refer to <persName>God</persName>, <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>, they are referred in
            the way just described, O <persName>King of Kings</persName>. Who is more closely united to <persName>God</persName> than <persName>His Word</persName>
            through which He created all, governs all land directs all? Or who is nearer to Him than
            His Spirit through which He vivifies, sanctifies and renews all? David spoke thus: <quote>By
               the Word of the <persName>Lord</persName> were the heavens made, and all His hosts by the Spirit of His
               mouth;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n126"/> and, <quote>He sent <persName>His Word</persName> and healed them, and delivered them from
                  destruction;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n127"/> and <quote>Thou sendest forth <persName>Thy Spirit</persName> and they are created, and Thou
                     renewest the face of the earth.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n128"/> </p>
         <p><quote>If one asserts that the expressions, <quote>Our image</quote> and <quote>Our <pb n="67"/> likeness</quote> used by <persName>Moses</persName>
            and the expressions, <quote>We made,</quote> and <quote>We breathed,</quote> used by <persName>Muḥammad</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n129"/> do not refer to
            <persName>God</persName> but to the angels, how disgraceful it would be to believe that the image and the
            likeness of <persName>God</persName> and those of the angels, that is of the creator and the created, are
            one! How dishonourable it would be to affirm that <persName>God</persName> says, orders and does with the
            angels and His creatures! <persName>God</persName> orders and does like the <persName>Lord</persName> and the creator, and orders
            and does in a way that transcends that of all others; but the angels being creatures and
            servants, do not order with <persName>God</persName>, but are under the order of <persName>God</persName>; they do not create with
            <persName>God</persName>, but are very much created by <persName>God</persName>. The angels are what <persName>David</persName> said about them, <quote>Who
               maketh His angels spirits and His ministers a flaming fire.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n130"/> In this he shows that
            they are made and created.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>As to the <persName>Word</persName> and <persName>Spirit of God</persName> the prophet <persName>David</persName> says that they are not created and
            made, but creators and makers:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n131"/> <quote>By the Word of the <persName>Lord</persName> were the heavens made,</quote> and
            not <persName>His Word</persName> alone; and <quote>the heavenly hosts were created by His Spirit</quote> and not His
            <quote>Spirit</quote> alone; and, <quote>Because He said and they were made, and He commanded and they were
               created.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n132"/> It is obvious that one who <hi rend="singleQuote">says,</hi> <hi rend="singleQuote">says</hi> and <hi rend="singleQuote">commands</hi> by word, and that
            the word precedes the action, and the thought precedes the deed. Since <persName>God</persName> is one
            without any other before Him, with Him and after Him, and since all the above
            expressions which denote plurality cannot be ascribed to angels, and since the nature of
            <persName>God</persName> is absolutely free from all compositions—to whom could we ascribe then all such
            expressions? I believe, O our victorious <persName>King</persName>, that they refer to the <persName>Word</persName> and the <persName>Spirit of God</persName>. If it is right
            that the expression <hi rend="singleQuote">One God</hi> is true, it is also right that the expression <hi rend="singleQuote">We
               ordered,</hi> <hi rend="singleQuote">We said,</hi> and <hi rend="singleQuote">We breathed from our Spirit</hi> are without doubt true and not
            false. It is also possible that the three letters placed before some Sūrahs in the
            <title>Ḳur'ān</title>, as I have learned, such as A.LR. and Ṭ.S.M. and Y.S.M. and others, <pb n="68"/> which are three in
            number, refer also in your Book to <persName>God</persName>, <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spiri</persName>t.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n133"/></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>And what did impede <persName>the Prophet</persName> from saying that this was
            so, that is that these letters clearly referred to <persName>God</persName>, <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>?</quote>—And I
            replied to his <persName>Majesty</persName>: <quote>The obstacle might have come from the weakness of those people
               who would be listening to such a thing. People whose ears were accustomed to the
               multiplicity of idols and false gods could not have listened to the doctrine of <persName>Father</persName>,
               <persName>Son</persName>, and <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>, or to that of one God, His Word, and His Spirit. They would have
               believed that this also was polytheism. This is the reason why your Prophet proclaimed
               openly the doctrine of one God, but that of the Trinity he only showed it in a somewhat
               veiled and mysterious way, that is to say through his mention of <persName>God</persName>, and of <persName>His Spirit</persName>
               and through the expressions <hi rend="singleQuote">We sent our Spirit</hi> and <hi rend="singleQuote">We fashioned a complete man.</hi><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n134"/>
               He did not teach it openly in order that his hearers may not be scandalised by it and
               think of polytheism, and he did not hide it completely in order that he may not deviate
               from the path followed by <persName>Moses</persName>, <persName>Isaiah</persName>, and other prophets, but he showed it
               symbolically by means of the three letters that precede the Sūrahs.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>The ancient prophets had also spoken of the unity of the nature of <persName>God</persName> and used words
            referring to this unity in an open and clear way, but the words which referred to His
            three persons they used them in a somewhat veiled and symbolical way. They did so not
            for any other reason than that of the weakness of men whose mind was bound up in
            idolatry and polytheism. When, however, <persName>Christ</persName> appeared to us in the flesh, He
            proclaimed openly and clearly what the prophets had said in a veiled and symbolical way,
            <quote>Go ye,</quote> said <pb n="69"/> He to His Disciples, <quote>and baptise all nations in the name of <persName>the
               Father</persName>, and of <persName>the Son</persName> and of <persName>the Holy Ghost</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n135"/> <persName>Moses</persName> also uttered the same thing in
            a way that means both one and three, <quote>Hear, O <placeName>Israel</placeName>,</quote> said he, <quote>The <persName>Lord</persName> your God is
               one Lord.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n136"/> In saying He <hi rend="singleQuote">is one,</hi> he refers to the one nature of Godhead, and in
            saying the three words, <hi rend="singleQuote">Lord, God, and Lord</hi> he refers to the three persons of that
            Godhead, as if one was saying that <persName>God</persName>, <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName> were one eternal God.
            <persName>Job</persName> also said, <quote>The <persName>Lord</persName> gave, and the <persName>Lord</persName> hath taken; blessed be the name of the
               <persName>Lord</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n137"/> In blessing the single name of the <persName>Lord</persName>, <persName>Job</persName> used it three times, in
            reference to one in three.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>If He is one, He is not three; and if He is three, He is not
            one; what is this contradiction?</quote>—And I answered: <quote>The sun is also one, O our victorious
               <persName>King</persName>, in its spheric globe, its light and its heat, and the very same sun is also three,
               one sun in three powers. In the same way the soul has the powers of reason and
               intelligence, and the very same soul is one in one thing and three in another thing. In
               the same way also a piece of three gold denarii, is called one and three, one in its
               gold that is to say in its nature, and three in its persons that is to say in the number
               of denarii The fact that the above objects are one does not contradict and annul the
               other fact—that they are also three, and the fact that they are three does not
               contradict and annul the fact that they are also one.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>In the very same way the fact that <persName>God</persName> is one does not annul the other fact that He is
            in three persons, and the fact that He is in three persons does not annul the other fact
            that He is one God. Man is a being which is living, rational and mortal, and he is one
            and three, one in being one man and three in being living, rational and mortal, and this
            idea gives rise to three notions not contradictory but rather confirmatory to one
            another. By the fact that man is one, he is by necessity living, rational and mortal,
            and by the fact that he is living, rational and mortal, he is by necessity one man. This
            applies also to <persName>God</persName> in whom the fact of His being three does not annul the other fact
            that He is one and vice versa, but these two facts confirm and corroborate each other.
            If He is one God, He is <persName>the Father</persName>, <persName>the Son</persName>, and <persName>the Holy Spirit</persName>; and if He is <persName>the
               Father</persName>, <persName>the Son</persName>, and <persName>the Holy <pb n="70"/> Spirit</persName>, He is one God, because the eternal nature of
            <persName>God</persName> consists in Fatherhood, Filiation, and Procession, and in the three of them He is
            one God, and in being one God He is the three of them.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Do you say that the nature of <persName>God</persName> is composed of the above
            three, as the human nature is composed of its being living, rational, and mortal, and as
            the sun is composed of light, heat, and sphericity, and as the soul is composed of
            reason and intelligence, and as gold is composed of height, depth, and width?</quote>—And I
            denied this and said: <quote>No, this is not so.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>Why then do you
               wish to demonstrate with bodily demonstrations One who has no body and is not
               composed?</quote>—And I answered his <persName>Majesty</persName>: <quote>Because there is no other God like Him, from
                  whom I might draw a demonstration as to what is a being that has no beginning and no
                  end.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>It is never allowed to draw a demonstration from the
                     creatures concerning <persName>the Creator</persName>.</quote> —And I said to Him: <quote>We will then be in complete
                        ignorance of <persName>God</persName>, O <persName>King of Kings</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>Why?</quote>—And I answered: <quote>Because all that we say about <persName>God</persName> is deducted
            from natural things that we have with us; as such are the adjectives: King of all Kings,
            Lord of all Lords, Mighty, Powerful, Omnipotent, Light, Wisdom, and Judge. We call <persName>God</persName>
            by these and similar adjectives from things that are with us, and it is from them that
            we take our demonstration concerning <persName>God</persName>. If we remove Him from such demonstrations and
            do not speak of Him through them, with what and through what could we figure in our mind
            Him who is higher than all image and likeness?</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said to me: <quote>We call <persName>God</persName> by these names, not because we
            understand Him to resemble things that we have with us, but in order to show that He is
            far above them, without comparison. In this way, we do not attribute to <persName>God</persName> things that
            are with us, we rather ascribe to ourselves things that are His, with great mercy from
            Him and great imperfection from us. Words such as: kingdom, life, power, greatness,
            honour, wisdom, sight, knowledge, and justice, etc, belong truly, naturally and
            eternally to <persName>God</persName>, and they only belong to us in an unnatural, imperfect, and temporal
            way. With <persName>God</persName> they have not begun and they will not end, but with us children of men
            they began and they will end.</quote></p>
         <p>And I replied to his <persName>Majesty</persName>: <quote>All that your <persName>Majesty</persName> said on <pb n="71"/> this subject, O our
            victorious <persName>King</persName>, has been said with perfect wisdom and great knowledge; this is
            especially true of what you have just now said. It was not indeed with the intention of
            lowering <persName>God</persName> to a comparison with His creatures, that from the latter I drew a
            comparison concerning Him who, in reality, has no comparison with the created beings at
            all. I made use of such similes solely for the purpose of uplifting my mind from the
            created things to <persName>God</persName>. All the things that we have with us compare very imperfectly with
            the things of <persName>God</persName>. Even in saying of <persName>God</persName> that He is one, we introduce in our mind
            division concerning Him, because when we say for instance one man, one angel, one
            denarius, one pearl, we immediately think of a division that singles out and separates
            one denarius from many denarii, one pearl from many pearls, one angel from many angels,
            and one man from many men.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>A man would not be counting rightly but promiscuously if He were to say: one man and
            two angels, one horse and two asses, one denarius and two pence, one pearl and two
            emeralds. Every entity is counted with the entities of its own species, and we say: one,
            two, or three men; one, two, or three angels; one, two, or three denarii; one, two, or
            three pearls, as the case may be. With all these calculations in saying one we
            introduce, as I said, the element of division, but in speaking of <persName>God</persName> we cannot do the
            same thing, because there are no other entities of the same species as Himself which
            would introduce division in Him in the same sense as in our saying: one angel or one
            man. He is one, single and unique in His nature. Likewise when we say three we do not
            think of bodies or numbers, and when we say: <persName>Father</persName>, <persName>Son</persName>, and <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>, we do not say
            it in a way that implies division, separation, or promiscuity, but we think of it as
            something high above us in a divine, incomprehensible, and indescribable way.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Our fathers and our children were born from marital union and intercourse, and their
            fatherhood and filiation have a beginning and an end. Further, a father was a son before
            becoming a father, and all relationships are liable to natural dissolution and
            cessation. As to Fatherhood, Filiation, and Procession in <persName>God</persName> they are not in a way
            similar to those of our humanity, but in a divine way that mind cannot comprehend. They
            do not arise from any intercourse between them, nor are they from time or in the time
            but eternally without beginning and without end. Since the above three attributes are of
            the nature <pb n="72"/> of <persName>God</persName>, and the nature of <persName>God</persName> has no beginning and no end, they also are
            without a beginning and without an end. And since He who is without a beginning and
            without an end is also unchangeable, that Fatherhood, therefore, that Filiation and that
            Procession are immutable and will remain without any modification. The things that are
            with us give but an imperfect comparison with the things that are above, because things
            that are <persName>God</persName>'s are above comparison and likeness, as we have already demonstrated.</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>The mind of rational beings will not agree to speak of
            <persName>God</persName> who is eternally one in Himself in terms of Trinity.</quote>—And I answered: <quote>Since the
               mind of the rational beings is created, and no created being can comprehend <persName>God</persName>, you
               have rightly affirmed, O <persName>King of Kings</persName>, that the mind of the rational beings will not
               agree to speak of one God in terms of Trinity. The mind, however, of the rational beings
               can only extend to the acts of <persName>God</persName>, and even then in an imperfect and partial manner; as
               to the nature of <persName>God</persName> we learn things that belong to it not so much from our rational
               mind as from the Books of Revelation, i.e. from what <persName>God</persName> Himself has revealed and taught
               about Himself through <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>Spirit</persName>:</quote></p>
         <p><quote><persName>The Word of God</persName> said, <quote>No one knoweth <persName>the Father</persName> but <persName>the Son</persName>, and no one knoweth <persName>the
            Son</persName> but <persName>the Father</persName>,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n138"/> and, <quote><persName>The Spirit</persName> searcheth all things even the deep things of
               <persName>God</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n139"/> No one knows what there is in man except man's own spirit that is in him, so
            also no one knows what is in <persName>God</persName> except the <persName>Spirit of God</persName>. <persName>The Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> of
            <persName>God</persName>, being eternally from His own nature—as heat and light from the sun, and as reason<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n140"/> 
            and mind from the soul—alone see and know the Divine nature, and it is they who have
            revealed and taught us in the sacred Books that <persName>God</persName> is one and three, as I have already
            shown in my above words from the <title>Torah</title>, the Prophets, the Gospel, and the <title>Ḳur'ān</title>
            according to what I have learned from those who are versed in the knowledge of your
            Book.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Were it not for the fact that <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName> were eternally from His own
            nature <persName>God</persName> would not have spoken of Himself in the <title>Torah</title>, as, <quote>Our image and Our
               likeness;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n141"/> and <quote>Behold <pb n="73"/> the man is become as one of us;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n142"/> 
            and <quote>Let us go down and there confound their language;</quote> and the <title>Ḳur'ān</title> would not have said, <quote>And we sent                                                                                                                                 </quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n143"/> and the Kur'an would not have said, 'And we sent
            to her our Spirit;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n144"/> and <quote>We breathed into her from our Spirit;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n145"/> and <quote>We did,</quote>
            <quote>We said,</quote> and so on. By such expressions (The <title>Ḳur'ān</title>) refers to <persName>God</persName> and <persName>His Word</persName> and
            <persName>His Spirit</persName> as we have said above. Has not the mind of the rational beings, O our
            victorious <persName>Sovereign</persName>, to follow the words of <persName>God</persName> rather than its own fanciful
            conceptions? The inspired Books are surely right, and since we find in them that one and
            the same prophet speaks of <persName>God</persName> as one and as three, we are compelled by the nature of the subject to believe it.</p>
         <p>And our powerful <persName>Sovereign</persName> said to me: <quote>How does the nature of the subject compel us to
            believe it?</quote>—And I answered: <quote>Because my <persName>Sovereign</persName> and my <persName>King</persName> granted full freedom to
               his obedient servant to speak before him, may I further implore your <persName>Majesty</persName> to be
               willing that I ask more questions?</quote> And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>Ask anything you want.</quote>—And I
            then said: <quote>Is not <persName>God</persName> a simple and uncircumscribed Spirit?</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> said
            <quote>Yes.</quote>—And I asked his <persName>Majesty</persName>: <quote>Does He perceive in an uncircumscribed way with all His
               being, or does He perceive like us with one part only and not with another?</quote>—And <persName>our
                  King</persName> answered: <quote>He perceives with all its nature without any circumscription.</quote>—And I
            asked: <quote>Was there any other thing with Him from eternity, or not?</quote>— And <persName>our King</persName>
            answered: <quote>Surely not.</quote>—And I asked: <quote>Does not a perceiver perceive a perceived object?</quote>
            And <persName>our King</persName> answered: <quote>Yes.</quote></p>
         <p>And I then asked: <quote>If <persName>God</persName> is a perceiver and knower from the beginning and from
            eternity, a perceiver and a knower perceives and knows a perceived and known object, and
            because there was no created thing that was eternally with <persName>God</persName>—since He created
            afterwards when He wished—in case there was no other being with Him, whom He might
            perceive and know eternally, how could He be called a perceiver and a knower in a Divine
            and eternal sense, and before the creation of the world?</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> answered: <quote>What you have said is true. <pb n="74"/> It is indeed
            necessary that a perceiver should perceive a perceived object, and the knower a known
            one, but it is possible to say that He perceived and knew His own self.</quote>—And I asked:
            <quote>If He is all a perceiver without any circumscription, so that He does not perceive and
               know with one part and is perceived and known with another part, how can a perceiver of
               this kind perceive Himself? The eye of man is the perceiver and it perceives the other
               objects, but it can never perceive its own self except with another eye like itself,
               because the sight of the eye is unable to perceive itself. If the sight of the composed
               eye cannot be divided into parts so that a part of it perceives itself, and the other
               part is perceived by itself, how can we think of <persName>God</persName> who is a Spirit without body,
               without division, and without parts that He perceives Himself and is perceived by
               Himself?</quote></p>
         <p>And our intelligent <persName>Sovereign</persName> asked: <quote>Which of the two do you admit: does <persName>God</persName> perceive
            Himself or not?</quote>—And I answered: <quote>Yes; He perceives and knows Himself with a sight that
               has no limits and a knowledge that has no bounds.</quote>—And <persName>our King</persName> asked: <quote>How is it that
                  your argumentation and reasoning concerning divisions, separations, and partitions do
                  not rebound against you?</quote>— And I replied to him: <quote><persName>God</persName> perceives and knows Himself
                     through <persName>His Word</persName> and the <persName>Spirit</persName> that proceeds from Him. <persName>The Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> are a
                     clear mirror of <persName>the Father</persName>, a mirror that is not foreign to Him but of the same essence
                     and nature as Himself, without any limits and bounds. He was perceiving <persName>His Word</persName>, <persName>His
                        Spirit</persName>, and His creatures, divinely, eternally, and before the worlds, with this
                     difference, however, that He was perceiving and knowing <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName> as His
                     nature, His very nature, and He was eternally perceiving and knowing His creatures not
                     as His nature but as His creatures. He was perceiving and knowing <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His
                        Spirit</persName> as existing divinely and eternally, and His creatures not as existing then but as
                     going to exist in the future. Through <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName> He perceives and knows the
                     beauty, the splendour, and the infiniteness of His own nature, and through His creatures
                     the beauty of His wisdom, of His power, and of His goodness, now, before now, and before
                     all times, movements, and beginnings.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> asked philosophically: <quote>Are they parts of one another, and placed at a
            distance from one another, so that one part <pb n="75"/> perceives and the other is
            perceived?</quote>—And I replied to his <persName>Majesty</persName>: <quote>No, not so, O <persName>King of Kings</persName>. They are not
               parts of one another, because a simple being has no parts and no composition; nor are
               they placed at a distance one from the other, because the infiniteness of <persName>God</persName>, of <persName>His
                  Word</persName>, and of <persName>His Spirit</persName> is one. <persName>The Father</persName> is in <persName>the Son</persName>, and <persName>the Son</persName> in <persName>the Spirit</persName>,
               without any break, distance, and confusion of any kind, as the soul is in the reason and
               the reason in the mind, without break and confusion; and as the spheric globe of the sun
               is in its light, and this light in its heat; and as the colour, scent, and taste are in
               the apple, without any break, confusion, and promiscuity. All figures, comparisons, and
               images, are far below that adorable and ineffable nature of <persName>God</persName>, so there is fear that
               we may be falsely held to believe in the plurality of Godhead.</quote></p>
         <p>And our powerful and wise <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>There is such a fear indeed.</quote>—And I said: <quote>O <persName>King
            of Kings</persName>, this would arise in case we diminished something from Godhead, just as well as
            if we added something to it. As it is a blasphemy to add something to Godhead, it is
            also a blasphemy to diminish something from it in our belief, and as it is not allowed
            to add anything to the sun or to the pearl, so it is not allowed to diminish anything
            from them. He who divests <persName>God</persName> of <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>, resembles the one who would
            divest the sun of its light and its heat, and the soul of its reason and its mind, and
            the pearl of its beauty and its lustre. As it is impossible to conceive a pearl without
            lustre, or a sun without light, or a soul without reason and mind, so it is never
            possible that <persName>God</persName> should be without <persName>Word</persName> and <persName>Spirit</persName>. If, therefore, <persName>Word</persName> and <persName>Spirit</persName> are
            <persName>God</persName>'s by nature, and <persName>God</persName> is eternal, it follows that <persName>the Word</persName> and the <persName>Spirit of God</persName> are
            also eternal. They are not added to Him from outside that one might think of the
            plurality of Godhead, but it is of the essence of <persName>God</persName> to possess both <persName>Word</persName> and
            <persName>Spirit</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>In your previous words you said that the perceiver
            perceives the one that is perceived, and the one that is perceived perceives also the
            one that perceives; and that if they be near a thing they are all there at the same
            time, because <persName>the Word</persName> and the <persName>Spirit of God</persName> are the object that is perceived by <persName>God</persName> and
            are eternal like the perceiver; and if there is no perceiver there is no perceived
            object either, and if there is no perceived object there is no perceiver. Did you say
            these things, or not?</quote>—And I answered: <pb n="76"/> <quote>I did say them, O our victorious <persName>King</persName>.</quote>—And
            the <persName>King of Kings</persName> said: <quote>But it is possible that <persName>God</persName> was perceiving His creatures before
               He created them.</quote>—And I said: <quote>O our victorious <persName>King</persName>, we cannot think or say otherwise.
                  <persName>God</persName> perceived and knew eternally His creatures, before He brought them into being.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said: <quote>The nature of the subject will not compel us, therefore, to believe
            that if the perceiver is eternal, the perceived should also be eternal, because the fact
            that <persName>God</persName> is an eternal perceiver of the creature does not carry with it the necessity
            that the creature which is perceived by Him is also eternal, and the fact that die
            creature is perceived does not carry with it the necessity that He also is the perceived
            object like it. As such a necessity as that you were mentioning in the case of the
            creature has been vitiated, so also is the case with regard to <persName>the Word</persName> and <persName>the
               Spirit</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And I said: <quote></quote>O <persName>our King</persName>, it is not the same kind of perception that affects the creature
            on the one hand, and <persName>the Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> on the other. This may be known and
            demonstrated as follows: it is true that <persName>God</persName> was perceiving the creature eternally, but
            the creature is not infinite, and <persName>God</persName> is infinite, the creature has a limited
            perceptibility, and the perception of <persName>God</persName> has no limits. Further, the nature of <persName>God</persName>
            having no limits, His knowledge also has no limits, as the divine <persName>David</persName> says, <quote>His
               understanding is infinite.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n146"/> If <persName>God</persName>, therefore, has any perception, and if He is
            infinite and unlimited, that perception must by necessity be infinite and unlimited, and
            if His perception is infinite, it perceives a perceived object that is likewise
            infinite; but the perceived object that is infinite being only the nature of <persName>God</persName>, it
            follows that <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName> are from His nature, in the same way as the word
            and the spirit of a man are from human nature. It is, therefore, obvious that if <persName>God</persName> is
            an infinite perceiver, <persName>the Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> that are from Him are also infinite.</p>
         <p><quote><persName>God</persName> knows <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName> in an infinite way as His Knowledge and His
            perception are infinite, but He perceives and knows His creature not in the same
            infinite way as are His perception and His Knowledge, but in a finite way according to
            the limits of the creature and of the human nature. He perceived His creature only <pb n="77"/>
            through His prescience, and not as a substance that is of the same nature as Himself,
            and, on the contrary, He perceived <persName>the Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> not through His prescience
            but as a substance that is of the same nature as Himself. This is the reason why the
            prophet <persName>David</persName> said, <quote>For ever, art thou O <persName>Lord</persName>, and <persName>Thy Word</persName> is settled in heaven;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n147"/>
            and likewise the prophet <persName>Isaiah</persName>, <quote>The grass withereth and the flower fadeth, but <persName>the
               Word</persName> of <persName>our Lord</persName> shall stand forever,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n148"/> In this passage <persName>Isaiah</persName> counts all the world
            as grass and flower, and <persName>the Word</persName> and the <persName>Spirit of God</persName> as something imperishable,
            immortal, and eternal.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>If, therefore, <persName>God</persName> is an infinite perceiver, the object that is perceived by Him has
            also to be infinite, in order that His perception of the perceived should not be
            incomplete in places. And who is this infinite-perceived except <persName>the Word</persName> and the <persName>Spirit
               of God</persName>? <persName>God</persName> indeed was not without perception and a perceived object of the same nature
            as Himself till He brought His creature into being, but He possessed along with His
            eternal perception and eternal knowledge a perceived object that was eternal and a known
            object that was also eternal. It is not permissible to say of <persName>God</persName> that He was not a
            perceiver and a knower, till the time in which He created. And if <persName>God</persName> is eternally a
            perceiver and a knower, and if a perceiver of the perceived and a knower of the known is
            truly a perceiver and a knower, and if <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName> were perceived by Him
            divinely and eternally, it follows that these same <persName>Word</persName> and <persName>Spirit</persName> were eternally with
            Him. As to His creatures, He created them afterwards, when He wished, by means of <persName>His
               Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>our King</persName> said to me: <quote>O <persName>Catholicos</persName>, if this is your religion and that of the
            Christians, I will say this, that <persName>the Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> are also creatures of <persName>God</persName>, and
            there is no one who is uncreated except one <persName>God</persName>.</quote>—And I replied: <quote>If <persName>the Word</persName> and <persName>the
               Spirit</persName> are also creatures of <persName>God</persName> like the rest, by means of whom did <persName>God</persName> create the
               heaven and the earth and all that they contain? The Books teach us that He created the
               world by means of <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>—by means of whom did He then create this Word
               and this Spirit? If He created them by means of another word and another spirit, the
               same conclusion would also be applied to them: will they <pb n="78"/> be created or uncreated? If
               uncreated, the religion of the <persName>Catholicos</persName> and of the Christians is vindicated; and if
               created, by means of whom did <persName>God</persName> create them? And this process of gibberish
               argumentation will go on indefinitely until we stop at that Word and that Spirit hidden
               eternally in <persName>God</persName>, by means of whom we assert that the worlds were created.</quote></p>
         <p>And the <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>You appear to believe in three heads, O <persName>Catholicos</persName>.</quote>—And I said:
            <quote>This is certainly not so, O our victorious <persName>King</persName>. I believe in one head, the eternal <persName>God
               the Father</persName>, from whom <persName>the Word</persName> shone and <persName>the Spirit</persName> radiated eternally, together, and
               before all times, the former by way of filiation and the latter by way of procession,
               not in a bodily but in a divine way that befits <persName>God</persName>. This is the reason why they are not
               three separate Gods. <persName>The Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> are eternally from the single nature of
               <persName>God</persName>, who is not one person divested of word and spirit as the weakness of the Jewish
               belief has it. He shines and emits rays eternally with the light of <persName>His Word</persName> and the
               radiation of <persName>His Spirit</persName>, and He is one head with <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>. I do not
               believe in <persName>God</persName> as stripped of His Word and Spirit, in the case of the former without
               mind<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n149"/> and reason, and in the case of the latter without spirit and life. It is only
               the idolaters who believe in false gods or idols who have neither reason nor life.</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>It seems to me that you believe in a vacuous <persName>God</persName>, since
            you believe that He has<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n150"/> a child.</quote>—And I answered: <quote>O <persName>King</persName>, I do not believe that <persName>God</persName>
               is either vacuous or solid, because both these adjectives denote bodies. If vacuity and
               solidity belong to bodies, and <persName>God</persName> is a Spirit without a body, neither of the two
               qualifications can be ascribed to Him.</quote>—And the <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>What then do you believe
                  that <persName>God</persName> is if He is neither vacuous nor solid?</quote>—And I replied to His <persName>Majesty</persName>: <quote><persName>God</persName> is a
                     Spirit and an incorporeal light, from whom shine and radiate eternally and divinely <persName>His
                        Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>. The soul begets the mind and causes reason to proceed from it, and
                     the fire begets the light and <pb n="79"/> causes heat to proceed from its nature, and we do not
                     say that either the soul or fire are hollow or solid. So also is the case with regard to
                     <persName>God</persName>, about Whom we never say that He is vacuous or solid when He makes <persName>His Word</persName> shine
                     and <persName>His Spirit</persName> radiate from His essence eternally.</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>What is the difference in <persName>God</persName> between shining and
            radiating?</quote>—And I replied: <quote>There is the same difference between shining and radiating
               in <persName>God</persName> as that found in the illustration furnished by the fire and the apple: the fire
               begets the light and causes heat to proceed from it, and the apple begets the scent and
               causes the taste and savour to proceed from it. Although both the fire and the apple
               give rise, the former to light and heat, and the latter to scent and savour, yet they do
               not do it in the same manner and with an identical effect on the one and the same sense
               of our body. We receive the heat of the fire with the sense of feeling, the light with
               the eyes, the scent of the apple with the sense of smell, and the sweetness of its
               savour with the palate. From this it becomes clear that the mode of filiation is
               different from that of procession. This is as far as one can go from bodily comparisons
               and similes to the realities and to <persName>God</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>And the <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>You will not go very far with <persName>God</persName> in your bodily comparisons and
            similes.</quote>—And I said: <quote>O <persName>King</persName>, because I am a bodily man I made use of bodily metaphors,
               and not of those that are without any body and any composition. Because I am a bodily
               man, and not a spiritual being, I make use of bodily comparisons in speaking of <persName>God</persName>. How
               could I or any other human being speak of <persName>God</persName> as He is with a tongue of flesh, with lips
               fashioned of mud, and with a soul and mind closely united to a body? This is far beyond
               the power of men and angels to do. <persName>God</persName> Himself speaks with the prophets about Himself
               not as He is, because they cannot know and hear about Him as He is, but simply in the
               way that fits in with their own nature, a way they are able to understand. In His
               revelations to the ancient prophets sometimes He revealed Himself as man, sometimes as
               fire, sometimes as wind, and some other times in some other ways and similitudes.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>The divine <persName>David</persName> said, <quote>He then spoke in visions to His holy ones;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n151"/> and the <persName>Prophet
            Hosea</persName> said on behalf of <persName>God</persName>, <quote>I have <pb n="80"/> multiplied my visions and used similitudes by
               the ministry of the prophets;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n152"/> and one of the Apostles of <persName>Christ</persName> said, <quote><persName>God</persName> at
                  sundry times and in divers manners spake in time past unto our fathers by the prophets.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n153"/> 
            If <persName>God</persName> appeared and spake to the ancient in bodily similitudes and symbols, we with
            stronger reason find ourselves completely unable to speak of <persName>God</persName> and to understand
            anything concerning Him except through bodily similitudes and metaphors. I shall here
            make bold and assert that I hope I shall not deserve any blame from your <persName>Majesty</persName> if I
            say that you are in the earth the representative of <persName>God</persName> for the earthly people; now <persName>God</persName>
            maketh His sun to rise on the evil and on the good, and sendeth His rain on the just and
            the unjust.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n154"/> Your <persName>Majesty</persName> also in the similitude of <persName>God</persName> will make us worthy of
            forgiveness if in the fact of being earthly beings we speak of <persName>God</persName> in an earthly way and
            not in a spiritual way like spiritual beings.</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>You are right in what you said before and say now on the
            subject that <persName>God</persName> is above all the thoughts and minds of created beings, and that all the
            thoughts and minds of created beings are lower not only than <persName>God</persName> Himself but also His
            work The fact, however, that you put the servant and the <persName>Lord</persName> on the same footing you
            make the creator equal with the created, and in this you fall into error and
            falsehood.</quote></p>
         <p>And I replied: <quote>O my <persName>Sovereign</persName>, that <persName>the Word</persName> and the <persName>Spirit of God</persName> should be called
            servants and created I considered and consider not far from unbelief. If <persName>the Word</persName> and
            <persName>the Spirit</persName> are believed to be from <persName>God</persName>, and <persName>God</persName> is conceived to be a Lord and not a
            servant, His Word and Spirit are also, by inference, lords and not servants. It is one
            and the same freedom that belongs to <persName>God</persName> and to His Word and Spirit and they are called
            <persName>Word</persName> and <persName>Spirit of God</persName> not in an unreal, but in a true, sense. The kingdom which my
            victorious <persName>Sovereign</persName> possesses is the same as that held by his word and his spirit, so
            that no one separates his word and his spirit from his kingdom, and he shines in the
            diadem of kingdom together with his word and his spirit in a way that they are not three
            Kings, and in a way that he does not shine in the diadem of kingdom apart from his word
            and his spirit.</quote> <pb n="81"/> </p>
         <p><quote>If it please your <persName>Majesty</persName>, O my powerful Sovereign, I will also say this: the splendour
            and the glory of the kingdom shine in one and the same way in the <persName>Commander of the
               Faithful</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n155"/> and in his sons <persName>Mūsa</persName> and 
            <persName>Hārūn</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n156"/> and in spite of the fact that kingdom
            and lordship in them are one, their personalities are different For this reason no one
            would venture to consider, without the splendour of kingdom, not only the <persName>Commander of
               the Faithful</persName> but also the beautiful flowers and majestic blossoms that budded and
            blossomed out of him; indeed the three of them blossom in an identical kingdom, and this
            one and the same kingdom shines and radiates in each one of them, so that no one dares
            to ascribe servitude to any of them. In a small and partial way the same light of
            kingdom, lordship, and divinity shines and radiates eternally in <persName>the Father</persName>, <persName>the Son</persName> and
            <persName>the Holy Spirit</persName>, or if one prefers to put it, in <persName>God</persName>, <persName>His Word</persName>, and <persName>His Spirit</persName>, and no
            one is allowed to give to any of them the name of servant. If <persName>the Word</persName> and <persName>the Spirit</persName> are
            servants of <persName>God</persName>, while they are from <persName>God</persName> Himself, the logical conclusion to be drawn I
            leave to a tongue other than mine to utter.</quote></p>
         <p>And the <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>It is very easy for your tongue, O <persName>Catholicos</persName>, to prove the
            existence of that <persName>Lord</persName> and <persName>God</persName>, and the existence also of that consubstantial servant,
            and to draw conclusions sometimes or to abstain from them some other times, but the
            minds and the will of rational beings are induced to follow not your mind which is
            visible in your conclusions, but the law of nature and the inspired Books.</quote></p>
         <p>And I replied: <quote>O our victorious <persName>King</persName>, I have proved my words that I have uttered in the
            first day and to-day both from nature and from the Book. So far as arguments from nature are
            concerned, I argued, confirmed, and corroborated my words sometimes from the soul with
            its mind and its reason; sometimes from the fire with its light and its heat; sometimes
            from the apple with its scent and its savour; and some other tunes from your <persName>Majesty</persName> and
            from the rational and royal flowers that grew from it: <persName>Mūsa</persName> and <persName>Hārūn</persName>, the sons of your
            <persName>Majesty</persName>. As to the inspired Books, I proved the object under <pb n="82"/> discussion sometimes
            from <persName>Moses</persName>, sometimes from <persName>David</persName>, and some other times I appealed to the <title>Ḳur'ān</title>, as a
            witness to prove my statement.</quote></p>
         <p><quote><persName>God</persName> said to the prophet <persName>David</persName> and caused him further to prophesy in the following
            manner concerning <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>, <quote>I have set up my King on my holy hill of
               <placeName>Zion</placeName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n157"/> Before this He had called Him His Christ, <quote>Against the <persName>Lord</persName> and against His
                  Christ.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n158"/> If the <persName>Christ</persName> of <persName>God</persName> is a King, it follows that the <persName>Christ</persName> is not a servant
            but a King. Afterwards <persName>David</persName> called Him twice Son, <quote>Thou art my <persName>Son</persName> and this day I have
               begotten Thee,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n159"/> and, <quote>Kiss <persName>the Son</persName> lest the <persName>Lord</persName> be angry and ye perish from His
                  way.</quote>'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n160"/> If the <persName>Christ</persName>, therefore, is a Son, as <persName>God</persName> called Him through the prophet
            <persName>David</persName>, and if no son is a servant, it follows, O <persName>King</persName>, that the <persName>Christ</persName> is not a servant.
            In another passage the same prophet <persName>David</persName> called the <persName>Christ</persName> <hi rend="singleQuote">Lord,</hi> <hi rend="singleQuote">Son,</hi> and <hi rend="singleQuote">A priest
               for ever,</hi> because he said, <quote>The <persName>Lord</persName> said unto my <quote>Lord</quote>, Sit Thou at my right hand.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n161"/>
            And in order to show that <persName>Christ</persName> is of the same nature and power as <persName>God</persName>, he said on
            behalf of <persName>the Father</persName> as follows, <quote>In the beauties of holiness from the womb I have
               begotten Thee from the beginning.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n162"/> <persName>God</persName>, therefore, called <persName>Christ</persName> <hi rend="singleQuote">a Lord</hi> through
            the prophet <persName>David</persName>, and since no true Lord is a servant, it follows that <persName>Christ</persName> is not a
            servant.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n163"/> </p>
         <p><quote>Further, <persName>Christ</persName> has been called through <persName>David</persName> one <hi rend="singleQuote">begotten of God</hi> both <hi rend="singleQuote">from
            eternity</hi> and <hi rend="singleQuote">In the beauties of holiness from the womb.</hi> Since no one begotten of <persName>God</persName>
            is a servant, the <persName>Christ</persName>, therefore, O <persName>King of Kings</persName>, is not a servant and created, but
            He is uncreated and a Lord. <persName>God</persName> said also through the prophet <persName>Isaiah</persName> to <persName>Ahaz, King of
               <placeName>Israel</placeName></persName>, <quote>Behold a virgin shall conceive and bear a Son, and His name shall be called—not
                  a servant—but <persName>Emmanuel</persName>, which being interpreted is, <persName>God</persName> with us.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n164"/> The same <persName>Isaiah</persName>
            said, <quote>For unto <pb n="83"/> us a Child—and not a servant—is born, and unto us a Son—not a
               servant and a created being—is given, and His name has been called <persName>Wonderful,
                  Counsellor, the Mighty God of the Worlds</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n165"/> If the <persName>Christ</persName>, therefore, is the Son of
            <persName>God</persName>, this <persName>Son of God</persName>, as <persName>God</persName> Himself spoke through the prophet <persName>Isaiah</persName>, is the <hi rend="singleQuote">mighty
            God of the worlds,</hi> and not a servant in subjection, but a Lord and a Prince. It
            follows, O our victorious <persName>King</persName>, that the <persName>Christ</persName> is surely a Lord and a Prince, and not a
            servant in subjection.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>As your Majesty would wax angry if your children were called servants, so also <persName>God</persName> will
            be wrathful if anybody called <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName> servants. As the honour and
            dishonour of the children of your <persName>Majesty</persName> redound on you, so also and in a higher degree
            the honour and dishonour of <persName>God</persName>'s Word and Spirit redound on Him. It is for this reason
            that <persName>Christ</persName> said in the Gospel, <quote>He that honoureth not <persName>the Son</persName>, honoureth not <persName>the Father</persName>
               who hath sent Him,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n166"/> and, <quote>He who honoureth not <persName>the Son</persName> shall not see life, but the
                  wrath of <persName>God</persName> shall abide on him.</quote></quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n167"/></p>
         <p><quote>The above is written in the Gospel. I heard also that it is written in the <title>Ḳur'ān</title> that
            <persName>Christ</persName> is <persName>the Word</persName> and the <persName>Spirit of God</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n168"/> and not a servant. If <persName>Christ</persName> is <persName>the Word</persName>
            and the <persName>Spirit of God</persName>, as the <title>Ḳur'ān</title> testifies, He is not a servant but a Lord, because
            <persName>the Word</persName> and the <persName>Spirit of God</persName> are Lords. It is by this method, O <persName>our God-loving King</persName>,
            based on the law of nature and on divinely inspired words, and not on purely human
            argumentation, word, and thought, that I both in the present and in the first
            conversation have demonstrated the lordship and the sonship of <persName>Christ</persName>, and the Divine
            Trinity.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n169"/> </p>
         <p>Our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>Has not the <persName>Christ</persName> been called also several times a servant
            by the prophets?</quote>—And I said: <quote>I am aware, O my <persName>Sovereign</persName>, of the fact that the <persName>Christ</persName>
               has also been called a servant, but that this appellation does not imply a real
               servitude is borne out by the illustration that may be taken from the status of <persName>Hārūn</persName>,
               the blossom and the flower of your <persName>Majesty</persName>. He is now <pb n="84"/> called by everybody <hi rend="singleQuote">Heir
                  Presumptive,</hi><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n170"/> but after your long reign, he will be proclaimed King and Sovereign by
               all He served his military service through the mission entrusted to him by your <persName>Majesty</persName>
               to repair to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> against the rebellious and tyrannical Byzantines.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n171"/> Through
               this service and mission he will not lose<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n172"/> his royal sonship and his freedom, nor his
               princely honour and glory, and acquire the simple name of servitude and subjection, like
               any other individual. So also is the case with the <persName>Christ, the Son</persName> of the heavenly <persName>King</persName>.
               He fulfilled the will of His Father in His coming on His military mission to mankind,
               and in His victory over sin, death, and <persName>Satan</persName>. He did not by this act lose His royal
               Sonship, and did not become a stranger to Divinity, Lordship, and Kingdom, nor did He
               put on the dishonour of servitude and subjection like any other individual.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Further, the prophets called Him not by what He was, but by what He was believed by the
            Jews to be. In one place the prophets called Him, according to the belief of the Jews,
            <quote>A Servant, a Rejected one, one without form or comeliness, a Stricken one, a Smitten
               one, a man of many sorrows.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n173"/> In another place, however, it has been said of Him
            that, <quote>He is the fairest of the children of men</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n174"/> the Mighty God of the worlds, the
            Father of the future world, the Messenger of the Great Counsel of God, Prince of Peace,
            a Son, and a Child,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n175"/> as we demonstrated in our former replies. The last adjectives
            refer to His nature, and He has been spoken of through the first adjectives on account
            of the mission that He performed to His father for the salvation of all, and in
            compliance with the belief of the Jews who only looked at Him in His humanity, and were
            totally incapable of considering Him in the nature of His divinity that clothed itself
            completely with humanity.</quote><pb n="85"/> </p>
         <p><quote>Some ignorant Byzantines who know nothing of the kingship and sonship of your son
            <persName>Hārūn</persName>, may consider him and call him a simple soldier and not a Prince and a King, but
            those who know him with certainty will not call him a simple soldier, but will consider
            him and call him King and Prince. In this way the prophets considered the <persName>Christ our
               Lord</persName> as God, King, and Son, but the unbelieving Jews believed Him to be a servant and a
            mere man under subjection. He has indeed been called not only a servant, on account of
            His service, but also a stone, a door, the way, and a lamb.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n176"/> He was called a stone,
            not because He was a stone by nature, but because of the truth of His teaching; and a
            door, because it is through Him that we entered into the knowledge of <persName>God</persName>: and the way,
            because it is He who in His person opened to us the way of immortality; and a lamb,
            because He was immolated for the life of the world. In this same way He was called also
            a servant, not because He was a servant by nature, but on account of the service which
            He performed for our salvation, and on account of the belief of the Jews.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>I heard also that it is written in your Book that the <persName>Christ</persName> was sent not as a servant,
            but as a son, <quote>I swear by this mountain and by the begetter and His Child.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n177"/> A child
            is like his father, whether the latter be a servant or a freeman, and if it is written,
            <quote>The <persName>Christ</persName> doth surely not disdain to be a servant of <persName>God</persName>,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n178"/> it is also written that
            <persName>God</persName> doth not disdain to be a Father to <persName>Christ</persName> because He said through the prophet about
            the <persName>Christ</persName>, <quote>He will be to Me a Son<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n179"/> —and not a servant</quote> —and, also <quote>I will make Him a
               first-born—not a servant—and will raise Him up above the Kings of the earth.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n180"/> If
            <persName>Christ</persName> has been raised by <persName>God</persName> above the Kings of the earth, He who is above the Kings
            cannot be a servant, <persName>Christ</persName> is, therefore, O <persName>King</persName>, not a servant and one under <pb n="86"/>
            subjection, but a King of Kings and a Lord. It is not possible that a servant should be
            above angels and kings.</quote></p>
         <p><quote><persName>God</persName> said also about the <persName>Christ</persName> through the same prophet <persName>David</persName>, <quote>His name shall endure
            for ever, and His name is before the sun. All men shall be blessed by Him, and all shall
            glorify Him.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n181"/> How can the name of a servant endure for ever, and how can the name of
            a servant be before the sun and other creatures, and how can all nations be blessed by a
            servant, and how can all nations glorify a servant? <persName>God</persName> said to <persName>His Word</persName> and <persName>His Spirit</persName>,
            <quote>Ask of me, and I shall give Thee the nations for Thine inheritance and the uttermost
               parts of the earth for Thy possession. Thou shalt shepherd them with a rod of iron. Be
               wise now, O ye Kings, and be instructed, ye judges of the earth. Serve the <persName>Lord</persName> with
               fear, and hold to Him with trembling. Kiss <persName>the Son</persName>, lest He be angry, and ye stray from
               His way, when His wrath is kindled but a little. Blessed are all they that put their
               trust in Him.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n182"/> If all the nations and the uttermost parts of the earth are the
            inheritance and the possession of the <persName>Christ</persName>, and if he who has under his authority all
            the nations and the uttermost parts of the earth is not a servant, the <persName>Christ</persName>,
            therefore, O our victorious <persName>Sovereign</persName>, is not a servant, but a Lord and Master; and if
            the Kings and the judges of the earth have been ordered by <persName>God</persName> to serve the <persName>Christ</persName> with
            fear and hold to Him with trembling, it is impossible that this same <persName>Christ</persName> who is
            served, held to, and kissed by the Kings and judges of the earth should be a
            servant.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>It follows, O our victorious <persName>Sovereign</persName>, that the <persName>Christ</persName> is a King of Kings, since Kings
            worshipped and worship Him; and a Lord and judge of judges, since judges served and
            serve Him with fear. If He were a servant, what kind of a wrath and destruction could He
            bring on the unbelievers, and what kind of a blessing could He bestow on those who put
            their trust in Him? That He is a Lord over all and a Master over all, He testifies about
            Himself, and His testimony is true. Indeed He said to His disciples when He was about to
            ascend to heaven, and mount on the Cherubim and fly on the spiritual wings of the
            Seraphim, <quote>All power is given unto me in heaven and in earth.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n183"/> If <persName>Christ</persName> has been
            given all the power of heaven and earth, He who <pb n="87"/> is constituted in this way in heaven
            and in earth is <persName>God</persName> over all, and <persName>Christ</persName>, therefore, is <persName>God</persName> over all. If He is not a
            true God, how can He have power in heaven and in earth; and if He has power in heaven
            and in earth, how can He not be true God? Indeed He has power in heaven and in earth
            because He is <persName>God</persName>, since any one who has power in heaven and in earth is <persName>God</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>The <persName>Archangel Gabriel</persName> testified to this when he announced His conception to the always
            virgin <persName>Mary</persName>, <quote>And He shall reign over the house of <persName>Jacob</persName>, and of His Kingdom there shall
               be no end.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n184"/> If the <persName>Christ</persName> reigns for ever, and if the one who reigns for ever there
            is no end to his kingdom, it follows, O <persName>our Sovereign</persName>, that <persName>Christ</persName> is a Lord and <persName>God</persName>
            over all. The prophet <persName>Daniel</persName> testified also to this in saying, <quote>I saw one like the son
               of men coming on the clouds of heaven, and they brought Him near before the Ancient of
               days, who gave Him dominion and glory and a kingdom, that all nations should serve Him
               and worship Him. His dominion is an everlasting dominion, and His kingdom shall not pass
               away and be destroyed.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n185"/> If the kingdom of <persName>Christ</persName> shall not pass away and be
            destroyed, He is <persName>God</persName> over all, and <persName>Christ</persName> is, therefore, <persName>God</persName> over all, O <persName>our King</persName>: over
            the prophets and the angels.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186"/> </p>
         <p><quote>If <persName>Christ</persName> has been called by the prophets God and Lord, and if it has been said by some
            people that <persName>God</persName> suffered and died in the flesh, it is evident that it is the human
            nature which the <persName>Word-God</persName> took from us that suffered and died, because in no Book,
            neither in the prophets nor in the Gospel, do we find that <persName>God</persName> Himself died in the
            flesh, but we do find in all of them that <persName>the Son</persName> and <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> died in the flesh.
            The expression that <persName>God</persName> suffered and died in the flesh is not right.</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> asked: <quote>And who are those who say that <persName>God</persName> suffered and died in
            the flesh.</quote>—And I answered: <quote>The Jacobites and Melchites say that <persName>God</persName> suffered and died
               in the flesh, as to us we not only do not assert that <persName>God</persName> suffered and died in our
               nature, but that He even removed the passibility of our human nature that He put on from
               <persName>Mary</persName> by His impassibility, and its mortality by His immortality, and He made it to
               resemble divinity, to the extent that a created being is capable of resembling his
               Creator. A created <pb n="88"/> being cannot make himself resemble his Creator, but <persName>the Creator</persName>
               is able to bring His creature to His own resemblance. It is not the picture that makes
               the painter paint a picture in its own resemblance, but it is the painter that paints
               the picture to his own resemblance; it is not the wood that works and fashions a
               carpenter in its resemblance, but it is the carpenter that fashions the wood in his
               resemblance. In this same way it is not the mortal and passible nature that renders <persName>God</persName>
               passible and mortal like itself, but it is by necessity <persName>God</persName> that renders the passible
               and mortal human nature impassible and immortal like Himself. On the one hand, this is
               what the Jacobites and Melchites say, and, on the other, this is what we say. It behoves
               your <persName>Majesty</persName> to decide who are those who believe rightly and those who believe
               wrongly.</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>In this matter you believe more rightly than the others.
            Who dares to assert that <persName>God</persName> dies? I think that even demons do not say such a thing. In
            what, however, you say concerning one Word and <persName>Son of God</persName>, all of you are wrong.</quote>— And I
            replied to his <persName>Majesty</persName>: <quote>O our victorious <persName>King</persName>, in this world we are all of us as in a
               dark house in the middle of the night. If at night and in a dark house a precious pearl
               happens to fall in the midst of people, and all become aware of its existence, every one
               would strive to pick up the pearl, which will not fall to the lot of all but to the lot
               of one only, while one will get hold of the pearl itself, another one of a piece of
               glass, a third one of a stone or of a bit of earth, but every one will be happy and
               proud that he is the real possessor of the pearl. When, however, night and darkness
               disappear, and light and day arise, then every one of those men who had believed that
               they had the pearl, would extend and stretch his hand towards the light, which alone can
               show what every one has in hand. He who possesses the pearl will rejoice and be happy
               and pleased with it, while those who had in hand pieces of glass and bits of stone only
               will weep and be sad, and will sigh and shed tears.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>In this same way we children of men are in this perishable world as in darkness. The
            pearl of the true faith fell in the midst of all of us, and it is undoubtedly in the
            hand of one of us, while all of us believe that we possess the precious object. In the
            world to come, however, the darkness of mortality passes, and the fog of ignorance
            dissolves, since it is the true and the real light to which the fog of ignorance is <pb n="89"/>
            absolutely foreign. In it the possessors of the pearl will rejoice, be happy and
            pleased, and the possessors of mere pieces of stone will weep, sigh, and shed tears, as
            we said above.</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>The possessors of the pearl are not known in this world,
            O <persName>Catholicos</persName>.</quote>—And I answered: <quote>They are partially known, O our victorious <persName>King</persName>.</quote>—And
            our victorious and very wise <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>What do you mean by partially known, and by
               what are they known as such?</quote>—And I answered: <quote>By good works, O our victorious <persName>King</persName>, and
                  pious deeds, and by the wonders and miracles that <persName>God</persName> performs through those who possess
                  the true faith. As the lustre of a pearl is somewhat visible even in the darkness of the
                  night, so also the rays of the true faith shine to some extent even in the darkness and
                  the fog of the present world. <persName>God</persName> indeed has not left the pure pearl of the faith
                  completely without testimony and evidence, first in the prophets and then in the Gospel.
                  He first confirmed the true faith in Him through <persName>Moses</persName>, once by means of the prodigies
                  and miracles that He wrought in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and another time when He divided the waters of
                  the <placeName>Red Sea</placeName> into two and allowed the Israelites to cross it safely, but drowned the
                  Egyptians in its depths. He also split and divided the <placeName>Jordan</placeName> into two through <placeName>Joshua</placeName>,
                  son of <persName>Nun</persName>, and allowed the Israelites to cross it without any harm to themselves, and
                  tied the sun and the moon to their own places until the Jewish people were well avenged
                  upon their enemies. He acted in the same way through the prophets who rose in different
                  generations, viz.: through <persName>David</persName>, <placeName>Elijah</placeName>, and <placeName>Elisha</placeName>.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>Afterwards He confirmed the faith through <persName>Christ our Lord</persName> by the miracles and prodigies
            which He wrought for the help of the children of men. In this way the Disciples
            performed miracles greater even than those wrought by <persName>Christ</persName>. These signs, miracles, and
            prodigies wrought in the name of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> are the bright rays and the shining lustre
            of the precious pearl of the faith, and it is by the brightness of such rays that the
            possessors of this pearl which is so full of lustre and so precious that it outweighs
            all the world in the balance, are known.</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>We have hope in <persName>God</persName> that we are the possessors of this
            pearl, and that we hold it in our hands.</quote>— And I replied: <quote>Amen, O <persName>King</persName>. But may <persName>God</persName>
               grant us that we too may share it with you, and rejoice in the shining and beaming <pb n="90"/>
               lustre of the pearl! <persName>God</persName> has placed the pearl of His faith before all of us like the
               shining rays of the sun, and every one who wishes can enjoy the light of the sun.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>We pray <persName>God</persName>, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, to preserve the crown of the
            kingdom and the throne of the <persName>Commander of the Faithful</persName> for multitudinous days and
            numerous years! May He also raise after him <persName>Mūsa</persName> and <persName>Hārūn</persName> and <persName>'Ali</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n187"/> to the throne of
            his kingdom for ever and ever! May He subjugate before them and before their descendants
            after them all the barbarous nations, and may all the kings and governors of the world
            serve <persName>our Sovereign</persName> and his sons after him till the day in which the <placeName>Kingdom of Heaven</placeName>
            is revealed from heaven to earth!</quote></p>
         <p>And our victorious <persName>King</persName> said: <quote>Miracles have been and are sometimes performed even by
            unbelievers.</quote>—And I replied to his <persName>Majesty</persName>: <quote>These, O our victorious <persName>King</persName>, are not
               miracles but deceptive similitudes of the demons, and are performed not by the prophets
               of <persName>God</persName> and by holy men, but by idolaters and wicked men. This is the reason why I said
               that good works and miracles are the lustre of the pearl of the faith. Indeed, <persName>Moses</persName>
               performed miracles in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and the sorcerers <persName>Jannes</persName> and <persName>Jambres</persName> performed them also
               there, but <persName>Moses</persName> performed them by the power of <persName>God</persName>, and the sorcerers through the
               deceptions of the demons. The power of <persName>God</persName>, however, prevailed, and that of the demons
               was defeated.</quote></p>
         <p><quote>In <placeName>Rome</placeName> also <persName>Simon Cephas</persName> and <persName>Simon Magus</persName> performed miracles, but the former performed
            them by the power of <persName>God</persName>, and the latter by the power of the demons, and for this reason
            <persName>Simon Cephas</persName> was honoured and <persName>Simon Magus</persName> was laughed at and despised by every one, and
            his deception was exposed before the eyes of all celestial and terrestrial beings.</quote></p>
         <p>At this our victorious <persName>King</persName> rose up and entered his audience chamber, and I left him and
            returned in peace to my patriarchal residence.</p>
         <p>Here ends the controversy of the <persName>Patriarch Mar Timothy I</persName>. with <persName>Mahdi, the Caliph of the
            Muslims</persName>. May eternal praise be to <persName>God</persName>!</p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">5 The correspondent of the Patriarch. He was possibly either Sergius
               priest, monk and teacher of the monastery of Mar Abraham, or Sergius, Metropolitan of
               Elam.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">1 These sentences amplify a little the original.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">1 The Christian apologist Kindi refutes an objection of his adversary,
               `Abdallah b. Isma`il al-Hashimi, which was in almost identical terms: "We never say
               about the Most High God that He married a woman from whom He begat a son," Risalah,
               p. 37. </note>
            <note xml:id="n4">2 Cf. Is. ix. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">1 Kur'an, iii. 41; xxi. 91.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">2 Luke i. 37. Kur'an iii. 41, etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">1 Note the semi-Nestorian expression of "putting on, clothing oneself
               with" as applied to the union of God with man in the Incarnation. In the following
               pages we shall not attempt to render this expression into English at every
               time.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8">2 Parsopa = πρόσωπον.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9">1 John xx. 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10">2 The Arabic muhal.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11">1 There is no doubt therefore that the official letters and documents
               of the early Abbasids were written on papyrus and not on parchment. The Arabic word
               Kirtas seems by inference to indicate papyrus in the majority of cases, if not
               always.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12">1 In Syr. the same root milltha is used to express both "reason" and
               "word." The author plays on this identical root in a constant manner. </note>
            <note xml:id="n13">2 In Syr. "Spirit" which means also "soul." </note>
            <note xml:id="n14">3 Ps. xxxiii. 6 (Peshitta). </note>
            <note xml:id="n15">4 Ps. lvi. 10 (Peshitta).</note>
            <note xml:id="n16">1 Ps. civ. 30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17">2 Ps. cxix. 89 (Peshitta).</note>
            <note xml:id="n18">3 Is. xl. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19">4 John i. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20">5 John i. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21">6 John xvii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22">1 Matt. xxviii. 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23">2 Most of the above Biblical passages are quoted also by the
               Christian apologist Kindi in his Risalah, pp. 43, 147-148.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24">1 Cf. Matt v. 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25">2 This objection about the circumcision of Christ and the
               uncircumcision of Christians is also mentioned and refuted by the Christian apologist
               Kindi, Risalah, p. 109. It is likewise alluded to by the Muslim apologist `Ali
               Tabari, Kitab ud-Din, pp. 159-160 of my translation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26">3 The same Syriac word means both "mystery" and "sacrament"</note>
            <note xml:id="n27">1 I.e. Temple. Syr. baita d-makdsha from which the Arab, bait
               al-makdis.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28">2 This teaching is that of Theodore of Mopsuestia.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29">1 That the Paradise of Eden was situated in the direction of the East
               is the opinion of the majority of Eastern Fathers, many of whom believe also that it
               is found in the firmament. To it, according to them, the souls of the just go till
               the day of the Resurrection.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30">2 Kur'an, xix. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31">1 The Arab, a`udhu billahi.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32">1 That the name of Muḥammad is found in Jewish and Christian Books is
               the claim made by the Prophet himself in Kur'an, vii. 156: "The ummi prophet whom
               they find written down with them in the Torah and the Gospel." See also lxi.
               6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33">2 Is. vii. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34">3 Is. vii. 14 and ix. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35">4 Is. xxxv. 4-6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n36">5 Is. liii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37">6 Ps. xvi. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n38">7 Ps. ii. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39">8 Ps. lxviii. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40">9 Ps. xlvii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41">1 Dan.vii. 13-14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42">2 John xiv. 16, 26; xv. 26; xvi. 7; 1 Cor. ii. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43">3 The Muslims have always believed that the Paraclete spoken of in
               the Gospel referred to Muḥammad. See Kitab ad-Din of Ibn Rabban (pp. 140-141 of my
               translation), who even corroborates his statement by an appeal to the numerical value
               of the letters of the word. Many other writers (such as Yahsubi in his shifa) counts
               the name Paraclete among the various names of the Prophet.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44">1 Kur'an, vi. 50; vii. 188; xi. 33, etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="n45">2 John xiv. 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46">1 Ps. xxxiii. 6; cir. 30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47">2 The bulk of Muslim testimony, based on Kur'an, vii. 156, is to the
               effect that the name of Muḥammad is found in the Gospel. Almost all the work of Ibn
               Rabban entitled Kitab ad-Din wad-Daulah has been written for the purpose of showing
               that this name is found in Jewish and Christian scriptures. (See especially pp.
               77-146 of my translation.) Cf. Ibn Sa'd's Tabakat, i., ii., 89 and i. i., 123, and
               see the commentator Tabari on Kur'an, vii. 156, and the historians Ibn Hisham and
               Tabari.</note>
            <note xml:id="n48">1 Read samya in sing. </note>
            <note xml:id="n49">2 Read d-nishre.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50">3 Muslim tradition, somewhat against Kur'an, xxix. 49, etc., is full
               of miracles of all sorts attributed to the Prophet. All these miracles have
               apparently been invented in order to answer the objection of the Christians to the
               effect that since Muḥammad performed no miracle he was not a prophet. Pp. 30-60 of my
               edition of Ibn Rabban's Apology, the Kitab ad-Din wad-Daulah, have been written for
               this purpose. The extent to which later tradition amplified this fabulous theme may
               be gauged by the references given in Wensinck's Handbook of Early Muhammadan
               Tradition, pp. 165-168. The theme of the lack of miracles on the part of the Prophet
               is emphasised by the Christian apologist Kindi, Risalah, pp. 62 sqq. and 67.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51">1 Read l-Parsaye. </note>
            <note xml:id="n52">2 Is. xxi. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n53">1 Dan. vii. 5-6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54">2 Dan. ii. 31 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55">3 Ezech. ix. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n56">4 A great deal is made of this prophecy of Isaiah concerning the
               rider on an ass and the rider on a camel in Ibn Rabban's Apology the Kitab ad-Din
               (pp. 95-97 of my edition). The author concludes his references to it in the following
               words of my own translation: "Are not men of intelligence and science amongst the
               People of the Book ashamed to attribute such a clear and sublime prophecy to some
               rude and barbarous people? . . . Did not the adversaries feel abashed in saying that
               the rightly guided prophets of the family of Isaac prophesied about the Kings of
               Babylon, Media, Persia, and Khuzistan, and neglected to mention such an eminent
               Prophet and such a great and Abrahamic nation?"</note>
            <note xml:id="n57">5 Gen. xlix. 10 (Peshitta with slight changes).</note>
            <note xml:id="n58">1 Dan. ix. 24 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n59">2 Matt. xi. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60">3 The last of the prophets, according to Muslim apologists, is
               Muḥammad: "If the prophet had not appeared the prophecies of the prophets about
               Ishmael and about the Prophet who is the last of the prophets would have necessarily
               become without object." Ibn Rabban's Apology, the Kitab ad-Din, p. 77 of my edition
               et passim.</note>
            <note xml:id="n61">1 Read we-azlegh with a waw.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62">2 This subject of the worship of the Cross is also alluded to at some
               length by the Christian apologist Kindi in his Risalah, p. 139.</note>
            <note xml:id="n63">3 Here as above on p. 31 the Arab, a`udhu billahi.</note>
            <note xml:id="n64">1 Kur'an, iv. 156. The Kurra apparently read the verb as shabbaha and
               not shubbiha in the time of the Patriarch Timothy.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65">2 Kur'an, xix. 34.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66">3 Kur'an, iii. 48. The Syriac marfa` from Arab, wa-rafi`uka. </note>
            <note xml:id="n67">4 Ps. xxii. 16-18 (Peshitta).</note>
            <note xml:id="n68">5 Is., liii. 5 (Peshitta).</note>
            <note xml:id="n69">6 Cf, Jer. Lam., iii. 4 and 30 etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70">7 Dan. ix. 26. Read laih. </note>
            <note xml:id="n71">8 Zech. xiii. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n72">1 The Arabic word often used in the Kur'an to express "Apostles." It
               is of Ethiopic origin.</note>
            <note xml:id="n73">2 The word "Jew " has been, and is often in our days, a term of
               derision in the East, where also it indicates weakness and powerlessness.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74">1 John x. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n75">1 The Arabic Kur'anic word iblis.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76">2 The Arabic: mutawwa`in bi-sabil il lahi.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77">3 Syr. ganntha from which the Kur'anic Arabic jannah.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78">1 I.e. the Kur'an. This Kur'anic word is the Syriac furkana,
               "salvation."</note>
            <note xml:id="n79">2 Jer. xxxi. 32-34. This prophecy is with much ingenuity ascribed to
               Muḥammad and to Islam by the Muslim apologist, `Ali b. Rabban Tabari, who concludes
               his statement as follows: "These meanings cannot be ascribed to any other besides the
               Muslims." Kitab ad Din, p. 125 of my translation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n80">3 Joel ii. 28-29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n81">1 Joel ii. 30. </note>
            <note xml:id="n82">2 The Cod. repeats inadvertently.</note>
            <note xml:id="n83">3 Cf. Matt. xxv. etc. </note>
            <note xml:id="n84">4 Deut. xviii. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n85">5 Lit. Ishmaelites. </note>
            <note xml:id="n86">6 Cod. Joktan ex errore see Gen. xxv. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n87">1 Cf. 1 Kings xiv. 14; Jer. xxx. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n88">2 Arab. Kaum.</note>
            <note xml:id="n89">1 Great ingenuity is shown by the Muslim apologist, `Ali b. Rabban
               Tabari, to ascribe this prophecy to Muḥammad. We will quote him here in full: "And
               God has not raised up a prophet from among the brethren of the children of Israel
               except Muḥammad. The phrase, 'from the midst of them' acts as a corroboration and
               limitation, viz. that he will be from the children of their father, and not from an
               avuncular relationship of his. As to Christ and the rest of the prophets, they were
               from the Israelites themselves; and he who believes that the Most High God has not
               put a distinction between the man who is from the Jews themselves and the man who is
               from their brethren, believes wrongly. The one who might claim that this prophecy is
               about the Christ, would overlook two peculiarities and show ignorance in two aspects;
               the first is that the Christ is from the children of David, and David is from
               themselves and not from their brethren; the second is that he who says once that the
               Christ is Creator and not created, and then pretends that the Christ is like Moses,
               his speech is contradictory and his saying is inconsistent." Kitab ad-Din, pp. 85-86
               of my translation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n90">1 The following pronoun and verb are probably to be used in feminine:
               lah for lan, tithiledh for nithiledh.</note>
            <note xml:id="n91">2 Matt. xix. 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n92">3 Peshitta Version.</note>
            <note xml:id="n93">4 John x. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94">1 Luke vi. 43, etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95">2 That the line of defence of the Christians against the Muslims of
               the eighth and ninth centuries was to the effect that no prophet will rise after
               Christ is borne out by the Muslim apologist, `Ali b. Rabban Tabari, who in his
               Apology (Kitab ad-Din, pp. 15, 17-18 of my edition) quotes against the Christians,
               Acts xi. 24; xiii. 1; xxi. 9, in which St. Luke speaks of prophets. On the Christian
               side it is well emphasised by the apologist Kindi in his Risalah, p. 78.</note>
            <note xml:id="n96">3 Mal. iv. 4-6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97">1 Read d-naphne with a Dalath.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98">2 Luke i. 13-17</note>
            <note xml:id="n99">3 John i. 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n100">4 Matt iii. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n101">5 Luke iii. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n102">1 Is. liii. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n103">2 Cf. Is. li. 9; Prov. viii. 23-24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n104">3 Cf. Ps. ii. 7; Ixxii. 17; Is. xliv. 2, 24. This prophecy of David,
               "His name is before the sun" is referred by the Muslim apologist, `Ali b. Rabban
               Tabari, to Muhammud himself. Kitab-ad-Din, pp. 90 and 115 of my translation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n105">4 Is. vii. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n106">1 That the Jews and Christians are enemies and that this enmity is a
               guarantee of the genuineness of the Biblical text is also emphasised by Kindi in his
               Risalah, p. 150.</note>
            <note xml:id="n107">1 Or possibly: On another occasion.</note>
            <note xml:id="n108">2 Here also the Kur'anic Arabic word hawariyun.</note>
            <note xml:id="n109">1 Arab, tumar.</note>
            <note xml:id="n110">2 The Paradise of the Kur'an.</note>
            <note xml:id="n111">1 Put a waw before the verb.</note>
            <note xml:id="n112">2 Allusion to the Jacobites and Melchites.</note>
            <note xml:id="n113">1 Cf. the medieval Latin adage: Omne tritium perfectum.</note>
            <note xml:id="n114">1 The Christian apologist Kindi (Risalah, p. 35) develops this same
               idea of number one and number three to his adversary `Abdallah b. Ismail al-Hashimi
               and concludes as follows: "In number (also God is one because) He embraces all sorts
               of numbers, and number in itself is not numbered. Number, however, is divided into an
               even number and an odd number, and both even and odd numbers are finally included in
               the number three." Risalah, p. 36.</note>
            <note xml:id="n115">2 Gen. i. 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n116">1 Gen. iii. 22</note>
            <note xml:id="n117">2 Gen. xi. 7. The very same argument taken from the plural of
               majesty to prove the Trinity is used by Kindi in his Apology for Christianity
               (Risalah, pp. 40-44), where the same Biblical verses are quoted to the same
               effect.</note>
            <note xml:id="n118">3 Is. vi. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n119">4 Is. xlviii. 16. </note>
            <note xml:id="n120">5Ps. xxx. 6 (Peshitta).</note>
            <note xml:id="n121">6 Matt, xxviii. 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n122">7 Kur'an, xix. 17 (read luathah in fem.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n123">8 Kur'an, xxi. 91 (read bah in fem.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n124">9 The idea that there was no time in which God could have been
               devoid of mind and life or otherwise of word and spirit is developed also by Kindi in
               his Apology for Christianity, Risalah, p. 39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n125">1 Put a waw before d-akh. This idea is developed by Kindi in his
               Apology (Risalah p. 42) on the same lines.</note>
            <note xml:id="n126">2 Ps. xxxiii. 6 (Peshitta).</note>
            <note xml:id="n127">3 Ps. cm 20. </note>
            <note xml:id="n128">4 Ps. civ. 30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n129">1 This Kur'anic use of the plural we in connection with God is also
               taken as an argument in favour of the Trinity by the Christian apologist Kindi.
               Risalah, p. 42.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130">2 Ps.civ. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n131">3 It would perhaps be better to put the verbs and pronouns of this
               sentence in plural. </note>
            <note xml:id="n132">4 Ps. cxlviii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n133">1 The Patriarch refers here to the mysterious letters placed at the
               beginning of some Surahs of the Kur'an. It is highly interesting to learn that the
               Christians at the very beginning of the `Abbasid dynasty understood them to refer to
               the Holy Trinity. In the Kur'an of our day the letters A.L.R are found before Surahs
               10, 11, 12, 14 and 15, and the letters T.S.M. before Surahs xxvi. and xxviii., but
               the three letters Y.S.M. are not found before any Surah at all, but Surah xxxvi has
               only the two letters Y.S. Why this last change in our modern Kur'an? There is no
               question of a copyist's error in the Syriac text, because the letters are named in
               words and not written in figures only.</note>
            <note xml:id="n134">2 Kur'anic expressions.</note>
            <note xml:id="n135">1 Matt. xxviii. 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n136">2 Deut. vi. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n137">3 Job. i. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n138">1John passim.</note>
            <note xml:id="n139">2 1 Cor. ii. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n140">3 Here also the same Syriac word milltha means "word" and
               "reason."</note>
            <note xml:id="n141">4 Gen. i. 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n142">1 Gen. iii. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n143">2 Gen. xi. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n144">3 Kur'an xix. 17. (Here also read lwathah in fem.)</note>
            <note xml:id="n145">4 Kur'an xxi. 91 (Here also read bah in fem.)</note>
            <note xml:id="n146">1 Ps. cxlvii. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n147">1 Ps. cxix. 89 (Peshitta).</note>
            <note xml:id="n148">2 Is. xl. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n149">1 The author is constantly playing on the Syriac word milltha which
               means both "word" and "reason."</note>
            <note xml:id="n150">2 Cod. is; the reading ith laih seems, however, to be better than
               ithauh. The Caliph's objection bears on the fact that since God begets, something
               goes out of Him and He is consequently vacuous.</note>
            <note xml:id="n151">1 Ps. lxxxix. 19 (Peshitta).</note>
            <note xml:id="n152">1 Hos. xii. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n153">2 Heb.i. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n154">3 Matt. v. 45.</note>
            <note xml:id="n155">1 The Caliph Mahdi himself.</note>
            <note xml:id="n156">2 Harun is of course the future and famous Harun ar-Rashid. About
               Musa, the other son of the Caliph Mahdi, see Tabari, Annales, iii. 1, pp.
               452-458.</note>
            <note xml:id="n157">1 Ps. ii. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n158">2 Ps. ii. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n159">3 Ps. it 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n160">4 Ps. ii. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n161">5 Ps. cx. 1 and 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n162">6 Ps. cx. 3 (Peshitta).</note>
            <note xml:id="n163">7 The Muslim apologist, `Ali b. Rabban Tabari, argues that the term
               "lord" in Syriac mara is applied sometimes in the Bible to men, and therefore in
               Deut. xxxiii. 23; Is. xl. 10-11 and lxiii. 14-16 the word designates Muḥammad. See
               Kitab ad-Din, pp. 87, 100, and 116 of my edition. The idea that the word mara,
               "Lord," refers sometimes in the Bible to men is of course taken by Tabari from Syrian
               commentators whom he knew perfectly.</note>
            <note xml:id="n164">8 Is. vii. 14; Matt. i. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n165">1 Is. ix. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n166">2 John v. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n167">3 John iii. 36, where "believeth" for "honoureth."</note>
            <note xml:id="n168">4 Kur'an, iv. 169. Cf. iii. 40.</note>
            <note xml:id="n169">5 Some of the above Biblical verses are quoted also by the Christian
               apologist Kindi in his Risalah, pp. 146-148.</note>
            <note xml:id="n170">1 Arab, wali al-'ahd.</note>
            <note xml:id="n171">2 This expedition of Harun, son of the Caliph Mahdi, against the
               Byzantines led by Nicetas and governed by the Empress Irene and Leo is told at some
               length on the Muslim side by Tabari under the year A.H. 165 (A.D. 781), Annales, iii.
               i. pp. 503-505. Cf. also the historians, Ibn Khaldun, iii. p. 213, and Mukaddasi, p.
               150, etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="n172">3 It appears that this second conversation between Timothy and the
               Caliph took place in A.D. 781, while Harun, the Caliph's son, had not returned yet
               from his expedition against the Byzantines. The sentences used in the text do not
               seem to yield to another interpretation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n173">4 Is. liii. 2-4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n174">5 Ps. xlv. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n175">6 Is. ix. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n176">1 All these adjectives are known to the Muslim apologist Ibn Rabban.
               Kitab-ad-Din, p. 83 of my edition.</note>
            <note xml:id="n177">2 Kur'an xc. 1-3, is interpreted by late Muslim commentators to
               mean: 'I do not swear by the Lord of the land . . . nor by the begetter and what He
               begets.' In the early Islam the first word was evidently read as la-uksimu, 'I shall
               swear' (with an affirmation), instead of la-uksimu, 'I shall not swear' (with a
               negation). I believe that the ancient reading and interpretation preserved in the
               present apology are more in harmony with the Kur'anic text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n178">3 Kur'an iv. 170. The author is using the Arabic word istankafa as
               in the Kur'an.</note>
            <note xml:id="n179">4 2 Sam. vii. 14: Heb. i. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n180">5 Ps. lxxxix. 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n181">1 Ps. lxxii. 17 (Peshitta). See above p. 56 how Ibn Rabban, the
               Muslim apologist, refers this verse to Muḥammad.</note>
            <note xml:id="n182">2 Ps. ii. 8-12 (Peshitta).</note>
            <note xml:id="n183">3 Matt xxviii. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n184">1 Luke i. 33.</note>
            <note xml:id="n185">2 Dan. vii. 13-14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n186">3 About two words are here missing in the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n187">1 A third son of Mahdi, nicknamed ibn Ritah. See Tabari, Annales,
               iii. 3, pp. 137, 501, 522, 1035. The Cod. has erroneously `Alah.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
