<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of an Old Man who went Naked</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Ernest A. Wallis Budge, <title ref="http://syriaca.org/cbss/NV8KZX7S">The Book of
                  Paradise, Being the Histories and Sayings of the Monks and Ascetics of the
                  Egyptian Desert by Palladius, Hieronymus and Others: The Syriac Texts, According
                  to the Recension of ʿAnân-Îshôʿ of Bêth ʿÂbhê</title>, Edited with an English
               Translation, vol. 1, Lady Meux Manuscript 6 (London: W. Drugulin, 1904), p. 235-36.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_17">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_17 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Chapter 16a: Of <persName>a certain Old Man who went naked</persName></head>
            <ab>And they used to speak of a certain solitary monk who went out unto the desert
               carrying his apparel on his shoulder, and having gone a journey of three days, he
               climbed a rock, and saw below him an old man who was grazing like the beasts, and he
               came down secretly and gave chase to him. And the old man was naked, and his soul had
               diminished to such a degree that he could not bear the smell of men, and he was able
               to remove himself from them and to make his escape by flight. And having taken to
               flight that brother pursued him, and he cried out to him and said, <quote>I am
                  following after thee; for God’s sake wait for me.</quote> Then the old man
               answered and said unto him, <quote>And I, for God’s sake also, am fleeing from
                  thee</quote>; and finally, casting away from him the garment which was on his
               shoulder, he pursued him with all his might. Now as soon as the old man saw that he
               had cast away his garments he waited for him, and when the brother came up with him
               the old man said,. <quote>As thou didst cast away from thee the things of the world I
                  waited for <pb n="235"/>thee.</quote> Then that brother entreated him, saying,
               <quote>Speak to me a word [of advice] that I may be redeemed thereby</quote>; and
               the old man said unto him, <quote>Flee from the children of men, and keep silence,
                  and thou shalt live.</quote></ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
