<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Legend of Hilaria</title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreading and initial markup of persons, places, and titles by </resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#anorth">Adelaide North</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title level="a">The Legend of Hilaria</title>
                  <title level="m">Legends of Eastern Saints Chiefly from Syriac Sources, Volume
                     3.</title> Edited and translated by <editor>A. J. Wensink</editor>
                  <pubPlace>Leyden</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>E.J. Brill Ltd.</publisher>
                  <date>1913</date>
                  <citedRange unit="p" from="35" to="57">35-57</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <p>Initial transcription of the text by Roger Pearse, downloaded from Tertullian.org on
               10/02/2025: <ref target="https://www.tertullian.org/fathers/hilaria_07_syriac.htm">
                  https://www.tertullian.org/fathers/hilaria_07_syriac.htm</ref>. The present
               transcription has followed Roger Pearse in renumbering the original footnotes.</p>
            <p>Both the original translation by Wensink and the transcription by Pearse are in the
               public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="p" n="1">
            <p>For the pious, my Beloved, it is always good to occupy themselves with the holy
               doctrines, teaching the fear of <persName>God</persName> and leading us in the right ways which are
               pleasing unto <persName>God</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="2">
            <p>And especially with the stories of the memory of the works of the Saints, who lived
               well with <persName>God</persName> and were perfect in the holy service. For there is nothing of such
               profit to the pious soul as such meditations which show forth the excellent life and
               holy works and humble habit of monasticism.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="3">
            <p>For it is well known that there is no small consolation to be gathered from [an
               examination] as to how they lived and pleased <persName>God</persName> in humbleness; how they persisted
               in patience and in that love, which is a perfect sign of being a disciple of <persName>Christ</persName>,
               and in great works; how they persevered in steady and long fasting, how they humbled
               themselves in ascetic exercises beyond all power, and in performing abundant services
               beloved by <persName>God</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="4">
            <p>Not only blessed men have been seen doing this, but there have also been found women
               in all generations shining like stars in the whole world. And now, because <pb n="38"
               /> it is, as I have said, meritorious to make known by writing the memory of the
               deeds of the Saints, it is also beautiful for us to hand down and to write that which
               we have heard from trustworthy men who were eyewitnesses of the pious persons who
               were leading an angelic life by their deeds, and mortified their bodies by
               asceticism.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="5">
            <p>So [we will speak] firstly about a woman of royal descent, whose story is above [the
               power] of our weak words. So it would be becoming for us to be silent, because of our
               inability, but as such a work, however weak, is of profit for such persons as are
               longing with a pious mind to hear such things, we will not refrain from speaking,
               asking the help of <persName>God</persName>, giver of knowledge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="6">
            <p>So we will begin with the time when the famous and pious king <persName>Zeno</persName>, was reigning
               beautifully; he was equal in faith and love of <persName>Christ</persName> to the glorious and great
               <persName>Constantine</persName>; but he was vexed and suffering from his having no son and successor to
               the throne after his death. His desire made him frequently pray and entreat <persName>God</persName> and
               send to saintly-living men in mountains and caverns and monasteries, that they should
               ask <persName>God</persName> to grant him his wish. This he did because he was very pious and expected
               that on account of their intercession<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> with <persName>God</persName>, who loveth his elected, they could
               acquire all from him. So shortly after-his accession to the throne a daughter was
               born to him, she with whom this story dealeth, truly a firstborn fruit of the prayer
               of the Saints and a reward of his rich vows. When she was sanctified by baptism, the
               holy sign of divine birth, she was called <persName>Hilaria</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="39"/>
         <div type="p" n="7">
            <p>She was educated as is becoming to children of faithful parents. A heavenly grace was
               spread over her and with her was to be found humbleness and great peacefulness; the
               doctrine of the holy Scriptures she learned soon and excelled by great wisdom. She
               had governesses who taught her the good doctrine, chaste women who were ascetically
               living as virgins. I mean nuns, who were visiting her constantly. While she recited
               with them the holy Scriptures and songs and services, there awoke in her the desire
               of assuming their habit. They told her about the life of holy men and humble virgins
               who had given themselves to <persName>God</persName> and were betrothed to <persName>Christ</persName> and had mortified their
               flesh by asceticism. They told her especially about the holy Fathers who were aboding
               in the desert of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, which is called <placeName>Skete</placeName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="8">
            <p>All these things she concealed secretly in her soul and hoped that they could be
               realised in good season. But though she was anxious to assume the holy life and to
               perform the duties of waking and fasting which are becoming to the holy habit, she
               would not do this openly because she knew that it was not agreeable to the king and
               queen, that she had such plans: for they hoped that she would be a source of temporal
               joy to them; and they thought already about her marrying and having children, that
               would bear the royal dignity after them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="9">
            <p>But she, while living alone in a room in the palace, was, according to a rule of
               divine wisdom, symbolically practising monasticism, fasting steadily and sometimes
               eating only every evening or every second day, with long vigils and constant standing
               in prayer, day and <pb n="40"/> night, reading the holy Scriptures and the stories of
               elect holy men and holy women. Meanwhile she looked for the realisation of the plan
               which she had conceived namely to go away secretly and to adopt the solitary life in
               the foreign country. She hoped fervently to see the Egyptian desert and to live with
               the solitary ascetics there.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="10">
            <p>Now her parents, the king and queen, were usually admitted to see her every fifth or
               tenth day, according to the rule laid down by her; because she would not converse
               with them frequently, for she lived in a retired manner and was in this way quietly
               practising the habit of chastety and humbleness under a pretext. Then it happened
               that the king, when visiting her, perceived that the grace and royal beauty, that was
               spread over her handsome face, was fading away, that her body was becoming emaciated,
               that her strength was diminishing and day by day she was fading away and decaying and
               that she was sinking into a serious decline. So he said: <quote>What hath befallen thee, my
                  daughter? Perhaps thou art sick and, because of thy bashfulness, thou wilt not reveal
                  it to us? Or is there a sickness of heart of which thou informest us not? Verily,
                  thou givest us much trouble and pain, on seeing thee fading away and decaying like
                  one wounded and sick.</quote> But she said to them: <quote>Suffer not anyhow, my father; for there
                     is nothing that maketh me suffer, nor is there a pain that troubleth me. On the
                     contrary, my heart rejoiceth very much, because thou art spared and enjoyest peace.</quote>
               So she cheered them up by these words.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="11">
            <p>As a rule her waiting-woman with whom she had intercourse brought her food from the
               palace, dishes of all kinds; but she took only the bread and the rest of <pb n="41"/>
               the food she sent secretly to the poor by the medium of that servant. When she had
               lived in such a way five years, steadily fasting every second day (she was at that
               time five and twenty years old), she thought that this was the time for going away to
               the abode she was longing for; but how could this plan be carried out if she was seen
               by her servant every day? And if she were to be sought in vain, they would turn every
               stone and seek her in every direction and there would be no means of escaping.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="12">
            <p>But what devised she and what contrived she?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="13">
            <p>She adopted the rule of delaying [the visits of her servant] more and more, saying to
               her: <quote>To day I have got food that will be sufficient for three days; trouble me not
                  with thy visit till the fourth day hence. Let nobody know this; otherwise thou wilt
                  be in danger on my account. But take the food, which is given to thee to bring it me,
                  and take it secretly to the poor. And if my parents ask thee, say, as usually: She
                  hath taken and eaten it.</quote> In this way she would, when being ready to go away, be able
               to prolong the interval between her visits and hinder her from entering during five
               days or more, in order to be able to reach a far distance on her journey before being
               sought and missed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="14">
            <p>Thus she did during one year, saying to her servant: <quote>Till the fourth day hence
               approach not unto my door.</quote> And soon she said: <quote>Till the fifth day,</quote> and then: <quote>Till
                  the seventh.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="15">
            <p>When the day had come, that she was prepared for going away, she said secretly to her
               servant: <quote>Take this dinar and buy for it a coat of hair and sandals and a cowl, but
                  let nobody see or know it, for I will <pb n="42"/> give this to that nun, which often
                  visiteth me, because I see that she is poorly dressed.</quote> The servant took the dinar
               and accomplished all according to her command. After a few days <persName>Hilaria</persName> said to her:
               <quote>Visit me not during five days.</quote> Thereupon she prepared herself for departing, took
               off the princely dress she was wearing and put on the coat of hair and the
               sandals.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="16">
            <p>Then she threw on the capuchin, took some food and some money for expenses and went
               away in the morning, while no one saw her, to the seashore which was not very far
               from the town, while a steady prayer was in her mouth and tears stood in her
               eyes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="17">
            <p>Thus she prayed: <quote>O <persName>God</persName>, Thou who guidest the Saints and leadest them on Thy eternal
               way, who art everywhere with them and leavest them never, lead me on this way and
               direct my feet on the way of salvation and bring me to the place which I long for,
               that I may have intercourse with Thy Saints and serve Thee with them in holiness and
               praise Thee eternally.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="18">
            <p>Now it happened that, by divine Providence, at that time a ship was ready for
               departing in the direction of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, the place where she wished to go
               to. When she had asked the people there and had heard what she hoped, she gave the
               fare and embarked. And nobody of those who saw her, knew whether she was a man or a
               woman, because she was dressed humbly and chastely in the humble monastic dress and
               in the royal residence there were many of such monks and nuns; so those who saw her
               thought that she was like the rest.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="19">
            <p>The ship sailed and reached <placeName>Egypt</placeName> in a few days. <pb n="43"/> Then she left the ship,
               entered <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> and visited the holy places there, churches and monasteries and
               strengthened herself by the prayers of those who were performing in holiness the
               service there. While she was still walking through the town she saw an old hermit, an
               excellent man of those of the desert. Addressing him she asked in the first place
               after the way of living of the hermits in the desert, and whether they received
               strangers gladly into their community, and which place or convent was the first to be
               reached in the desert.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="20">
            <p>The hermit said to her: <quote>Their way of living is that each of them reciteth separately
               and in his own way and every one accomplisheth the holy service in his cell, which he
               leaveth not during the whole week. But on Sundays, at the time of the ministration of
               the holy sacrifice, they go to the church that is situated in the midst of the cells
               and partake of the holy sacraments. Some of them cover their faces with their caps so
               as not to see anyone and not to be seen by anyone; every one fasteth as he chooseth
               and according to his strength, some of them every second day, others every third or
               fourth day. The conspicuous take food only once a week.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="21">
            <p><quote>This consisteth of dry bread and olives, sometimes they take also boiled vegetables;
               others feed upon herbs like the beasts.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="22">
            <p><quote>The monastery which is at the entrance of the desert is called that of <placeName>Aba Macarius</placeName>.
               It is said that the number of hermits belonging to it, amounteth to three thousand.
               And as to their love of strangers, it is great, praiseworthy and divine. But they
               admit amongst them no beardless youths nor indulgeth any one in seeing a woman.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <pb n="44"/>
         <div type="p" n="23">
            <p>When she heard this she replied and asked after the way to the desert. He told it her
               and she made an obeisance before him and received his blessing<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> and each of them
               went his own way, without knowing the other's sex and without asking after it. When
               he was far from her and out of sight, she knelt down in order to pray before <persName>God</persName> and
               thus she spoke: <quote>Our <persName>Lord Jesus Christ</persName>, the life and salvation that hath dawned for
                  us, thou who hast come to seek the forlorn, and to bring back to the way of truth
                  those who have gone astray, Thou who leadest Thy Saints to the eternal way ---- turn
                  to me the lost one, for I seek Thee, my <persName>Lord</persName>, and lead me at Thy right hand to Thy
                  way of life, for Thee alone my soul loveth. And direct my feet in the way of
                  salvation and receive me into Thy good harbour. For Thou art my strong hope and in
                  Thee I have confided from my youth, now and for ever. Amen.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="24">
            <p>When she had finished her prayer and sealed herself with the holy sign, she took the
               way to the desert while continually prayer was in her mouth. After three days of
               travelling, she reached the convent of <persName>Aba Macarius</persName>, at the entrance of the
               desert.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="25">
            <p>It was a sabbathday, and while she was passing between the cells she saw none of the
               solitaries without the door of his cell. She ventured not to knock at a door; but on
               going round in order to find some one, she came to the church, their place of
               congregation. She entered to pray and saw the Presbyter who constantly was aboding
               there. After having finished her prayer, she asked his blessing, and he invited her
               to take rest, <pb n="45"/> saying: <quote>From where cometh your pious person, o Father?
                  and what is the cause, why thou visitest us, poor creatures?</quote> For he thought that she
               was a man because of her manly dress and the changed colour of her face which had
               become dusky and black.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="26">
            <p>And thus she answered him in a manly tone: <quote>Your servant, Father, cometh from
               <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, in order to be the disciple of your holiness, if it please <persName>God</persName> and
               you.</quote> The Presbyter said: <quote>What is Thy name?</quote> She answered: <quote><!-- Should "John" get a placeName or since it is a false identity does it not receive one? -->John the eunuch. As to
                  my class I am a slave and I belonged to a noble and well-known Roman<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> man and
                  performed with him the service of a slave. And when he deceased in peace, he freed
                  me. Then being master of my own person, I have sought to please <persName>God</persName> above all and
                  from fear of <persName>God</persName> I assumed the holy habit. But I had an infinite longing to see the
                  Saints who in this desert are living ascetically and devoting their lives to <persName>God</persName>, and
                  to pass the rest of my life with them. For that reason I have hastened to come to you
                  now.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="27">
            <p>Thereupon the Presbyter said: "Thy coming is right, Father. Stay here and take rest
               to-day. Tomorrow, which is a Sunday, the solitaries will assemble here as usually in
               order to partake of the holy sacrifice".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="28">
            <p>So on Sunday morning, at the third hour the solitaries assembled into the above
               mentioned church; and when they had partaken of the sacramental sacrifice, the
               Presbyter told them the story of John, the eunuch. On their wish, she<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> was brought
               before them and throwing herself at their feet, her<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> lips murmered a prayer, <pb
                  n="46"/> while she<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> was trembling from fear, that it might be known who and what
              <ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> she<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> was.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="29">
            <p>Then they prayed over her, blessed her, spoke to her words of admonition and taught
               her how to conduct herself; they gave her also a separate cell and ordered a very old
               man in her neighbourhood: "Take John the eunuch and let him be as a son to thee and
               take care to be his guide in the doctrine which is necessary and in the rules laid
               down amongst us".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="30">
            <p>Thereupon the old man took her with him and showed her the cell and she dwelt amongst
               them and regulated her life as they did, in good work and labour. ----Thus far about
               her departing and arriving in the desert. ----</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="31">
            <p>As to the governess which had served her while being in the royal palace, when the
               days had passed during which Hilaria had forbidden her to enter, she went to her
               service and saw that Hilaria was gone and that her royal garments were put aside in a
               corner of the apartment she at once understood that Hilaria had gone to devote
               herself to the service of God, and that therefore she had wanted the coat of hair and
               the capuchin.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="32">
            <p>Weeping and crying she went to the queen and told her what had happened but she
               revealed nothing about the rule of her food and her [rare] visits to her; for she was
               afraid of being endangered, because she had not told them the secret.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="33">
            <p>The king and the queen, being troubled by what they had heard, went to the apartment,
               and seeing that <pb n="47"/> their daughter Hilaria had gone, they were in great
               sorrow and grief.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="34">
            <p>The king wept, sobbing in a loud voice, and thus lamented: "Woe, my beloved daughter.
               Who hath severed thee from me? How can I live without thee, support of my old age,
               crown on my head? Now may death hasten to me and take from me the trouble that never
               can be consoled away".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="35">
            <p>When the nobles of the king heard what had happened, they came to lament with him. At
               once they sent messengers in all directions to ask and to seek. The convents were
               also examined but she was not found. After a few days the king recovered from his
               trouble, because he was certain that she had gone to devote herself to God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="36">
            <p>And Hilaria, being in the desert of Skete, was going through great struggles and
               performing works of self-denial above human strength, in many vigils and long
               fasting, so that even the solitaries wondered at her endurance and patience.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="37">
            <p>And she was praiseworthy and great in the eyes of all people of her class, because of
               her great humility and her placidity and meekness.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="38">
            <p>When she had passed ten years in the desert, another daughter was born to her father
               the king. When this girl was five years of age, she was tried by the Evil-one. And as
               the Devil attacked her vehemently, her father said to himself: "There is no hope of
               healing my daughter, except by the prayers of the solitaries in Skete, who are very
               near to God and are allowed to speak to Him."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/></p>
         </div>
         <pb n="48"/>
         <div type="p" n="39">
            <p>Thus he resolved in his mind and prepared for her departing. He ordered a trustworthy
               man, one of his relatives, and he and an escort of soldiers took her, went on their
               way and reached the desert.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="40">
            <p>The solitaries had heard of this and many of them had departed, lest they should be
               seen by the soldiers and the other persons. John the eunuch too had hid himself,
               without knowing the case exactly.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="41">
            <p>When the messengers of the king arrived, they told the monks about his belief and his
               hope on them and explained the reason of their coming. They left the girl with them
               and returned to the king without delay.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="42">
            <p>On the next day the solitaries returned to their places and discussed to whom they
               should entrust the little girl. They choosed John the eunuch because he was a eunuch
               and advanced in holiness. Thereupon they sent for him and said to him: "The Fathers
               have discussed with whom the girl should be; and all of them agreed upon giving her
               to thee, be thou her support and teacher".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="43">
            <p>Being forced thus he obeyed their will and took the girl to his cell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="44">
            <p>One time Hilaria asked the girl: "Answer, my sister, what I ask thee. What is the
               name of thy father, and what is the name of thy mother?" The girl said: "My father is
               called Zeno, my mother Augusta". She asked again: "Have they a son or daughter
               besides thee?" The girl answered: "I have no brother or sister at all, but as I have
               heard of my mother, who told it me weeping, before my birth they had another
               daughter, named Hilaria. But she went away from them secretely and nobody knoweth
               what became of her. They sought her industriously but she was not found".</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="49"/>
         <div type="p" n="45">
            <p>When she heard this from her, she knew certainly that the girl was her sister, the
               daughter of the parents who had borne herself and with the fervour of a love not to
               be checked, she embraced her, the tears dropping from her eyes, on account of the
               girl's saying: "My mother told me weeping, that they had another daughter before me,
               who went away from them secretly".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="46">
            <p>When the girl had passed five years with Hilaria, she got recovery from the Lord and
               became excellent in wisdom and knowledge. She was also distinguished by humbleness
               and chastity, because Hilaria had taken great care to adorn her with all praiseworthy
               qualities.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="47">
            <p>So, when the messengers of the king, whom he used to send in order to get tidings of
               the girl, came, the Fathers sent her with them to her father. After her arrival, he
               noticed during his intercourse with her, that she excelled in wisdom and good works,
               and that she had got spiritual as well as bodily aid, being freed from the influence
               of the Evil one. So he rejoiced greatly and thanked and praised God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="48">
            <p>He asked her: "My daughter, who was it to whom thou wast entrusted and with whom thou
               hast been? And how was he treating thee? For I will reward him with becoming signs of
               honour". The girl answered plainly: "When I was sent by thy majesty and the old men
               had taken me up, they discussed the next day to whom they should entrust me. And they
               agreed opon giving me to a trustworthy man, whose name is John the eunuch. With him I
               have been thenceforth and I have improved by him. He shew unto me an infinite love
               and honoured me greatly. I have never seen him eating before my eyes, nor lying down
               on the floor to sleep. <pb n="50"/> But when he was overcome by sleep, he would lean
               against the wall for some time and so he took some comfort from sleep. Innumerable
               was his kneeling down on the floor, and he ceased not praying and reciting night and
               day. He took food only once a week".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="49">
            <p>When the king heard this, he was grieved and he took up evil suspicions against John
               the eunuch, thinking that he was no eunuch. Being anxious to examine the matter
               exactly and to be relieved from his care, he sent for John and about ten of the other
               old men. Here Providence was already at work, in order to make known who John was and
               that he might be a good example to the glory of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="50">
            <p>When John and his companions had arrived, he lodged them in a quiet place as was
               becoming to their habit. But he took John and introduced him separately into the
               palace and held with him many discourses.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="51">
            <p>Hilaria had a cowl covering her face lest her father should recognise her. While she
               spoke to him words of admonition an unchecked stream of tears flowed from her eyes,
               on seeing her father and mother and her sister that was healed. But the king thought
               that her tears came from repentance. Sometime afterwards, the king said to her: "I
               have heard of the beautiful things thou art working and of the good thou hast wrought
               towards my daughter and that she hath received healing from the Lord by thy hands. I
               have called and forced thee to come towards me, that I may be deemed worthy of seeing
               thee and being helped by thy prayers and that my house may be blessed by thy
               footsteps. But I wish to hear from thee who thou art and from where thou earnest to
               the desert, and what <pb n="51"/> thy sex is". She answered: "Why askest thou me
               about this, the poorest and most miserable of all children of man? But, now that thou
               wilt know it, I say: as to my class I am a slave and as to my sex a eunuch. My lord
               freed me when dying; and being my own master I sought God, the true Lord, above all;
               Him I loved and to his service I devoted myself. Above all places, I have chosen the
               dwelling in the desert in order to receive support from the Saints there, by whose
               prayers I have had the joy of healing the girl".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="52">
            <p>When the king had interrogated her circumstantially and revealed the trouble of his
               thoughts and the doubts of his heart, she resolved to relieve him from his cares and
               from the thoughts which were making a pernicious war against his soul. For she pitied
               him as a good father and a just king. She said to him: "I will reveal to thee a
               secret. But swear to me first by the Lord, that thou shalt accomplish my will in all
               things 1 ask and that thou shalt not oppose me in any thing I wish and that this
               secret shall not be revealed to any one besides the queen and the girl".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="53">
            <p>When Hilaria had said this to the king, the tears flowed unchecked from her eyes and
               she was choked by sobbing. The king swore to her plainly, without thinking of who she
               might be, for her face was invisible by the cowl which covered it and her speech was
               altered<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> by reciting in the Egyptian language; and, besides, twenty years had
               elapsed since she left them, and he thought that she had already died.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="54">
            <p>When she saw that the king had given his assurance <pb n="52"/> by his oath, she took
               them with her to an inner apartment, took the capuchin off, uncovered her face,
               showed herself to him and said: "I am whom thou seest, Hilaria, the poor, thy
               daughter whom thou knowest".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="55">
            <p>When the king and the queen heard the name Hilaria, they were disturbed and they
               swooned and fell down on the floor and were as dead.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="56">
            <p>When Hilaria saw what happened and that her parents were near dying, she took water
               and signed them with the cross, and sprinkled it on their faces, so that they revived
               and rose. The king weeped vehemently and they were in great sorrow and scarcely could
               check their crying and weeping. Then the king and the queen threw themselves at her
               and kissed her eyes and her hands.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="57">
            <p>Some time afterwards the king, having recovered from his weeping, said to her:
               "Hilaria, my beloved daughter, it is a great thing to me, to have seen to-day in
               thee, that an offspring pleasing to God cometh forth from me and that I may give to
               God a daughter who is accepted by Him. If thou wouldst only show me this kindness".
               Hilaria said: "What wishest thou?" The king said: "I have sworn the oath, and thy
               will shall be accomplished wholly. Only, if thou art willing, allow me to make for
               thee and those with thee a dwelling-place in our neighbourhood, that will be an abode
               to thee, in the same manner as there, be it for dwelling separately or commonly, as
               thou desirest".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="58">
            <p>But Hilaria agreed not with this, speaking: "It is not well to alter the beautiful
               institutions which have pleased to the Ancients, and to change a place which has been
               fittingly set apart by the chosen Fathers for their rest and abode. But, if thou
               allowest, we soon will <pb n="53"/> take leave in peace. The king submitted to her
               will and withstood not the word of her mouth concerning all which she said to
               him".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="59">
            <p>Five days afterwards, he dismissed her and those with her. And they gave them
               presents and signs of honour and gifts of gold and silver, and tapers and perfumes
               and oil, and costly garments for adorning the altars and churches of the convents in
               the desert.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="60">
            <p>But Hilaria accepted not the gold and the silver saying: "Gold and silver are usually
               not to be seen, in the desert. But we will take these other presents". Secretly she
               said to him: "If thou wilt, we shall spend this gold and silver for works which I
               will mention to thee. There are places in the desert, where the solitaries are
               distressed by want of water and the large distance of it. Others are unfit for
               dwelling, because of the absence of materials necessary for buildings. Send a
               trustworthy man and let him dig pits and build well-secured dwelling-places and make
               holes and hidden caves for those who wish to dwell in them secretly, not openly. This
               will give thee the wages of righteousness".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="61">
            <p>Her father said to her: "Ay, beloved mistress, I shall accomplish all according to
               thy wish". Then she took leave and departed from the palace with weeping and crying,
               and reached the desert of Skete, with the Fathers who were accompanying her.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="62">
            <p>A few days afterwards the king sent a trustworthy man according to Hilaria's wish. He
               gave him much money for the expenses of the buildings and for erecting well-secured
               towers. And thus he spake to him: "Go straightway to John who is called the eunuch;
               he will tell thee what to do, accomplish his will".</p>
         </div>
         <pb n="54"/>
         <div type="p" n="63">
            <p>When this trustworthy man arrived he did all that Hilaria told him; [he made] cells
               and pits and caves fit for dwelling therein and high, well-secured houses.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="64">
            <p>Having finished all, he went back in peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="65">
            <p>Hilaria took up her former way of life, struggling in work and difficult tasks. Her
               father sent continually messengers to her.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="66">
            <p>So within every month he sent some one to ask about her, secretly, nobody knowing of
               it. But this remained not concealed from the solitaries; although not knowing it
               certainly, yet they presumed John to be a relative or an acquaintance of the king.
               From that time they began to show her<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/> signs of honour in the assemblies and in the
               church. When she perceived their presumption, she began to be afraid that gradually
               her position might become known and her labour might be lost by vain glory.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="67">
            <p>So she left them secretly, while they perceived it not, and went to a more remote
               part of the desert. She concealed herself in a suitable cave in the earth, which she
               found according to her desire. At fixed intervals she went through the ravine, which
               led from the bottom of her cave under the earth to the ground, and got up to take the
               fresh air during a long time. At the mouth of the cave was a well and a little garden
               of wild vegetables. Whenever she wanted some food she took it there, and drank from
               the well; so she lived in the cave for ten years. The whole time of her staying in
               the desert was thirty years. By her heavy labour she was fast decaying so that she,
               from weakness and old age, <pb n="55"/> lay down on the bottom of her cave to perform
               her prayer to God. At that time God exhorted three solitaries of the desert, Aba
               Isidorus and Aba Isaie and Aba Isak, to go through the desert in order to visit the
               solitaries. They took with them fruits and bread made of flour, garments and coats,
               to provide and strengthen the sick and weak people with, if they should find them; or
               if they were dead, to shroud their corpses and to bury them honourably.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="68">
            <p>On their march through the desert, one day at noontime, they came near the place
               where Hilaria was living and hearing from within the earth a sound of groaning as
               from a sick person they wondered and investigated what it might be; so they found the
               entrance of the ravine on the surface of the earth, but, on going down to enter it
               they feared that that sound might come from a wild animal there. Going round they
               perceived the garden and the well and signs of human footsteps. Then they understood
               that a solitary must be living there. They took heart and entered the ravine and
               reaching the bottom of the cave, they saw a light as clear as daylight, as the rays
               of the sun. Then they looked and saw a human being lying on the ground and groaning;
               the hair of the head was white as wool. When they had prayed and said: "Bless me my
               Lord", she raised her eyes, perceived them, rose quickly and received them with a
               salutation. Then they sat down and asked about her coming there, saying: "When hast
               thou come here, Father? and from which direction hath come thy pious person?"</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="69">
            <p>For they presumed her to be a man.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="70">
            <p>She answered them and spoke with them excellent <pb n="56"/> words. At last she said
               to them: "My Fathers, you are sent to-day by God, in order to bury me". Then she
               rose, and prayed. Having finished her prayer, she stretched herself on the earth and
               entrusted her spirit to God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="71">
            <p>When the Fathers saw that she was dead they praised God and took her immediately from
               that cave to the ground. There they performed over her the burial service and were
               going, as was becoming, to shroud her body, presuming her to be an ascetic man like
               others, who are beardless by great heat.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/> But touching her corpse outwardly, they
               perceived it to be a woman's and, full of astonishment, they praised Christ, who
               kindleth the fire of His Love in all mankind, men and women, old men and youths and
               children.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="72">
            <p>Then they buried her as she was, and interred her. While their lips murmured a hymn
               of praise, they went to wash their hands in the well from which she used to drink and
               to eat of the vegetables there in order to receive a blessing thereby. But they found
               that well dried up and the garden withered; but in the cave</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="73">
            <p> where she had lived, the water rose, and went up to the surface of the earth and
               streamed there. Then they praised still more on account of a wonder, the like of
               which they had neither seen nor heard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="74">
            <p>They stayed there three days, entreating God and saying: "O Lord, show thy servants
               who thy servant was and from where she came".</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="75">
            <p>When the days of death were over, in a divine revelation, there was said to them:
               "Make a memorial-day for the odour<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> which was accepted by God, three <pb n="57"/>
               days before, which belongeth to Hilaria, the daughter of king Zeno, who, while
               dwelling amongst you before, was called John the eunuch". Three days afterwards they
               departed and went and told the Fathers what they had seen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="76">
            <p>This is the Life and holy works of Hilaria. We, chaste brethren and faithful sisters,
               being envious of the works of the Saints, must imitate their beautiful deeds and
               perform good works, that we may attain life everlasting, of which we may be deemed
               worthy by the Grace and Love of Christ. To Him be praise with His Father and the Holy
               Spirit for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="p" n="77">
            <p>Here endeth the story of Hilaria, the daughter of king Zeno, who left the house of
               her parents secretly and led an ascetic life in the desert of Egypt.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <desc>[Footnotes renumbered and moved to the end]</desc>
            <note xml:id="n1">1) Parrhsi/a .</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">1) Litt, his prayer.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">1) i. e. Byzantine. </note>
            <note xml:id="n4">2) The MS. has the masculine.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">1) The MS. has the masculine. </note>
            <note xml:id="n6"> 2) I. e. her sex.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">1) Litt.: Who have parrhsi/a.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8">1) According to a correction of the text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9">1) MS. "him".</note>
            <note xml:id="n10">1) Cf. the Introduction.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11">2) Cf. Acta Martyrum , ed. Bedjan, I, 187, 17.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
