<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Life of Mar Aba</title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Translated by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreading and initial markup of persons, places, and titles by </resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#anorth">Adelaide North</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Anonymous. <title>The Life of Mar Aba</title>. Translated by Roger Pearce. 2013. <ref
                  target="https://www.tertullian.org/fathers/life_of_mar_aba_1_text.htm"
                  >https://www.tertullian.org/fathers/life_of_mar_aba_1_text.htm</ref>.</p>
            <p>Downloaded from Tertullian.org on 09/25/2025: <ref
                  target="https://www.tertullian.org/fathers/life_of_mar_aba_1_text.htm">
                  https://www.tertullian.org/fathers/life_of_mar_aba_1_text.htm</ref>.</p>
            <p>This translation by Pearse is in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Anonymous, <title>Life of Mar Aba</title></head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <p>The history of the wonderful and divine struggles of the holy witness <persName>Mar Aba, the
               Catholicos, the Patriarch of the East</persName>.</p>
            <p>(Introduction: if we honour great men with statues, how much more then is it fitting
               to honour the witnesses to <persName>Christ</persName>, especially <persName>Mar Aba</persName>.)</p>
            <p><persName>Mar Aba</persName> was originally a pagan, and surpassed most heathens in his (zeal for)
               paganism. He also was learned in Persian literature. Because he was very learned in
               literature, the nobles of his area recognised that he was very learned and
               perceptive, and invited him to join them, and they considered that he was suitable
               for the civil service and gave him an official position. And since the <persName>Blessed One</persName>
               listened to them, they made him an Arzabed; he went in and out with them, and was
               respected by many.</p>
            <p>He was a hard, bitter pagan; he reviled the Christians and taunted the Sons of the
               Covenant.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> But as he crossed the <placeName>Tigris</placeName>, <persName>Jesus</persName> threw his net over him and caught him
               in it. For the <persName>Lord</persName> is accustomed to do as he did to the blessed <persName>Paul</persName>, when he went
               to <placeName>Damascus</placeName> to persecute his followers, to chain them and deliver them to death. He
               transformed him from a persecutor into a persecuted; he was chained, suffered and
               died for him. Similarly <persName>Jesus</persName> sent to the saint, as he went from the village of <placeName>Chale</placeName>
               to his home, and sat with others in a boat (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κέρκουρος</foreign>), a student (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχολάριος</foreign>) as
               teacher, a mortified ascetic, a humble and gentle man, modest and humble in his
               appearance (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχῆμα</foreign>), named <persName>Joseph</persName>, with the surname <!--should the last name get a placename or is the first name sufficent-->Moses. On his rod he had the sweet
               and pleasant bait of the spiritual life, to entice the saint from death to life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <p>When the blessed one sat in the boat to go across, the student also got in, to go
               across with him. Then the saint saw his dress (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχῆμα</foreign>), took him for a Son of the
               Covenant, beat him, and took the bag that he had with him and threw it ashore, and
               forced him to get out. The student said nothing in reply, but got out and sat on the
               bank of the <placeName>Tigris</placeName>. But once the blessed one and his companions had set out and had
               moved away a little distance from the shore, by the grace of <persName>God</persName> a violent wind blew
               against them; the <placeName>Tigris</placeName> became stormy like a zealous servant and its waves rose up
               against them, and it roared against the blessed one, because he had fought against
               the disciple of <persName>Christ</persName> and mocked him and prevented him from crossing. Fear came over
               him, and he ordered the boat to return to the shore. After he landed, the wind ceased
               and there was a great calm. Then he got into the boat again, and the student also got
               in with him, and sat down with him in the boat, and again the blessed one rose
               against him and forced him to go ashore. And when they had gone a little way, the
               wind awoke again against this pagan audacity, that he did not recognised the <persName>Creator
                  of All</persName>, and he was even more disturbed than before. And again the blessed one and his
               companions returned to the shore and got out. But the excellent student was sitting
               on the bank of the <persName>Tigris</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <p>When the blessed one looked at the habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχῆμα</foreign>), which was chaste and (not)
               colourful (?), he became doubtful whether he was perhaps not a Son of the Covenant,
               but a Marcionite or a Jew, and he asked him, <quote>Are you a Jew?</quote> He said, <quote>Yes.</quote> Again
               he spoke, <quote>Are you a Christian?</quote> He said, <quote>Yes.</quote> Again he spoke, <quote>Do you worship the
                  <persName>Messiah</persName>?</quote> He said, <quote>Yes.</quote> </p>
            <p>The blessed one was very angry at this answer by the student and said, <quote>How can you
               be Jew, Christian and Messianist (<foreign xml:lang="grc">meschîchâjâ</foreign>)?</quote> For by <hi rend="doubleQuote">Christian</hi> he meant, after
               the local custom, the Marcionites. </p>
            <p>The student said, <quote>In private I am a Jew. I worship the living <persName>God</persName> and believe in his
               Son, <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, and in the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>. I avoid idolatry and all uncleanness. I am
               a Christian in truth, not like those the Marcionites lead astray and call themselves
               Christians. Because <hi rend="doubleQuote">Christian</hi> is a Greek word, which means in Syriac <hi rend="doubleQuote">Messianist</hi>.
               And if you ask me, <quote>Do you worship the messiah?</quote>, I worship him in truth and I avoid
               all evil for the sake of true life.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <p>When the blessed one heard this, he rejoiced in his spirit. He recognised the wisdom
               and humility of the student, the disciple of <persName>Christ</persName>. Again he got into the boat and
               sat down, and the student also got on. And since the blessed one stopped despising
               the student, the wind also ceased; the waves of the <placeName>Tigris</placeName> calmed; they went across
               and came ashore. As both got out, the student said, <quote>What did it cost you, that I
                  came across with you?</quote> The blessed one wondered at his calm, and very much regretted
               insulting him. He went to him and fell down before him, and said, <quote>I ask you by the
                  living and true <persName>God</persName>, forgive me for this sin committed against you.</quote> The student
               said, <quote>The <persName>Lord</persName> has commanded us Christians, to retain anger against no-one, and
                  never to return evil for evil.</quote> Then they drew near each other, greeted one another,
               and parted.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <p>As the blessed one saw the virtue of this student, and thought much about his words,
               he decided in his heart to go and learn at the Christian college, and fasted and
               prayed much. </p>
            <p>He was working for a respectable man named <persName>Chudaibod</persName>, the secretary of the Finance
               Director of the district of <placeName>Beit Aramaye</placeName>, and was then in <placeName>Radan</placeName>. After the latter was
               called to <placeName>Ctesiphon</placeName>, the blessed one also went down with the secretary for whom he
               was working. He fasted daily and prayed constantly at the stone church.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/></p>
            <p>The secretary heard, where he was, that the blessed was being instructed in
               Christianity and said one day, <quote><persName>Aba</persName>, have you become a messianist?</quote> He said, <quote>Yes, I
                  am a messianist.</quote> The secretary said, <quote>I will say this and accuse you before the
                     Finance Director, and you will be put in chains.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> The blessed one said, <quote>Just say
                        it; I am willing to allow myself to be chained and to die for the name of <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote> So
               spoke the saint, although he had not yet received the seal of baptism. </p>
            <p>After he had spent some time in <placeName>Ctesiphon</placeName>, he returned to his home and after fasting
               and praying constantly, he entered into holy baptism in the village of <placeName>'KD</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> From
               then on he was more eager in fasting, prayer and virtuous works. He left the
               secretary and his service, renounced the world, and decided to go into the desert and
               the mountains, there to live and to please <persName>God</persName> by his conduct.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <p>Then he went up to <placeName>Nisibis</placeName>, and joined the local holy school, and gained the
               opportunity to handle the divine scriptures, dearer than his life. He learned the
               (Psalter) of <persName>David</persName> in a few days, and began with the contemplation of the divine
               scriptures. He associated with the at-peace-in-God <persName>Ma'na</persName>, the bishop of <placeName>Arzon</placeName>, a
               godly man and teacher of truth, who mainly by his good manners and through his acumen
               and scholarship surpassed all who were around at that time and (even) most of his
               predecessors. After <persName>Mar Ma'na</persName> became a bishop, he joined him and went with him and
               was entrusted with the authority to teach in the province of <placeName>Arzon</placeName>. Everyone there
               profited greatly from him, and he converted many heretics to the true faith. </p>
            <p>Afterwards he returned to <placeName>Nisibis</placeName> and made great strides every day, in dealing with
               the explanation (of the scriptures) and spiritual studies. </p>
            <p>Then he felt obliged to go even into the Roman empire, in order to see the longed-for
               places of the saints, to receive the blessing of their prayers and then about a man
               named <persName>Sergius</persName>, who had linked the Arian ideas with paganism, with whom he wanted to
               dispute and establish the true faith.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <p>When he came to <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, he was joined by a brother named <persName>Thomas</persName>, who had been
               instructed (in the faith) from a young age. And thus he surpassed most people in his
               knowledge, which he acquired from the blessed one in the many years that he was with
               him. After wandering about a lot teaching, because he had been instructed in the
               Greek language also by him, he went into the Egyptian desert and enlightened many
               with his teaching and virtues. He went into distant lands with great effort and by
               difficult ways of travel. In <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> he expounded the holy scriptures and
               converted many who held pagan opinions. He refuted those who dealt in magic, and put
               down the heretics (<foreign xml:lang="grc">αἱρεσιώτης</foreign>), in which he put them in a state of admiration by his
               attractive conduct. Everyone was amazed at his mortification and enlightened by his
               teaching. From there he went to <placeName>Athens</placeName>, and chastised the Athenians who believed that
               they were something great because they had been busy from the start with pagan
               knowledge and he converted many to the knowledge of the truth by signs and wonders,
               which were done by him there and in <placeName>Corinth</placeName>. We would like to recount a double
               miracle.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <p>In a holy nunnery the Superior had long been ill with lower abdominal pain and
               dysentery, and was near to death. In the same nunnery was a heretic woman who was
               arrogant towards the Superior and embittered her with her blasphemies. When the
               Superior, a large, excellent woman, heard of the learning and virtue of the blessed
               one, she believed that, if he would send her a blessing on her food, she would
               instantly be healed. She sent to ask. </p>
            <p>Because she ate only peas, on which she lived, he sent her some, because she had
               nothing else. When the Superior, who was near to death, ate the peas, she became well
               and immediately the dysentery stopped, although peas are harmful for this disease.
               But the divine providence wills what it will. And as through the blessed <persName>Moses</persName> with
               bitter wood, or through the prophet <persName>Elisha</persName> with salt, bitter water was made sweet, so
               did it here through this blessed one.</p>
            <p>And the Superior pleaded with <persName>God</persName>, through the prayer of the blessed one, because of
               the blasphemy of that woman in the monastery, and in the night, she died, because she
               blasphemed <persName>God</persName> and the blessed one, because the Superior had recovered through his
               blessing. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <p>Some sophists (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σοφιστής</foreign>) who were well-known for their paganism, were impressed when
               they listened to his erudition and knowledge of the truth and burned their books of
               fables. The news of this spread throughout the whole land of <placeName>Achaia</placeName>, and became known
               and <persName>God</persName> was praised. </p>
            <p>The heretics who were there were stirred up by his erudition, because he competently
               solved their objections and refuted their arguments, and they therefore sought to
               kill him. He got into a ship, travelled to the imperial capital <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and
               there he taught the true faith for about a year. Many brought him some gold and
               costly clothing; but he did not condescend to take it. He supported himself by the
               work of his own hands, so far as his livelihood necessitated, by weaving baskets
               (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σπυρίς</foreign>) and selling them and living thereby, so that in the land of <placeName>Cilicia</placeName> (?) five
               loaves (? <foreign xml:lang="grc">φοῦρνος</foreign>) of bread and a little green plant were enough to support him and
               his disciple for seven months. </p>
            <p>What can I say about the thieves who left off their robberies and returned to the
               cities and villages, repented of their wrongdoing and became friendly to strangers
               (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ξένοι</foreign>)? One day when he was in the <placeName>Thebaid</placeName>, which is full of robbers, he took a road
               which looked dangerous, and he encountered (some) who said, <quote>Take off and put down
                  everything you have.</quote> He did so, and they saw that he had nothing other than his
               textbook. The robbers wept, fell at his feet and begged him to forgive them for
               troubling him and said to him, <quote>Take gold and silver from us, as much as you want.</quote>
               But he would not. They turned away from their work and gave what they possessed to
               the poor.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <p>Such things and more did he work in the west, so that even the emperor of the west
               desired to see him because of the reputation of his teaching and piety.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> When the
               blessed one heard this, he went away to <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. And when he came to <placeName>Nisibis</placeName>, and saw
               the schism in the hierarchy, he desired to hurry away into the desert. But when the
               bishop of the province (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπαρχία</foreign>) heard this, he forbade him to leave under threat of
               ecclesiastical penalties. He now remained for a long time as a teacher and delighted
               in intellectual pursuits more than in all the blessings of this world. </p>
            <p>Of his works then I will tell you of just one. </p>
            <p>There was a brother studying there who was tormented by an evil devil. The blessed
               one fasted and prayed with the brothers, in which he said, <quote>I trust in <persName>God</persName>, that the
                  evil spirit will depart rapidly from him.</quote> As he spoke, it did. After three days that
               spirit went out of the brother and came to him no more. All who heard and saw this
               knew it and praised <persName>God</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <p>Afterwards without his knowledge he was elected by the metropolitans and bishops and
               all the clergy and believers of the (two) cities to the high office of the
               Catholicate.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> The king sent horsemen after him, although he did not suspect this, and
               he was elevated to the patriarchate without having thought about it. He inherited the
               throne of the catholicos <persName>Mar Simon</persName> (bar Sabbâ'ê), of splendid witness, and of his
               blessed companions, and he inherited also their beloved struggle (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀγών</foreign>).</p>
            <p>He brought peace to the churches, extirpated the hostility that the devil had
               introduced at the time of the schism, sowed peace in the remote, inaccessible
               provinces and cities, in which he bore much heat (and cold), renewed the old man,
               lightened the darkness, and established the canons of the apostles in the east. </p>
            <p>After he had held a consultation in the provinces of <placeName>Hûzâjê</placeName>, <placeName>Pârsâjê</placeName> and <placeName>Maischânâjê</placeName>,
               which reconciled the divided churches and brought peace, and had dismissed the
               accompanying metropolitans and bishops to their homes, he went to meet the <persName>King of
                  Kings</persName>, stood before him and was received by him. </p>
            <p>Afterwards he returned to his cathedral and his cities of residence. At night he
               worked on the letter which he sent regarding church government in the provinces; by
               day (he worked) until the fourth hour on the explanation of the scriptures and from
               then until evening on legal matters and resolving disputes between believers, as well
               as between them and the pagans. The servants of <persName>Christ</persName> were pleased with him, and the
               churches of all the provinces of his patriarchate rejoiced. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <p><persName>Satan</persName>, the enemy of our race, could not look on, but writhed threateningly. He worked
               on the chief magian, the Mobedan Mobed, named <persName>Dadhormizd</persName>, and his companions, the
               chiefs of the magians, so that they went to the <persName>King of Kings</persName> and stirred him up with
               their accusations, so that they said, <quote>The <persName>Catholicos Aba</persName>, the leader of the
                  Christians, does not respect you as King and Lord, and he does not honour these, your
                  great and glorious majesty. When he came to <placeName>Pars</placeName> and into the eastern provinces of
                  your realm, they received him with great honour. The religion of the magians, which
                  <persName>Hormizd</persName> was given by <persName>God</persName>, who ruled in your realm, he attacks as reprehensible and
                  destroys it. He has converted many magians to Christianity. Our religion he harms;
                  his own he promotes. We, the chiefs of the magians, he treats as nobodies. In short,
                  he is a friend of the emperor<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> and an enemy of your majesty.</quote></p>
            <p>The peaceful and benevolent <persName>King of Kings</persName> did not accept their accusations. But after
               they came often before him and talked, he gave over the matter to them. When they
               found an opportunity (to carry out) their desire, the magians sent a message to the
               blessed one and called him before their assembly, when the king, in the twelfth year
               of his reign, set out from the royal quarter (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ôstân</foreign>) in order to go into the northern
               district of the Armenians and <placeName>Gûrzânâjê</placeName> <!-- place?-->and make war with the Khazars.</p>
            <p>After he had come, everyone acted as very angry and gnashing their teeth against him
               in great bitterness. The holy one did not allow himself to be frightened, but he made
               the cross of <persName>Christ</persName> on his forehead, which reinforced him with every invincible
               shield, and he rejoiced and exulted to be tried for the sake of <persName>Christ</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <p>When the chief magian and his companions saw that he was not afraid of their threats,
               they marvelled at the courage of the champion of <persName>Christ</persName> and released him the same day
               without asking him anything. The chief magian did the same on the second and third
               days. On the fourth day they clamoured violently against him, shouting, <quote>Whoever is
                  against our religion will be swept off the earth.</quote> Then two noble magians got up; one
               was Shahrdawer, named <persName>Adorpareh</persName>; the other was the <persName>Rad of <placeName>Pars</placeName></persName>, and they accused him,
               <quote>When this one came down into the region of <persName>Pars</persName>, he caused many magians of the
                  religion (<foreign xml:lang="grc">dên</foreign>) of <persName>Hormizd</persName> to alienate and he made them Christians. Many Christians in
                  <placeName>Pars</placeName>, who ate the flesh of the mutterings<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> now consider it anathema to eat. When the
                  magians heard this, they clamoured more violently still and said, <quote>This man shall be
                     killed, because he is an opponent of magianism.</quote></quote> Although it was the duty of the
               chief magian as judge to evaluate the words, and to ask the accused about the
               accusation, and then to pronounce judgement (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀπόφασις</foreign>) as the legal code (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κανών</foreign>) and
               case-law require, he did not do so because he was an enemy of truth. Instead, as if
               overcome with horror, he also howled and screamed, <quote>If this man had a hundred heads,
                  they would have to be cut off.</quote></p>
            <p>Then the soldier of <persName>Christ</persName> made the sign of the cross on his forehead, raised his
               voice and said, <quote>In everything wherein I am accused by the magians concerning the
                  true faith of <persName>Christ</persName>, O Mobedan Mobed, I am full of great joy that I have been
                  honoured to defend it in your assembly. But only by the order of the <persName>King of Kings</persName>,
                  when others are joined with you — then I will answer.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <p>When the chief magian and his companions heard these words of the blessed one, they
               grew even more enraged. They went to the <persName>King of Kings</persName> and complained to him, <quote>This
                  man, the leader of the Christians, must not live, because he is destroying the
                  religion (<foreign xml:lang="grc">dên</foreign>) of <persName>Hormizd</persName>.</quote> Since they now pressured the <persName>King of Kings</persName> strongly, the
               latter allowed the blessed one to be taken to the <persName>PSNIK' DRWSPN</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/> to appear before
               the Mobedan Mobed, that <persName>PSNIK'</persName>, and to explain himself to the magians who were
               accusing him.</p>
            <p>When the blessed one heard this message, he threw himself down, turned to the east,
               made the sign of the cross on his face, stood up boldly and said, <quote>There is one God,
                  the <persName>Creator</persName>, Lord and ruler of all, and he is in three persons without beginning and
                  end. To believe in and confess him is available for any man who of his own free will
                  takes him as his Creator, and believes and confesses his Lordship. No-one can use
                  that belief in <quote>God</quote>, of which anyone who confesses Him is guilty, to say, <quote>He is mine
                  alone,</quote> as other, pointless religions do. And, like the air that we breathe, which
               all men have in common, and like the light of the sun, the moon, the stars, and
               millions more, Christianity is not just mine, but for all rational people, past,
               present and future, who want to believe it. I say before men, what I learned from the
               holy scripture. Anyone who listens, accepts and does, I commend, honour and praise,
               and I do not push him out of the church. Because he knows his Creator, and believes
               in His Providence. The holy scripture does not tell me to bind someone, beat them, or
               take something from them. But we pray and implore <persName>God</persName> for those who err, that he will
               lead them to the knowledge of truth; but I would warn the Christians to guard against
               the uncleanness of sacrificial victims.</quote></p>
            <p>Then the Mobedan Mobed, and all those present gave the verdict: He is worth of
               death.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <p>At the meeting where they were negotiating with the blessed one was also a respected
               believer from <placeName>Bet Ardashir</placeName>, named <persName>Abrodak</persName>, a man who was very close to the king and
               his nobles. When he heard the words of the Catholicos, he was filled with divine zeal
               and said to the Mobedan Mobed, <quote>You too, you who are the chief magian, will agree
                  with the Catholicos, if you listen to his teaching, and will desire to become a
                  Christian, and we Christians will not push you out of the church.</quote> The Mobedan Mobed
               and the magians were very angry at this, but because the believer was an important
               man, they could do nothing to him. However the chief magian and his companions arose
               and came in great anger to the king, and complained bitterly of these words, <quote>A
                  Christian has said to the Mobedan Mobed, <quote>If you become a Christian, we will receive
                     you with joy.</quote></quote> The <persName>King of Kings</persName> said, to appease their anger, <quote>Why didn't you
                        prosecute him without delay?</quote> When they were gone from the king, they sought to catch
               him, but they did not find him, because he had gone at the king's command on official
               business to the (capital) cities. Thus he escaped the hands of the magians.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <p>After this the blessed one went daily into the assembly of the magians, who were
               negotiating with him and asking him about all sorts of things. And the Mobed of <placeName>Bet
                  Aramaje</placeName> got up and said, <quote>Often, when Christians bring a prosecution, and obtain a
                     written (judgement) from the Mobedan Mobed, he sends for them, takes them out of the
                     court house and tears up the written (judgement). All the cases that come to us are
                     actually decided by him, and we suffer much violence through him.</quote> </p>
            <p>The Catholicos said, <quote>If a Christian maliciously accuses his brother, I will not
               allow him to come into the church.</quote></p>
            <p>Then a man from <placeName>Samarra</placeName> (?) named <persName>Dendad</persName> got up, who had put on the name of
               Christian, but in this, as in many other accusations, he had joined with the magians,
               and since he had exchanged <persName>God</persName>'s truth for a lie, after a few days his body was
               swollen up, by <persName>God</persName>'s punishment. Then he stood up publicly before the magians and
               said, <quote>I have maliciously accused the Catholicos.</quote> But he died mid-sentence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <p>Because the blessed one had given himself over to the commandments of the <persName>Lord</persName> and
               the apostles, he warned the bishops and priests, their flock, all the time to warn
               all ranks of the Christian community not to break the canons of the apostles and
               marry their stepmother, niece, wife of their uncle, or to approach two (sisters).
               Anyone who did otherwise he expelled from the church with bindings and anathemas.
               Then the rad and the Mobed of <placeName>Bet Aramaye</placeName> arose and accused him also of this. </p>
            <p>The Mobedan Mobed said to the blessed one, <quote>Those who, before you were Catholicos,
               married such men or women, allow them into the church because it did not happen in
               your time.</quote> </p>
            <p>The Catholicos said, <quote>I will not transgress the command of my <persName>Lord</persName>, and to those who
               do, whether they have transgressed or are transgressing, I will refuse entry to the
               church, so that they do not contaminate the people of the <persName>Lord</persName>.</quote></p>
            <p>The chief Magian said, <quote>Those who did so in your time should not enter.</quote></p>
            <p>The Catholicos said, <quote>Whether the devil entered someone before or during my
               Catholicate, should he leave him or not?</quote></p>
            <p>The chief Magian said, <quote>He should leave him.</quote></p>
            <p>The Catholicos said, <quote>In the same way should also those who have transgressed the
               divine commandment be freed, so that they are not delivered with <persName>Satan</persName> and the devils
               to eternal hell.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <p>As the Mobedan Mobed and the magians recognised that they had been refuted by the
               blessed one with these words, they sought out another method to link the issue with
               the command of the king. The Mobedan Mobed said, <quote>If in your (holy) scriptures it
                  says, <quote>If you do this, you do rightly</quote> and if is it written in another text, that you
                  should not do it because it is not right, and if the <persName>King of Kings</persName> says to you, that
                  this, which you are commanded to do, you shall not do, and to do what it says not to
                  do, will you obey the orders of the <persName>King of Kings</persName> and do his will, or will you
                  transgress his command?</quote></p>
            <p>The Catholicos said, <quote>Far be it from the <persName>King of Kings</persName> that he, with respect to the
               good which is commanded of me, and the evil, which is forbidden to me, shall order me
               not to do good and to do evil.</quote></p>
            <p>The Mobedan Mobed and the magians said, <quote>But what if he does?</quote></p>
            <p>The Catholicos said, <quote>He does not.</quote></p>
            <p>And as they pressured him so much, he said, <quote>If he commands it, I will at that time
               answer, <quote><persName>God the Creator</persName> and Lord of all things must be obeyed rather than men.</quote></quote></p>
            <p>They said nothing in reply.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <p>A few days later, the <persName>King of Kings</persName> saw the blessed one on the road; he spoke to him
               and accepted the salutation which the godly one made him. This excited the envy of
               the magians and they again brought him before their assembly. When he appeared before
               them, one arose as prosecutor and said, <quote>This one used to be a pagan and the son of a
                  pagan, and later became a Christian.</quote> </p>
            <p>Then they all clapped their hands and said, <quote>This man is deserving of death.</quote> Then
               they drew up a document of the investigation and read it to each other. </p>
            <p>They showed him the piece of writing, which they had drawn up against him, and said,
               <quote>If you do our will, and write and sign with us, that you do not forbid those who
                  have married their stepmother, sisters and stepdaughters, as well as those others who
                  (have contracted marriages) forbidden by your scripture, do not come before the
                  court, do not bring any magians and pagans into Christianity, and do not forbid the
                  Christians to eat the flesh left over from magian sacrifices, then we will leave you
                  free and we will not throw you into prison. Go into your house and manage your
                  Catholicate. But if you do not listen to us, then we will draw up an indictment
                  (<foreign xml:lang="grc">purschaschnâmag</foreign>) against you and throw you in prison.</quote></p>
            <p>The Catholicos said, <quote><persName>God</persName>, whom I serve, forbids me to transgress the true Christian
               faith, which I hold and teach, and to do you will in any of the above matters. For
               anyone who does something like this denies <persName>Christ</persName> and is no Christian.</quote></p>
            <p>After they heard this, they sealed the indictment and ordered that he be thrown into
               prison.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <p>But since the Christians at court clamoured violently and shouted because of the
               blessed one, the <persName>King of Kings</persName> ordered that he should not be thrown into prison. He
               was handed over to the <persName>Rad of <placeName>Azerbaijan</placeName></persName>, named <persName>Dad(d)en</persName>, a man evil and hardened
               against everyone, but who through <persName>God</persName>'s grace was gentle, friendly and peaceful to
               the blessed and his disciples. </p>
            <p>On the advice of the devil, the enemy of truth, the Mobedan Mobed and the noble
               magians secretly arranged to send down the holy one into his custody in the province
               of <placeName>Azerbaijan</placeName>, which is eclipsed by error,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/> in a district (<foreign xml:lang="grc">rûstâkâ</foreign>) darkened by
               paganism named <placeName>PRHRWR</placeName>, in a village named <placeName>SRSCH</placeName> by the magians, which is the
               birthplace of magianism. </p>
            <p>There the magians of the whole Persian realm gather together in order to learn the
               foolish mutterings of <persName>Zardusht bar Spidtahman</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> people who are the enemies of all
               truth. They wander about in droves and bands, follow their masters, talk and argue in
               the nonsense of their errors, stuttering and yelling and gnashing their teeth like
               wild pigs. The blessed one had to endure the sight and sound of the wildness and
               pugnacity of the people, who had never heard the name of Christian, faced them with
               his greeting and attempted to talk rationally to them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12"/></p>
            <p>They placed a watch on him. And because of <persName>Satan</persName>'s influence, they did not allow him
               the slightest relief from his pains, which they made him endure so that he would
               quickly depart from this life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <p>When the holy one heard this, he praised <persName>God</persName>: <quote>I praise you, <persName>Lord Christ</persName>, Lord of all
               kings and King of all lords, that you have done me, a weakling, this great honour,
               that I am persecuted and reviled, because I confess you in truth as <persName>God</persName>, your Father
               and the holy, life-giving <persName>Spirit</persName>, and that I, for the sake of your great and terrible
               name, have been handed over by your persecutors to prison and imprisonment. Show your
               mercy, O <persName>Lord</persName>, to me and to all your holy church, which is useful and profitable for
               the glory and increase of your holy name.</quote></p>
            <p>Then he said to the <persName>Mobedan Mobed</persName>, <quote>The earth in all its fullness, the world and all
               its inhabitants, belong to the <persName>Lord</persName>.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> Boldly he took the <persName>Rad of <placeName>Azerbaijan</placeName></persName> by the
               hand and said, <quote>Come, take me wherever you have been ordered to take me; see, I am
                  pleased with you.</quote> The vigorous fighter (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀγωνιστής</foreign>) went to the field of combat in
               the strong power of <persName>Christ</persName>, and after his struggle had lasted seventy days, by the
               power of <persName>Christ</persName> he had not been overcome by the magians, but was strengthened by the
               struggle. The lamb of <persName>Christ</persName> emerged victorious, so that he might go and battle with
               the young lions.</p>
            <p>After the Rad handed him over to the captain (Ainbed) and the policemen of the
               province, the Christians at the court of the <persName>King of Kings</persName> arose; they went with the
               blessed one and accompanied their spiritual father, who was being sent by his enemies
               to prison. They remembered the spiritual milk, which they had drawn constantly from
               his teaching, and the good shepherd, who taught and pastured them on the meadow of
               his spiritual words, and of which they were deprived. Some wept and sobbed, others
               tore their clothes and hair, others kissed his tortured feet and took grace from his
               footsteps. </p>
            <p>The blessed one was very sad, and worried about what he saw his flock do, more than a
               wet-nurse; and they wept more than children if their mother is taken into captivity.
               Lastly he prayed in great anguish, blessed them, and handed them over to <persName>God</persName> and the
               words of his grace, and so they parted.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <p>Then the blessed one came to the village which is the centre of magianism. When he
               came to them, they said, <quote>It has never happened, that a Christian came into this
                  village and spent the night here. But now the leader of the Christians has been sent
                  to us, so that we must give him a house and he live with us.</quote> Those who were gathered
               there from the various provinces were at once angry, and boasted at once, <quote>We will
                  dispute with him and convert him to magianism.</quote> But <persName>God</persName> altered their feeling against
               him, and they came to greet him. And when they heard the divine wisdom that was in
               him, they came constantly with their arguments to him and disputed with the holy one,
               and through <persName>God</persName>'s grace he dissolved their objections, countered their arguments and
               refuted their errors. Often also they sought to kill him; but <persName>God</persName> limited their
               wickedness and confined them to peace. When they stopped disputing with him and just
               asked him about <persName>God</persName> and the world, good and evil, the resurrection, the judgement to
               come and the life ever after in <persName>Christ</persName>, the Master spoke with them and taught them
               about all this. They marvelled at his spirit-filled words and closeness to <persName>God</persName>. Some
               disputed about this with each other, some with their teachers. Also many magians came
               from other places, to hear the teaching of the Master and to see how he behaved. For
               everywhere they called him the god of the place because of his spirit-filled
               teaching, his compassion for the poor and his care for the sick. But he had no
               financial dealings with any of them, and although the local Rad and the gentleman of
               the place said that he might satisfy his needs from them, he would not do so. Many
               believed in him. For thus did <persName>God</persName> turn their evil into good.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <p>There was at that place a plague, and those who saw it trembled and those who heard
               about it were terrified. The blessed one was asked to leave; but he would not, and
               said, <quote>Death and life are in <persName>God</persName>'s hand; wherever I am, I am his in life and death.
                  It is necessary only that we believe in him and walk in good works according to his
                  will. Believe in him, and stay.</quote> And many remained and were not struck down by that
               harsh plague. But if anyone was hit, he blessed oil and gave it, and they anointed
               him and, depending on his faith, he recovered from that disease.</p>
            <p>A woman from that village, whose husband, named <persName>Arwândâd</persName> (?), was the judge, was
               tempted by the evil spirit. She came and with her husband threw herself for a long
               time at the door of the blessed one, to get him to come and put his hand on her head.
               But he would not, but blessed oil and sent it to her. She anointed herself and the
               devil departed from her and she was tempted no more. All who knew her previously saw
               what had happened and praised <persName>God</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <p>He turned the house in which he lived into a church. He set up there an altar of
               <persName>Christ</persName>, and every day gave himself with his disciples to fasting and prayer. What in
               the beginning was the dwelling of <persName>Satan</persName> became then a house of prayer to the true
               <persName>God</persName>. From the provinces Metropolitans, bishops, priests, deacons and believing men
               and women came together there, in fact, to pray and to receive his blessing. Some
               were standing at his door in sackcloth and ashes, for their sins, and received
               remission. Some received the blessing of the spiritual dignity of the episcopate.
               Some received the dignity of the priesthood, diaconate or other ecclesiastical ranks
               (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τάξις</foreign>). All the houses of the persecutors and blasphemers became offices of the
               saints and houses of prayer and praise to <persName>God</persName>. Crowds of bishops met and the sound
               was heard of their songs of the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>. A stream of priests came to the offices
               of their comrades and told each other of the great and wonderful things that they had
               seen and heard. The mountains and heights of <placeName>Azerbaijan</placeName> became like cities, wherever
               the feet of the <persName>Saint</persName> went. Old men who came to see the <persName>Saint</persName> forgot their age and
               sprang up like deer, and those struck down by disease recovered when they were
               carried to him to seek his blessing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <p>After the saint had spent seven years in this way, without ever crossing the
               threshold of the house in which he lived, being constant in fasting, prayer, and
               writing letters excellent in every way, which he sent out in order to govern his
               subordinate provinces, <persName>Satan</persName> became full of envy and could not endure these
               magnificent things.</p>
            <p>He caused a second <persName>Judas</persName>, unworthy of the name of <persName>Petrus Gurganara</persName>, who from a
               spiritual pastor had become a ravening wolf, to deny <persName>Christ</persName> and embrace the error of
               magianism, because the purity and integrity of the church expelled him from its womb
               because of his many abominations and immoralities, like a splinter from the eye, and,
               with the traitor, his associates.</p>
            <p>He went to the chief magian and at the command of the king obtained a order of
               apostasy,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/> that any of the bishops, priests and deacons ordained by the blessed one
               who did not resign should be thrown into prison, and that no-one should refer to him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15"/>
               as Catholicos, because he only became a Christian in later life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <p>When this command was broadcast by the machinations of the apostate and his
               associates, some fearful people were influenced, and all prayed to <persName>God</persName> that he would
               have mercy on his church and not deliver it into the hands of the destroyer. But when
               the traitor got this order and took it to <placeName>Azerbaijan</placeName> and convinced the Mobed of the
               area to prosecute the disciples of the blessed one before him and, because of his
               murderous ambition, to treat the blessed one in the same way as his disciples, the
               <persName>Lord</persName> did not fulfil his wicked desire. Instead he inspired the Mobedan (Mobed) and
               the magians to call him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16"/> before them and to question him in the way he<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17"/> wanted.
               And the Mobed said, <quote>I do not have the authority to question him.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18"/> Some of the
               magians mentioned said, however, <quote>He shall come before us as we are very determined
                  to see him.</quote> </p>
            <p>And because he was persuaded to, he came before their assembly and they let him seat
               himself in great honour. And because they heard sound thinking from his mouth, they
               reviled and beat the apostate, so that he hid himself from them. </p>
            <p>When he saw his hopes come to nothing, he sought another way to kill the saint. He
               hired some rascals and came with them to the place where the godly one lived, to
               murder him and give as an excuse that he<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19"/> was escaping from custody. </p>
            <p>But <persName>God</persName>, who knew the thoughts of the traitor, did not allow it. For when the traitor
               arrived secretly at night with his men, entered and searched for his disciples, he
               heard the voice of the blessed one, and from fright and shame became weak and trembly
               and could not lay a hand on him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20"/> The men of the house found out, and the people of
               the village, and they came, beat the apostates, and drove him away, together with the
               magians that he had brought with him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <p>Afterwards the blessed one reflected, <quote>Perhaps the murderer will find an opportunity
               to fulfil his murderous desire upon me, and then spread the rumour that I have run
               away.</quote> Then he gave himself up to death in the open, got up in the night with his
               disciple, named <persName>Jacob</persName>, and, trusting <persName>God</persName>, left the village accompanied by the
               zealous, stout and God-loving bishop of <placeName>Azerbaijan</placeName>, <persName>Mar Johannan</persName>. He travelled in the
               winter, in cold, frost and snow, over the mountains and hills, to the royal court,
               entered and went to the <!-- is this a person or place?-->HRPDKA.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21"/></p>
            <p>When the <persName>King of Kings</persName> heard of his arrival, he was greatly astonished, that he had
               not gone elsewhere, but had come there, where everybody was afraid of ending up in
               the HRPDKA. The Christians of the (two) cities and everywhere arose and came to see
               the blessed one, and everyone awaited the outcome of this unfortunate business. But
               the magians rejoiced and said, <quote>Now that he has ignored the command of the <persName>King of
                  Kings</persName>, the latter will at once command his execution and rid us of him.</quote> </p>
            <p>Since everyone was watching and waiting to see what would happen, the <persName>King of Kings</persName>
               sent to the blessed one by means of <persName>Ferruchdad Hormizd DZ'DGW</persName>, <quote>What is the judgement
                  on he who transgresses the command of his lord?</quote> The Catholicos said, <quote>If he is a
                     serf, his food and clothing shall be taken; if he works for pay, he will not receive
                     his pay.</quote></p>
            <p><persName>Hormizd DZ'DGW</persName> said, <quote>What is your judgement, when you have ignored the command of
               the king of kings and come here against his command?</quote> The Catholicos said, <quote>I have
                  not ignored the command of the king of kings, but I am his friend and obey his
                  command. Because a renegade came against me, to murder me secretly, I left there and
                  came to his court, so that no-one would think that I had run away. If I have done
                  wrong, let him execute me openly.</quote> Then <persName>Hormizd DZ'DGW</persName> went and reported this to the
               <persName>King of Kings</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <p>Then the <persName>King of Kings</persName> told him: <quote>That you ignored our command and come here, we
               forgive you. But the four very serious accusations that the magians make against you
               are as follows: that you make magians leave their religion (<foreign xml:lang="grc">dên</foreign>) and into Christians;
               that you do not let your people marry many women as they wish; that you subvert the
               legal processes of the magians; that you were originally a heathen and only later
               became a Christian. Add to this that when you were interned, you appointed bishops,
               priests and deacons and ordered them to teach and convert people to Christianity as
               you do. All this we forgive you in our benevolence. Only the fact that you became a
               Christian later, must you account for, if the Mobedan Mobed requires it from you. Now
               go home and be at peace.</quote> Then the <persName>Saint</persName> worshipped and praised <persName>God</persName>; he blessed the
               <persName>King of Kings</persName>, and went out of the HRPDKA with great joy.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22"/> But because of the crush
               of the crowd accompanying him he could not get through the city gate, but went over
               the city moat. At this the aforementioned magians were amazed and upset; they went
               and woke the King and said: <quote>The man, who is the enemy of the religion (<foreign xml:lang="grc">dên</foreign>) of
                  <persName>Hormizd</persName>, you have let go free and he is going to his house!</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="29">
            <p>On the morning of the (following) day, when the blessed one in the company of the
               Christians went to the court in order to thank the <persName>King of Kings</persName>, the aforementioned
               magians sought for a way to kill him. They were afraid to seize him openly on account
               of the number of believers accompanying him, in case there should be an uproar when
               they approached him, and decided to send the Rad and the Ainbed to arrest him
               secretly. That day there was heavy rain, and so they went into the hunting lodge at a
               place called the <placeName>Birdhouse</placeName>, near the (palace of) the <persName>King of Kings</persName>. The magians send
               to him, as if they wanted to speak to him. After he entered, they closed the door so
               that no-one could follow him and said to the blessed one: <quote>Ever since you became a
                  Christian, you have converted many magians into Christians, and you cannot be allowed
                  to live (longer).</quote> Some said, <quote>He should be thrown to the lions.</quote> Some said, <quote>He
                     should be strangled.</quote> Others said, <quote>We'll throw him into a well so that he dies
                        there, without the Christians knowing.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="30">
            <p>While they devised these things, the Christian people came up and went about
               everywhere in the belief that he had been crowned,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23"/> or that he was about to be
               crowned. But <persName>God</persName> in his mercy delivered him from their hands. By his secret work he
               inspired one of the great men of the empire to stand up before the King and say,
               <quote><persName>King of Kings</persName>, best of men, may you live in eternity and may your majesty reign
                  forever. The Christian people who are in your empire are a strong, great people, an
                  innumerable multitude, and also useful for the service of the government. If this
                  man, their leader, is put to death, it injures them greatly and your empire suffers
                  no small damage.</quote> When the <persName>King of Kings</persName> in his benevolence heard this from this man,
               it pleased him and his whole court, so that they would not hear the petition (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τάγμα</foreign>)
               of the Magians, and he ordered that the holy one of <persName>Christ</persName> must not be killed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="31">
            <p>Then they bound the saint hand and foot and neck with heavy iron fetters, and covered
               his face so that no-one would know him and no rebellion would break out, placed him
               on a mule and handed him over to the mobed who had oversight of the prison at court.
               The mobed did as he was commanded and the house in which the blessed one was was
               guarded by horsemen and foot soldiers. When the saint heard that zealous believers
               were hanging about, looking to break open the house, he was very worried and forbade
               them to remain in the vicinity of the house. Immediately they left at his command;
               but the saint stayed in the prison guarded by <persName>God</persName>, who had said, <quote>With the righteous
                  am I in distress; I will strengthen and honour him and show him my salvation.</quote> And
               although fettered, he consecrated bishops, priests and deacons, strengthened them
               with blessings and prayers, and sent them out to the provinces.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="32">
            <p>At the time of the journey, when the <persName>King of Kings</persName> set out to go to <placeName>Azerbaijan</placeName>, the
               saint was led with him in his fetters, in great discomfort, over mountains and hills,
               in heat and drought, in thirst and hunger, in much prayer with his disciples.
               Wherever they came, the believers welcomed him with great joy and everyone went to
               his tent as a means of grace and blessing. Wherever the king camped, believers came
               from place and asked that the <persName>Saint</persName> should be released from these harsh restraints.
               When the <persName>King of Kings</persName> came to <placeName>Azerbaijan</placeName> and the magians of the place where the
               <persName>Blessed One</persName> had been in custody, hearing that he was at court, all came to honour and
               greet him, weeping that by the removal of the <persName>Noble One</persName> they had been robbed of such
               a blessing. Everywhere they went, wherever the great ones of the Kingdom were, they
               spoke of his wisdom and manner of life. The leaders of the magians at court forbade
               them to say such things about him, until, of the leaders of the magians, <persName>Kardag the
                  Ainbed</persName>, and <persName>Shahrdawer</persName>, and <persName>Azadsad the Mobedan Mobed</persName>, calmed down in their anger
               against him, because they became ashamed of themselves through the beautiful things
               which people said about him. So they told him through a Mobed, <quote>We hear from many
                  people that you are a good and an upright man, and we are anxious that you should be
                  released from your bonds. Just state publically that you are not opposed to magianism
                  and will not convert (anyone) else to Christianity, and we will immediately release
                  you and you can go wherever you like.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="33">
            <p>After the Mobed spoke thus to the Lordly one, the latter instructed him extensively
               from the Holy Scriptures on the true faith, the permanence of Christianity, the
               greatness of the economy of <persName>God</persName>, about the resurrection and the judgement, about the
               blessings which are prepared for the righteous in heaven, and the punishments which
               are prepared for the wicked in eternal hell with <persName>Satan</persName> and the devils.</p>
            <p>When the Mobed heard this, he was seized with amazement and fear; he clapped his
               hands together at the great manysidedness and invincibility of these thoughts, and he
               stood up and recognised and praised <persName>God</persName>. Then the Lordly one said, <quote>Go and tell them:
                  I am the servant of <persName>God</persName> and I do not transgress the command of my <persName>Lord</persName>, who says, <quote>Go
                     into all nations and baptise them in the name of <persName>the Father</persName> and <persName>the Son</persName> and the <persName>Holy
                        Spirit.</persName></quote> I shall not go to eternal <placeName>Hell</placeName> with <persName>Satan</persName> and the devils; I am not afraid of
                  the long agony of passing time, and I do not confuse the true life and eternal
                  blessings with the corruptible (blessings) of this impermanent world.</quote> When the Mobed
               went and said this to the Magians, they marvelled at the courage of the Lordly one
               and said, <quote>You see that he does not obey us and does not give way so that we might
                  release him from his fetters. Now he can only blame himself.</quote> After a few days, when
               he was exhausted from his heavy fetters and the effort of (walking) the difficult
               paths, and had come to a stop in order to rest from the rigours, the Magians brought
               two pairs of thick, new fetters, took the old ones away, and left him bound with them
               hand and foot, so that he could no longer get up because of their weight. He received
               these joyfully and confessed and praised <persName>God</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="34">
            <p>After the <persName>Saint</persName> had been dragged along in these fetters in the wake of the king for
               about 400 parasangs, until the <persName>King of Kings</persName> went down to the (two) cities, he went
               down also and lived in fetters with his disciples in a house, where by the power of
               <persName>Christ</persName> he managed the patriarchate and all its obligations. Then the <persName>King of Kings</persName>
               commanded, in his goodness, that he should be freed; but the Magians persisted in
               their usual hostility and left the Saint in his fetters. Once the King of Kings
               departed from the (two) cities, he was taken in chains in the wake of the court to a
               place named <placeName>PS'I</placeName>. After they had tortured and tormented him in these hard fetters and
               the wonderful beauty of his patience in the fear of <persName>God</persName> had been revealed, then
               almighty <persName>God, the Lord of All</persName>, in his wonderful power, through his inexpressible
               works, gave an irresistible hint to the mind of the <persName>King of Kings</persName>, so that he sent
               and by a miracle loosed the athlete (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀθλήτης</foreign>) of <persName>Christ</persName> from all his fetters. Then
               there was great joy in the whole people of <persName>God</persName> and they offered praise and
               worship.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="35">
            <p>While the <persName>King of Kings</persName> intended that he should remain a few days after his release,
               and then go to the cities of his throne, <persName>Satan</persName> stirred up unrest and rioting through
               the actions of the heathen in <placeName>Bet Huzaye</placeName>. The Magians accused the <persName>Blessed One</persName> before
               the <persName>King of Kings</persName>: <quote>If the Catholicos had wanted, the rioting would not have broken
                  out.</quote> Immediately he was chained to a foot-soldier (<!-- I am having trouble figuring out what language this word is or if it does not need to be rendered-->paig) by a strong chain to the
               neck, and brought to the court of the <persName>King of Kings</persName>, and everyone believed that he
               would be executed immediately. The <persName>King of Kings</persName>, exasperated through the slander of
               the Magians, sent word to him by means of his commissioner <persName>(Farruchdâd Hôrmîzd)
                  DZ'DGW</persName>: <quote>You are an enemy of <persName>Our Majesty</persName>, and the Christians have become arrogant
                     because of you. In many cities they have risen up against the noble Magians, beaten
                     and robbed them, and even now are rioting. You chose bishops and priests and sent
                     them into the provinces, even though you are in prison; but myself you treat as
                     nothing. Therefore I command that in the morning you will be taken and thrown into a
                     pit, so that you will die there.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="36">
            <p>The Catholicos boldly raised his voice and said, <quote>Once the <persName>King of Kings</persName> has made
               such a decision about me, because of the whisperings of my enemies, (further) words
               are unnecessary. He orders my immediate death, and with great joy do I accept death
               for the truth of <persName>Christ</persName>. The Magians persecuted me, an innocent, and imprisoned me
               for seven years in the power of my persecutors, and sent a renegade to murder me. But
               <persName>God</persName> in his invincible power rescued me, after I came to the court of his Majesty the
               <persName>King of Kings</persName>, and they did violence on me and the people of <persName>God</persName>, although they
               fettered me hand and foot and neck as a malefactor, and <persName>God</persName> the almighty knows that I
               was dragged away by them by force. The King of Kings said that he would release me
               from the fetters, and after he retracted this, and they slandered me before his
               sublime Majesty, and he finally decided against me, so let him now demand my
               immediate execution.</quote></p>
            <p>The <persName>PSNIK'</persName> went and reported these words to the king. Then the <persName>King of Kings</persName> left the
               <persName>Saint</persName> alone and said to him in a friendly way, <quote>Go and write letters to the
                  Christians of each province, that, if the insurgents do not settle down peaceably,
                  the sword, bow and arrows will be drawn against them, they will be attacked, and any
                  found fighting will be killed, be they Magian, Jew or Christian.</quote> After the <persName>PSNIK'</persName>
               brought the message, he undertook to write it.</p>
            <p>After this was done, <persName>God</persName> worked on the <persName>King of Kings</persName>, and it was suggested to him
               that he should release the <persName>Saint</persName>. And when the <persName>King of Kings</persName> went into (winter)
               quarters near the (two) cities, the <persName>Saint</persName> went with him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="37">
            <p>Some time later, the chief of the Hephthalites (<foreign xml:lang="grc">haftarân chudâ</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24"/> sent a priest to
               the <persName>King of Kings</persName>, and many Christian Hephthalites sent a letter to the <persName>Saint [Mar
                  Aba]</persName> to ask him to consecrate the priest as a bishop for the whole Hephthalite
               realm.</p>
            <p>After the priest had come before the King, and set forth the business of his mission,
               [the King] wondered at what he heard, and marvelled at the great power of <persName>Christ</persName>,
               that the Christian Hephthalites also considered the <persName>Lordly One [Mar Aba]</persName> as their
               chief and regent, and he said to him that he should go and adorn the church as was
               custom, and should go into his church and house and collect the bishops according to
               custom, and ordain the man sent by the prince of the Hephthalites.</p>
            <p>When the people of the <persName>Lord</persName> heard this message, and the <persName>Saint</persName> came out of prison and
               into the cathedral of his apostolic seat, what joy was like that joy, that the <persName>Lordly
                  One</persName> had returned to his blessed flock after nine years, which he had spent in combat
               with lions and panthers for his beloved flock,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25"/> and returned victorious.</p>
            <p>What shepherd loves his flock like our father, the master of the holy flock, who bore
               every trouble and persecution for it, and gave himself over to death? As the good
               shepherd led his blessed sheep into the holy sheepfold, so the sheep and lambs of
               <persName>Christ</persName> ran in to him from all sides, when they heard his beloved voice, surrounded
               him, sought refuge with him, and kissed his hands and feet and whole body, which was
               torn and mangled by the claws and fetters. And they waited to hear the sound of his
               sweet hymns and to suck spiritual milk from his beloved teaching. Because the sheep
               heard the voice of the blessed shepherd, they were very happy about this, and only
               with difficulty could he enter his blessed appartment because of the crush of
               people.</p>
            <p>The following morning the church was adorned with throngs of believers; the <persName>Saint</persName>
               ordained the Hephthalite priest as bishop for the land of the Hephthalites, and in
               the people of the <persName>Lord</persName> joy grew over the arrangements of divine providence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="38">
            <p>Afterwards the <persName>King of Kings</persName> sent him [<persName>Mar Aba</persName>] into the province of <placeName>Bêt Hûzâjê</placeName>, and
               by <persName>God</persName>'s work and his care many priests were saved from death and their blood was not
               shed. He encouraged them and filled their hearts with the words of spiritual
               teaching. Then he returned to the court of the <persName>King of Kings</persName>, who allowed him to
               reside wherever he wanted. The captain of the foot-soldiers (paig) who guarded him
               was ordered to leave him in peace.</p>
            <p>He took up his dwelling next to the church of <persName>Bêt Narkôs</persName>. There he lived and
               concerned himself with divine instruction, and every day he said wonderful things to
               those who came to him, and converted many from heresy who had come with the <persName>King of
                  the Arabs</persName> to pay homage to the <persName>King of Kings</persName> and that made pilgrimage to him.</p>
            <p>When he became ill for some time because of his imprisonment, the King ordered that
               doctors should be sent to him to heal him; but they could not.</p>
            <p>The <persName>Saint</persName> slept from his holy struggle on the Friday of the second week of Lent.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="39">
            <p>Then the magians made so much fuss, that nobody dared to bury him until the King
               commanded it. When he was laid on the bier (<foreign xml:lang="grc">λεκτίκιον</foreign>) and brought out, with great
               difficulty because of the crowd of believers, who threw onto it many handkerchiefs
               (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σουδάριον</foreign>) or coats and took them back again, as means of grace and blessing, until
               it reached the cathedral of <!-- is this a person or place? I could not find a place or this name being used -->Koke, the magians ordered that he should be thrown to the
               dogs.</p>
            <p>Then the believers in droves shouted, <quote>If anyone approaches the body of the saint, we
               will begin a bloodbath.</quote> They came en masse seized the litter (? BSPK') and took it
               as a relic, and left nothing except the coffin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γλωσσόκομον</foreign>) in which was the body of
               the saint.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="40">
            <p>He was honoured for seven days in the cathedral, day and night, with scripture
               readings, hymns, sermons and spiritual songs, and all the hosts of believers from all
               the provinces took the blessings home, by means of small towels (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ὠράριον</foreign>) and
               garments, that they laid on his body. Then the <persName>King of Kings</persName> and the Mobedan Mobed
               sent the Mobed (of the province?) and the judge and other magians to see whether it
               was the saint or not, because, out of fear and terror, they didn't believe in his
               death.</p>
            <p>After these delegates had seen him, the body of the saint was placed on another bier
               (<foreign xml:lang="grc">λεκτίκιον</foreign>) and buried with great honour while spiritual songs were sung. Countless
               multitudes eagerly honoured him with perfumes and lamps all the way through the city
               to the monastery of <placeName>Seleucia</placeName>. Likewise the judges and magians who had been sent went
               before the litter (? BISPK'), in which the saint's body was, and after he had been
               honoured through <persName>God</persName>'s almighty power, the magians returned, amazed and astonished at
               what they had seen and heard, to those who had sent them.</p>
            <p>Thus the multitude applauded and praised <persName>God</persName> because of the wonderful things that
               happened at the death of the saint.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="41">
            <p>In order to avoid wearying you, through hearing too much, let us pass over what <persName>God</persName>
               soon did through him and for his sake in many distant countries, through arbitrating
               disputes which <persName>Satan</persName>, the enemy of our nature, had aroused; then in the imprisonment,
               which he endured for seven years in <placeName>Azerbaijan</placeName>; then in the fetters which he wore for
               three years around his neck, hands and feet at the king's court.</p>
            <p>There is much of this, and in many parts; the mouth is unable to tell it all, and you
               already know much of it.</p>
            <p>So we end our words with the words of the blessed <persName>David</persName>, and say: <quote>Blessed is the
               people that has such a man, and blessed is the people at whose head stands such a
               man, to feed the flock of our <persName>Saviour Jesus Christ</persName>.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">This group (Syriac <foreign xml:lang="syr">bnay qyāmâ</foreign>) were a monastic-like group who combined
               asceticism with an politically and socially active life. See also Wikipedia
               article.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">German <hi rend="doubleQuote">Kalkkirche.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n3">It was illegal in the Sassanid realm for Zoroastrians to convert to
               Christianity, and the convert could be executed.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">This name is given in this unvocalised form in the BKV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">Justinian may have desired to see him for various reasons; but Mar
               Aba's refusal and quick exit across the frontier suggests that the invitation was of
               a threatening kind, where he might be asked to anathematise Nestorius.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">I.e. as Nestorian patriarch.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">The Roman emperor.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8">Flesh of animals offered in sacrifice.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9">According to J. Labourt, <foreign xml:lang="fr">Le christianisme dans l'empireperse sous la
               dynastie Sassanide</foreign>, Paris, 1904, p.181 n.3, this is the pasaniqarusphan, the director
               of prisons, although he doesn't seem that sure about it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10"><hi rend="doubleQuote"><foreign xml:lang="ge">die durch den Irrtum verfinstert ist</foreign></hi> — I am not sure that I have
               rendered this correctly.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11">I.e. Zoroaster.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12">Not sure about this sentence at all: <quote><foreign xml:lang="ge">Welchen Anblick und welches
               Anhören der Wildheit und Streitsucht von Leuten, die nicht einmal den Christennamen
               hören, seinen Gruß annehmen und mit ihm wie Menschen reden mochten, vermochte der
               Selige auszuhalten</foreign>.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n13">I.e. that wherever he is, God is with him.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14">The writer seems to mean that the order itself indicated that the
               person brandishing it was an apostate.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15">Mar Aba.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16">Mar Aba.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17">Petrus Gurganara.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18">Is this <hi rend="doubleQuote">question</hi> as in <hi rend="doubleQuote">being put to the question</hi>, i.e.
               torture?</note>
            <note xml:id="n19">Mar Aba.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20">Not an experienced conspirator, it seems.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21">The BKV text gives no clue as to what this is. It would seem to be a
               rather grim prison.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22">The HRPDKA is clearly close to the court.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23">I.e. martyred</note>
            <note xml:id="n24">Also known as the White Huns; a serious military threat to the
               Persian state located in the north.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25">The <hi rend="doubleQuote">lions and panthers</hi> no doubt refers to his battles with the
               Zoroastrian clergy.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
