<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3014">To Oecumenius the Count</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Letters I to LXI</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">176 [3]-186 [14]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">12</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1">
            <head type="number">I.</head>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE SAME<note type="footnote" n="1" resp="#ebrooks">The
               letter to Anastasia (ep. 69) precedes in the ms.</note> A LETTER TO OECUMENIUS<note
                  type="footnote" n="2" resp="#ebrooks">Text 'Oecumunius', and so in the subscription, and in the
                  title of ep. 2.</note> THE COUNT<note type="footnote" n="3" resp="#ebrooks">Select Letters of
                     Severus, p. 12, 38, 92.</note>, ABOUT PROPERTIES AND OPERATIONS, WHICH IS OF THOSE WRITTEN
               BEFORE EPISCOPACY. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0508" notAfter="0512">508-12</date>
            </dateline>
            <p>We also have in the God-inspired Scripture supplies of humility, and no lack of arguments to
               bring us down and help us to keep silence. If you, as if you were about to go up to Mt. Sinai,
               shrink from writing 'to such a man' (referring to me), and think fit to use David's words which
               he says to those who were urging him to take Saul's daughter in marriage, "Is it a small thing
               in your eyes that I should be son-in-law to the king?"<note type="footnote" n="4"
                  resp="#ebrooks">1 Sam. xviii, 18.</note>, while I am a poor man and inglorious, I also, when
               required to make answer to your question, make use of these words: "I am not a prophet, nor the
               son of prophets, but I am a shepherd, and a scraper of sycamore fruit"<note type="footnote"
                  n="5" resp="#ebrooks">Amos, vii, 14.</note>, if it is not too much for me to say even this: for
               I am not worthy to tell the righteousnesses of God, and to take his covenant in <pb n="4"/> my
               mouth<note type="footnote" n="6">Ps. XLIX, 16.</note>. However, since the time of the present
               struggles does not allow silence, I accept an honourable defeat from you, and turn to the
               question. And in this I defeat you, since I show that you do not practise humility in a
               philosophic spirit<note type="footnote" n="7">The word <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >φιλοσοφῆσαι</foreign> is here transliterated.</note>. As to your statement that the holy old
               men called bold speech<note type="footnote" n="8" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >παρρησία</foreign>.</note> fire or warmth, I say this, that we must not use this method of
               speaking without discrimination, but there are occasions for using it and circumstances to which
               to apply it. Our Lord in the Gospels in many parables teaches us in the case of spiritual
               petitions to knock without ceasing and display a praiseworthy audacity. And the saying of the
               Proverbs also instructs us that 'there is shame which brings sin, and there is shame which
               brings glory and grace'<note type="footnote" n="9" resp="#ebrooks">Pr., xxvi, 11a.</note>. Know
               then, mighty man, (for I now return to make answer) that for us to anathematize those who speak
               of properties of natures (I mean the Godhead and the manhood of which the one Christ consists)
               is not permissible. Flesh does not renounce its existence as flesh, even if it has become God's
               flesh, nor has the Word departed from his nature, even if he has been hypostatically united to
               flesh which possesses a rational and intelligent soul: but the difference also is <pb n="5"/>
               preserved, and the propriety in the form of natural characteristics of the natures of which
               Emmanuel consists, since the flesh was not converted into the nature of the Word, nor was the
               Word changed into flesh. We mean in the matter of natural characteristics, and not that those
               which were naturally united are singly and individually separated and divided from one another:
               this is the assertion of those who cleave our one Lord Jesus Christ into two natures. For, since
               the union in hypostasis is acknowledged, it follows that those which were united are not
               separated from one another; but there is one Son, and one nature of God the Word incarnate
               himself, as the holy Cyril also says in the work against Diodorus: "Let him know therefore that
               the body which was born at Bethlehem, even if it is not the same as the Word from God and the
               Father (I mean in natural characteristics), yet nevertheless became his, not anyone else's
               separate from the Son: and there is recognised to be one Son and Christ and Lord and Word who
               took flesh"<note type="footnote" n="10" resp="#ebrooks">Contr. Diod.,.fr. 17 (Cyr. in Jo. Ev.,
                  ed. Pusey, III, p. 499).</note>. Those therefore who confess one incarnate nature of God the
               Word, and do not confuse the elements of which he consists, recognise also the propriety of
               those that were joined in union (and a property is that which <pb n="6"/> exists in the form of
               a manifestation of natural differences), and not that we should ascribe the acts of the manhood
               only to the human nature, and impute again those of the Godhead separately to God the Word, but
               they recognise the difference only, not admitting a division: for the principle of union does
               not admit of division. Hear what the holy and wise doctor Cyril says in the second volume<note
                  type="footnote" n="11" resp="#ebrooks">
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">τόμος</foreign>.</note> of the work against the blasphemies of
               Nestorius: "For between Godhead and manhood I also allow that there is great distinction and
               distance. For the things which have been named on the principle of manner of existence are
               clearly different, and in no point like one another. But, when the mystery in Christ is
               introduced among us, the principle of union is not oblivious of difference", but rejects
               division, not by mixing or commingling the natures with one another, but that, after the Word of
               God has partaken of flesh and blood, he is even so understood and named as one Son"<note
                  type="footnote" n="12" resp="#ebrooks">Adv. Nest., ii, 6 (ed. Pusey, VI, p. 113).</note>. But,
               if Emmanuel is one, consisting of Godhead and manhood which have a perfect existence according
               to their own principle, and the hypostatic union without confusion shows the difference of those
               which have been joined in one in dispensatory union, but rejects division, both the elements <pb
                  n="7"/> which naturally belong to the manhood have come to belong to the very Godhead of the
               Word, and those which belong to the Word himself have come to belong to the very manhood which
               he hypostatically united to him. On this subject we will again adduce the sacred words of Cyril.
               In the prosphonetikon to the religious king Theodosius he spoke as follows: "As therefore it
               came to belong to the humanity to be the Only one, because it had been united to the Word in a
               dispensatory union, so it came to belong to the Word to be 'the first-born among many
               brethren'<note type="footnote" n="13" resp="#ebrooks"> Rom., viii, 29.</note>, because of the
               union with flesh"<note type="footnote" n="14" resp="#ebrooks">De rect. fide ad Theod. imp., 30
                  (ed. Pusey, VII, p. 97).</note>. Gregory the Theologian<note type="footnote" n="15"
                     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">Θεολόγος</foreign>.</note> also in the letter to
               Gledonius wrote words which agree with him as follows: "As the natures are mingled, so also are
               the appellations; and they run into one another on the principle of coalescence"<note
                  type="footnote" n="16" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. 51 (P. G., XXXVII, 181).</note>. Do not let the term
               'mingle' disturb you: for he used it very clearly and without danger<note type="footnote" n="5"
                  resp="#ebrooks"> </note> with the intention of denoting the primary union: for, where there is
               a union of something incorporeal with a body, no danger<note type="footnote" n="17"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κίνδυνος</foreign>.</note> anywhere arises from
               mingling. For this is manifestly a quality of fluid bodies, to be confounded together by
               intertwining, and, so to speak, come out of their nature. We therefore anathematize not <pb
                  n="8"/> those who confess the properties of the natures of which the one Christ consists, but
               those who separate the properties, and apportion them to each nature apart. When the one Christ
               has once been divided (and he is divided by the fact that they speak of two natures after the
               union), with the natures which have been cut asunder into a duality and separated into a
               distinct diversity go the operations and properties which are the offspring of this division, as
               the words of Leo's impious letter state in what he said: "For each of the forms effects in
               partnership with the other that which belongs to itself, the Word doing that which belongs to
               the Word, and the body performing the things which belong to the body"<note type="footnote"
                  n="18" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. 28, 4 (P. L., LIV, 768).</note>. Against these things it is well to
               set the much-honoured words of the holy Cyril which refute impiety. In the Scholion about the
               coal he speaks as follows: "Nevertheless we may see in the coal as in a figure that God the Word
               was united to the manhood, but has not cast off being that which he is, but rather changed what
               had been assumed or united into his glory and operation. For, as fire when it takes hold of wood
               and is introduced into it, prevails over it, and does <pb n="9"/> not make it cease being wood,
               but rather changes it into the appearance and force of fire, and performs all its own acts in
               it, and is already reckoned as one with it, so understand in the case of Christ also. For, since
               God was ineffably united with manhood, he has preserved it as what we say it is, and he himself
               also has remained what he was. But, after he has once been united, he is reckoned as one with
               it, appropriating its qualities to himself, but he himself also carried on the operation of his
               nature in it"<note type="footnote" n="19" resp="#ebrooks">Schol. de Inc. Unig., 9 (ed. Pusey,
                  VI, p. 51ff).</note>. If<note type="footnote" n="20" resp="#ebrooks">This passage as far as
                     'operating' (p. 10, 1. 6) is cited in Mansi, XI, 444, where the letter is described as the 2nd
                     to Oecumenius.</note> then the Word changed the manhood which he had hypostatically united to
               him, not into his nature, for he remained that which he was, but into his glory and operation,
               and things which manifestly belong to the flesh have come to belong to the Word himself, how
               shall we allow that each of the forms performs its own acts? But we must anathematize those who
               confine the one Christ in two natures and say that each of the natures performs its own acts.
               Between the things performed and done by the one Christ the difference is great. Some of them
               are acts befitting the divinity, while others are human. For example, to walk and travel in
               bodily form upon <pb n="10"/> the earth is without contention human; but to bestow on those who
               are maimed in the feet and cannot walk upon the ground at all the power of walking like sound
               persons is God-befitting. Yet the one Word incarnate performed the latter and the former, and
               the one nature did not perform the one, and the other the other; nor, because the things
               performed are different, shall we on this account rightly define two natures or forms as
               operating. Again the Tome of Leo says: "For each of the natures preserves its own property
               without diminution"<note type="footnote" n="21" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. 28, 3 (P. L., LIV,
                  766).</note>, distributing the properties to the two natures severally, as one who divides the
               one and only Christ into two natures. For the property of the natures of which Emmanuel
               consists, which is shown in the natural characteristics, continues constant and fixed, as the
               holy Cyril also says in the second letter to Succensus: "But, while each of them both remains
               and is perceived in the property which is. by nature, according to the principle which has just
               been enunciated by us, the ineffable and incomprehensible union has shown us one nature of the
               Son, yet, as I have said, an incarnate nature"<note type="footnote" n="22" resp="#ebrooks">Ep.
                  46, 2 (P. G., LXXVII, 241).</note>. But God the Word did not permit his flesh in all things to
               undergo the passions proper to it, in order that its <pb n="11"/> property might be preserved
               undiminished, as the impious disputer said. For observe what the wise doctor Cyril says, in
               answer to the objections made by Theodoret, in the defence of the tenth anathema: "When the
               lowness arising from the exinanition seems hard to you, wonder greatly at the love of the Son
               toward us. For, what you say is a mean thing, this he did voluntarily for your sake. He wept in
               human fashion, that he might take away your weeping. He feared by dispensation, inasmuch as he
               sometimes permitted his flesh to undergo the passions proper to it, that he might make us
               valiant"<note type="footnote" n="23">Cyr., ed. Pusey, VI, p. 476.</note>. If he sometimes
               permitted his flesh by dispensation to undergo the passions proper to it, he did not preserve
               its property undiminished: for in many instances it is seen not to have undergone the things
               which manifestly belong to its nature; for it was united to the Word, the Maker of nature. The
               Word therefore who had become incarnate walked upon the sea, and after his death under the wound
               of the lance caused a stream of salvation to well forth from his side: again, after the
               Resurrection, he came in while the doors were shut, and appeared to the disciples in the house;
               whom he also allowed to touch him, showing that his flesh was tangible and solid, and of one
               essence<note type="footnote" n="24" resp="#ebrooks">
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> with us, and was also <pb n="12"/> superior to
               corruption; and thereby he subverted the theory of phantasy. It belongs therefore to those who
               part the one Christ into two natures and dissolve the unity to say, "For each of the natures
               preserves its property unimpaired". But those who believe that, after God the Word had been
               hypostatically united to flesh that possessed an intelligent soul, he performed all his own acts
               in it, and changed it not into his nature (far be it!), but into his glory and operation, no
               longer seek the things that manifestly belong to the flesh without diminution, to which flesh
               the things that manifestly belong by nature to the Godhead have come to belong by reason of the
               union. But, if they senselessly divide it from God the Word by speaking of two natures after the
               union, it then walks in its own ways following its nature, and preserves its properties
               undiminished on the principle of the impious men. But these things are not so (how could they
               be?), but indeed very different: for union rejects division, as the holy Cyril said: "For,
               though it is said that he hungered and thirsted, and slept and grew weary after a journey, and
               wept and feared, these things did not happen to him just as they do to us in accordance with
               compulsory ordinances of nature; but he <pb n="13"/> himself voluntarily permitted his flesh to
               walk according to the laws of nature, for he sometimes allowed it even to undergo its own
               passions"<note type="footnote" n="25" resp="#ebrooks">I cannot find the source of this
                  citation.</note>. For from Cyril's words, as from a sacred anchor, I do not depart. And the
               same statement is made by Gregory the Theologian<note type="footnote" n="26" resp="#ebrooks"
                  ><foreign xml:lang="grc">Θεολόγος</foreign>.</note> of Nazianzus also in the sermon on
               baptism: "For he is purity itself, and did not need purification; but he is purified for you;
               just as for you he put on a garb of flesh, while he is fleshless: and he would have run no
               danger at all from putting off baptism; for he himself was a warden of passion to himself"<note
                  type="footnote" n="27" resp="#ebrooks">Or. XL, 29.</note>. Accordingly then<note
                     type="footnote" n="28" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄρα</foreign>.</note> he was a
               warden to himself of hungering as well as of being tired after a journey, and of accepting the
               other human passions, such as do not fall under sin, in order to display the Humanization truly
               and without phantasy<note type="footnote" n="29"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >φαντασία</foreign>.</note>. Of what we have said this is the sum; that we must anathematize
               those who divide the one Christ: and they divide him by speaking of two natures after the union,
               and consequently apportioning the operations and properties between the natures. Accordingly
               good doctrine is contained in the<note type="footnote" n="30" resp="#ebrooks">I do not know what
                  is hidden under <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܢܛܘܣ</foreign>: possibly it is a corruption of
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">τύπος</foreign>, since the only theological edict of Anastasius known
                  is the <foreign xml:lang="grc">τύπος</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="grc">πληροφορία</foreign>
                  of Select Letters of Severus, p. 3. The word however rather suggests <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                     >προσφωνητικός</foreign>.</note> ---- of the serene king: for it anathematizes those who
               divide the one Son who was <pb n="14"/> hypostatically united to flesh into two natures, and the
               operations and properties of the same two natures: for thus also says the impious Theodoret:
               "How does he range under impiety those who divide the properties of the natures of God who is
               before the ages and of the man who was assumed in the last days?"<note type="footnote" n="31"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Cyr., ed. Pusey, VI, p. 410.</note> I have written these things though I am
               poor in intellect and praise the greatness of your God-loving understanding; and because, as you
               are wise, I give you an opportunity to attain wiser results. Forgive me that on account of the
               lack of leisure caused by the present struggles I have been late in writing. Greet your honoured
               consort, who is a partner and a helper in the affairs of God.</p>
            <trailer resp="#compiler">The end of the first letter to Oecumenius the count.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
