<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3172">To the Emesenes</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Letters I to LXI</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m"> A Collection of Letters of <persName
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName> , from
                     Numerous Syriac Manuscripts </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">222 [50]-248 [76]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">12</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="25">
   <head type="number">XXV</head>
   <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE HOLY SEVERUS, THE LETTER THAT WAS WRITTEN BY HIM TO THE
    EMESENES. </head>
   <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
    <date notBefore="0512" notAfter="0518">512-8</date>
   </dateline>
   <p>To the devout presbyters and orthodox<note type="footnote" n="117" resp="#ebrooks">
     <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὀρθόδοξοι</foreign>.</note> deacons, and to the rest who compose the
    holy order<note type="footnote" n="118" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
     >τάγμα</foreign>.</note> of the clergy<note type="footnote" n="119" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">χλῆρος</foreign>.</note>, and to the magnificent and Christ-loving magistrates
    of the city, and to all the people of the holy church, Severus greeting in our Lord.</p>
   <p>To those who are not wise in their mind or are otherwise without intelligence, and are lacking
    in true instruction, the holy Scripture gives the proper rule and place, in order that their
    emptiness of mind and lack of instruction may be turned to wisdom: for indeed it commands those
    who are such both to learn and to ask, or to be silent altogether; for the holy book <pb n="51"
    /> of Proverbs somewhere said: "To the fool who asketh wisdom shall be reckoned: but, when a man
    maketh himself silent, he is thought to be wise"<note type="footnote" n="120" resp="#ebrooks">
     Prov., xvii, 28.</note>. But the man who keeps this rule it raises and advances, and incites to
    learn things that are of use and profit, and it says, "Give thine heart to wisdom, and prepare
    thine ears for words of understanding"<note type="footnote" n="121" resp="#ebrooks">Prov. xxiii,
     12.</note>. I am surprised therefore that the brother whom you mention (out of tenderness for
    his soul I do not mention his name) did not know his own measure, and, besides not knowing
    originally the subject on which he was talking, neglected this legally established and salutary
    rule; and, when he ought to have bent a ear of understanding to those who are wiser than he is,
    he on the contrary threatened to take the ignorance that is in him to the city of Alexandria,
    like an invincible warrior, who is able to overcome and take captive all that meet him, and sell
    them where he likes. Therefore I have both accepted your wisdom in the Lord, which is worthy of
    the church and very honourable, and your patience, which is such as befits Christians, and have
    crowned them also with a decree of many praises, since in accordance with the apostolic model
    you both received and admonished him as your member and brother<note type="footnote" n="122"
     resp="#ebrooks">2 Thess. iii, 15.</note>, and brought forward the teachings of the holy
    fathers. And, <pb n="52"/> whereas you once and twice secretly and openly refuted and corrected
    him on the points on which he spoke without knowledge, and he was again involved in the same
    errors, and you behaved like doctors and churchmen, and on all sides seek to gain his salvation,
    and by actual deeds show that you look to the apostolic commandment which commands, "Let
    everything be done decently and in order"<note type="footnote" n="123" resp="#ebrooks">1 Cor.
     xiv, 40.</note>, but he, though he was thought worthy to receive so much attention, had no
    mercy on his soul, and did not restrain himself so as to show moderation and humility, I
    expressed blame and at the same time showed mercy and still show mercy, since ignorance is free
    from danger<note type="footnote" n="124"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κίνδυνος</foreign>.</note>, for
    a man is not blamed because he does not know. He is trying to bring upon himself the sin that
    does not deserve forgiveness, in that he does not yield to those who are wise among the
    brethren, or seek from wiser men a cure for his ignorance by desire to learn, but pettily
    searches into things that are unknown and uncertain, and does his best to find men to share his
    opinions, in order that he may seem to be saying something when he is saying nothing that is
    sound. But the other things which he said without <pb n="53"/> knowledge he has with difficulty
    come to honour by silence, in that he assented to the passages from the holy fathers (that were
    brought before him; and he was reduced to one passage, the words used by the holy Cyril in the
    second volume<note type="footnote" n="125" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >τόμος</foreign>.</note> against the blasphemies of Nestorius, which are as follows: "For,
    because the Word who is from God the Father took flesh and came forth as a man like us, he would
    not for this reason be also termed a double thing. For he is one, and not without flesh, who in
    his own nature is without flesh and blood"<note type="footnote" n="126" resp="#ebrooks">Adv.
     Nest., ii, 6 (ed. Pusey, VI, p. 112).</note>. After you had quoted to him the<note
     type="footnote" n="127" resp="#ebrooks"> (C) 'You said that from the very'.</note> words used
    by the doctor, he persisted and said<note type="footnote" n="128" resp="#ebrooks"> (C) 'contends
     and says'. </note> that after his own Resurrection<note type="footnote" n="129" resp="#ebrooks"
     > (C) 'the Incarnation'.</note> we must confess that God the Word is without flesh<note
     type="footnote" n="130" resp="#ebrooks"> (C) ins. 'and blood'.</note>, inasmuch as he put off
    that which was without variation and without<note type="footnote" n="131" resp="#ebrooks">In
     another version (C) om.</note> separation hypostatically united to him, a thing that is beyond
    all impiety and profanity, so that <pb n="54"/> everyone who has natural (I will not say,
    spiritual) intelligence must wonder if a fact which is so universally admitted has ever been
    made a subject of contention, and has<note type="footnote" n="132" resp="#ebrooks">Sic.</note>
    passed the lips of anyone who has duly believed in our one Lord and God and Saviour<note
     type="footnote" n="133" resp="#ebrooks"> (C) om.</note> Jesus Christ. If he were skilled in
    divine doctrine, he should have (to omit everything else) considered the anathemas of Gregory
    the Theologian, who in the great letter to Cledonius which begins, 'I wonder what this
    innovation is', clearly lays down these principles in it, "If anyone says that the flesh<note
     type="footnote" n="134" resp="#ebrooks">Sev. therefore did not read <foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >ἁγίαν</foreign>: see Migne, n. 40.</note> was now laid down by him, and the Godhead is
    stripped of a body, and does not confess that he both is and will come with the thing assumed
    itself, may he not see the glory of his coming. For where is the body now except with him who
    assumed it? For it has not been laid up in the sun, as the silly tale of the Manichees goes, in
    order that he may be honoured through the object of contempt, or diffused and dissolved in the
    air, like the nature of a voice and the wafting of a smell, and the course of lightning that
    does not stand still. But what becomes of the fact that he was actually touched after the
    Resurrection, or that he will again some time <pb n="55"/> be seen by those who pierced him? For
    the Godhead by itself is invisible. But he will come with the body, according to my account, and
    such as he was seen by, or was shown to, the disciples on the mount, inasmuch as the Godhead
    easily overcomes the flesh"<note type="footnote" n="135" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. 101 (P. G., XXXVII,
     181).</note>. Who.that reads these words resplendent with truth, and flashing with the rays of
    the Holy Spirit, will dare to say that the Word of God, who was humanized immutably and without
    any phantasy<note type="footnote" n="136" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >φαντασία</foreign>.</note>, is without flesh after the inexplicable and incomprehensible
    union? Accordingly it is clear that you also have not gone beyond what is fitting in opposing
    the precipitous error of that man and saying in order to remove him from this error, "The words
    used by the doctor about the Word of God, In his own nature he is without flesh and blood',
    refer to the time before the Humanization". Indeed, since he himself said that 'he is one, and
    not without flesh', how can it be anything but wholly unreasonable, and presumptuous and
    irreverent, for us to gainsay this, and contend that he is without <pb n="56"/> flesh? But the
    words which he went on to add, 'who in his own nature is without flesh and blood', plainly
    introduce this thought, that in his own nature, that is in the Godhead, he has no association
    with flesh and blood. He did not take the flesh into the fulness of his own divine nature and
    mix it with it, nor did he mingle it with his own Godhead, but that in the dispensatory
    assumption we might understand him to be not without flesh, Emmanuel being wonderfully composed
    and consisting of two elements, the Godhead and the manhood: but even so he preserved the
    absence, of mixture in the divine essence<note type="footnote" n="1" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note>, and did not change the essence<note type="footnote"
     n="137" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> of the Godhead into the
    nature of flesh. And that this is so I bring as a witness to the accuracy of his doctrines the
    doctor himself, who by the operation of the Holy Spirit is an accurate doctor. In the first
    letter to Succensus, when certain men had advanced a similar objection, he expressed himself
    thus: "Since I found in <pb n="57"/> the memorial an assertion of this kind stated, that since
    the Resurrection the holy body of Christ the Saviour of us all has passed into the nature of the
    Godhead, so as to be all Godhead only, I thought it right to speak against this also". And
    thereupon, after he has above in a brief compass gone through all the statement of the
    dispensation of the Humanization, he brings against it this argument: "It is impossible for a
    body taken from earth to endure the change into the divine nature. And, if not, we bring against
    the Godhead the charge that it is as a thing that is made and as a thing that has taken into it
    something that is not its by nature"<note type="footnote" n="138" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. 45 (P. G.,
     LXXVII, 233, 236).</note>. See! how plainly he denies that the divinity of the Word has taken
    anything into its essence<note type="footnote" n="139" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >οὐσία</foreign>.</note> which is not its by nature, though we confess that flesh possessing
    an intelligent soul was taken by God the Word, and he united this to him hypostatically, but not
    so that anything should be added to his divine essence<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"
      ><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note>, as if it were deficient (for he is truly
    complete in everything), but that from the unmixed union of the Incarnation, and the composition
    out of two elements, the Godhead <pb n="58"/> and the manhood, Emmanuel should be made up, who
    in one hypostasis is ineffably composite; not simple, but composite: as the soul of a man like
    us, which by nature is bodiless and rational, which is naturally intertwined with the body,
    remains in its suprasensual and bodiless nature, but by reason of the composition with the body
    makes up one composite animal, man. Accordingly the assumption of the body makes no addition to
    the essence<note type="footnote" n="140" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
     >οὐσία</foreign>.</note> of the soul, but makes up the composite animal, as it is reasonable to
    understand with regard to the theory<note type="footnote" n="141" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">θεωρία</foreign>.</note> of Emmanuel also. The Word did not take the flesh
    intelligently possessed of a soul in order to complete his being God, as we have said, but that
    one hypostasis might be wonderfully and immutably made up out of two elements, the Godhead we
    mean and the manhood, and the one incarnate nature of the Word himself, and one person: for the
    Word of God, according to the saying of Paul the apostle, partook of blood and flesh after our
     pattern<note type="footnote" n="142">Hebr., 11, 14.</note>. And that this is so the approved
    Cyril further shows in the letter to Valerian bishop of Iconium; who wrote as follows: "For God
    and man did not come together, as they say, and make up <pb n="59"/> one Christ; but, as I have
    already said, the Word, being God, partook of blood and flesh like us, in order that he may be
    known to be God who was humanized, and who took our flesh, and made this his, because, as the
    man who was composed of soul and body is known to be one, so also now<note type="footnote"
     n="143" resp="#ebrooks">Cyr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">αὑτός</foreign>.</note> he is acknowledged
    to be one Son and Lord. For one nature and hypostasis of a man is acknowledged, though he is
    known to be made of diverse and heterogeneous elements: for the body is truly different in
    nature from the soul; but it belongs to it, and with it makes up the hypostasis of the one man.
    And in mental conception and in theory the difference of the things that have been named is not
    obscure, but by combination and concurrence that cannot be cut asunder one animal, man, is made
    up. The Word therefore, the Only one of God, did not come forth as man by taking a man, but,
    though his birth from the Father is ineffable, he became man by forming a man<note
     type="footnote" n="144" resp="#ebrooks">Cyr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ναόν</foreign>.</note> for
    himself through the Holy Spirit which is of one essence with him. Accordingly he is known to be
    one, though in the theory which is according to reason his own body is different in nature from
    himself. Let it therefore be everywhere acknowledged that he was not without soul, but that he
    was possessed of an intelligent soul"<note type="footnote" n="145" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. 50 (P.
     G., LXXVII, 257).</note>. Similarly also in the second volume<note type="footnote" n="146"
      ><foreign xml:lang="grc">τόμος</foreign>.</note>
    <pb n="60"/> against the blasphemies of Nestorius he clearly teaches that the assumption of
    flesh did not pass into the Godhead of the Word, but that the Word of God remained in his own
    nature, and apart from flesh, but by the immutable combination with flesh it was wisely and
    beyond all reason and understanding brought about that one Christ should be marvellously made
    up; for he speaks thus: "Accordingly confess one, not dividing the natures, while you know and
    understand that to flesh belongs one principle, and to Godhead that which befits it only. For we
    do not say that the flesh of the Word became Godhead, but rather that it is divine as being his.
    For, as the flesh of a man is called his, on what ground is it not right for us also to call
    that of the Word divine?" And again farther on: "If therefore he were a wise and intelligent man
    at all, he should say that the body is from a woman, but confess besides that by being combined
    in hypostatic union with the Word it has made up one Christ and one Son, and one Lord, who being
    the same is God and man"<note type="footnote" n="147" resp="#ebrooks">Adv. Nest., ii, 8, 13 (ed.
     Pusey, VI, p. 120, 130). </note>. The expressions therefore that are used by this genuine and
    very accurate father, 'for he is one, and not without flesh', and, 'he who in his own nature is
    apart from flesh and blood', demonstrate <pb n="61"/> this, as is plain from what we have
    demonstrated, that in the dispensatory conjunction he is not without flesh: for he is one
    composed of two elements, the Godhead and the manhood, which have a perfect existence in their
    own sphere; but in his own nature he is known to be apart from flesh and blood, and without a
    body; not that he mingled flesh with the nature or with the essence<note type="footnote" n="148"
     resp="#ebrooks"> </note> of the Godhead, but that he kept the Godhead sublime and pure and
    unmixed, in the characteristics of its own incorporeal character, as also he did not change the
    manhood which was hypostatically united to him, but kept it free and without change in its own
    characteristics. Wherefore also one may see that Nestorius and those who like Jews hold his
    opinions wish to reject the absence of change of the hypostatic union, and to put confusion into
    the minds of the believers, while they are everywhere making this charge, that we confess that
    the body was changed into the divine essence<note type="footnote" n="1" resp="#ebrooks">
     <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note>, and thereby hold one incarnate nature of God
    the Word, and they say that they themselves only, the wretched, unhappy men, keep the Godhead of
    the holy Trinity unmixed and pure, by confessing that the man from Mary, as they themselves say,
    in loving mercy was conjoined to <pb n="62"/> God the Word and shares with him in sonship and
    divine authority, and by this self-created scruple<note type="footnote" n="149" resp="#ebrooks"
     >This represents <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐθελοθρησκεία</foreign> (Col., ii, 23).</note> they
    make the Trinity a quaternity. And for this reason the wise Cyril shows Nestorius also, who was
    their leader in this fatuity, speaking thus: "Therefore God the Word is named Christ also,
    because he has the eternal conjunction with Christ, and God the Word cannot do anything without
    the manhood: for he knows the coalescence exactly<note type="footnote" n="150" resp="#ebrooks"
     >Cyr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀπηκρίβωται γάρ εἰς ἄκραν συνάφειαν</foreign>.</note>, not with
    the Godhead, as the new wise men amoug the doctors say"<note type="footnote" n="151"
     resp="#ebrooks">Ibid., 7 (ed. Pusey, VI," p. 116).</note>. And the same man of small intellect
    weaves the same charge, and in the treatise entitled 'Against the Theopaschites or Cyrillians',
    which he composed in the form of question and answer, speaks thus: "The Theopaschite says: 'And
    how can we be accused of the composition of the Diphysites, we who call Christ one incarnate
    nature of God?'</p>
   <p>The orthodox<note type="footnote" n="152" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >ὀρθόδοξος</foreign>.</note> says: 'Your own refutation, which you think is a defence, itself
    refutes. For you have confessed that one nature is prepared for Christ, from incorporeality and
    a body, and a hypostasis with one nature <pb n="63"/> of the incarnation of the Godhead. But
    this is the confusion of those who have two natures, that the natures themselves are deprived of
    the hypostases which they severally possess, that are confounded with one another'"<note
     type="footnote" n="153" resp="#ebrooks"> Kampffmeyer, ap. Loofs, Nestoriana, p. 369, from Add.
     17210 f. 57 r° (another version). Our ms. was unknown to Kampffmeyer.</note>.</p>
   <p>And again farther on in the same treatise:</p>
   <p>"The Theopaschite says: 'What do you think of an eggshell (?) of water that has been poured
    into the sea?' The orthodox<note type="footnote" n="154"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >ὀρθόδοξος</foreign>.</note> says: 'What else except that the unstable addition of the water
    has disappeared in the great volume of the sea?'</p>
   <p>The Theopaschite says: 'Something similar happened also to the flesh: for do not think that
    the Godhead is smaller than the sea in relation to the flesh as compared with the shifting
    character of the eggshell'.</p>
   <p>The orthodox<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
     >ὀρθόδοξος</foreign>.</note> says: 'By "shifting character" do you mean a kind of instability,
    or the change of that which was swallowed up into that which swallowed it up?'</p>
   <p>The Theopaschite says: 'The change of the essence<note type="footnote" n="155" resp="#ebrooks"
      ><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> of the body into the Godhead'.</p>
   <p>The orthodox<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
     >ὀρθόδοξος</foreign>.</note> says: 'The nature of the body remaining, or being dissolved into
    non-existence?' <pb n="64"/>
   </p>
   <p>The Theopaschite says: 'The flesh passing into the nature of the Godhead instead of the
     essence<note type="footnote" n="156" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
     >οὐσία</foreign>.</note> of flesh'"<note type="footnote" n="157" resp="#ebrooks">Not otherwise
     known.</note>.</p>
   <p>While very vainly putting together such reasons against the right confession of the
    Humanization, as I said before, reasons which contend against God, and saying that a man should
    be worshipped with the Trinity, Nestorius and those who think with him state of themselves that
    they preserve the unity of nature of the three hypostases unmixed, in that they do not confess
    that God the Word was hypostatically united to flesh possessing an intelligent soul, and call
    the union that is so far above nature and immutable and wonderful mingling. Wherefore also
    Dorotheus, who became bishop of Marcianopolis<note type="footnote" n="158" resp="#ebrooks">
     Zach. Rh., iii, 1; P. O., VIII, 83 L; G. B. M., p. 553, 927, 956, 967; Le Quien, I,
     1218.</note>, and belonged to the same Jewish company and party, presented a petition to
    Marcian's own self at the very beginning of his reign, and found fault with the position<note
     type="footnote" n="159" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κατάστασις</foreign>.</note>
    held by the bishops, and the sound opinion of the holy churches; and he speaks thus: "Therefore,
    merciful kings, in consideration of their so ridiculous, that is lamentable, opinions, renew the
    firm maintenance of the connaturality while it is possible, while there is time, by recalling
    Nestorius from exile<note type="footnote" n="160" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >ἐξορία</foreign>.</note>, and join together the people of Christ who are divided, lest, <pb
     n="65"/> as I pray may not happen, the past be repeated"<note type="footnote" n="161"
     resp="#ebrooks">Not otherwise known. Citations from the letter are found in G 53 ro b and L 24
     ro b.</note>. The holy Cyril therefore, having exposed such old people's fables and Jewish
     tales<note type="footnote" n="162" resp="#ebrooks">1 Tim. iv, 7; Tit., i, 14.</note> in every
    part of his writings, in the first letter to Succensus also, which I mentioned above, said thus:
    "But it is impossible for a body taken from earth to endure the change into the divine nature;
    for it cannot be done. And, if not, we speak of the Godhead as a thing that is made, and as a
    thing that has taken into it something that is not its by nature. For on the score of
    impropriety it is equal for us to say that the body was changed into the nature of Godhead, and
    also the other thing too that the Word was changed into the nature of flesh. For, as this is
    impossible (for he is invariable and immutable), so also is the other. For it is not among
    possibilities that any created thing can pass into the essence or nature of Godhead. But the
    body too is a created thing. Accordingly we say that Christ's body is divine, because it is also
    God's body, and resplendent with ineffable glory, incorruptible, holy, life-giving: but, that it
    was changed into the nature <pb n="66"/> of Godhead, none of the holy fathers has either thought
    or said, nor do we ourselves so hold"<note type="footnote" n="163" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. 45 (P.
     G., LXXVII, 23(5).</note>. This fact therefore according to the expression of the doctor, that
    the body of the Word is resplendent with ineffable glory, incorruptible and holy and
    life-giving, Gregory the Theologian also in the demonstration contained in the letter to
    Gledonius demonstrated by saying that the Godhead overcame the incarnation<note type="footnote"
     n="164" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. 101 (P. G,.. XXXVII, 181).</note>. Accordingly the flesh remained
    flesh, even after the God-befitting Resurrection and Ascension, but adorned with divine and
    ineffable glory, and with all the excellencies that befit God; and it is divine as something
    that is the body of God, and it was not changed into the essence<note type="footnote" n="165"
     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> of the Godhead. It is in this
    meaning that the expression of the doctor with which we are now concerned also should rightly be
    understood that God the Word is one and not without flesh: for he is incarnate by hypostatic
    union in flesh possessing an intelligent soul (but in his own nature he is without flesh and
    blood), that is, without mixture <pb n="67"/> with what he possesses in his essence<note
     type="footnote" n="166" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> and
    nature, that is the bodiless and immutable and incomprehensible Godhead.</p>
   <p>As for what you say at the end that the man who easily follows illusions (?) <note
     type="footnote" n="167" resp="#ebrooks">The best emendation of an impossible text that I can
     make. </note> and shifts his ground widely said on the advice of certain persons, that we must
    think of the Word of God in the infinity of his divine essence<note type="footnote" n="166"
     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> without flesh, is very foolish
    and senseless. Even though the Word of God is infinite, the whole of him was united to the flesh
    that was received from the holy Virgin, the God-bearer and ever-virgin Mary, even the very
    person of the Word and not a partial operation as in the prophets. How then is it anything but
    ridiculous for us to say that he who was in the actual divine hypostasis wholly united to a body
    naturally as well as miraculously is without flesh, even in the greatness of his infinite
     Godhead<note type="footnote" n="168" resp="#ebrooks"> (C) 'infinity'.</note>? For 'there is no
    limit to his greatness'<note type="footnote" n="169" resp="#ebrooks">Ps. CXLIV, 3.</note>, as
    David said, and he fills everything, and is above everything, and cannot be comprised by anyone.
    And the subtlety of <pb n="68"/> the mystery cannot be explored by reason and intellect, how the
    whole of him was in flesh, and the whole of him is in all things and the whole of him is
    superior to all things and he himself is Ruler of all in infinity. But, that we believe that the
    very hypostasis of God the Word became incarnate, according to the apostolic tradition of the
    church that has been handed down from of old, it is superfluous for us to demonstrate by
    testimonies to those who have once believed in the Gospel, when John who was divine in words
    beyond the evangelists said, "The Word became flesh and came to dwell in us"<note
     type="footnote" n="170" resp="#ebrooks">John I, 14.</note>. How ever, since there is a doubt
    about it, and in order that we may close the doors against all contention, on this point too let
    the words of the father himself, I mean the holy Cyril, come to our assistance, who in the
    defence of the second chapter<note type="footnote" n="171" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">κεφάλαιον</foreign>.</note> addressed to Theodoret the deceiver wrote thus:
    "Since Nestorius therefore everywhere eliminates the birth in flesh, and introduces among us a
    union of authority only, and says that a man was conjoined to God, who is honoured by identity
    of name of sonship, in contending against his propositions we were compelled to say that the
    hypostatic union took place, in which expression <pb n="69"/> the word 'hypostatic' denotes
    nothing else except this only, that the nature itself or his hypostasis, which is the Word
    himself, after it has been united to human nature without variation and confusion, as we have
    often said, is recognised as one Christ [and] is so, the same God and man"<note type="footnote"
     n="172" resp="#ebrooks"> Cyr., ed. Pusey, VI, p. 404.</note>. After the same fashion in the
    Scholia also he comes forward with the same words as follows: "'For in him dwelt all the fulness
    of the Godhead bodily', that is not by assumption simply<note type="footnote" n="173"
     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἁπλῶς</foreign>.</note>, like light that shines, or
    fire that imparts its heat [to] the objects near it, but, if we may so say, that the divine and
    incontaminable nature itself by a true union as I have said made the temple from the Virgin a
    dwelling-place for that which he is recognised to be. For thus Christ Jesus is recognised to be
     one"<note type="footnote" n="174" resp="#ebrooks">Schol. de Inc. Unig., 27 (ed. Pusey, VI, p.
     550); in Latin only.</note>. But, that the whole of him was in a body, and was hypostatically
    united to it, him of whom all things were divinely full, he himself confirms by his own words.
    For it is written in the Gospel of John also that he said to Nicodemus, "No man hath gone up to
    heaven, except him who came down from heaven, the Son of man who is in heaven"<note
     type="footnote" n="175" resp="#ebrooks">John iii, 13.</note>; though he did not come down from
    heaven in that he became man, for he did not bring the flesh down from <pb n="70"/> heaven, but
    he received it from the holy Virgin, flesh that is of our race, and of our nature. Nor again,
    when he was speaking to Nicodemus, was he corporeally in heaven; but incorporeally, in that he
    is God, heaven and earth and what is above heaven were perpetually full of him. And in the
    eighth section of the second of the books against<note type="footnote" n="176" resp="#ebrooks"
     >The Syriac is corrupt and the emendation doubtful.</note> Julian the great in demon-worship,
    which were written by him in defence of the Christian religion, the doctor shows how the Word of
    God, while he is all in all, was hypostatic ally united to the flesh derived from the holy Mary,
    and, beyond every creature, filled all things by reception from him (in a suprasensual sense
    nothing is empty of him), though the infinity of his greatness surpasses and soars above all
    things that exist with a great space between (how great it is impossible to say): by whom
    according to the words of Isaiah "all the nations have been reckoned as a drop from a pot, and
    as the sand of a balance"<note type="footnote" n="177" resp="#ebrooks">Is. XL, 15. </note>. But
    the holy Cyril again speaks thus: "He has become, as I said, in the likeness of men, as it is
    written, and in our human appearance truly. Nevertheless we did not say that he who cannot be
    comprised was <pb n="71"/> confined, nor that he was inclosed in the limits of the body. For it
    is utterly silly and complete folly to say anything of the kind of him who is by nature and in
    truth God. For, while he is one and the only Son, and completely above all human phantasy, the
    whole of him is in virtue of a gift in every man, and in each [one] by presence, not being
    divided nor cleft asunder, but [above] everything by nature, and in everything as God. 'But in
    that all-pure and holy body 'all the fulness of the Godhead bodily has come to dwell', as it is
    written. And he was as in his own flesh, but still even so he filled all things from him"<note
     type="footnote" n="178" resp="#ebrooks">P. G., LXXVI, 940.</note>. And in the treatise
    addressed to the queens the opening words of which are, Those who administer the divine and
    heavenly preaching', he explains the meaning of the statement that the Word of God and all the
    fulness of the Godhead came to dwell in flesh as written by Paul in this way: "But we believe
    that the Word became flesh, not by way of removal or change, but rather that he came to dwell in
    us, and, to speak correctly, made the body that was in truth united <pb n="72"/> to him,
    possessing an intelligent soul, his own temple. And the divine Paul, declaring the indwelling of
    the Word in the holy flesh, or the true union, said that in him all the fulness of the Godhead
    came to dwell, not so much by way of assumption or presence, or by way of a gift of grace, but
    bodily, that is in essence; as in the case of a man also it is said [that] his spirit dwells in
    him, though it is not something different from him"<note type="footnote" n="179" resp="#ebrooks"
     >Ad regin., 14 (ed. Pusey, VII, p. 285).</note>. How then shall we say [that] he who is wholly
    in everything by way of gift, and in each man in presence (for he receives all things from him
    and they depend upon his presence), and who further also is in everything and is nowhere cleft
    asunder or divided, and further is wholly in the all-holy flesh in essence, and so is united to
    it, after the fashion in which the soul of a man like us is united to its own body, how shall we
    say that he is without his own flesh, because he filled all these things with the gift of
    himself, he who is infinite, and is wholly in everything? But to inquire into such a marvellous
    subject is a piece of utter foolishness: for glorious things are sealed by faith only. In the
    other treatise addressed to the religious virgin queens, Arcadia and Marina, which begins, 'The
    world's boast', the same wise Cyril <pb n="73"/> inserted a demonstration from the holy John who
    became bishop of Constantinople, who spoke about the God-bearer Mary, and about the birth of God
    the Word, as follows: "'And instead of a sun she contained without confining the Sun of
    righteousness. And do not ask how: for, where God wills, the order of nature is defeated. For he
    willed, he was able, he came down, and he saved. All things run into one for God. To-day he who
    is is born, and he who is became that which he was not. For, being God, he became man, not by
    departing from being God; for he did not became man by departure from Godhead, nor did he become
    God by growth from man: but, being the Word, he became flesh on account of suffering<note
     type="footnote" n="180" resp="#ebrooks">Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">διὰ τὸ
     ἀπαθές</foreign>.</note>, while he remained invariable in his nature'. And he adds to these
    things: 'He who sits upon a lofty and high throne is laid in a manger. He who is intangible and
    simple and bodiless is grasped by human hands. He who cuts asunder the bonds of sin is wrapped
    in swaddling-clothes'"<note type="footnote" n="181" resp="#ebrooks">Jo. Chrys. ed. Par. 2a, VI,
     459; Cyr., ed. Pusey, VII, p. 165.</note>. And the saintly Proclus who became bishop of the
    same city in the exposition which he delivered in the church of Anthimus on the feast of the
    Resurrection spoke to the same effect as follows: "The heaven <pb n="74"/> cries, 'He who became
    man, who was crucified in flesh, is God: for as God he caused me to incline and came down'. The
    sun also cries, 'He who was crucified in flesh is my Lord: for I in fear of the light of the
    Godhead held-back my rays'. The earth also cries, 'He who clothed himself in a body, who was
    crucified in flesh, is the Maker: for, though I embraced his flesh in a manger, yet I did not
    confine the might of his Godhead'"<note type="footnote" n="182" resp="#ebrooks">Or. xiii. 4 (P.
     G., LXV, 793).</note>. It would have been possible to add other things also which are like
    these and resemble them, but it is superfluous to add to what has been so wisely said, and make
    the discussion inordinately long. But I pray your holy assembly and lawful church to be of the
    same mind, as the apostle said<note type="footnote" n="183" resp="#ebrooks">2 Cor. xiii,
     11.</note>, and conform to the same rule<note type="footnote" n="184" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">κανών</foreign>.</note>, and, if any disputed point arises, not make this a
    cause of strife and division, and of useless contentions, but lovingly join with one another in
    the inquiry. But, if any of you has anything to say, let him speak with humble mind, as the
    words of God, as Peter the 'chosen apostle gave admonition<note type="footnote" n="185"
     resp="#ebrooks">1 Pet. iv, 11.</note>. If anything also needs further explanation, you must not
    act hastily, nor be in a hurry, but await the proper time, and bring it before the saintly
    bishops, and accept the healing that they shall apply. As for <pb n="75"/> the brother who gave
    occasion for this dispute, since we have written these few words, receive him lovingly, and
    strengthen him, and acknowledge him as your member. And, whether he is one man, or many who were
    associated with him in this dispute or ignorance, act in the same way towards them: for
    concerning those who are such the apostle commands us and says, at one time, "Him that is weak
    in the faith bring near to you"<note type="footnote" n="186" resp="#ebrooks">Rom. xiv,
    1.</note>, and at another, "And reckon them not as enemies, but admonish them as brothers"<note
     type="footnote" n="187" resp="#ebrooks">2 Thess. iii, 5.</note>. It is not because they made
    inquiries, or because they were ignorant that they are blameworthy; on the contrary they would
    actually have been praised, if they had discussed the point with humility, and not with haste
    and confusion, and with a desire to add to ignorance; for this is what prevented them from being
    received in regard to the discussion which they raised. However, now that we have written so
    much, let love vanquish everything, and let not these distressing matters come even into
    remembrance: for 'love' also, as it is written, 'covers a multitude of sins'<note
     type="footnote" n="188" resp="#ebrooks">1 Pet. iv, 8.</note>; which love may the God of love
    and the lawgiver Christ also strengthen in you. <pb n="76"/>
   </p>
   <p>The signature. May you be made perfect in the Lord, being sound, and living in the Spirit, and
    remembering me, our religious and Christ-loving brothers.</p>
   <p>The end.</p>
  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
