<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3180">To the Monks of the East</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Letters I to LXI</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m"> A Collection of Letters of <persName
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName> , from
                     Numerous Syriac Manuscripts </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">279 [107]-291 [119]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">12</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="35">
            <pb n="107"/>
            <head type="number">XXXV</head>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE PATRIARCH SEVERUS TO THE MONKS OF THE EAST<note
               type="footnote" n="280" resp="#ebrooks">This letter is prefixed to the correspondence with
               Julian of Halicarnassus in the Roman mss., but is absent in Add. 17000, which contains that
               correspondence. It was clearly written at the time of the expulsion of the monks (Land, Anecd.
               Syr., II, 289; Zach. Rh., viii, 5).</note>. </head>
            <note type="date" resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0520" notAfter="0525">520-5</date>
            </note>
            <p>To the holy fathers and archimandrites of the holy cloisters in the East and the presbyters
               and deacons, and all the brothers who are practising the God-loved life of monasticism Severus
               greeting in our Lord.</p>
            <p>I have heard that the great convents of the holy monasteries in the East, who are honoured for
               eminence in life and in asceticism and for age, have withdrawn, and that to this same thing they
               have been driven by compulsion, by those who without fear stretch out their hands against every
               man: and I groaned deeply; and I continued weeping till there was no strength left in me to weep
               more, as the Holy Scripture somewhere says<note type="footnote" n="281" resp="#ebrooks">1 Sam.
                  xxx, 4.</note>. For I sorrowed not for you (no tears are needed for you) but for the countries
               which have been deprived of you, and for those who live a religious life in them, and to speak
               generally for all that district<note type="footnote" n="282" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">χώρα</foreign>.</note>. If there were not universal wrath, and the face of God
               were not averted, you at least would <pb n="108"/> have remained, as pillars of the great house
               who would have prevented the ruin that was threatening it. So also, when Jerusalem was being
               chastised for her sins, and was being delivered to various chastisements, the God of mercy, 'he
               that taketh pleasure in mercy'<note type="footnote" n="283" resp="#ebrooks">Mich., vii,
                  18.</note> (for so the divine Scriptures term him), again spared her on account of his great
               mercifulness, and, because he did not wish to bring a complete destruction, is seen to address,
               those who administered such chastisements as were to come, things which Jeremiah saw and heard
               by prophetic perception, in this way: "Go up to her walls and pull down; but make not a full
               end. Leave her foundations because they are of the Lord"<note type="footnote" n="284"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Jer. v, 10.</note>. If then you, who are the foundations of the Lord which
               stave off destruction, have now been disturbed and shaken, what is there to expect, save sore
               stripes from God, and great evils that cannot be assuaged and wrath that is poured out, which he
               who in just judgment brings it declares in such words as these: "Behold! my wrath and mine anger
               is poured out upon this country and upon men and upon cattle and upon all things that are in the
               field, and upon all the fruits of the earth, and they shall be burnt up and shall not be
               extinguished"<note type="footnote" n="285" resp="#ebrooks">Id., vii, 20.</note>? </p>
            <pb n="109"/>
            <p>For these reasons I sorrowed, and I perceived not the number of my groans, while I
               contemplated the desolation of the ways that led to your convents and sent to you those who had
               a zealous desire to delight their souls by the remembrance of divine things, and to whom
               constant standing and angelic singing were a festival, and the upward-pressing life, which
               reminds rational souls of the imitation of God. For thus Jeremiah also made lament after the
               destruction of Jerusalem, and said as in a figure: "The ways of Zion mourn because there is none
               to come to the feast. All the gates in her are desolate"<note type="footnote" n="286"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Lam. i. 4.</note>. (And he himself clearly said that her produce is given to
               destruction). "Whose priests shall go into captivity groaning, and they that have taken upon
               them the virgin life shall be led away. And she that was abandoned by them hath bitterness for
               these things". For, in order that none might think that the lamentation that was made was not
               right, on account of beams and stones and great buildings that were razed to the earth and the
               dust, exalting plainly by words the greatness of the disaster, he made proclamation and said:
               "Her priests groan and her virgins <pb n="110"/> are carried away, and she herself within
               herself hath bitterness"<note type="footnote" n="287" resp="#ebrooks">Lam. i, 4.</note>. And
               Elisha the great, who received a double portion of the spirit that was in Elijah, the man of
               many visions and miracles, foreseeing that which was future like the present, and how many evils
               the people of Israel was to endure, inasmuch as Hazael, King of Syria, was to come against them
               to war, wept bitterly when he .considered the incurability of the evils that were coming, and
               under stress of these things he could not refrain, and abstain from tears, and from pity, though
               they were about to endure these chastisements as they deserved. And therefore also the divine
               Scripture says as in wonder: "And the man of God wept"<note type="footnote" n="288"
                  resp="#ebrooks">2 Kings viii, 11.</note>. But I beg and entreat your sanctities (for you are my
               affection no less than he<note type="footnote" n="289" resp="#ebrooks">Sic Syr.</note>), you who
               also suffer with your kindred, and, to speak in the words of the apostle, "have a heart of mercy
               and of grace"<note type="footnote" n="290" resp="#ebrooks">Col. iii, 12.</note>, pray for the
               sheep and avert the wrath, and cease not holding up your saintly hands to your Jesus, saying to
               him from the divine Scriptures, "These sheep what have they done? Have pity, Lord, upon thy
               people, and give not thine inheritance to shame"<note type="footnote" n="291" resp="#ebrooks">2
                  Sam. xxiv, 17; Joel, ii, 17.</note>. Perhaps he will be turned by these prayers and repent, and
               will leave in his country a blessing, <pb n="111"/> a sacrifice and a libation to the Lord our
               God. For on your account I have no weight of care and no anxiety: for well I know that
               everything is easy to you, and there is no impediment or difficulty of walking for your feet,
               which are adorned in apostolic fashion with bareness, and by their steps are able to bless even
               the uninhabited deserts and make them habitable; . and that the lack of money in your girdles is
               a fulness of all abundance, so that it provides a superfluity for others also, and the staff in
               your hands is a symbol of the very fixity and firmness of the faith that is in you, so that it
               supports those who are shaken also and they do not fall; but the earth and the heaven and the
               air<note type="footnote" n="292" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀήρ</foreign>.</note>
               are your purse, and all the elements supply food in diverse forms and coming of itself, and make
               it known to everyone that "man liveth not by bread alone, but also by every word that proceedeth
               out of the mouth of God"<note type="footnote" n="293" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. iv, 4.</note>: I
               forbear to say, what is a great thing and very true, that, since you have a spiritual rock going
               before you (and Paul said that Christ is a rock<note type="footnote" n="294" resp="#ebrooks">1
                  Cor. x, 4.</note>), that is to you food and drink; for you were persecuted with this same rock
               when it was persecuted. For in the case of the sons of Israel of old, who saw little, and had
               their eye blinded by Egyptian <pb n="112"/> darkness, and could scarcely see the writing of the
               law and could not contemplate the depth of hidden mysteries, the apostle justly wrote that "that
               rock followed them"<note type="footnote" n="295" resp="#ebrooks">1 Cor. x, 4.</note>: for it was
               right that they who were so-imperfect should be first exercised in the law, and afterwards see
               Christ following them. Wherefore also in waterless countries he gave them water in tangible
               form, assuaging the thirst of the flesh; and, whenever they desired flesh, he invisibly brought
               birds like rain from the air<note type="footnote" n="296" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">ἀήρ</foreign>.</note>, and other things like these and resembling them. But
               before your own perfections, who can contemplate the very glory of the Lord 'with open face', as
               again Paul said<note type="footnote" n="297" resp="#ebrooks">2 Cor. iii, 18.</note>, that rock
               continually goes in front, giving suprasensual food and drink, and showing everyone that through
               the things which you have endured you cry and say, "Who shall separate me from the love of
               Christ? Tribulation, or distress, or persecution, or hunger or nakedness or clanger or the
               sword, as it is written, 'For thy sake we die every day; we have been reckoned as sheep for
               slaughter'; but in all these things we are victorious through him who loved us"<note
                  type="footnote" n="298" resp="#ebrooks">Rom. viii, 35-37.</note>. For the results of your
               victory are not only <pb n="113"/> in this evil present world, in which you showed
               invincibility, but all of them are more truly in the future world. Then all who have been
               exercised in the life of virginity, and have prevailed over shameful passions and are honoured
               for white-haired old age of the intellect, and for the holy order, and deceive the accompanying
               honour, shall be gratified with such joy that their soul shall be made drunk with good things,
               as to which Jeremiah the prophet, depicting them beforehand, spoke thus: "Then shall virgins
               rejoice in gatherings of young men and old men shall rejoice: and I will turn their mourning
               into joy, and I will make them rejoice: and I will make great and make drunken the soul of the
               priests the sons of Levi, and my people shall be filled with my good things"<note
                  type="footnote" n="299" resp="#ebrooks">Jer. xxxviii, 13, 14.</note>; and these things that
               fail not and are as they are, and are never destroyed. Such as these are the blessed homes and
               mansions. But, if there is yet an extension and we have not been brought to the end of time,
               assuredly 'he who scattered Israel he will gather him, and he will keep him as a shepherd who
               feedeth his flock' and will say, "With weeping went they out, and with consolation will I bring
               them: and I will make them to dwell by streams of waters in a right way and they shall not again
               go astray"<note type="footnote" n="300" resp="#ebrooks">Ibid., 9, 10.</note>. </p>
            <pb n="114"/>
            <p>But pray that we also may hold to the right and unerring way, and our foot may not turn aside
               to the right hand or to the left from the king's highway<note type="footnote" n="301"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Num. xx, 17.</note> which was rightly traversed by those seers and ministers of
               the word. For, inasmuch as you exercise yourselves in the law of the Lord by night as well as by
               day, you know well that, even if a man contend, he is not crowned unless he contends lawfully.
               For certain men have come in upon us, wishing to put a blemish on the 'good confession' to which
               we were called and which we confessed 'before many witnesses'<note type="footnote" n="302"
                  resp="#ebrooks">1 Tim. vi, 12.</note> as the apostle said, that is, before the whole church and
               'the elect angels'<note type="footnote" n="303" resp="#ebrooks"> Id., v, 21.</note>, never
               having yielded to remissness. For that 'we are not of remissness which leads to perdition'<note
                  type="footnote" n="304" resp="#ebrooks">Hebr., x, 39.</note> you also well know: for you are
               the first who testify. For, 'having no sound knowledge of what they say or the things about
               which they strive'<note type="footnote" n="305" resp="#ebrooks"> 1 Tim. i, 7.</note>, they do
               not consent to confess that the true flesh of God and the Word which is from the holy God-bearer
               and ever-virgin Mary and from the Holy Spirit, which was hypostatically united to him, so that
               from the fact that he came to be with us as God who became man he was named Emmanuel, and that
               he was made like unto us in all things except sin, suffers <pb n="115"/> like us and is
               susceptible of innocent passions, but say that he suffered in semblance, and that the flesh was
               impassible and immortal at the time of the voluntary and saving Cross; and besides other
               impossible things the wretched men foolishly speak of false passions, and in false words they
               name phantasy<note type="footnote" n="306" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >φαντασία</foreign>.</note> incorruptibility, and deny the true incorruptibility, and they
               fail to notice the wisdom of the dispensation whereby the impassible God united to himself those
               of our passions which do not fall under the description of sin, wishing in it to taste our death
               voluntarily, destroy its dominion over us, and by means of the Resurrection to set us free in
               incorruptibility, that is in impassibility and immortality, and raise us to our first state in
               which also we were created. If the Word of God desired to display passions and death in unreal
               form, the Incarnation is quite superfluous. He had the divine impassibility and immortality, and
               so also he might have suffered as in semblance and shown himself after the fashion of former
               appearances, as he appeared as a man who wrestled with Jacob and was received in Abraham's
               house, and was represented in many forms through the prophets: for this he himself is seen to
               have said in Hosea the prophet<note type="footnote" n="307" resp="#ebrooks">Hos. XII,
                  10.</note>. But this was not <pb n="116"/> what he desired, but that by means of a real death he
               might save the man who had died through the deceit of the serpent, and make his own Resurrection
               the gate and way of return to everlasting life. For this reason Paul cries louder than all
               trumpets in the ears of men who will not hear: "For, since by man came death, by man also cometh
               the resurrection of the dead. For, as in Adam all died, so also in Christ shall all live"<note
                  type="footnote" n="308" resp="#ebrooks">1 Cor. XV, 21, 22.</note>. But<ab type="ellipsis"
                     >...</ab> with<ab type="ellipsis">...</ab> the Scriptures and<ab type="ellipsis">...</ab> these
               hasty and presumptuous men presumed blasphemously to say against the divine Scriptures and
               against the holy fathers who interpreted them in approved fashion, who at various times fed the
               holy churches. From these things you see clearly how much difference and distinction there is
               between truth and error even as the heaven is far from the earth, and that out of the thought of
               their heart they have 'devised words of iniquity' and that 'truth has perished in their ways,
               and they could not walk in the right way', and also that 'they have removed their thoughts from
               understanding'<note type="footnote" n="309" resp="#ebrooks">Is. LIX, 13-15.</note>. For well
               did Isaiah the prophet expose them beforehand by these words. <pb n="117"/>
            </p>
            <p>Pray therefore, saintly ones (for indeed I say the same thing many times) that we may be
               delivered from evil and unjust men. For they have been unable not only to endure reproof on
               account of their wickedness, but even to give drink to them that thirst: for, besides their
               thoughts that blaspheme against God, 'their counsels<note type="footnote" n="1" resp="#ebrooks"
                  > </note> also 'are counsels of murder'<note type="footnote" n="310" resp="#ebrooks">Is. LIX,
                     7.</note>. For this very thing Isaiah says with me concerning them. But that these same men may
               be changed to what is right make the subject of your own prayers. For we on our part look to him
               who willeth not the death of a sinner so much as that he be converted and live<note
                  type="footnote" n="311" resp="#ebrooks">Ez. xxxiii, 11.</note>. Indeed at first on the entreaty
               (and to speak the truth on the compulsion) of him who wrote unsoundly and rashly upon this same
               matter<note type="footnote" n="312" resp="#ebrooks">Julian: see the correspondence in Zach.
                  Rh., ix, 10-13.</note>, while far away and in hiding I wrote and admonished him in a brotherly
               manner and urged him to have regard to the holy fathers and to the approved doctors and follow
               them, and correct himself. And even upon this he attacked my meanness in a ferocious manner,
               worse than any raging savage beast, and kept bitterly complaining because he did not find me a
               partner of his error, and over the whole world, as far as he could, he sent out and scattered
               abroad what he had <pb n="118"/> written, which came from his heart 'not from the mouth of the
               Lord'<note type="footnote" n="313" resp="#ebrooks">Jer. XXIII, 16.</note>: and we were set
               forth as a laughing-stock to those who contend for the Chalcedonian impiety; and in Palestine,
               as I have learned, and in other provinces<note type="footnote" n="314"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >ἐπαρχίας</foreign>.</note> they were going about, and everywhere opening and extending their
               capacious mouth and saying: "See! Those who pride themselves on being orthodox<note
                  type="footnote" n="315"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὀρθόδοξος</foreign>.</note> have been
               manifestly seen to be zealous for the semblance of Eutyches, which is the error of the followers
               of Mani". Then indeed, being pierced by the judgments of God after the manner of goads and
               being<ab type="ellipsis">...</ab> in my soul because I could not endure the slander and the
               blasphemy against the glory of the Most High and the fact that one man's error should be a stain
               upon the whole body of the church, I made the true facts known to everyone, facts which are
               known and familiar to you also, saying with courage as well as faith in accordance with the
               truth (for Jesus is very God and Saviour), "If it be my lot to die with thee I will not deny
               thee"<note type="footnote" n="316" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. XXVI, 35.</note>, but, "I will go up
               upon the mountains, and will preach to Jerusalem"<note type="footnote" n="317" resp="#ebrooks"
                  >Is. XL, 9.</note>. May I gain his boldness of speech<note type="footnote" n="318"
                     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>.</note>, and may I receive help from
               him, through your saintly prayers and entreaties. </p>
            <pb n="119"/>
            <p resp="#compiler" rend="ital">The handwriting of the patriarch himself.</p>
            <p>May the holy Unity in Trinity (for this is our God) keep your holinesses, and all the
               brotherhood that is with you, illustrious in divine contests, in perfect concord and endurance
               and praying for our meanness. My spirit greets you. "Greet one another with a holy kiss"<note
                  type="footnote" n="319" resp="#ebrooks">1 Cor. xvi, 20; 2 Cor. xiii, 12.</note>. Grace be with
               you.</p>
            <p>Blessed be God for ever, and praised be his name to all generations.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
