<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3103">To Sergius the Count and Archiatros</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">140 [310]-146 [316]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="85">
            <head type="number">LXXXV.</head>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of THE SAME HOLY SEVERUS FHOM THE 27th LETTER OF THE 2nd BOOK
               OF THOSE WRITTEN AFTER BANISHMENT, WHICH WAS ADDRESSED TO SERGIUS THE COUNT AND archiatros<note
                  type="footnote" n="843" resp="#ebrooks">Perh. the physician of ep. 31.</note>. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0538">519-38</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> You ask why our Lord and God Jesus Christ took Peter and the sons of Zebedee, James that is
               and John, apart from the other apostles and disciples, and this when he raised the daughter of
               the president of the synagogue who was dead, and again when he took them up with him into the
               mountain, and as the text of the gospel says ' was transfigured before them, and his face <pb
                  n="311"/> shone like the sun, and his raiment Became bright like the light'<note
                     type="footnote" n="844" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. xvii, 2. What follows to 'appellation' (p. 312,
                     1. 5) is published in Greek in Mai, Class. Auct., X, 453 under the heading <foreign
                        xml:lang="grc">Σ. εἰς τὸ κατὰ Λοθκᾶν</foreign>.</note>. My opinion is that he shows them such
               honours beyond the others because they had a more specially acute mind, and one that rose with
               the height of the Godhead of him who voluntarily humbled himself for us and condescended to
               become incarnate and remained in the same and did not leave his most exalted glory and his
               divine height<note type="footnote" n="845" resp="#ebrooks">Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐν
                  ταυτότητι μείναντος τῆς ὑπερτάτης δὀξης τε κ. λαμπρότητος</foreign>.</note>. For Peter after
               he had confessed him and said, "Thou art the Christ the Son of the living God", heard the plain
               words, "Blessed art thou, Simon Bar Jona, for flesh and blood revealed it not to thee but my
               Father which is in heaven"<note type="footnote" n="846">Matth. xvi, 16, 17. In the Greek the
                  citations are paraphrased.</note>. And James and John, as Mark the Evangelist related, being
               brothers in the spirit more than in the body, were named by our Saviour Bnai ragsh, that is
               'sons of thunder'<note type="footnote" n="847" resp="#ebrooks">Mark iii, 17.</note>. The reason
               for which they merited such an appellation was that he who proclaimed, "In the beginning was the
               Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God"<note type="footnote" n="848"
                  resp="#ebrooks">John I, 1.</note>, loudly thundered the divine utterance from heaven <pb
                     n="312"/> and the gift of the Spirit that in truth came down thence, and stirred the attention
               of all nations by reason of the wonder, and tore up from its roots and as one might say from its
               foundations every false and human opinion that creeps upon the earth<note type="footnote"
                  n="849" resp="#ebrooks">Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">μεγαλοφώνως βροντῆσαι τὴν θεολογίαν ἐκείνην
                     τὴν ἐξ οὐρανοῦ κ. τῆς ἐκεῖθεν ἐπιπνοίας κατενεχθεῖσαν, τὸ ἐν ἀρχῇ ἦν ὁ Λ. κ. τὰ
                     ἑξῆς</foreign>.</note>. For it is manifest that James also was rich in the same grace as his
               brother, according to the unerring testimony of him who honoured them by one comman appellation.
               But some have said that the reason for which those three were peculiarly honoured beyond the
               rest of the disciples was that they specially loved Jesus, and in the same way he also too loved
               them, because of the virtues that were in them, as the very wise John bishop of Constantinople
               also said in the 56th homily of the Commentary on the Gospel of Matthew, where he thus
               interpreted the words concerning them: "Why did he take these? Because these excelled the
               others. And Peter showed the superiority by the fact that he loved him much, and John by the
               fact that he was much loved, and James by the answer which he returned saying, 'We can drink the
               cup', and not by the answer only, but also by other actions, among them the fact that he carried
               out what he said. For he was so troublesome and burdensome to the Jews that Herod <pb n="313"/>
               thought this would be a great present to give to the Jews if he put him to death"<note
                  type="footnote" n="850" resp="#ebrooks">In Matth. Hom. LVI, 1 (ed. Par. 2a, VII, 637). </note>.
               The words used by our Lord to his disciples, "Greet no man by the way"<note type="footnote"
                  n="851" resp="#ebrooks">Luke x, 5.</note> naturally cause perplexity among those who read the
               divine Scriptures superficially: for greeting more especially becomes ministers of peace and
               teachers of a humble disposition. But it is not possible for us to take the actual injunction as
               bearing this meaning; for our Saviour is thereby shown to contradict himself and to be making
               use of injunctions which do not agree with one another; for Matthew wrote of him that he said to
               his disciples, "And, if ye greet your friends only, what special thing do ye? Do not the
               tax-gatherers also the same?"<note type="footnote" n="852" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. v, 47.</note>.
               How then can he who enjoins us to greet not only those who are friends but also enemies prohibit
               us from greeting those who meet us on the way? Accordingly therefore it is manifest that we must
               direct the purport of the injunction to another meaning. It is the habit of men to visit their
               acquaintances who live at a distance from them, and whom they have not seen for a long time,
               making this the occasion <pb n="314"/> of a journey, the greeting of those persons, as Luke
               wrote of Mary the God-bearer that the reason for which she went to the hill-country was to greet
               Elizabeth, saying thus: "And Mary arose in the same days, and went to the hill-country in haste,
               to a city of Judah, and entered the house of Zacharias, and greeted Elizabeth"<note
                  type="footnote" n="853" resp="#ebrooks">Luke I, 39, 40.</note>. Since therefore our Lord and
               God wished his disciples to be unencumbered and self-reliant, and that they should be very
               zealous for the preaching-journey, he prohibited such greeting, when they were setting out on
               the apostolic and divine journey, lest they should give up the zeal for the journey set before
               them and enter upon the journey that is called vain, which leads aside to another path. For he
               wished the divine service of the gospel-message and of the saving preaching to be honoured
               before fitting human affection and the love that creeps upon the earth. And the approved Cyril
               also bishop of Alexandria wrote in agreement with these things in precise words and at length,
               in the 62nd homily of the Commentary on the Gospel of Luke: "Again how could it not be incumbent
               on men who were to enlighten those that were in darkness and to bring <pb n="315"/> them to the
               knowledge of the truth above all others to adopt a gentle demeanour and great affability, and
               not roughly shun intercourse with them, so as to refuse even to greet them? though it indeed
               becomes saints together with other good qualities to have that also of approaching people in a
               proper way and giving greeting. For perhaps it would happen that those who met them were not
               under all circumstances unbelievers, but also some of those who shared their opinions, or of
               those who had been already enlightened, so that for this reason it was necessary to give them a
               message of love, I mean the word ' Hail! '. What therefore? And for this reason Christ does not
               give the injunction in order that they may be misanthropes, nor does he give it in order to show
               honour to<note type="footnote" n="854" resp="#ebrooks">The translator seems to h ave
                  misunderstood the Greek. The Syr. version of Cyr. has "What therefore does Christ teach by this
                  also? He did not ordain that they should be rude, nor that they should honour".</note> a
               refusal to offer greeting, but rather he teaches them to avoid such refusal. It is not
               unreasonable for us to understand that, when the disciples were going round the cities and
               villages, and propounding the mysteries relating to the divine doctrines to those in every
               place, they did not then wish to do this without distraction, but so to speak at leisure,
               turning out of the way and making use of certain diversions, because someone perhaps wished to
               see a man whom he knew <pb n="316"/> and his friend, and afterwards spend the time proper for
               teaching in gluttony, not in urgent things. Accordingly he says that, showing unencumbered zeal
               for the divine proclamation, they should be sure not to give attention that does not profit to
               friendships (but rather that which pleases God is placed before every thing), and, while
               employing acts of courtesy that cannot be impugned and do not occupy attention, to give close
               attention to the apostolic business"<note type="footnote" n="855" resp="#ebrooks"> Comm. in Luc.
                  (Syr.), éd. Chabot, p. 238. Not extant in Greek.</note>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
