<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3120">To Caesaria the Hypatissa</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">200 [370]-213 [383]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="98">
            
            <head type="number">XCVIII.</head>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF MAR SEVERUS FROM THE 5th LETTER OF THE 4th BOOK OF THOSE
               AFTER EXILE, WHICH WAS ADDRESSED TO CAESARIA THE HYPATISSA, WHICH BEGINS, "When I read the
               letter of your magnificence's love of God, not once nor twice". </head>
            <note type="date" resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0538">519-38</date>
            </note>
            <p> But to the question which your excellency's magnificence has asked me by letter I return an
               easy answer, that for my part I have never accepted or expressed agreement with those who speak
               of an apokatastasis, and an end to the judgment involved in the torments that are threatened us
               in the future world, and the man who says that he has a letter of mine which proclaims this
               opinion manifestly lies. Therefore I praised your God-loving magnificence for asking for such a
               letter to be shown to you; a letter which the man who concocted it necessarily set himself
               falsely to show to be my composition. Those who hold such an opinion, wishing to accomplish
               their desires, as if forsooth on the basis of plausible suppositions, make use of arguments that
               are gratifying to the hearers, saying that it is unbecomingto or unworthy <pb n="371"/> of God,
               and far removed from his mercifulness, that the man who has sinned for 50 or 100 years in this
               world should endure torments for unending ages, forgetting this, that God's laws and those
               which, prevail among men think fit to requite sins according to the intention of the sinner, and
               one may hear even wise men outside saying of certain persons who have done foul deeds and acts
               that are not permitted, "This man deserves to die not once but many times"<note type="footnote"
                  n="975" resp="#ebrooks">This seems to be a citation, but I do not know the source.</note>. But,
               when a man hears as we do that God who became incarnate and was humanized without variation for
               our salvation, and who for this reason came down from heaven and conversed with us plainly
               threatens<note type="footnote" n="976" resp="#ebrooks"> (EKT) 'became <ab type="ellipsis"
                  >...</ab> salvation, and that for <ab type="ellipsis">...</ab> reason he came <ab
                     type="ellipsis">...</ab> heaven, plainly threatening'.</note> fire that is not quenched and an
               undying worm<note type="footnote" n="977" resp="#ebrooks">Mark ix, 44.</note>, and<note
                  type="footnote" n="978" resp="#ebrooks"> (EKT) ins. 'after all these things'. This version has
                  many additions, which from a comparison with the originals of the citations contained in the
                  extract I infer to be interpolations.</note> makes light of it, how does he not deserve, if it
               is possible to say so, to be condemned <pb n="372"/> twice over to<note type="footnote" n="979"
                  resp="#ebrooks"> (EKT) ins. 'eternal fire and'. </note> endless torment? If a man live 100
               years or more in this present world and spend such a period in vanity, it is certain that this
               man, if he were allowed to live this same temporal life<note type="footnote" n="980"
                  resp="#ebrooks"> (EKT) om.</note> without end<note type="footnote" n="981" resp="#ebrooks">
                     (EKT) ins. 'remaining without death'.</note>, would not cease from his eternal<note
                        type="footnote" n="980" resp="#ebrooks"> (EKT) om.</note> greed and wantonness<note
                           type="footnote" n="982" resp="#ebrooks"> (EKT) ins. 'and lasciviousness and a foul life in
                           lusts'.</note>. How therefore will this man in accordance with his disposition not justly<note
                              type="footnote" n="980" resp="#ebrooks"> </note> be tormented without end? Even the very men
               who introduce an apokatastasis<note type="footnote" n="983"> (ET) ins. 'or end of
                  judgment'.</note> say of sinners that they will be tormented for many<note type="footnote"
                     n="984"> (ET) ins. 'years'.</note> and long periods so to speak<note type="footnote" n="985"
                        resp="#ebrooks"> (ET) 'of such a kind and protracted future ages'.</note>, and then afterwards
               will be purified and admitted to clemency and attain to the promised blessedness. But they<note
                  type="footnote" n="986" resp="#ebrooks">In another version (ET) 'those who say these
                  things'.</note> forget that their human reasonings <pb n="373"/> themselves show God to be
               unrighteous in his judgments<note type="footnote" n="987" resp="#ebrooks">A.v. (ET) 'and
                  unjust'.</note>. If a man lives<note type="footnote" n="988" resp="#ebrooks"> (ET) ins. 'up and
                     down'.</note> in sin 50 or 80 years, but<note type="footnote" n="989" resp="#ebrooks"> (ET)
                        ins. 'is requited with a severe sentence and'.</note> endures torments many long generations,
               it is again apparent on their principle that this is not worthy of God's mercifulness<note
                  type="footnote" n="990" resp="#ebrooks"> (E) ins. 'nor yet becoming to the kindness existing in
                  him'.</note>, to extend the period of torment beyond the time of the life in sins, If God
               agreed with the reasonings of those who think thus<note type="footnote" n="991" resp="#ebrooks"
                  >A.v. (E) ins. 'and agreed and assented to their opinions'.</note>, the man who sins for 50
               years should endure torment for 50 years, and it<note type="footnote" n="992" resp="#ebrooks">
                  (E) 'only, and the judgment.' </note> should not be thus long extended over many generations,
               as they say<note type="footnote" n="993" resp="#ebrooks">In another version (E) ins. 'and his
                  torment endure for ages'. What follows to 'distinction' (p. 374 l. 4) isomitted in vers.
                  F.</note>. For our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ also, in the holy words of his preaching, when
               <pb n="374"/> separating the righteous from the sinners, said, "These shall go to eternal
               torment, and the righteous to eternal life"<note type="footnote" n="994" resp="#ebrooks">Matth.
                  xxv, 46.</note>, and with regard to both the classes<note type="footnote" n="995"
                     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">τάγμα</foreign>.</note>, that of the former and that of
               the latter, he spoke in exactly the same fashion of an equality without distinction, applying
               the word ' eternal' to both without distinction. Basil the great among teachers of the truth
               shows this clearly in the teaching composed by him in the form of question and answer addressed
               to the brethren of the convents; and it is the 219th question, which is expressed as follows:
               "The brethren say<note type="footnote" n="996" resp="#ebrooks"> (F) 'when be was asked by the
                  brethren'</note>. 'If<note type="footnote" n="997" resp="#ebrooks">In another version (EKL)
                     ins. 'it is said of the two slaves described in the gospel that'; Bas. om.</note> one shall be
               beaten with many stripes and another with few, how <pb n="375"/> say some that there is no end
               to the sentence of those who are tormented?'</p>
            <p>Basil<note type="footnote" n="998" resp="#ebrooks"> (F) 'the great among doctors'.</note>
               says.</p>
            <p>Points which are matters of dispute and seen to be obscurely expressed m various places of the
               Holy Scriptures are elucidated by clear statements in other places. Since therefore our Lord
               says at one time, 'These shall go into eternal torment<note type="footnote" n="999"
                  resp="#ebrooks"> (F) and EL ins. 'and the righteous into eternal life; Bas. om.</note>', and at
               another dismisses some to 'the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels', and at
               another mentions 'the gehenna of fire', uttering further the words,<note type="footnote"
                  n="1000">A.v.(EKL) om.</note> 'Where their worm dieth not, and their fire is not quenched', and
               again said before through the prophet about certain <pb n="376"/> men,<note type="footnote"
                  n="1001" resp="#ebrooks"> (EKL); "Ye shall go out and see the corpses of them who have
                  committed iniquity against me, for'.</note> 'Their worm shall not die, and their fire shall not
               be quenched'; while these and similar expressions, are often<note type="footnote" n="1002"
                  resp="#ebrooks"> (F) 'here and there'; Bas. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πολλαχοῦ</foreign>.</note>
               used in the divine Scriptures, this also was brought about by the machination of the devil, in
               order that men, forgetting these and similar decrees of our Lord, might presume to sin without
               restraint, persuading themselves that there is an end to judgment. For, if it is possible for
               there to be<note type="footnote" n="1003" resp="#ebrooks">A.v. EKL.) 'it is certain that the
                  devil by his craft contrived to deceive the minds of many, in order that while they forget our
                  Lord's sentences, he may sow this in their thoughts that there<ab type="ellipsis">....</ab>
                  judgment, and make them yet more presume<ab type="ellipsis">...</ab> restraint in the evil
                  deeds of hateful things. For, if there is'; Bas. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἕν κ. τοῦτο τῆς
                     μεθοδείασ τοῦ διαβ., τὸ τοὺς πολλοὐς τῶν ἀνθρώπων ὥσπερ ἐπιλαθομένους τῶν τοσούτων κ. τοιούτων
                     τοῦ Κ. ῥημάτων κ. ἀποφάσενω τέλος κολάσεως εἰς τὸ μαλλόν κατατολμὰν τῆς ἁμαρτίας ἑαυτοῖς
                     ὑπογράφειν. Εἰ γ. τῆς αἰςνίου κολάσεως ἔσται ποτέ</foreign>.</note> an end to eternal
               judgment, there will assuredly also be an end to eternal life. But, if we do not consent to
               think this with regard to<note type="footnote" n="1004" resp="#ebrooks"> (EKL) 'that there is an
                  end to eternal'.</note> life, what plausibility is there in our assigning<note type="footnote"
                     n="1005" resp="#ebrooks"> (EKL) 'room is there for the theory that there is'.</note> an end to
               eternal judgment? For the addition of the word 'eternal' is made equally in both cases. 'These
               shall go into eternal <pb n="377"/> judgment, and the righteous into eternal life'. These things
               therefore being thus admitted, we must know that the words 'He shall be beaten with many
               stripes' and 'shall be beaten with few' are not an end, but signify a difference of torment.
               For, if God is an upright judge, not only to the good but also to the evil<note type="footnote"
                  n="1006" resp="#ebrooks">A.v. (EK) om.</note>, and requites each according to his deeds, it is
               possible for one to be in the fire that is not quenched<note type="footnote" n="1007">A.V. (EK)
                  ins. 'and another to be in fire'.</note>, burning either less or more than the other, and
               another in the worm that dies not, both one that hurts little and one that hurts much<note
                  type="footnote" n="1008" resp="#ebrooks">In another version (EK) 'and another in bitter
                  habitations, and one in milder torments, and one in torments more severe than they'.</note>,
               each as he deserves, and another in gehenna that has a variety of torments, and another in outer
               darkness, and that there <pb n="378"/> is a place where a man is found amidst weeping only, and
               there is a place where he is amidst gnashing of teeth also from the severity of the pains<note
                  type="footnote" n="1009" resp="#ebrooks">In another version(E) 'one may recognise moreover in
                  gehenna a variety of torments of those who are being requited'.</note>. But the outer darkness
               signifies that there is in truth an inner darkness also.<note type="footnote" n="1010"
                  resp="#ebrooks"> A. v, (E) ins. 'And there is a place of requital where a man is in weeping
                  only, and there is one again where he is in gnashing of teeth, from the severe torments of the
                  bitter sentence'.</note> And the words used in the Proverbs<note type="footnote" n="1011"
                     resp="#ebrooks">A.v. (F) ins. 'of Solomon'.</note> 'at the bottom of Sheol<note type="footnote"
                        n="1012" resp="#ebrooks"> (E) 'bringeth down to the depths of Sheol and to the bottom of the
                        pit'.</note>' signify that there are persons in Sheol and not at the bottom of it, because
               their torment is smaller<note type="footnote" n="1013" resp="#ebrooks"> (E) ins. 'and there is
                  one who is in the pit and not as it were at the bottom of it. By all which things the
                  difference is signified of the retribution in the judgment of those who are requited as their
                  deeds deserve, either by a severe sentence or by a vengeance with mitigation in it according to
                  their acts'.</note>. And this is depicted now also in bodily afflictions. For there is aman who
               is in a fever together with other pains, and another <pb n="379"/> who is in a fever only, and
               the latter is not like the former, and another has no fever, but is troubled by pain in some
               limb<note type="footnote" n="1014"> 1. A.v. (E) 'other pains of every kind'.</note>, and one
               again either less or more than another. But this expression 'much' or 'little' is employed by
               our Lord in accordance with customary usage, as are also many other similar phrases. For we know
               that this form of speech is frequently adopted even with regard to those who are suffering from
               one disease<note type="footnote" n="1015" resp="#ebrooks"> (E) ins. 'or illness'. </note>. For
               example, in the case of a man who has a fever only, or has pain in the eye only<note
                  type="footnote" n="1016"> (E) om.</note> we<note type="footnote" n="1017" resp="#ebrooks"> (F)
                     'they'.</note> say in astonishment 'How much he has suffered!' or 'What anguish he has
               endured!' Accordingly the expression 'shall be beaten with many' <pb n="380"/> and 'with few', I
               say again, stands not in the extent of the time and the shortness<note type="footnote" n="1018"
                  resp="#ebrooks"> (E)' which has received an end'; Bas. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἢ
                     συμπληρώσει</foreign>, which latter word the author of the E version has taken as a verb.
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܠܝܠܘܬܐ</foreign> must app. be rendered 'shortness', though this
                  meaning is not otherwise known. </note>, but in the difference of the torment"<note
                     type="footnote" n="1019" resp="#ebrooks">P. G., XXXI, 1264.</note>. These things this great
               ruler and shepherd of rational souls Basil taught and stated with great completeness.<note
                  type="footnote" n="1020" resp="#ebrooks"> (F) om.</note> And Gregory, who became bishop of
               Nazianzus, himself in the homily of defence thinks that the future torment is endless, teaching
               thus: "But for us, the salvation of whose blessed and immortal soul is in danger, which will be
               undyingly tormented or glorified<note type="footnote" n="1021"> (EK) 'gratified in the eternal
                  kingdom'. </note> by reason of wickedness or of virtue, how great do you think should the
               contest be<note type="footnote" n="1022" resp="#ebrooks"> (EK) ins. 'concerning this'.
               </note>?"<note type="footnote" n="1023" resp="#ebrooks">Or. ii, 28.</note> And John in the 66th
               homily<note type="footnote" n="1024" resp="#ebrooks"> (EK) ins. 'delivered by him'.</note> of
               the commentary on the Gospel of Matthew <pb n="381"/> states things consonant with these as
               follows: "For all these reasons accordingly let us first pay the taxes; for it is indeed
               very<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"> (EK) 'Before all things let us have a struggle on
                  behalf of good things; for labour for fair things is'.</note> easy, and the reward is greater,
               and there is great abundance of<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"> (F) om.</note> profit, and
               worse is the torture if we do not understand, and<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"> (EK)
                  'which will be exacted from us, which is'.</note> a torture that has no end"<note
                     type="footnote" n="4" resp="#ebrooks">In Matth. Hom. LXVI, 4 (ed. Par. 2a, VII, 742).</note>.
               And the same again in the 79th exposition when speaking of the Passion referred to the kingdom,
               and to the endless torment.<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">A. v. (F) om.</note> And in the
               82nd about the man who approaches<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"> (E) ins. 'our Saviour's
                  body and blood'.</note> the communion of the holy mysteries in a careless mood and without
               caution he gives teaching in the following words: "He who approaches after he has sinned is
               worse than a demoniac; for the: latter because they have a demon<note type="footnote"
                  resp="#ebrooks"> (E) 'are involuntarily controlled by demons'.</note> do not receive
               punishment<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">In another version (E) ins. 'and are not
                  judged'.</note>, but the <pb n="382"/> former, because they approach unworthily, are delivered
               to undying torment<note type="footnote" n="1025" resp="#ebrooks">A. v. (E) 'judgment without
                  mercy and torment that does not finish'; (F) 'undying torments; Jo. Chrys. <foreign
                     xml:lang="grc">ἀθανάτῳ τιμωρίᾳ</foreign>.</note>"<note type="footnote" n="1026"
                        resp="#ebrooks">Op. cit., LXXXII, 6 (ed. Par. 2a, VII, 890).</note>. And at the end of the
               commentary on the epistle to the Ephesians he<note type="footnote" n="1027"> (E) ' the same
                  blessed John again'.</note> expressed himself thus: "For a man to be burnt<note type="footnote"
                     n="1028" resp="#ebrooks"> (EK) ins. 'in gehenna'.</note> and not consumed, and to be
               perpetually gnawed by a<note type="footnote" n="1029" resp="#ebrooks">In another version (EK)
                  'an undying'.</note> worm is indestructible<note type="footnote" n="1030" resp="#ebrooks"> (EK)
                     ins. 'and unperishing'.</note> destruction, as happened to<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"
                        > (EK) 'we hear of'.</note> the blessed Job, who<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"> (EK)
                           'whose body'.</note> was in process of destruction and did not perish for a considerable time,
               but was constantly suffering and wasting away<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">A. v. (F)
                  om.</note>, while he scraped off putrid matter from his body<note type="footnote" n="1031"
                     resp="#ebrooks"> (EK) 'with a potsherd' (Job, n, 3). Neither is in Jo. Chrys.</note> for a long
               time. Something similar will happen to the soul at that time, when the<note type="footnote"
                  n="1032" resp="#ebrooks"> (EK) ins. 'undying'</note> worms surround and gnaw it, not for two
               years<note type="footnote" n="1033" resp="#ebrooks">A. v, (EK) ins. 'only'.</note> nor for ten
               nor for a hundred nor <pb n="383"/> for myriads<note type="footnote" n="1034" resp="#ebrooks"
                  >Jo. Chr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">μυρίοις</foreign>.</note>, but for years without end; for
               'their worm', he says, 'shall not die'"<note type="footnote" n="1035" resp="#ebrooks">In Ep. ad
                  Eph. Hom. xxiv, 28, 29 (ed. Field).</note>. The wise Cyril<note type="footnote" n="1036"
                     resp="#ebrooks"> (EK) 'blessed C. wise in divine things'.</note> also in the 1st book of the
               commentary on the Gospel of John said: "We ought not to be ungrateful to God but on the
               contrary<note type="footnote" n="1037" resp="#ebrooks"> (EK) 'the contrary, i.e.'</note> to
               thank him because by means of the Resurrection from the dead he has appointed for us torment
               that does not pass away<note type="footnote" n="1038" resp="#ebrooks">In another version (EK)
                  ins. 'unless we repent completely'.</note>"<note type="footnote" n="1039" resp="#ebrooks">In
                     Jo. Ev., ed. Pusey, I, 119; but our text differs widely.</note>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
