<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3139">To Thomas, Bishop of Germanicea</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">264 [434]-272 [442]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="108">
            <head type="number">CVIII.</head>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE HOLY SEVERUS PATRIARCH OF ANTIOCH, FROM THE 27th LETTER
               OF THE 9th BOOK AFTER EXILE WHICH WAS ADDRESSED TO THOMAS BISHOP OF GERMANICEA. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0538">519-38</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> "Thus saith the Lord: 'I found a hot one in the wilderness with the slain of the sword. Go
               and destroy not Israel. The Lord shall be revealed upon him afar off. With perfect love I loved
               thee; therefore I drew thee with mercy. Again I will build thee and thou shalt be built, virgin
               Jerusalem'"<note type="footnote" n="1131" resp="#ebrooks">1131. 3. Jer., xxxviii, 2-4.</note>.
               Certain men with experience of war say that generals<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"
                  ><foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηγός</foreign>.</note> of <pb n="435"/> armies have a custom of
               bringing besides the armed forces physicians also, and, after the hosts engage with one another
               and the battle is joined, and the opposite side is defeated, they send the physicians to search
               among the fallen, and examine carefully lest there be found a man among them who is warm and has
               breath in him, and may by medical skill recover from the deadly wounds that are upon him.
               Therefore also the purport of this figurative prophecy which we have cited is that, when Israel
               was reckoned with the dead, he restored him to life; but some have not discovered the meaning
               contained in this figure, or the explanation of the words, 'I found a hot one in the
               wilderness', but have given a foolish interpretation. They changed the reading 'hot', and
               instead of saying 'hot' said 'solitary', and supposed from this that there is some herb which
               grows of itself in the wilderness, and signifies the solitariness of Israel. For it is not so.
               The words of the following context refute and truly banish their supposition; and the words of
               Scripture are as follows: "I found a hot one in the wilderness with the slain of the sword". So
               therefore I also am in this manner lifted up, and am constrained to take courage and speak a few
               words about the communications that have been addressed to me by your eloquent wisdom.</p>
            <pb n="436"/>
            <p><supplied reason="ellipsis" resp="#compiler">(<emph rend="ital">And after other things.</emph>)</supplied></p>
            <p>But that our Lord Jesus Christ our God was pierced in the side with a lance by that
               soldier<note type="footnote" resp="#compiler"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >στρατιώτης</foreign>.</note> after he gave up the ghost, and blood and water came forth from
               it in a miraculous manner, the divine John the Evangelist recorded, and no one else wrote about
               this. But certain persons have clearly falsified the Gospel of Matthew and inserted this same
               passage, when the contrary is the fact, in order to show that it was while he was alive that the
               soldier<note type="footnote" resp="#compiler"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >στρατιώτης</foreign>.</note> pierced his side with the spear, and afterwards he gave up the
               ghost<note type="footnote" n="1132" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. xxvii, 49. See Tischendorf ad loc.,
                  where this passage of Sev. is cited from Assemani, Bibl. Or., II, 81.</note>. This question was
               examined with great carefulness when my meanness was in the royal city, at the time when the
               affair of Macedonius was being examined, who became archbishop of that city, and there was
               produced the Gospel of Matthew, which was written in large letters, and was preserved with great
               honour in the royal palace, which was said to have been found in the days of Zeno of honourable
               memory in a city of the island of Cyprus buried with the holy Barnabas, who went about with Paul
               and spread the divine preaching; and, when the Gospel of Matthew was opened, it was found to be
               free from the falsification contained in this addition, <pb n="437"/> of the story of the
               soldier<note type="footnote" resp="#compiler"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >στρατιώτης</foreign>.</note> and the spear. I do not know how and for what reason the holy
               John who became bishop of the same royal city, and the admirable Cyril, bishop of Alexandria,
               did not test this question, and allowed the two passages to stand, in the two evangelists,
               neglecting the evidence to the contrary;<note type="footnote" n="1133" resp="#ebrooks">The
                  passage is not in the extant fragments of Cyril's commentary on Matth. For Jo. Chrys. see
                  below.</note> but perhaps in order that this also might be known, that, while they speak and
               write everything under the operation of the Holy Spirit, and while these men are higher than we
               (for we are men who creep along the earth), as the heaven is higher than the earth<note
                  type="footnote" n="1134" resp="#ebrooks">The sentence is not completed.</note>, and that they
               themselves also might be known to be men, and to leave omniscience to God only, and that there
               is something in affairs which cannot be expressed, the complete revelation of which is not made
               known. Thus Samuel also, who as one may say saw with the eye of prophecy everything that was
               about to happen, did not know Saul when he was present and standing among all Israel, Because
               God by means of these things was instructing his bondmen, and teaching them to pay regard to
               humility. Wherefore also the divine Scripture is written thus: "And Samuel asked in the Lord and
               said, 'Cometh that man hither?' And the Lord said, ' Lo! he is hidden among the vessels'. And
               <pb n="438"/> he ran and took him thence"<note type="footnote" n="1135" resp="#ebrooks">1 Sam.
                  x, 22, 23.</note>. And at the time when the Shilumite woman's son died, and she had come to
               Elisha in great distress, as a mother who had been deprived of her beloved son, and, when she
               had just fallen at the feet of the prophet of God, and Gehazi tried to prevent her, the bondman
               of God, being moved by love and sorrow, said to Gehazi, "Let her alone, because her soul is
               bitter in her, and the Lord hid it from me and showed it not to me"<note type="footnote"
                  n="1136" resp="#ebrooks">2 Kings iv, 27.</note>. Accordingly you should know that Eusebius of
               Caesarea also who is called 'Pamphili', who wrote the canons of the gospel, and imitated those
               who wrote on this subject before him, and had more complete knowledge of this question than the
               others, in the 10th canon, in which he recorded the places peculiar to one of the evangelists,
               inserted this passage also about the soldier<note type="footnote" resp="#compiler"><foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">στρατιώτης</foreign>.</note> and the lance, saying that John alone recorded
               it<note type="footnote" n="1137" resp="#ebrooks">Novum Testamentam, ed. Lloyd and Sanday, p.
                  xx; P. G,, XXII, 1292.</note>. And we also agree with this careful accuracy, not that we
               contend against our fathers (far be it!), but that we place the evangelists at a greater height
               than them, and assign to the evangelists only the intention which properly belongs to them, in
               order that in everything Jesus, who is God, who spoke in the <pb n="439"/> evangelists, may be
               glorified, 'in whom are all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge hidden'<note type="footnote"
                  n="1138" resp="#ebrooks">Col. ii, 3.</note>, according to the saying of Paul. But for the rest
               we find that the holy John himself also, the bishop of Constantinople, in the commentary on the
               same Matthew the Evangelist with regard to this same addition which we are now discussing,
               himself also said things that fit the truth; for he expressed himself thus: "'But another came
               up and perforated his side with a lance'. And what could be more wicked than these men? And who
               could be lawless like them? And who could be more savage than these same men, who showed their
               madness to such an extent, that they attacked a dead body. But do you mark how their madness was
               brought about for our salvation. For after the wound the fountain of life welled forth for
               us"<note type="footnote" n="1139" resp="#ebrooks">In Matth. Hom. LXXXVIII, 1 (ed. Par. 2a, VII,
                  932).</note>. But these are the words of a man who follows the footsteps of the narrative of
               John the Evangelist and nothing else; for he called the body 'dead'; because it was after he
               gave up the ghost that the soldier<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >στρατιώτης</foreign>.</note> pierced him, and gave occasion for the fountain of our salvation
               to well forth thence, as the doctor John the bishop said. But this addition to the narrative of
               Matthew the Evangelist has never been inserted by any of the earlier <pb n="440"/> commentators
               who wrote, not by Origen, who examined such questions minutely, though he sinned<note
                  type="footnote" n="1140" resp="#ebrooks">Perh. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἥμαρτε</foreign>
                  ('erred'); see p. 77, n. 3.</note> in matters that are necessary for the truth of the faith of
               the church, nor by Didymus, nor by any other man who has written on this subject. But
               Eusebius<note type="footnote" n="1141" resp="#ebrooks">This passage to 'letter' (p. 441,1.12)
                  is published in Greek in Cramer, Cat. in Luc. et Jo., p. 389 (cf. Corderius, Cat. in Jo., p.
                  436; P. G., XXII, 1009).</note> of Caesarea, who is called 'Pamphili', whom we mentioned a
               little above, when writing to a man called Marinus about questions concerning the passions of
               our Saviour and about his Resurrection, showed us nothing whatever about the said addition, as
               being unknown and having no place in the books of the gospel. But in the same letters to
               Marinus, who had asked him for an interpretation on the subject of our Saviour's passions and
               his Resurrection, he inserted the following exposition also in his letters, that the divine Mark
               the Evangelist said that it was the 3rd hour at the time when Christ who is God and our Saviour
               was crucified, but the divine John (he said) wrote that it was at the 6th hour that Pilate sat
               upon his judgment-seat at the place called 'the pavement', and judged Christ. And therefore
               Eusebius said that this is an error of a scribe, who was inattentive when writing <pb n="441"/>
               the Gospel<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">παραγοραθὲν</foreign>
                  (conj. Cr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">παραγραφθὲν</foreign>, P. G., <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                     >παροραθὲν</foreign>) <foreign xml:lang="grc">παρὰ τῶν ἐξ ἀρχῆς ἀπογραψαμένων τὰ
                        Εὐαγγέλια</foreign>.</note>. For it is the letter gamal that denotes 3 hours, while the letter
               which is called in Greek episemon denotes the number of 6 hours, and these letters are like one
               another in Greek, and, the scribe wishing to write '3' quickly, and having turned the letter a
               little backwards, it was thereby found to be '6', because, since the letter had been turned
               backwards, it was supposed to be the letter that denotes '6'. Since therefore the three other
               evangelists Matthew, Mark, and Luke stated alike as with one mouth that from the 6th hour to the
               9th there was darkness over all the land, it is plain that our Lord and God Jesus Christ was
               crucified before the 6th hour, at which the darkness took place, that is from the 3rd hour,
               as<note type="footnote" n="1142" resp="#ebrooks">Some words have perh. fallen out; Gr. <foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">Μάρκος ἱστόρησε· κ. τοῦ Ἰωάννοι τὸν ὅμοιον τρόπον τὴν ὥραν τρίτην εἶναι
                  ἐπισημανομένου</foreign>.</note> the blessed John himself wrote. Similarly we say that it is
               the 3rd hour, because those who wrote before, as we have said, changed the letter. We must
               insert also in this our letter upon this matter a part of what Eusebius himself stated at
               length; and his words are as follows: "We agree not with any chance man, but with the evangelist
               who gave this testimony, <pb n="442"/> Mark. For it happened that there was an error on the part
               of the scribe so that he changed the letter by adding length to it, and it was thought that the
               letter which represents '3' was '6', on account of the likeness of the two letters [of that
               which denotes '3' and that which denotes '6'. If the refore it is stated by John that it was the
               preparation of the day of unlevened bread, and it was about the 6th hour, and Pilate said to the
               Jews "Behold! your king"<note type="footnote" n="1143" resp="#ebrooks">John xix, 14.</note>, and
               so on, let there be read instead of '6th' '3rd', since the beginning of his trial took place at
               that time, and in the middle of the hour or after it had been completed they crucified him, so
               that the result is that they judged and crucified him at the same hour"<note type="footnote"
                  n="1144" resp="#ebrooks">Not known ecc. from Sev.</note>; If you look for and find the volume
               addressed to Marinus about the interpretation of these things, you will find the accuracy of the
               writer as regards these matters. For our part we do not wish to write much on these subjects in
               this our letter. May the industry of your holiness be preserved for us meditating on these
               things and occupied with these things in priestly fashion, and rousing up the gloom of our
               silence and urging it to speak<note type="footnote" n="1145" resp="#ebrooks">A Greek extract
                  from a letter to Th. of Germanicea is published in Cramer, Cat. in Epp. Cath., p. 159.</note>.
               <pb n="443"/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
