<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3174">A Canon Concerning the Holy and Great Severus
               Patriarch of Antioch in Syria which is Performed on the 8th of February, and is in
               the 4th Oblique Tone</title>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m"> A Collection of Letters of <persName
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName> , from
                     Numerous Syriac Manuscripts </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">292 [462]-298 [468]</biblScope>
                  <!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head type="main">APPENDIX A CANON CONCERNING THE HOLY AND GREAT SEVERUS PATRIARCH OF ANTIOCH IN
               SYRIA WHICH IS PERFORMED ON THE 8th OF FEBRUARY, AND IS IN THE 4th OBLIQUE TONE<note
                  type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἦχος πλάγιος
                     τέταρτο(ς)</foreign>.</note>.</head>
            <head type="sub">The 1st hymn. Praise the glorious Lord.</head>
            <p>The rod which was cleft<note type="footnote" n="1194" resp="#ebrooks">The author took <foreign
               xml:lang="grc">αὐτήν</foreign> in Ex., xiv, 16 to refer to the rod instead of the sea.</note>
               divided the indivisible sea and the sun saw land which had never seen it; and it whelmed the
               iniquitous foeman in the water of the deep, and Israel passed through by a road that had not
               been trodden, singing a hymn and saying, "Let us praise the Lord God for he is gloriously
               splendid and glorious"<note type="footnote" n="1195" resp="#ebrooks">Ex. xv, 1.</note>.</p>
            <p>Who is able and sufficient as is meet to praise thy triumphs, O saintly and blessed Severus?
               For they overcome and surpass all intelligence and reason and knowledge. Thee Christ raised up
               as a champion of the orthodox faith, Christ whom also thou didst praise 'for he is gloriously
               splendid and glorious'. </p>
            <pb n="463"/>
            <p>Since thou first receivedst the seal of light, thou didst never consent to defile this by the
               lusts of the world, but straightway betookest thyself to the life of asceticism and didst
               commune with Christ the King, the Saviour of all created things, whom also thou didst praise
               'for he is gloriously splendid and glorious'.</p>
            <div>
               <head>My heart hath been strengthened.</head>
               <p>Thou art the strength and confirmation of them that hope in thee. Lord of all, thou art the
                  light of them that are in darkness and to thee my spirit maketh confession without ceasing.</p>
               <p>Thou art the strength of the truth, thou art the sound prop. Thou art the pillar and the
                  foundation of the churches and we honour the day of thy commemoration.</p>
               <p>Thou didst raise up and confirm the right faith in the churches which were torn by heresies,
                  our father, and we honour the day of thy commemoration.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Lord, I have heard.</head>
               <p>Thou rodest in procession upon horses which are those who please thee, <pb n="464"/> Lord of
                  all, and with strength thou didst hold these reins in thine hands and they became as it were a
                  great salvation in that comeliness becometh (?)<note type="footnote" n="1196" resp="#ebrooks"
                     >There is perh. some corruption here.</note> them that cry in faith "Praise to the might of
                  thy being, Lord of all".</p>
               <p>That wolf once attacked as one that is bold when Justinian overthrew and expelled the party
                  of the orthodox; but Severus opposed him in the mind of the Lord, and by the shafts of his
                  words rescued and saved the flock that was being despoiled.</p>
               <p>Thou didst set up and strengthen the right teachings of the faith without blame, having
                  thrust away alike the cleavage and the confusion of those who foolishly dared io divide or
                  confound, in that thou taughtest us rightly to proclaim the doctrine of one incarnate
                  nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>In the night my soul.</head>
               <p>Give light to us all, Lord, by thy life-giving commands, and, leading us with thine exalted
                  arm, grant thy peace to our souls, merciful one.</p>
               <p>Supplicate, saintly one, on behalf of the members of the holy church, that <pb n="465"/> they
                  may quickly in mercy be at peace and be united, and through thy prayer be delivered from the
                  assaults of heresies.</p>
               <p>Arise saintly one now also to defend the flock which hath fled to thee for refuge, and
                  restrain by the might of thy prayer the treacherous wolves of all the heresies, who are howling
                  to break it in pieces, and make them cease from it.</p>
               <p>Thou confessedst the incarnate Word to be one hypostasis. and nature only, that was in no
                  wise divided or changed; and therefore the believers zealously honour the day of thy
                  commemoration.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>"I cried unto the Lord"<note type="footnote" n="1197" resp="#ebrooks">Ps. CXLI,
                  2.</note>.</head>
               <p>I pour out my prayer before God, and to him I reveal and declare my distress, because my soul
                  hath been filled with evil things, and my very life hath approached and reached Sheol. Lift me
                  up from destruction, my God, like Jonah from beneath the sea and save me.</p>
               <p>Thou passedst wisely through the grievous storm<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">χειμών</foreign>.</note> of this perturbed world, holding the definition of
                  the orthodox faith, and now in heaven thou dwellest with the saints because thou showedst
                  thyself a strenuous defender of the teachings that are full of life, O blessed one. <pb n="466"
                  />
               </p>
               <p>In knowledge and in a life of virtue, as in these two things<note type="footnote" n="1198"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Sic Syr.</note> thou didst glitter and shine brightly, while thou wast eminent
                  in all things, and didst urge all nations to come to the faith and diligently admonish everyone
                  with thy sound words, O blessed one.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>"Blessed art thou"<note type="footnote" n="1199" resp="#ebrooks">Dan. iii,
                  52.</note>.</head>
               <p>Once that tyrant commanded and provided the furnace to be heated in the plain of Dura to burn
                  those who feared God, the furnace in which the three boys, having been made like to the one
                  God, uttered a triple song of praise and said, "God of our saintly fathers, blessed art
                  thou"<note type="footnote" n="2" resp="#ebrooks">Dan. iii, 52.</note>.</p>
               <p>When Marcian once set up the evil invocation of two natures to overthrow the orthodox,
                  thereby, our father, thou becamest more illustrious in that thou didst urge and teach all men
                  to cry and say, "God of our saintly fathers, blessed art thou".</p>
               <p>Thou showedst thyself an approved one among the doctors, O saintly Severus, and with them
                  thou didst profess and proclaim and fill the world with the right doctrines and saidst, "The
                  Son, the Word who became <pb n="467"/> incarnate, is one nature and hypostasis" and taughtest
                  us to cry and to say, "God of our saintly fathers, blessed art thou".</p>
            </div>
            <head>"Bless, all ye"<note type="footnote" n="1200" resp="#ebrooks">Dan. iii, 90.</note>.</head>
            <p>Praise him who was glorified on the holy mountain, and in the flame in the bush figured
               beforehand and showed to Moses by a miracle the mystery of the Virgin, the Lord of all, and
               exalt him without ceasing for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>Praise him who bestowed such a luminary upon his church, one who stood forth as an
               advocate<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >συνήγορος</foreign>.</note> of the right doctrines, and in all his contests was shown as
               victor, the Lord of all.</p>
            <p>Thou becamest a teacher of the apostolic faith, and a subverter of the heresy that is full of
               impiety, thou who didst never divide Christ the Son, but who didst confess him. Praise the Lord
               of all.</p>
            <div>
               <head>"My soul magnifieth"<note type="footnote" n="1201" resp="#ebrooks">Luke I, 46.</note>. </head>
               <p>Thee we confess to be verily the God-bearer in whom we have been saved <pb n="468"/> and
                  delivered, O pure Virgin, and<note type="footnote" n="1202" resp="#ebrooks">Ms. om.</note>
                  together with the bodiless hosts we all magnify thee.</p>
               <p>We who have been enlightened through thee proclaim thee to be verily the teacher of
                  orthodoxy, and therefore the church and all its children honou-reth the day of thy
                  commemoration.</p>
               <p>Truly thou art the invariable image of all the orthodox teachers, carrying their doctrine and
                  their manner of life at the same time, saintly Severus.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
