<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
        <div>
           <div n="1">
              <p>In the year 180 kings began to rule in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.</p>
              <note type="section">The year 180, <abbr>i.e.</abbr> of the <persName>Greeks</persName>, of the <persName>Seleucidae</persName>, or of the
                 <persName>Syro-Macedonians</persName>, coincides, says <persName>Assemani</persName>, with B.C. 129. <persName>Dionysius</persName> places the
                 commencement of <placeName>the Edessene kingdom</placeName> in B.C. 136, or, as he calls it, in the year of
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2202">Abraham</persName> 1880.----"The year 1880 of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2202">Abraham</persName>, there began to reign over <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> (Urhoi) the
                 first <persName>King Orhoi</persName>, son of <persName>Hevia</persName>, five years, and after his name it was called <persName>Urhoi</persName>." No
                 great antiquity is ascribed to the name of the city by this version of its story.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="2">
              <p>In the year 266 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2238">Augustus Caesar</persName> was made emperor.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="3">
              <p>In the year 309 our Lord was born.</p>
              <note type="section">The chronicle of Edessa says, "In the year 309 our Lord was born," <abbr>i.e.</abbr>, in
                 the forty-fourth of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2238">Augustus</persName>. See Pagi in <title>Apparatu</title>, No. 157.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="4">
              <p>In the year 400 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> the king built a mausoleum for himself.</p>
              <note>The Syriac is remarkable. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> "built 
                 a <hi rend="italic">naphsho</hi> in  honour of his death." The 
                 word <hi rend="italic">naphsho</hi>  is usually translated "soul," or " self," but 
                 is said sometimes to denote a sepulchre or mausoleum. Perhaps the word should 
                 be <hi rend="italic">nauso</hi>, a shrine or temple. <persName>Assemani</persName> says this 
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> Bar Ajazat, the nineteenth King of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>. <persName>Bayer</persName> thinks he 
                 was old when he began to reign, because he built a mausoleum 
                 for himself. <title>Bibl. Or.</title>, i., 421; Bayer, <title>Hist. Osrhoena</title>, 
                 p. 147.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="5">
              <p>In the year 449 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/616">Marcion</persName> forsook the Catholic Church.</p>
              <note type="section"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/616">Marcion</persName> is joined with <persName>Manetes</persName> in the extracts from the Syriac Chronicle quoted in
                 <title>Syriac Miscellanies</title>, p. 87. "In the year 448, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/616">Marcion</persName> and <persName>Manetes</persName>, heretics
                 in <placeName>Phrygia</placeName>, were famous." This is a year earlier than the date above given.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="6">
              <p>The year 465, in the month Tammuz, on the eleventh day <abbr>i.e.</abbr>, July 11th, 154
                 A.D.), <persName>Bardesanes</persName> was born.</p>
              <note type="section">Other dates have been given for <persName>Bardesanes</persName>. Thus in <title>Syriac Miscellanies</title>, p.
                 87, we read that <persName>Bardesanes</persName>, who promulgated the doctrine of <persName>Valentinus</persName>, was famous or
                 flourished in the year 479. If he were only born in 465 (A.D. 154) this can hardly be
                 correct; but other authorities clearly imply an earlier date than that of the Edessene
                 Chronicle.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="7">
              <p><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2288">Lucius Caesar</persName>, with his brother, subjugated the Parthians to the <persName>Romans</persName> in the fifth
                 year of his reign.</p>
              <note type="section">This event really occupies an earlier place in the chronicle under the year 449,
                 which <persName>Assemani</persName> says is wrong, and he has therefore corrected it.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="8">
              <p> 8. In the year 513, in the reign of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2302">Severus</persName>, and in the reign of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> the king, son of
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2291">Maano the king</persName>, in the month Tishrin the latter (<abbr>i.e.,</abbr>, November), the fountain
                 of water which proceeds from the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2579">great palace</placeName> of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> the great king increased, and it
                 prevailed, and it went up according to its former manner, and overflowed and ran out on
                 all sides, so that the courts and the porches and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2583">the royal houses</placeName> began to be filled
                 with water. And when our lord <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> the king saw it, he went up to the level ground on
                 the hill above his palace, where dwell and reside those who do the work for the
                 government. And while <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2220">the wise men</persName> considered what to do to the waters which had so
                 greatly increased, it happened that there was a great and violent rain in the night, and
                 <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/191">the Daisan (river)</placeName> came, neither in its day, nor in its month. And strange waters came;
                 and they encountered the <hi rend="italics">cataracts</hi>(? flood gates) which were fastened with great
                 pieces of iron which were overlaid upon them, and with bars of iron which supported
                 them. But not prevailing against them, the waters rose like a great sea beyond the walls
                 of the city. And the waters began to come down from the apertures of the wall into the
                 city. And <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> the king stood on the great tower which was called that of the <persName>Persians</persName>,
                 and saw the water by the light of torches, and he commanded, and they took away the
                 gates and the eight <hi rend="italics">cataracts</hi>(? flood-gates) of the western wall of the city
                 where the river flowed out. But that very hour the waters broke down the western wall of
                 the city, and entered the city, and overthrew the great and beautiful palace of our lord
                 the king, and they carried away everything that was found before them, the desirable and
                 beautiful edifices of the city, whatever <pb n="31"/>
                 was near the river on the south and on the north of it. And they destroyed the temple of
                 <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2580">the church of the Christians</placeName>. And there were killed by that occurrence more than
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2228">two thousand men</persName>, upon many of whom as they slept in the night the waters came suddenly, and
                 they were drowned, and the city was filled with the sound of lamentation.</p>
              <p> And when <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> the king saw this destruction which had befallen, he commanded that all
                 the craftsmen of the city should remove their cottages (or huts) from near the river,
                 and that no man should build near the river any cottage. And by the wisdom of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2230">measurers and men of skill</persName>
                 the cottages were placed so that the breadth of the river might be
                 increased, and they added to its former measure. For if the waters were many and strong,
                 the width of the river was too small to receive the water of twenty-five brooks with
                 what they gathered from all sides. And <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> the king commanded that 
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2231">all who lived in the porch</persName>, and were occupied over against the river, from Tishrin the former to Nisan
                 (October to April), should not lodge in their cottages, except <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2232">the islanders</persName> (Gazireans)
                 who kept the city, five of whom should lodge on the wall above the place where the
                 waters entered the city all the time of winter, and when they perceived by night and
                 heard the sound of strange waters, which began to enter the city, and whoever heard the
                 sound and neglected it, and did not publish it, behold the waters should drown the
                 contempt of him that despised the command of the king. And this commandment was decreed
                 from this time wherein it was so to the end of the world.</p>
              <p> Our lord <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> the king commanded, and there was built for him a building for his royal
                 house----a winter house at Tabara ----and there he dwelt all the time of winter; and in
                 summer he came down to the new palace which was built for him at the fountain head. And
                 his nobles also built for themselves buildings to live in, in the neighbourhood in which
                 the king was, in the high street (?) which is called <placeName>Beth Saharoye</placeName>. And in order to
                 restore the welfare of the former city, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> the king commanded, and the tributes due
                 from those within, and from those who dwelt in towns, and in hamlets, were remitted: and
                 tribute was not demanded from them for five years, until the city was enriched with men,
                 and was crowned with buildings.</p>
              <p> Now <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2313">Mar Yahab Bar Shemesh</persName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2285">Kajuma Bar Magartat</persName>, the scribes of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, recorded this
                 event, and the command of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> the king: and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2239">Bar Din</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2243">Bulid</persName>, who are prefects over
                 the archives of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, received and deposited it within them as trusted of the city
                 (<abbr>i.e.,</abbr>, archivists.) <pb n="32"/>#nbsp.</p>
              <note type="section"><persName>Dionysius</persName> places this flood in A.D. 216.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="9">
              <p>And in the year 517, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2201">Abgar</persName> built a palace in his own citadel (? town).</p>
              <note type="section">This palace probably stood upon the hill where the citadel of modern <placeName>Urfah</placeName> now
                 stands.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="10">
              <p>The year 551 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/608">Manes</persName> was born.<note type="footnote">See <title>Syrian Miscellanies</title>, p. 87; 
                 <quote>In the year 448, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/616">Marcion</persName> and <persName>Manetes</persName> (<abbr>i.e.</abbr>, Manichaeus), heretics in <placeName>Phrygia</placeName>, 
                    were famous (<abbr>i.e.,</abbr>, flourished);</quote> and again, 
                 <quote>In the year 573 arose the deceiver <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/608">Manes</persName>.</quote></note></p>
           </div>
           <div n="11">
              <p>The year 614, were broken down the walls of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> the second time in the days of
                 <persName>Diocletian</persName> the king.<note type="footnote">At the end we read, 
                    <quote>And again a second time were broken down its walls, in the days of 
                       <persName>Diocletian</persName> who was king,----the year 614, in the month Iyar (May).</quote></note>.</p>
              <note type="section">This overthrow of the walls in 303 was also caused by a flood, as shewn by <persName>Dionysius</persName>
                 in his chronicle, and as stated below. The account of <persName>Dionysius</persName>, as quoted by <persName>Assemani</persName>,
                 is to this effect,----" In the year 614 of <persName>Alexander</persName>, <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> was taken by the waters,
                 and its eastern walls were broken down and fell, and (the river) carried away and
                 removed all that was in it; and the flood made great havoc in it, both upon men and
                 cattle, and in all the plain of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> and <placeName>Haran</placeName>." <pb n="41"/></note>
           </div>
           <div n="12">
              <p>In the year 624, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2247">Conon</persName> the bishop laid the foundations of the Church of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>; and
                 <persName>Sha'ad</persName>, the bishop who came after him, built and finished the structure.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="13">
              <p>In the year 635, the cemetery of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> was built, in the days of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/326">Ethalaha</persName> the
                 bishop, the year before the great synod of <placeName>Nicea</placeName> was held.</p>
              <note type="section">This cemetery is perhaps the first on record constructed for the special use of
                 Christians.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="14">
              <p>The year 635, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/326">Ethalaha</persName> became bishop in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>; and he constructed the cemetery, and
                 the eastern side<note type="footnote"><persName>Assemani</persName> says <quote>southern side,</quote> 
                    and we may guess why.</note> of the church.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="15">
              <p>And the year after, a synod of three hundred and eighteen bishops was assembled at
                 <placeName>Nicea</placeName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="16">
              <p>The year 639, there was building and enlargement in the church of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="17">
              <p>In the year 649, died Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/811">Jacob</persName>, bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2351">Nisibis</placeName>.</p>
              <note type="section"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/811">Jacob of Nisibis</persName> was one of the most famous of the bishops of his time. He was at
                 the council of <placeName>Nicea</placeName>, and so was <persName>Ethilhas</persName> or <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/326">Ethalaha</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="18">
              <p>The year 657, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2202">Abraham</persName> became bishop in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, and he built the house (or church) of
                 the Confessors.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="19">
              <p>The year 660, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2249">Constantius</persName>, the son of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1655">Constantine</persName>, built the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="20">
              <p>And in the year 661, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2249">Constantius</persName> built <placeName>Tela</placeName>, a city which was before called
                 Antipolis.</p>
              <note type="section"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2249">Constantius</persName> is said to have built <placeName>Tela</placeName>, but probably he restored or enlarged it, and
                 called it <placeName>Constantina</placeName>. <persName>Dionysius</persName> refers this restoration to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1655">Constantine</persName>. <persName>Assemani</persName> says
                 the new name was <placeName>Constantina</placeName>, and not <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, as <persName>Dionysius</persName> affirms.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="21">
              <p>The year 667, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2202">Abraham</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3056">Chidon</placeName>, a recluse, became (bishop).</p>
              <note type="section"><placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3056">Chidon</placeName> was not far from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="22">
              <p>In the year 670, <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/502">Nicomedia</placeName> was overthrown.</p>
              <note type="section">This happened in consequence of an earthquake, at the very time a council was being
                 held in the city. The bishops removed to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/174">Seleucia</placeName>, in <placeName>Isauria</placeName>, and finished their
                 business there.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="23">
              <p>In the year 672, Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2202">Abraham</persName>, bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, left the world.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="24">
              <p>And in the same year, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2312">Vologesh</persName>, bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2351">Nisibis</placeName>, departed from this world.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="25">
              <p>And in the same year came <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2241">Barses</persName>, the bishop from <placeName>Haran</placeName> to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> by command of the
                 king (<abbr>i.e.,</abbr>, the emperor <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2249">Constantius</persName>, then in that region).</p>
              <note type="section"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2241">Barses</persName> seems to have been translated from <placeName>Haran</placeName> to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> simply by the command of
                 the emperor.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="26">
              <p>And in the year 674, in the month Haziran (June), <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2283">Julian</persName> went down and made war with
                 the <persName>Persians</persName>, and died there.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="27">
              <p>In the year 675, in the month Shebat (February), <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2310">Valentinian</persName> the Great became king,
                 and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2309">Valens</persName> his brother. <pb n="33"/>#nbsp.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="28">
              <p>In the year 678, Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/834">Julian Saba</persName> departed from the world.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="29">
              <p>The year 681, was built the great <hi rend="italic">Beth-ma'amuditho</hi>(House of Baptizing) of
                 <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.</p>
              <note type="section">The great baptistery may have stood where Mr. Badger says a mosque now
                 stands,----"The mosque called <placeName>Oloor Jamesi</placeName> was an old Christian church, as is evident
                 from the hexangular belfry which is now converted into a minaret, and from the lower
                 parts of the building. As in the case of the <placeName>Great Mosque at Diarbekir</placeName>, the nave of the
                 church has been turned into a court-yard, in which a fountain has been introduced for
                 the religious ablutions of the Mussulmans; and the southern wall of the church is now
                 the northern wall of the mosque. The fountain is surmounted by a dome raised upon four
                 Corinthian pillars taken from some more ancient building." (Nestorians, i., 326). May
                 not the fountain be really of ancient origin?</note>
           </div>
           <div n="30">
              <p>In the year 684, in the month Haziran (June), on the ninth in it, departed from the
                 world Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName> "of his wisdoms" (= the wise).</p>
              <note type="section">The grave of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName>, or rather his tomb in a cave, is still shewn at <placeName>Urfah</placeName>, and
                 upon it the <persName>Jacobites</persName> consecrate the Eucharistic elements.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="31">
              <p>And in the month Elul (September) of that year, the people departed from the church
                 of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, through the persecution of the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2211">Arians</persName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="32">
              <p>In the year 689, in the month Adar, Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2241">Barses</persName>, bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, departed from the
                 world.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="33">
              <p>And on the twenty-seventh day in the mouth Canun the former (December), of the same
                 year, the orthodox came in and recovered the church of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.</p>
              <note type="section">Certainly not in the same year as the death of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2241">Barses</persName>. It is not clear when these
                 years begin. They are usually supposed to begin Sept. 1, but our author seems to have
                 some other day, as several of his entries suggest. Above in No. 31 he reckons September,
                 as in the same year with the preceding June. <persName>Assemani</persName> says this belongs to the year 690.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="34">
              <p>And in those days Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1718">Eulogius</persName> became bishop in the year that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2271">Theodosius</persName> the Great
                 became king; and that Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1718">Eulogius</persName> built the house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2257">Daniel</persName>, which was called the
                 house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2258">Demet</persName>.</p>
              <note type="section">Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2258">Demet</persName> is rendered by <persName>Assemani</persName> as if it were a contraction of <placeName>Domitius</placeName>, <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">Domus
                 Mar <persName>Domitii</persName>.</foreign>.</quote> He prints it in italics, apparently as if in doubt. The vowels are
                 as we give them, and therefore we prefer to think <persName>Demetrius</persName> is meant, both here
                 and elsewhere (<title>B. O.</title>, i., 215).</note>
           </div>
           <div n="35">
              <p>The year 692, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2271">Theodosius</persName> the Great built in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/145">Osrhoene</placeName> the city <placeName>Resaina</placeName>.</p>
              <note type="section"><placeName>Resaina</placeName> signifies Fountain-head, and was restored by <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2271">Theodosius</persName>. <pb n="42"/></note>
           </div>
           <div n="36">
              <p>The year 693, was gathered the synod of one hundred and fifty bishops in
                 <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>.</p>
              <note type="section">The second general council in A.D. 381. It began in October, hence the author
                 assigns it to 693, and not 692; <persName>Assemani</persName> at least puts it in October, with which however
                 others do not agree. <persName>Socrates</persName> assigns it to May; and the very ancient MS. quoted in
                 <title>Syriac Miscellanies</title>(A.D. 500) refers it to August. So also the Syriac
                 Chronicle quoted, in <title>Syriac Miscellanies</title>, p. 89. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1718">Eulogius</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> attended the
                 council.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="37">
              <p>In the year 698, Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1718">Eulogius</persName> the bishop departed from the world on the Friday of
                 the crucifixion.</p>
              <note type="section"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1718">Eulogius</persName> died on Good Friday.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="38">
              <p>The year 705, in the month Ab (August), on the twenty-second day in it, they brought
                 the <foreign xml:lang="en">glossocom</foreign> (<abbr>i.e.,</abbr>, coffin) of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2123">Mar Thomas the Apostle</persName> to his great temple
                 in the days of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2253">Cyrus</persName> the bishop.</p>
              <note type="section">It does not appear where they obtained the relics of <persName>the Apostle</persName>. They were,
                 however, deposited in "his great temple," <abbr>i.e.,</abbr>, a church dedicated to his name,
                 or called after him.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="39">
              <p>In the year 706, and on the seventeenth of Canun the latter (January), departed from
                 the world <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2271">Theodosius</persName> the great king; and on the twenty-seventh in Nisan (April),
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2266">Arcadius</persName> entered <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>; and on the eighth in Tishrin the latter (November), the
                 body of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2271">Theodosius</persName> entered <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="40">
              <p>And in the month of Tammuz (July) of the same year, the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2224">Huns</persName> crossed over to the
                 territory of the <persName>Romans</persName>.</p>
              <note type="section">This invasion of the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2224">Huns</persName> or <persName>Asiatic Tartars</persName> (A.D. 395) was probably the first in
                 that direction; it was not the last.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="41">
              <p>In the year 707, in the month Tammuz (July), on its twenty-second, departed from the
                 world Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2253">Cyrus</persName>, bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="42">
              <p>And in the year 708 Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2304">Silvanus</persName> became bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="43">
              <p>In the year 710, on the seventeenth of Tishrin the former (October), Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2304">Silvanus</persName>,
                 bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, departed from the world.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="44">
              <p>And on the twenty-third of the month Tishrin the latter <pb n="34"/> (November) of that year, Mar <persName>Pakida</persName> became bishop in
                 <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="45">
              <p>And in that year arose <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/573">Johanan Chrysostomos</persName>, bishop in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="46">
              <p>The year 714 began <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/780">Theodorus</persName>, bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2345">Mompsesta</placeName>, to expound the Scriptures.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="47">
              <p>The year 715, '<persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/16">Absamia</persName> Kashisha(presbyter), son of the sister of the blessed
                 Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName>, composed madroshé(poems?) and discourses upon the coming of the
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2224">Huns</persName> to the territory of the <persName>Romans</persName>.</p>
              <note type="section">The Madrashé of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/16">Absamia</persName> may have been poems, but the word is also used of prose.
                 <persName>Assemani</persName> says <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">odas et sermones composuit.</foreign></quote></note>
           </div>
           <div n="48">
              <p>The year 720, Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2262">Diogenes</persName> became bishop in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, and he began to build the house
                 of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2240">Barlaha</persName>.</p>
              <note type="section">Who was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2240">Barlaha</persName>, "the son of God?" A writer of the name copied <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName>'s works in
                 A.D. 551, and is spoken of by <persName>Assemani</persName> as an "egregius scriptor." <title>B. O.</title>, i., 83.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="49">
              <p>And in that year, in the <foreign xml:lang="la">neomenia</foreign> of Ab (August), Mar <persName>Pakida</persName>, bishop of
                 <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, departed from the world.</p>
              <note type="section">The Syriac text has the word <foreign xml:lang="la">neomenia</foreign></note>
           </div>
           <div n="50">
              <p>The year 721, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/430">Cyrillus</persName> became bishop in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2620">Alexandria</placeName> the great.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="51">
              <p>The year 723, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/26">Rabula</persName> became bishop in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>. And he built the house of Mar
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1710">Stephanus</persName>, which had been formerly a house of Sabbath (synagogue) of the Jews. Now he
                 built it by command of the king.</p>
              <note type="section">This adaptation of a Jewish synagogue for Christian worship at the emperor's
                 bidding, was probably an act of spoliation perpetrated upon the Jews.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="52">
              <p>The year 724, the walls of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> were again broken down by water the third time, in
                 the days of <persName>Honorius</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2266">Arcadius</persName> the victorious kings.<note type="footnote"></note>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="53">
              <p>The year 732, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/482">Eutychius</persName> the monk arose, who rejected the incarnation.</p>
              <note type="section">The Eutychian heresy began later than A.D. 421, and probably later than 431 by a few
                 years at least. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/482">Eutyches</persName> affirmed that there was but one nature in <persName>Christ</persName>, and there are
                 many Monophysites to this day.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="54">
              <p>At that time the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1296">Jacob</persName>, the mutilated, was a martyr.</p>
              <note type="section">Possibly <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1296">Jacob</persName> the "mutilated," had misunderstood and misapplied Matthew xix. 12.
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1296">Jacob</persName> was, however, doubtless a real martyr; as he was certainly a famous one.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="55">
              <p>The year 739, the heresy of those who say that sin is implanted in nature, became
                 known.</p>
              <note type="section"><persName>Assemani</persName> understands this to allude to the heresy of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/780">Theodore</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2345">Mopsuestia</placeName>, and
                 thinks the writer favoured him and <persName>Pelagius</persName>, from the form in which he puts the record.
                 The orthodox held that "sin was implanted in nature;" it was the heterodox who
                 maintained that it was not. The scribe then makes the orthodox the heretics.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="56">
              <p>The year 740, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/891">Andrew</persName>, bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2607">Samosata</placeName>, became famous.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="57">
              <p>The year 741, dust came down from heaven.</p>
              <note type="section">A shower of dust at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> must have been a rare event.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="58">
              <p>The year 742, was assembled the first synod at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/623">Ephesus</placeName>.</p>
              <note type="section">For 742 the MS. had 744, which <persName>Assemani</persName> corrected.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="59">
              <p>The year 746, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/26">Rabula</persName>, bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, departed from the world on the eighth of Ab
                 (August), and the great <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/534">Hiba</persName> became (bishop) instead of him. He built the new church
                 which now is called the house of the apostles.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="60">
              <p>The year 749, in. the days of the excellent <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/534">Hiba</persName>, Senator brought a great table of
                 silver, in which were seven hundred and twenty pounds (of silver), and it was put in the
                 old church of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>. <pb n="35"/>#nbsp.</p>
              <note type="section">The weight of the table offered by Senator is put down at 
                 720 litra, the same as the Latin <foreign xml:lang="la">libra,</foreign> a pound of about twelve 
                 ounces <foreign xml:lang="fr">avoirdupois</foreign>. This would make
                 about 540 lbs. <foreign xml:lang="fr">avoirdupois</foreign>.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="61">
              <p>The year 753, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2204">Anatolius</persName>, the <foreign>stratelates</foreign>(military commander) made a coffin
                 of silver, in honour of the bones of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2123">Thomas</persName> the holy apostle.</p>
              <note type="section">In the Syriac we read that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2204">Anatol</persName> the <foreign>Stratelates</foreign> made 
                 a <foreign>nauso</foreign> of
                 silver. The name <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2204">Anatol</persName> is, of course, a shortened form of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2204">Anatolius</persName>,----proper names
                 are frequently abbreviated in this
                 chronicle, but we have not always indicated the fact. The <foreign xml:lang="la">Nauso</foreign> seems to be a
                 mere variation of <foreign>Naos,</foreign> a temple or shrine. Christianity was now looking up the
                 trappings of exploded idolatry. The reader will be reminded of the silver shrines of
                 Artemis in Acts xix. 24, where the Greek has this very word, and so has the Syriac
                 Peshito. The other word <foreign>Stratelates</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατηλάτης.</foreign>, a commander of soldiers, is as old as <persName>Sophocles</persName> and
                 <persName>Euripides</persName>.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="62">
              <p>The year 756, <persName>Dioscurus</persName> became bishop in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2620">Alexandria</placeName> the great.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="63">
              <p>And there was assembled again at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/623">Ephesus</placeName> another synod. This anathematized the great
                 <persName>Flavianus</persName> bishop of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2264">Domnus</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/847">Irenaeus</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/195">Tyre</placeName>, and
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/534">Hiba</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2280">Eusebius</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2572">Dorylaeum</placeName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2257">Daniel</persName> of <placeName>Haran</placeName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2306">Sophronius</persName> of <placeName>Tela</placeName>,
                 and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/781">Theodoret</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/65">Cyrus</placeName>.</p>
              <note type="section">The second synod of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/623">Ephesus</placeName>, says <persName>Assemani</persName>, was held, not in 756, but in 760, or
                 A.D. 449. Although <persName>Ibas</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> was anathematised on that occasion, the fact is
                 recorded without a remark. The bishop, we are told in the following article, left <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>
                 on January 1st, 759; if, however, the synod was held in 760, the bishop could not have
                 been removed till the next year. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nounus</persName>, called <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nono</persName> in the Syriac text, "made a
                 <foreign>hierateion</foreign> in the church." A <quote><foreign>hierateion</foreign></quote> is a 
                 <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">locus sacer ac venerandus, tabulate inclusus, clericis tantum, viris saecularibus raro, mulieribus
                 nunquam penetrabilis</foreign>.</quote></note>
           </div>
           <div n="64">
              <p>The year 759, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/534">Hibas</persName> the bishop departed from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> on the first day in the month
                 Canun the latter (January 1), and on the twenty-first day of the month Tammuz (July),
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nonnus</persName> came in in his stead, and continued two years, and made a <foreign>hierateion
                 </foreign> (sacristy) in the church.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="65">
              <p>Anno 760, arose <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2299">Leo</persName> bishop in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/166">Rome</placeName>.</p>
              <note type="section">This reference to a <quote>bishop <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/166">Rome</placeName></quote> (as the Syriac has it), 
                 is the first and only indication given by the chronicle that there were bishops there at all. From first
                 to last there is no sign of dependence upon <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/166">Rome</placeName>, or of any connection with it.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="66">
              <p>Anno 762, a synod was assembled in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622">Chalcedon</placeName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="67">
              <p>An. 763, Mar <persName>Isaac</persName>, a composer (an author) and abbot (or Archimandrite) was famous.</p>
              <note type="section">Mar <persName>Isaac</persName> is called an Archimandrite by <persName>Assemani</persName>, but the Syriac is "head of a
                 convent," or monastery,----the Greek word is not used.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="68">
              <p>An. 769, in the month Tishriu the former (October), on the twenty-eighth, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/534">Hiba</persName>,
                 bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, went to rest; and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nonnus</persName> came into his place, and built the house of
                 Mar <persName>Johanan the Baptist</persName>, and (he constructed) a place for poor invalids, outside the
                 gate of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2601">Beth Shemesh</placeName>; and in the place for the poor he built the house of martyrs to Mar
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1650">Cosma</persName> and Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1669">Damian</persName>. Now he built also convents and towers, and made bridges, and
                 levelled the roads.</p>
              <note type="section"><persName>Ibas</persName> was restored and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nonnus</persName> removed; but when <persName>Ibas</persName> died <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nonnus</persName> resumed episcopal
                 functions. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nonnus</persName> was no doubt a zealous churchman, for he not only made a sacristy in
                 the church, he built <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2599">the Church of John the Baptist</placeName>, etc. As <persName>Assemani</persName> renders it, he
                 also built a "nosocomium pauperum invalidorum extra portam Beth-Semes." The Syriac is
                 here peculiar, and might be rendered "the field of the house of poor invalids."
                 <persName>Michaelis</persName> says "videtur significare hortos, subdio sed porticibus cinctos, in quibus
                 obambulari aegroti poterant." Within this inclosure <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nonnus</persName> built a church. His
                 philanthropy and religious zeal further appear in his erection of convents, towers and
                 bridges, and in the improvement of the highways. These things certainly indicate wealth,
                 influence and public spirit.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="69">
              <p>In the year 771, departed the blessed Simeon of "his column" (Stylites) from the
                 world, on Elul the second (September 2), on Wednesday (the fourth day in the week), the
                 time the eleventh hour.</p>
              <note type="section">The death of this famous enthusiast, whom <persName>Assemani</persName> calls "Sanctissimum Stylitam," is
                 said to have happened in the year 770, or A.D. 459. So the Chronicle quoted in <title>Syriac
                    Miscellanies</title>(p. 83), <quote>In 730 Mar Simeon ascended the pillar, and in 770 he died
                 on the 2nd of Elul.</quote></note>
           </div>
           <div n="70">
              <p>The year 777, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2270">Leo</persName> built <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/109">Callinicns</placeName> in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/145">Osrhoene</placeName>, and named it after his own name
                 <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/109">Leontopolis</placeName>; and set in it also a bishop.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="71">
              <p>An. 782, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nonnus</persName>, bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, rested, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2253">Cyrus</persName> became (bishop) in his stead.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="72">
              <p>An. 795, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2287">Leontios</persName> rebelled against <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2273">Zeno</persName>, and reigned in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName> two years.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="73">
              <p>An. 800, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2225">the school of the Persians</persName> was eradicated from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="74">
              <p>An. 809, the (tribute of) gold was remitted to the artificers in all the land, in
                 the month Iyar (May).</p>
              <note type="section">All artificers were required to pay a tax of one <foreign xml:lang="la">Aureus</foreign>
                 <pb n="44"/> every fourth year. The taxes levied are
                 enumerated in the extracts given by <persName>Assemani</persName> (<title>B. O.</title>, i., 268), and are very
                 curious, including horses, oxen, mules, asses, dogs, beggars, and dunghills.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="75">
              <p>And on the sixth in the month Haziran (June), <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2253">Cyrus</persName>, bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, rested, and
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2297">Peter</persName> became (bishop) in his stead, <pb n="36"/> and he
                 entered <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> on the twelfth of Elul (September) of the same year.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="76">
              <p>An. 810, many locusts appeared, but did no great damage that year: but the herbage
                 grew again. And there was a great earthquake. And the warm bath of the <persName>Iberians</persName> failed
                 three days. And the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2574">Nicopolis</placeName> was overthrown, and buried in it all its
                 inhabitants, save the temple, and the bishop, and two Syncelli (sons of his cell). And a
                 sign that was like a spear appeared in heaven many days, in the month Canun the latter
                 (January).</p>
              <note type="section">The <foreign xml:lang="la">Syncelli</foreign> were the personal attendants and assistants of the bishop.
                 <persName>Assemani</persName> overlooks in his translation the clause about the sign which appeared in the
                 sky, and which was probably a comet.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="77">
              <p>Now <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName> the king deposed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2277">Euphemius</persName>, bishop of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, from his place,
                 and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2696">Macedon</persName> became bishop in his stead.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="78">
              <p>An. 811, many locusts came and destroyed and devoured all the produce.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="79">
              <p>An. 813, a great fire appeared on the side of the north, which blazed all night on
                 the twenty-second of Ab (August).</p>
              <note type="section">The great fire in the north was no doubt the <foreign xml:lang="la">aurora borealis.</foreign> From this
                 record we should infer that it is seldom seen in those parts.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="80">
              <p>An. 814, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2286">Cavades</persName>, king of the <persName>Persians</persName>, encamped against <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, a <placeName>city of Beth
                 Naharotha</placeName> (Mesopotamia), on the fifth day in the month Tishrin the former (October), and
                 fought with it, and took it in ninety-seven days.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="81">
              <p>And in the month Elul (September) of that year, he came and encamped against <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>,
                 and by the grace of God, did it no harm, except that he burnt the house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1466">Sergius</persName>
                 and the northern basilica of <foreign>Beth-maudiné</foreign>(the House of Confessors, see above,
                 No. 18..</p>
           </div>
           <div n="82">
              <p>An. 821, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2297">Peter</persName>, bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, rested on the day of the Sabbath of the
                 resurrection (Saturday, April 10, 510 A.D.), and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2296">Paul</persName> was appointed instead of him.</p>
              <note type="section">The sabbath of the resurrection is, of course, the day before Easter Sunday. In the
                 tables of lessons appended by <persName>Widmanstadt</persName> to his Syriac Testament, the day after Good
                 Friday is called the "sabbath of the annunciation."</note>
           </div>
           <div n="83">
              <p>And in the year twenty-one of the reign of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastus</persName> (<persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName>), he commanded them
                 to open the coffin of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/479">Euphemia</persName> the martyr, and to bring forth from thence the book which
                 the synod that was assembled at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622">Chalcedon</placeName> had put there, and to burn it; and there came
                 forth fire from thence, and smote upon the faces of those who wished to bring it out,
                 and because of this <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName> refrained from taking it away from thence and burning it.</p>
              <note type="section">The receptacle in question was probably the shrine of St. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/479">Euphemia</persName>. According to
                 <persName>Theophanes</persName>, the book was laid up in the altar, and was actually conveyed to the emperor.
                 The miracle was of course an after-thought.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="84">
              <p>But he removed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2696">Macedon</persName>, the bishop of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, because he did not
                 anathematize the synod, and Timothy became (bishop) instead of him.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="85">
              <p>And in the twenty-fourth of the same <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName> <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2311">Vitalian</persName> rebelled against him.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="86">
              <p>An. 829, in the month Tammuz (July), on the ninth, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName> the king departed from
                 the world, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268">Justin</persName> became (king) in his stead. <pb n="37"/>#nbsp.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="87">
              <p>And in the second year of the reign of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268">Justin</persName>, which was An. 830, he thrust out of
                 <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName> <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2302">Severus</persName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/44">Xenaias</persName> from <placeName>Mabug</placeName>, and everybody that received not the four
                 synods.</p>
              <note type="section">To this item <persName>Assemani</persName> appends the words "<foreign xml:lang="la">exilio mulctavit,"</foreign> probably because
                 he supposed this implied by the previous verb.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="88">
              <p>Now such was the care and concern of the friend of God, king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268">Justinian</persName>, that he
                 wrote in the <hi rend="italics">diptychs</hi> of the church the four holy synods, that is to say, that of
                 <placeName>Nicea</placeName>, and that of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, and the first of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/623">Ephesus</placeName>, and that of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622">Chalcedon</placeName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="89">
              <p>And in An. 831 came the patrician (or Patricius) to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> to remove <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2296">Paul</persName> in the
                 month Tishrin the latter (November) on the fourth, and he urged him to do one of two
                 things, either to receive the synod and continue on his seat, or if he would not be
                 persuaded he would remove him from his seat. But he was not persuaded to do one of
                 these, but fled and went in and stayed in the House of Baptism. Now when the patrician
                 (or Patricius) saw that he was unpersuaded to do one of these, and was afraid of the
                 command of the king, he was compelled to remove him from the House of Baptism, and
                 conveyed him to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/174">Seleucia</placeName>. And when the king heard that he had taken him from the House
                 of Baptism, he commanded that he should return to his seat, in hope that he would repent
                 and receive the synod. And <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2296">Paul</persName> re-entered his seat in forty-four days, and he was a
                 long time without receiving the synod, and when the king saw that he was not persuaded,
                 he sent him to Euchata. And <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2296">Paul</persName> departed from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> on Tammuz (July) 27, of the year
                 833, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2236">Asclepius</persName> was (bishop) instead of him, and entered <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> on the 23rd of
                 Tishrin the former (October), of the year 834, three months after <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2296">Paul</persName> the bishop
                 departed from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.<note type="footnote">Lower down, said to have been on 
                    Tuesday the eighteenth of March, and the name of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2271">Theodosius</persName> properly substituted 
                    for that of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2266">Arcadius</persName>, who had been dead five or six years.</note></p>
              <note type="section">This <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2296">Paul</persName> was Bishop of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> twice. The Syrians call him an "interpreter of
                 books," either because he translated out of Greek into Syriac, or because he wrote
                 expositions of Scripture. Respecting him <persName>Assemani</persName> gives an interesting extract from <persName>John</persName>
                 of <placeName>Asia</placeName> (or of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/623">Ephesus</placeName>) preserved by <persName>Dionysius</persName> in his Chronicle. The baptistery alluded
                 to in the text is probably the one mentioned above, number 29.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="90">
              <p>And in the month Canun the former (December), on the 24th in it, after the entering
                 of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2236">Asclepius</persName> the bishop to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, he expelled the Oriental monks, and all the monks
                 their allies who were like them, because they did not consent to the synod of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/622">Chalcedon</placeName>.</p>
              <note type="section">For "December" <persName>Assemani</persName> has "October" by mistake. Who were the <hi rend="italic">oriental</hi> monks
                 so summarily ejected? They were monophysites, but how came they to be styled "orientals"
                 at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>?</note>
           </div>
           <div n="91">
              <p>And in the year 836 many waters entered <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, the fourth time, and broke down the
                 walls of it, and overturned its dwellings and drowned its children, and made in it much
                 destruction.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="92">
              <p>And through this circumstance <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2236">Asclepius</persName> fled from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, and went up to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName> the
                 city to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2278">Euphrasius the patriarch</persName>, and he was there, more or less, seventy days, and he
                 died there in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName> on the 27th in the month Haziran of that year, and was buried
                 there in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>. And on the 4th in the month Elul of the same year they brought his
                 body from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName> and buried it at Beth Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2240">Barlaha</persName>, by Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nonnus</persName> the bishop. <pb n="38"/>#nbsp.</p>
              <note type="section">The remains of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2236">Asclepius</persName> were exhumed and transferred to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> to be buried in the
                 Church of St. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2240">Barlaha</persName>, <hi rend="italic">upon</hi> or <hi rend="italic">beside</hi> those of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nonnus</persName>.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="93">
              <p>And when <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2296">Paul</persName> heard that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2236">Asclepius</persName> was dead he repented and offered a petition to
                 Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName> the patrician (<foreign xml:lang="la">Patricius</foreign>), and he made also a <foreign xml:lang="la">libellum
                 </foreign> to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2278">Euphrasius the patriarch</persName>, and because of the <foreign xml:lang="la">libellum</foreign> that he made, and
                 because of the epistle of the illustrious and friend of God, Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName> the patrician
                 (<foreign xml:lang="la">Patricius</foreign>), he was returned and restored to his seat, and he entered <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>
                 on the 8th in Adar (March) of the year 837, eight months after the death of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2236">Asclepius</persName>.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="94">
              <p>Now <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2296">Paul</persName> the bishop lived after he returned to his seat the third time, eight months
                 <hi rend="italics">minus</hi> eight days; and on the 30th in the month Tishrin the former (October)
                 of the year 838 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2296">Paul</persName> the bishop rested.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="95">
              <p>And <persName>Andreas</persName> became (bishop) in his stead, and entered <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> on the 7th of the month
                 Shebat of the same year 838.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="96">
              <p>And in the year 837 in the month Iyar (May), on the 29th in it on Friday at the
                 seventh hour, there was a great and violent earthquake, and there fell by it much of
                 <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>, and overwhelmed its children, and suffocated its inhabitants.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="97">
              <p>And in that earthquake died also <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2278">Euphrasius the patriarch</persName>, and was buried under the
                 houses, and as they say he was crying out all day beneath the houses. Now after him
                 <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName> became bishop in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>, who had been <foreign xml:lang="la">Comes</foreign> of the East.</p>
              <note type="section"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName> 
                 of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName> is called <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">Comes Orientis</foreign>,</quote> a dignity which he appears not
                 to have retained, although <persName>Assemani</persName> passes over the verbs which we translate "had been."</note>
           </div>
           <div n="98">
              <p>An. 838 on day 1 in the month of Nisan, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Mar Justinian</persName> became Caesar, and on the 10th
                 in the month Ab of the same year king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268">Justinian</persName> (<persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268">Justin</persName>) rested, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Mar Justinian</persName>
                 reigned alone.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="99">
              <p>And in An. 839, in the month Tishrin the latter, on the 15th in it, a great fire
                 happened at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>, and burned much of what remained from the earthquake; but
                 whence the origin of the fire remains unknown.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="100">
              <p>An. 842, in the month Tammuz, came down Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2259">Demosthenes</persName> to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> to command the
                 Roman forces.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="101">
              <p>And in the month Canun the former of An. 843, on the 18th in the month, the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2224">Huns</persName>
                 entered the Roman territory, and plundered and wasted as far as <placeName>the country of the
                 Alepponians</placeName>, and to the <foreign>dodecaton</foreign>[twelfth milestone] from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>. And through
                 this affliction Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2259">Demosthenes</persName> fell sick and died at the city of <placeName>Tela</placeName>, on the 10th in
                 the month Canun the latter of the same year.</p>
              <note type="section">The <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2224">Huns</persName> who thus come upon the 
                 scene, it is needless to say, were <persName>Asiatic Tartars</persName>.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="102">
              <p>And in An. 843, in the month Elul of the same year, Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2300">Rufinus</persName> the patrician made
                 peace between the <persName>Persians</persName> and the <persName>Romans</persName>, and this peace was prolonged to the year 851.</p>
              <note type="section"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2300">Rufinus</persName> is 
                 called "patricius" or the patrician, a name borne by the presidents or
                 prefects of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>. (See Nos. 89, 93.)</note>
           </div>
           <div n="103">
              <p>And in An. 844, in the month Canun the former in that year, Mar <persName>Andreas</persName>, bishop,
                 departed from the world, and he <pb n="39"/> was
                 deposited at Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2240">Barlaha</persName>'s by the bones of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2292">Nonnus</persName> and Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2236">Asclepius</persName>; and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2203">Addi</persName> became
                 bishop instead of him, and entered <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> on the 28th in the month Ab of An. 844.</p>
           </div>
           <div n="104">
              <p>In An. 13 of the reign of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName>, which was the year 850, indiction <foreign>deutra</foreign>(the second), a sign like a spear appeared in heaven on the 5th of Tishrin the
                 former (October).</p>
              <note type="section">The word "indiction" occurs in the text. This mode of reckoning is often given in
                 old Syriac writers. <persName>Procopius</persName> <pb n="45"/> says that a
                 comet appeared in the thirteenth of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName>, and hence <persName>Assemani</persName> infers that for 850 we
                 should read 851 in the text.</note>
           </div>
           <div n="105">
              <p>And in the same year in the month Iyar (May) <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2244">Chosroes</persName> king of the <persName>Persians</persName> broke
                 the peace, and crossed over to the territory of the <persName>Romans</persName>, and laid waste <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/185">Shura</placeName>, and
                 Haleb (Aleppo) and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>, and also took possession of <placeName>Apamea</placeName>, and turned and came as
                 far as <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, but by the grace of God protecting it, he did no harm in it; but the
                 great men of the city brought out to him, and he took away two <foreign xml:lang="la">centenaria
                 </foreign>(hundreds of pounds <hi rend="italic">or</hi> talents) of gold, and he returned to his place.</p>
              <note type="section"><placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/185">Shura</placeName> or <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/185">Sura</placeName> is mentioned by <persName>Procopius</persName>, <title>De Aedific. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268">Justin</persName>,</title> ii. 9. See
                 Martiniere <abbr>sub voc.</abbr> Surum. <persName>D'Anville</persName> places it on <placeName>the Euphrates</placeName>, and with others
                 calls it <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/185">Sura</placeName>. <persName>Procopius</persName> terms it <foreign xml:lang="grc">Συρων πολισμα.</foreign> ----the town
                 of <placeName>Suron</placeName>. The Syriac word means usually <quote>a wall.</quote> Instead of two hundred pounds of gold,
                 or, as the Syriac text has it, <quote>two centenaria of gold,</quote> <persName>Assemani</persName> writes 
                 <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">duobus auri pondo</foreign>,</quote> but surely <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">pondo</foreign></quote> 
                 does not equal <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">centenaria</foreign>;</quote> probably we should read
                 <quote><foreign xml:lang="la">ducentis auri pondo</foreign>.</quote></note>
           </div>
           <div n="106">
              <p>As we learn from the former histories, behold the waters have four times broken down
                 the walls of the blessed [city] and overthrown its towers, and choked its children,
                 since Messiah ascended to his glorious Father. The first time its walls were broken down
                 was in the days of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2302">Severus</persName> the king of the <persName>Romans</persName>, which was An. 513, by the reckoning
                 of the <persName>Ionians (Greeks)</persName>, in the month Tishrin the latter. And the second time its walls
                 were broken down was in the days of <persName>Diocletian</persName> the king, which was the year 614 in the
                 month Iyar. And the third time its walls were broken down was in the days of <persName>Honorius</persName>
                 and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2271">Theodosius</persName> the illustrious kings, which was. An. 724 in the month Adar, on the 18th
                 in it, on the 3rd in the week (Tuesday), when Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/26">Rabula</persName> had become bishop in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.
                 And the fourth time they were broken down was in the days of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268">Justin</persName> the king, which was
                 the year 836, when <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2236">Asclepius</persName> had become bishop in 
                 <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>.<note type="footnote">Observe, July was in 833, and October in 834.</note><pb n="40"/></p>
              <note type="section">This Chronicle is followed in <persName>Assemani</persName> by a list of the kings of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, and a list
                 of its bishops from A.D. 313 to 769. We may note that the Chronicle mentions no Bishop
                 of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName> before <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2247">Conon</persName>, "who laid the foundation of the Church of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>" in A.D. 313.
                 But we must not misinterpret this indication. There had long been Christians in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>,
                 as authentic records prove. Not only so, this very Chronicle, in recording the overthrow
                 of the city by water in 513 (A.D. 202), mentions the destruction of the "temple of the
                 church of the Christians." This remarkable phrase shews not only that the disciples had
                 a house of worship then, but that it was called a temple. More than this, the Christian
                 community seems to monopolize the word Church, which was not yet applied to the building
                 in which they assembled. <persName>Assemani</persName> observes that the words under notice shew that the
                 Archivists were still heathen, although the king was a Christian, as <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2280">Eusebius</persName> notes from
                 <placeName>Africanus</placeName> (in <placeName>Chron</placeName>). <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2247">Conon</persName>, above-named, refounded the church at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>, and hoped to
                 rebuild it, but this work was accomplished by his successor. It can hardly be supposed
                 that the reference is to the restoration of the "temple" destroyed in A.D. 202; it is
                 rather to what is called "the old church" in number 60; restored by <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2268">Justinian</persName> with
                 immense splendour.---- (Vid. Bayer, p. 250).</note>
           </div>
        </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
