<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3095">To Oecumenius the Count</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Letters I to LXI</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">186 [14]-194 [22]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">12</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="2">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE SAME THE SECOND LETTER TO THE SAME OECUMENIUS THE COUNT
               UPON THE SAME MATTER, AND IT IS AMONG THOSE WRITTEN DURING EPISCOPACY. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0513" notAfter="0518">513-8</date>
            </dateline>
            <p>I wonder how it is that your God-loving magnificence has picked <pb n="15"/> up again from the
               beginning the contention that had been put to silence. While confessing Emmanuel to be of two
               natures, to suppose the elements of which he consists to be generalities covering many
               hypostases (this is what is meant by the property of a generality) is a thing that is very
               abominable and inept, and one that confirms the charge falsely disseminated against us by the
               impious: for we are found to be imagining two natures before the union according to their
               account; for there would be the whole of humanity and of course the Godhead also, even before
               the Humanization of the Word. And these matters would need further conversation by word of
               mouth, not written words in a letter, which are subject to considerations of brevity, and bring
               danger<note type="footnote" n="32" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >κίνδυνος</foreign>.</note> to the writer, wherever any unusual name or unelaborated phrase is
               inserted in the document. You know what words that lead to rocks you have used in your recent
               composition, and, though admitting that you do this as a concession, you have still done it. But
               to us, who by ordinance from above and mercy have attained to this priestly office, it does not
               bring honour to take such ill expressions in our mouth and consign them to writing: for it is
               written, <pb n="16"/> "The lips of a priest will guard knowledge, and they will ask law from his
               mouth"<note type="footnote" n="33" resp="#ebrooks">Mal. ii, 7.</note>. Wherefore Paul also, who
               was taken up to the third heaven, and heard ineffable words<note type="footnote" n="34">2 Corinthians
                  xii, 2-4.</note>, knowing the difficulty of words of this kind, urged the believers to make
               earnest and constant prayer that speech might be granted him with eloquence<note type="footnote"
                  n="35" resp="#ebrooks">Ephesians vi, 19.</note>. Since then these things are so, and we decline to
               employ a multitude of words, which as a rule do not escape sin<note type="footnote" n="36"
                  resp="#ebrooks">This perhaps represents <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀμαρτεῖν</foreign> (to err):
                  see p. 77, n. 3. </note>, I will use shortness of speech to your wisdom and knowledge, and ask
               you a very easy question. Do you call the flesh possessing an intelligent soul, which God the
               Word voluntarily united to himself hypostatically without any change, a specimen or a
               generality, that is one soul-possessing hypostasis, or the whole human generality? It is
               manifest that, if you wish to give a right-minded answer, you will say one soul-possessing body.
               Accordingly we say that from it and the hypostasis of God the Word the ineffable union was made:
               for the whole of the Godhead and the whole of humanity in general were not joined in a natural
               union, but special hypostases. And the holy and wise Cyril plainly witnesses to us in that in
               <pb n="17"/> the third chapter<note type="footnote" n="37" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">κεφάλαιον</foreign>.</note> or anathema he spoke thus: "Whoever divides the one
               Christ into hypostases after the union, associating them in association of honour or of
               authority only, and not rather in junction of natural union, let him be anathema"<note
                  type="footnote" n="38" resp="#ebrooks">Mansi, IV, 1081.</note>. And again in the Scholia the
               same says: "Hence we shall learn that the hypostases have remained without confusion"<note
                  type="footnote" n="39" resp="#ebrooks">Schol. de Inc. Unig., 11 (ed. Pusey, VI, p.
                  520).</note>. Accordingly the natural union was not of generalities, but of hypostases of which
               Emmanuel was composed. And do not think that hypostases in all cases have a distinct person
               assigned to them, so that we should be thought, like the impious Nestorius, to speak of a union
               of persons, and to run counter to the God-inspired words of the holy Cyril, who in the second
               letter to the same Nestorius speaks thus: "But that it should be so<note type="footnote" n="40"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἰς τὸ οὕτως ἔχειν</foreign>.</note> will in no way
               help the right principle of faith, even if some men spread about a union of persons. For the
               Scripture did not say that God the Word united to himself the person of a man, but that he
               became flesh"<note type="footnote" n="41" resp="#ebrooks">Cyr., ed. Pusey, VI, p. 8.</note>.
               When hypostases subsist by individual subsistence, as for instance, those of Peter and of Paul,
               whom the authority of the apostleship united, then there will be a union of persons and a
               brotherly association, not a natural junction <pb n="18"/> of one hypostasis made up out of two
               that is free from confusion. For this is what those who adhere to the foul doctrines of
               Nestorius are convicted of saying with regard to the divine Humanization also. They first make
               the babe exist by himself separately, so that a distinct person is even assigned to him, and
               then by attaching God the Word to him impiously introduce a union of persons into the faith.
               This Gregory the Theologian<note type="footnote" n="42" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >Θεολόγος</foreign>.</note> also rejected by saying in the great letter to Cledonius: "Whoever
               says that the man was formed, and God afterwards crept in is condemned: for this is not a birth
               of God, but an escape from birth"<note type="footnote" n="43" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. 101 (P. G.,
                  XXXVII, 177).</note>. But, when hypostases do not subsist in individual subsistence, as also in
               the case of the man among us, I mean him who is composed of soul and body, but are without
               confusion recognised in union and composition, being distinguished by the intellect only and
               displaying one hypostasis made out of two, such a union none will be so uninstructed as to call
               one of persons. Though the hypostasis of God the Word existed before, or rather<note
                  type="footnote" n="44" resp="#ebrooks">
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">μᾶλλον</foreign>.</note> was before all ages and times, being eternally
               with God both the Father and the Holy Spirit, yet still the flesh possessing an intelligent soul
               which he united to him did not exist <pb n="19"/> before the union with him, nor was a distinct
               person assigned to it<note type="footnote" n="45" resp="#ebrooks">This must be the meaning,
                  though the grammar is awkward. Cf. p. 17, 1. 6 (text).</note>. And the great Athanasius bears
               witness, who in the letter to Jovinian the king says: "As soon as there is flesh, there is at
               once flesh of God the Word; and, as soon as there is soul-possessing and rational flesh<note
                  type="footnote" n="46" resp="#ebrooks">Omitted in the printed Greek text.</note>, there is at
               once soul-possessing rational flesh of God the Word<note type="footnote" n="46" resp="#ebrooks"
                  >Omitted in the printed Greek text.</note>: for in him also it acquired subsistence"<note
                     type="footnote" n="47" resp="#ebrooks">P. G., XXVIII, 531 (not in the genuine letter to
                     Jovian).</note>. And the holy Cyril also testifies, addressing the impious Diodorus as follows:
               "My excellent man, I say that you are shooting forth unlearned words much affected with what is
               abhorrent. For the holy body was from Mary, but still at the very beginning of its concretion or
               subsistence in the womb it was made holy, as the body of Christ, and no one can see any time at
               which it was not his, but rather simple as you say and the same as this flesh of other men"<note
                  type="footnote" n="48">Contr. Diod., fr. 15 (Cyr., in Jo. Ev., ed. Pusey, III, p. 498).</note>.
               Following these God-inspired words of the holy fathers, and confessing our Lord Jesus Christ to
               be of two natures, regard the distinct hypostases themselves of which Emmanuel was composed, and
               the natural junction of these, and do not go up to generalities and essences<note
                  type="footnote" n="49"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσίας</foreign></note>, of the whole of the
               Godhead and humanity in <pb n="20"/> general: for it is manifest that the whole of the Godhead
               is seen in the Trinity, and humanity in general draws the mind to the whole human race. How
               therefore is it anything but ridiculous and impious for us to say that the Trinity was united in
               hypostasis to the race of mankind, when the holy Scriptures say more plainly than a trumpet,
               "The Word became flesh and dwelt in us"<note type="footnote" n="50" resp="#ebrooks">John 1,
                  14.</note>, that is that one of the three hypostases who was rationally and hypostatically
               united to soul-possessing flesh? But neither do we deny, as we have also written in other
               letters on different occasions, that we often find men designating hypostases by the name of
               essence<note type="footnote" n="51" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >οὐσία</foreign>.</note>. Hence Gregory the Theologian named hypostatic union union in
               essence<note type="footnote" n="51" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >οὐσία</foreign>.</note> in the letter to Cledonius which we have just mentioned, speaking
               thus: "Whoever says that he worked by grace as in a prophet, but not that he was united and
               fashioned together with him in essence, may he be bereft of the excellent operation, or rather
               may he be full of the contrary"<note type="footnote" n="52" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. 101 (P. G.,
                  XXXVII, 180).</note>. And the wise Cyril in the second letter to Succensus calls the manhood
               which was hypostatically united to God the Word essence<note type="footnote" n="51"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note>, saying: "For, if after saying
               'one nature <pb n="21"/> of the Word' we had stopped and not added 'incarnate', but set the
               dispensation as it were outside, they would perhaps in a way have a plausible argument when they
               pretend to ask, 'Where is the perfection in manhood? or how was the essence after our model made
               up?' But, since the perfection in manhood and the characteristic of our essence has been
               introduced by the fact that we said 'incarnate', let them be silent, since they have leaned upon
               the staff of a reed"<note type="footnote" n="53" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. 46, 3 (P. G., LXXVII,
                  244).</note>. But saying that Emmanuel, is from two essences<note type="footnote" n="54"
                     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσίας</foreign>.</note> also, as we confess him to be
               from two natures, even if one understand the essences<note type="footnote" n="54"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσίας</foreign>.</note> as hypostases, we avoid, as a
               thing that is unscientific, and has not been stated in so many words by any of the God-clad
               fathers: for in such matters we must avoid novelty, even if it has some religiousness about it,
               and with the psalmist-prophet be preserved in the tent of caution, and be hidden by grace from
               on high, even from the contention of tongues<note type="footnote" n="55" resp="#ebrooks">Ps,
                  XXX, 21.</note>. These things we have written in epistolary style, though we are in the midst
               of many troubles, and of many tens of thousands of kinds of cares. But it rests with your
               truth-loving and God-loving soul to inform us by letter if you have given up the doubts, and if
               what we have written appeared <pb n="22"/> to have been well stated, Know that the religious
               deacon Anatolius<note type="footnote" n="56" resp="#ebrooks">Select Letters of Severus, p.
                  38(?).</note> has abandoned this opinion, and, though late, has thanked us. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
