<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3174">To John and Theodore and John the God-loving
               Presbyters and Archimandrites</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Letters I to LXI</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m"> A Collection of Letters of <persName
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName> , from
                     Numerous Syriac Manuscripts </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">248 [76]-259 [87]</biblScope>
                  <!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">12</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2427">John</persName>
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2765">Theodore</persName>
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2428">John</persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="27">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the Holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName> From the Letter to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2427">John</persName> And
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2765">Theodore</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2428">John</persName> the God-Loving Presbyters and Archimandrites, Against The
               Codicils<note type="footnote" n="190"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κωδικιλία</foreign>.
                  In Greek extracts this letter is called <foreign xml:lang="grc">κατὰ
                     Ἀλέξανδρου</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="grc">κατὰ τῶν κωδικιλίων
                     Ἀλεξανδρείας;</foreign> but <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܠܟܣܕܪܝܐ</foreign> occurs
                  in our text (p. 85, 1. 9) where it can only be rendered 'the Alexandrine'.</note>
               Of the Alexandrine. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0538">519-38</date>
            </dateline>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <p><persName>Alexander</persName> is manifestly found to say that [man] is in the form of angels, in that
                  he contends that the holy bodies become spiritual bodies, denying the resurrection
                  of the flesh and bones; if 'a spirit [hath] not flesh and bones'<note
                     type="footnote" n="191" resp="#ebrooks">Luke xxiv, 39.</note>, <pb n="77"/>
                  according to the unerring saying of the Lord. Accordingly it manifestly appears
                  that he preaches contrary to the prophets and apostles and holy doctors of the
                  church, who in revealing fashion taught the words of faith and expounded the
                  God-inspired Scriptures, and outside what we receive, according to the apostle's
                     ordinance<note type="footnote" n="192" resp="#ebrooks">Galatians i, 9.</note>; and
                  he is under anathema, even if we keep silence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head type="excerpt" resp="#compiler">Of the holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName> patriarch of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> from
                  the letter to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2427">John</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2765">Theodore</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2428">John</persName>, the God-loving presbyters and
                  archimandrites, which was written in answer to the <persName>Codicils</persName><note type="footnote"
                     n="193" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κωδικιλία</foreign>.</note> of
                  the Alexandrine.</head>
               <p>For we may hear wise men outside also saying, "Not to sin<note type="footnote"
                     n="194" resp="#ebrooks">Throughout this passage the translator seens to have
                     misunderstood <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἁμαρτεῖν</foreign> ('err' or
                     'fail').</note> at all, and to do everything rightly is of God"<note
                     type="footnote" n="195" resp="#ebrooks">I do not know the source of this
                     citation.</note>. And we see the divine Scripture also saying of each created
                  thing, "Let there be light, and there was light; and God saw the light that it was
                  good"; and again, "Let there be so-and-so and there was; and God saw that it was
                  good"; and after everything together so to speak which he called forth and which
                  answered, "God saw <pb n="78"/> all that he had made and lo! it was very
                     good"<note type="footnote" n="196" resp="#ebrooks">Genesis i, 3, 4, 6, 9-12,
                     14-16, 24, 25, 31.</note>. How then can anyone say that things which are good
                  both in themselves severally, and because they fit together with one another and
                  make up one world, are a sin on God's part? If so be they are a sin, they are not
                  good: but, if they are good, they are not a sin. But, if by reason that they are
                  corruptible, therefore they are a sin, yet rather, as a certain wise man says,
                  "God created everything that it might come into being, and salutary are the
                  creations of the world, and there is no poison of corruption in them; and Sheol
                  hath no kingdom upon earth"<note type="footnote" n="197" resp="#ebrooks">Sap., I,
                     14.</note>. Again, if the first man had kept the commandment, and not gone
                  astray after sin through the serpent's deceitfulness, and lost the grace of
                  immortality, having voluntarily drawn death upon himself, then creation itself
                  also would have continued, acquiring for its own self the grace of immortality
                  from God: for in accordance with the condition<note type="footnote" n="198"
                     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κατάστασις</foreign>.</note> in which
                  we are for whose sake it came into being its parts also pass away. For this reason
                  then, when man himself was condemned to death, it itself also served corruption
                  and 'was made subject to vanity'<note type="footnote" n="199" resp="#ebrooks">Romans
                     VIII, 20.</note>, as the apostle says; but it hopes further to gain with us
                  what it had from <pb n="79"/> the beginning: and it will have continuance without
                  corruptibility when we are admitted to the resurrection and the kingdom of heaven:
                  for the most wise <persName>Paul</persName> himself also cries, "Creation itself also shall be freed
                  from the bondage of corruption, into the freedom of the glory of the children of
                     Gods"<note type="footnote" n="200" resp="#ebrooks">Romans viii, 21.</note>.</p>
               <p><supplied reason="ellipsis" resp="#compiler">(<emph rend="ital">And after other
                        things</emph>).</supplied></p>
               <p>But, my good friend, neither indeed did God make the world in order that it might
                  be corrupted, for 'salutary are the creations of the world', as you have heard;
                  but, since it is of a very fluid nature, he on the contrary brought it into being
                  in order that it might partake of incorruption; for indeed 'even creation itself
                  shall be freed from the bondage of corruption into the freedom of the glory of the
                  children of God'. For what logic is it, tell me, that rational man who sinned of
                  his own accord should according to your argument be raised to incorruption, while
                  creation which is inanimate and without perception, which for his sake was made
                  subject to vanity, should be delivered to final destruction, and not partake of
                  the incorruptibility and the glory of those for whose sake it was made <pb n="80"
                  /> subject to corruption? For that the world shall be consummated is manifest
                  according to the faith in the divine Scriptures: for that the rudiments which
                  compose this visible creation will not pass into absolute non-existence, but will
                  be changed into something better, <persName>Paul</persName> testifies when he says, "The form of the
                  world passeth away"<note type="footnote" n="201" resp="#ebrooks">1 Corinthians vii, 31.</note>, 
                  and not 'this world', and <persName>Peter</persName> also testifies when he writes, "The
                  heavens shall be dissolved with fervent heat, and the elements shall burn and
                     collapse"<note type="footnote" n="202" resp="#ebrooks">2 <persName>Peter</persName> iii. 12.</note>.
                  (But those in whom righteousness dwells look for new heavens and a new earth
                  according to his promises.) And before him <persName>David</persName> sings about the heavens the
                  passage also, "They all shall grow old as a garment, and as a vesture shalt thou
                  fold them up, and they shall be changed"<note type="footnote" n="203"
                     resp="#ebrooks">Psalm ci, 27.</note>. Words agreeing with these were written by
                  the Theologian <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/511">Gregory</persName> also, in the sermon on the funeral of his brother
                  <persName>Caesarius</persName>, as follows: "But why am I faint-hearted about the hopes? Why do I
                  become a man of time? I await the voice of the archangel, the last trump, the
                  transformation of heaven, the changing of the earth, the emancipation of the
                  elements, the renovation of the whole world. Then shall I see <persName>Caesarius</persName>, no longer
                  departing, no longer carried, no longer <pb n="81"/> being mourned for, no longer
                  being pitied, bright, glorious, exalted, even as you have often appeared to me in
                  a dream, O most brother-loving<note type="footnote" n="204" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὦ φὶλτατε ἀδελφῶν ἐμοί</foreign>.</note>, and most
                  brother-loving; either as I have wished to depict thee, or in reality"<note
                     type="footnote" n="205" resp="#ebrooks">Or. VII, 21. The last clause runs
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἶτε τοῦ βούλεσθαι τοῦτο ἀνατυποῦντος εἶτε τῆς
                        ἀληθείας</foreign>.</note>. And the most wise <persName>John</persName>, the expounder of the
                  divine words, in the commentary on the epistle to the Hebrews speaks as follows:
                  "And besides this he demonstrated another thing also worth attention<note
                     type="footnote" n="206" resp="#ebrooks">Jo. Chrys. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πάρεργον</foreign>.</note> in parabolic form: for he also denoted the
                  transformation of the world by saying, 'As a garment shall they grow old; and as a
                  vesture thou shalt fold them up, and they shall be changed'; a thing which he also
                  states in the epistle to the <persName>Romans</persName>, that he shall transform the world: and
                  setting forth the easiness he added that, as a man may fold up a vesture, so shall
                  he fold them up . and change them. But, if he effected the transformation and the
                  creation into something better and higher so easily, for the creation of something
                  worse he needed another; how long will, you not be ashamed?"<note type="footnote"
                     n="207" resp="#ebrooks">In Ep. ad Hebrews Hom, iii, 5, 6 (ed. Field).</note>. And
                  in the commentary on the epistle to the <persName>Romans</persName> he gives an account of this matter
                  in very complete form, writing as follows : "'For the expectation of creation', he
                  says, 'looks for the revelation of the sons of God. <pb n="82"/> For creation was
                  made subject to vanity, not of its own accord, but because of him who subjected it
                  in hope'. For what he says is something like this. 'This same creation suffers
                  great pain expecting and hoping for the good things which we have just mentioned.
                  But expectation is earnest looking'. But, in order that the account may be
                  clearer, he also personifies the whole of this world, as the prophets too do, when
                  they introduce rivers clapping hands, and high places leaping, and the mountains
                  dancing; not that we may understand these to be animate, nor that we may assign
                  any reason to them; but that we may learn the abundance of the good things, so
                  that it reaches even to things without perception. And they often do this same
                  thing in the case of distressing things also, introducing a vine lamenting and
                  wine and mountains, and the roofs of the temple crying, that from this again we
                  may understand the greatness of the evil things. But, imitating these, the apostle
                     personifies<note type="footnote" n="208" resp="#ebrooks">A similar passage is
                        cited from <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName> in Cramer, Cat. in Ep. ad Rom. p. 137.</note> creation and
                  says that it groans and suffers pain; not because he had heard any groan come from
                  earth and sky; but that he may show the abundance of the future good things, and
                  the desire of escape from the prevailing evil things. 'For creation was <pb n="83"
                  /> made subject to vanity, not of its own accord, but because of him who subjected
                  it'. What is 'Creation was made subject to vanity'? It was made corruptible. Why
                  and wherefore? On account of you the man. For, since you received a body that is
                  mortal and passible, the earth also received a curse, and produced briars and
                  thorns. But, that heaven together with the earth will grow old and eventually pass
                  to the better ending, hear the prophet saying, 'In the beginning, Lord, thou
                  laidst the foundations of the earth, and the heavens are the work of thine hands.
                  They shall perish, but thou endurest; and they all shall grow old as a garment;
                  and as a vesture shalt thou fold them up, and they shall be changed'. And <persName>Isaiah</persName>,
                  demonstrating these things, said, 'Observe heaven above and the earth beneath;
                  because heaven hath been solidified as smoke, and the earth shall grow old as a
                  garment; and they that dwell therein shall perish like them'. You have seen how
                  'creation was made subject to vanity', how also it shall be freed from corruption;
                  for the former said 'As a vesture shalt thou fold them up, and they shall be
                  changed', and <persName>Isaiah</persName> said 'They that dwell therein shall perish like them',
                     not<note type="footnote" n="209" resp="#ebrooks">This passage to ' universe'
                     (p. 84, 1. 2) is cited in Greek from this letter in Mai, Scriptorum Veterum
                     Nova Collectio, IX, 745. The author of this Catena seems not to have noticed
                     that it occurs in a citation from Jo. Chrys.</note> speaking of utter
                  destruction, for neither shall the men who dwell in it undergo such as this, but
                  the temporary destruction, and through that very thing they shall pass to <pb
                     n="84"/> incorruption, just indeed as by saying 'like these things' he pointed
                  to creation itself, that is the universe<note type="footnote" n="210"
                     resp="#ebrooks">Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὥσπερ οὖν καὶ ἡ κτίσις· ἅπερ ἂπαντα
                        διὰ τοῦτο εἶπεν [<foreign xml:lang="en">Jo. Chrys</foreign>. διὰ τοῦ εἰπεῖν]
                        ὡς ταῦτα παρεδήλςωεν</foreign>.</note>, just indeed as <persName>Paul</persName> also says
                  farther on. However for the present he is speaking about its subjection and
                  showing why it was made of this kind, and assigning us as the reason. What then?
                  Was violence done to it in that it underwent these things for another? Not at all;
                  for it was indeed made for me. How then is a thing which was made for me injured
                  when it undergoes these things for my reformation? But, to look at it in another
                  way, we ought not even to raise the question of justice and injustice with respect
                  to things without life and perception. But <persName>Paul</persName> because he personified it uses
                  none of the arguments that I have stated, but by another method of reasoning sets
                  himself superfluously to comfort the hearer. But what was it? 'What say you? It
                  underwent evil things for you and has become corruptible. But it lost nothing; for
                  it shall also become incorruptible again through you': for this is the meaning of
                  'in hope'. But, when he says, 'It was not made subject of its own will', he does
                  not say this to show that it is possessed of thought, but that you may learn that
                     <pb n="85"/> everything was brought about by the will of <persName>Christ</persName>, and the one is
                  not a reformation of the other. But he stated also in what hope. 'Because creation
                  itself also shall be freed'. What is 'itself also'? That not you, but it also,
                  even a thing that is far inferior to you, and that does not partake of reason and
                  perception, this also shall partake with you in the good things. For it 'shall be
                  delivered', he says, 'from the bondage of corruption'; that is, it shall be no
                  longer corruptible; but it shall follow the beauty of your body. For, as, when it
                  became corruptible, creation also became the same, so, when it is rendered
                  incorruptible, creation also as well shall again follow; to denote which indeed he
                  added, 'into the freedom of the glory of the children of God'"<note
                     type="footnote" n="211">In Ep. ad Rom. Hom, xv, 16-19 (ed. Field).</note>.</p>
               <p>But, inasmuch as the Alexandrine is a stranger and a barbarian to the divine
                  Scripture, and is not accustomed to the teachings of this Scripture, he thinks
                  that God is a creator of corruption, and he calls the world his sin; a thing that
                  is of fluid nature, but is honoured by the grace of incorruptibility together with
                  man for whose sake also it was made. It was not as a sin of God that <persName>Christ</persName>
                  reformed the world's subjection also that was for man's sake, that he might bring
                  in one set of <pb n="86"/> things in place of another, as this wicked and
                  deceiving man says; in place of bodies that had been delivered to death the
                  immortality of spirits, and in place of the corruption of the world eternal
                  incorruptibility, and in place of abundance of sins abundance of right acts; but
                  in order that he might raise man, who had fallen, and by erring been stripped of
                  the grace of God through which he had immortality, to the original state, through
                  the resurrection of the bodies into incorruption, by which this world also shall
                  partake of the freedom and the glory, as we have written.</p>
               <div type="ellipsis">
                  <p resp="#compiler">(<emph rend="ital">And after other things.</emph>)</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p>But from the investigation you have plainly recognised his corruption on every
                     point, and his spuriousness in the matter of faith; in the theology which
                     concerns the Father and the Son mingling of hypostases (since he has cast
                     behind him the godlessness of <persName>Sabellius</persName> the Libyan); in the Incarnation of the
                     Only one phantasy and change, and the other things that do away the true
                     Humanization and fight against our salvation; in the Resurrection lessening of
                     hope, and denial of the resurrection of bodies; in the creation of the visible
                     world, a blaspheming tongue that under the appearance of good will arms itself
                     against the wise Creator and Maker, <pb n="87"/> and that utters follies akin
                     to those of <persName>Mani</persName> the madman and <persName>Marcion</persName> (for well was he named <persName>Mani</persName> from mania,
                     that is, from madness, who is the founder of the <persName>Manichees</persName>, who are most
                     exceedingly foul). But that these confused opinions are rejected and
                     anathematized by the holy Church, and those who were the originators of them,
                     there is none among <persName>Christians</persName> who does not confess. Accordingly therefore it
                     is manifest that <persName>Alexander</persName>, inasmuch as he has agreed with all these opinions,
                     shares the anathema of each one, being subject to many sentences or
                        punishments<note type="footnote" n="212" resp="#ebrooks">Greek fragments of
                        this letter are published in Gramer, Cat. in Act. Apost, p. 296, 379, 390;
                        in Epp. Cath., p. 73, 162; S. V. N. G., I, ii, 204, 220; IX, 739; and a ms.
                        extract exists in Add. 35123 f. 383 r°.</note>.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
