<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3179">To Elisha, the Presbyter and Archimandrite, and the Rest</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Letters I to LXI</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m"> A Collection of Letters of <persName
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName> , from
                     Numerous Syriac Manuscripts </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">269 [97]-279 [107]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">12</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2641">Elisha</persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="34">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the Holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName>, a Letter to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2641">Elisha</persName> the Presbyter And
               Archimandrite, and the Rest<note type="footnote" n="247" resp="#ebrooks">rammarian of Caesarea
                  (Joh., Vit. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName>, in P. O., II, 278), a work which exists only in fragments: see Wright,
                  Catalogue of Syriac MSS. in the British Meseum, p. 1323; Lebon, Le Monophysisme Severien, p.
                  147.</note>. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0521 (?)">519-21 (?)</date>
            </dateline>
            <p>The saintly presbyter <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2673">John</persName> has removed and gone to the place of light of the righteous, and to
               the rest above in which those who have so lived abide, expecting the day of the perfect and full
               promise, and not without us to be made perfect, as Paul who was initiated into the deep and
               ineffable things of the foreknowledge of God somewhere says<note type="footnote" n="248"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Hebrews xi, 40.</note>. What need is there even to say <pb n="98"/> what
               poignant and heavy sorrow has shaken my soul? For it is a great loss that this wretched
               turbidity of times in which we ourselves have been left alive should by such men being snatched
               away be gradually laid bare and reduced so to speak to the last dregs. About him there is much
               that I might write on the laudatory side, but, overcome by the multitude of subjects, I say this
               briefly, that he alone taught us and caused us to see before our eyes, what is the kingdom of
               heaven that is spoiled, which spoilers 
               seize<note type="footnote" n="249" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew, xi, 12.</note>. In such a a way, 
               clad in the feeble body as in a chain of lead, he
               parted and dispersed all things outside, and by taking little thought for things that draw
               downwards, and receiving strength through desire of heavenly things, he fitted himself wholly
               for things above, to which he has now easily departed. Therefore we must both weep and groan for
               our solitude, which has been deprived entirely of such a pattern and honourable example. But,
               since we ought to bow our neck before the just scales of the judgments of God, we praise him who
               so orders these things and brings them to pass: for the wise and strenuous Job somewhere says,
               "But if he too hath so judged, who is he that gainsaith him? For what he himself wished he also
               did"<note type="footnote" n="250" resp="#ebrooks">Job, xxiii, 13.</note>. And for <pb n="99"/>
               the rest we pray that by the saintly prayers of those who have made a good departure hence we
               may be saved, and as far as possible be kept unharmed, and not wander from the faith of these
               men, and may be raised to them in memory.</p>
            <p>May these things be so. But in respect of what has been written by your love of God about the
               sustenance of the poor, and our necessity or refreshment, and that you wish to share with us in
               everything, and give readily, know this, that we accept the full purpose of your mind, but,
               being small and weak, we look to Paul the doctor of the church, and as regards our needs set
               ourselves to feel shame and refrain, and look at him who says, "In all things I have kept myself
               without being burdensome to you and will keep myself"<note type="footnote" n="251"
                  resp="#ebrooks">2 Corinthians xi, 9.</note>. But with respect to the relief of our brethren who are
               labouring under the same distresses, by which life is oppressed, I will exert myself, and will
               be importunate, or rather<note type="footnote" n="252"><foreign xml:lang="grc">μᾶλλον</foreign>.</note> will use lawful boldness of speech<note type="footnote" n="253"
                     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">παρρησία</foreign>.</note>, and will beg, and
               grasp<note type="footnote" n="254" resp="#ebrooks">Perh. read <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܐܚܦܛ
               </foreign> 'and urge'.</note>, and incite to liberal giving; and I will again use his words and
               say, "He that soweth sparingly shall reap sparingly; and he that soweth bountifully shall reap
               bountifully": and this he seals by the <pb n="100"/> very wise and understanding addition,
               "Every man as his heart willeth, not grudgingly nor of necessity: for God loveth a cheerful
               giver"<note type="footnote" n="255" resp="#ebrooks">2 Corinthians ix, 6, 7.</note>.</p>
            <p>As to the book that I have composed against the heretical fatuity of the wicked grammarian, by
               often writing and asking for it to be sent to you before it was completely finished you were
               acting like men who urge a boy who is healthy and well-prepared, and instructed in military
               affairs, to appear in the line of battle when he has not yet put on his armour. But, now that by
               God's help it has been finished, as far as our little power goes, and has been duly written, and
               duly collated as far as was possible, it has been sent. It was a very difficult task and needed
               a great store of books, and it was so to speak difficult for me to correct, because I am moving
               from place to place, and I have not everywhere at hand fitting testimonies and demonstrations
               from the Scriptures. For I thought it right to meet not only the lamentable babblings of the
               grammarian, but also the whole web of impiety contained in what was defined and done by way of
               innovation at Chalcedon by the synod which met there, and the impious Tome of Leo, taking
               occasion from the very <pb n="101"/> things stated by him (I mean that grammarian) to expose the
               dishonesty of the adversaries, and cut the very root so to speak of bitterness<note
                  type="footnote" n="256" resp="#ebrooks">Hebrews xii, 15.</note>, and to show whence it sprang,
               and that these things are not new, but were evolved long ago by the impious company of those who
               unlearnedly held this evil opinion; and not only so, but also to show the agreement of the
               doctors of the orthodox<note type="footnote" n="257" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὀρθόδοξοι</foreign>.</note>, and of things which to men who are not practised in divine
               doctrines seem to be contrary, and have the same purpose before them, and to guard myself as far
               as possible against contention from all sides. Immediately therefore after the holy Cyril and
               Gregory the Theologian, and all who so to speak taught the same things, had also said that we
               must note the distinction in theory<note type="footnote" n="258" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">θεωρία</foreign>.</note> and in thought of the natures of which Emmanuel is
               composed, from which natures the different character and diverse essence<note type="footnote"
                  n="259" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> of the elements that
               were joined in union is recognised, Theodotus of saintly memory, bishop of Ancyra in Galatia,
               seems to deny this and not to accept the division in thought<note type="footnote" n="260"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Exp. Syn. Nic., 10 (P. G., LXXVII, 1328).</note>. On this account many of the
               orthodox<note type="footnote" n="257" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὀρθόδοξοι</foreign>.</note> also were confounded by the heretics as if they were adducing
               fathers who said <pb n="102"/> contradictory things, though the objectors could not discern even
               the reading of the words of Theodotus, but read them differently, not as the words stand. This
               therefore and all such points we have brought together from all quarters, and, God stretching
               forth his hand, have explained them, and so have shown the objections of the impious to be vain.
               The demonstrations which they adduce are of ancient date and not of yesterday and the day
               before, and they have been worked up by means of inventions and false attributions and tens of
               thousands of contrivances, since they wish on all sides to show the refutation of the impiety to
               be futile. Therefore it was indeed a task replete with great difficulties to find these
               passages, and lay bare the evil dealing and expose the deceit contained in them. These things
               the prophet's words fit, which were spoken in the name of God to those of Israel, "Ephraim hath
               surrounded me with falsehood, and the house of Israel and of Judah with impiety"<note
                  type="footnote" n="261" resp="#ebrooks">Hosea xi, 12.</note>: and still better that also which
               is written in Daniel, "They worked zealously to strengthen their deceit which consisted in
               transgressions"<note type="footnote" n="262" resp="#ebrooks">Not in our texts of Daniel</note>.
               Having therefore as far as possible read all the books, thoroughly and not negligently, I made
               myself acquainted with their evil purpose after <pb n="103"/> much labour and after searching
               for each one of them (often it could not be found at all), and this though I am in a
               condition<note type="footnote" n="263" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">σχῆμα</foreign>.</note> of exile, and flee from one place to another for refuge like
               boats<note type="footnote" n="264" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">καράβια</foreign>.</note> upon the sea. To me also it was gratifying that the wise and
               Christ-loving Zacharias the scholastic<note type="footnote" n="265" resp="#ebrooks">The
                  biographer of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName> (P. O., II, 7).</note> should read the dissertation mentioned: for in the
               royal city also I used to bring my works to him, when he would listen attentively with all care
               fulness, and received from God the privilege of being a wise hearer of Jerusalem, I mean of the
               church of God, and did not shrink from being an admirable adviser, on account of the great
               experience and instruction in the sacred books which he has enjoyed from his boyhood. And we
               believe that upon you the religious presbyter Victor<note type="footnote" n="266"
                  resp="#ebrooks">See above, ep. 30.</note> the same grace blooms, and that it in no way falls
               short of that which was given to him, or certainly it was even greater, and reaches a still
               higher standard on account of the order of the presbyterate, and the priestly seat to which you
               have been called by God. I therefore beg you all to read the composition diligently and with
               attentive thoughts and, as your habit is, wisely, and if as weak men we have anywhere gone wrong
               to point it out. "That a brother should be helped by a brother, this also is the firm strength
               of a fortified <pb n="104"/> city"<note type="footnote" n="267" resp="#ebrooks">Proverbs xviii,
                  19.</note>, the God-inspired words teach. Therefore also we made it our business, as far as
               possible, to bring this dissertation also to certain men of intelligence and skilled in
               argument, who are not without a share in divine and profane learning, and read it to them,
               generally stealing an opportunity for reading, and doing this in secret, on account of the
               present time. The beginning of this treatise I have put in such a form<note type="footnote"
                  n="268"><foreign xml:lang="grc">σχῆμα</foreign>.</note>, in order that I may seem to have
               prepared this while I was living in Antioch, lest perhaps these adversaries might kindle a
               greater flame of prejudice against me, if they perceived that this had been composed by me in
               exile: and in truth when I was there I began to prepare material for an answer, though, when the
               persecution came, it scattered these things.</p>
            <p>Since you, the God-loving presbyter Philip<note type="footnote" n="269" resp="#ebrooks">Select
               Letters of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName>, i, 51; p. 181, 384; see below, ep. 52.</note>, have often asked for the
               Book of Dispensations as you say to be sent you, the only reason for which we have put off doing
               this is that we are desirous of first carrying out your request, and casting an eye of criticism
               on what is written in it; which down to this day we have been confident of being able to do,
               though all our attention was occupied with the said composition. Therefore, when we have read
               your book also hastily, we will send it as soon as possible. <pb n="105"/></p>
            <p>As to those who have been converted from the error of Theodotus<note type="footnote" n="270"
               resp="#ebrooks">Bishop of Joppa (op. cit., p. 207, 356, 392, 472; Zach. Rh., v, 4; Evagr., in,
               6).</note>, we say this much, that, if there are some who received ordination from Theodotus
               himself, since he was a bishop legally appointed, but was afterwards perverted to the abominable
               tenet of a self-created observance<note type="footnote" n="271" resp="#ebrooks">This represents
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐθελοθρησκεία</foreign> (Colossians ii, 23).</note>, I mean that of the
               illegal re-anointing, and to a change as to the faith, so that he does not confess that our Lord
               and God Jesus Christ, who is of one essence<note type="footnote" n="272" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> with the Father in the Godhead, himself
               became also of one essence<note type="footnote" n="272" resp="#ebrooks"></note> with us without
               variation, and took our likeness, except sin only, let these be subject to the periods of
               penance which Timothy of saintly memory, archbishop of Alexandria, laid down with regard to
               those who are converted from the heresy of the Diphysites<note type="footnote" n="273"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Select Letters of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName>, p. 201, 368, 382; Zach. Rh., iv, 12 (Land, p. 162);
                  Wright, Catalogue of Syriac MSS. in the British Meseum, p. 643.</note>. But, if there are some
               others who derive the ordinations alleged to have been performed over them from the man called
               Gregory<note type="footnote" n="274" resp="#ebrooks">Select Letters of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName>, p. 232,
                  472.</note> or from others, who are not even bishops, let these be reckoned as laymen, and not
               dream of the name of service or priesthood; but eventually after some time, if some of them
               receive a report for good works, let these <pb n="106"/> be ordained, as if they had been
               advanced from the lay standing to the priestly chancel<note type="footnote" n="275"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">βῆμα</foreign>.</note>. But I was surprised to see that
               in your letter, though you termed them laymen, you afterwards asked the question "How long a
               period ought to be appointed for these men", as if they were clergymen<note type="footnote"
                  n="276"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κληρικοί</foreign>.</note>, men who never became such at all.
               Therefore also I praised the ignorance of the religious presbyter Victor about these men.</p>
            <p>As to the complete manuscript<note type="footnote" n="277" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
               xml:lang="grc">πανδέκτης</foreign>.</note> of the divine Scriptures which belonged to John
               whose soul is at rest, which may fill many bellies of poor men, sell it: for we by God's grace
               have books<note type="footnote" n="278" resp="#ebrooks">Or 'the Scriptures'.</note>, and would
               we had also perfect knowledge of these, which we pray may be given to us by God.</p>
            <p>We were not surprised to hear that those without are at peace with you, since we recalled to
               mind the divine declaration which says to the righteous man, "For the beasts of the field shall
               be at peace with thee"<note type="footnote" n="279" resp="#ebrooks">Job, v, 23.</note>.
               Therefore also we again praised him who confessed these things without falsehood.</p>
            <trailer resp="#compiler">The end of the letter to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2641">Elisha</persName> the presbyter and
               archimandrite.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
