<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3188">To Urban the Grammarian</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Letters I to LXI</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m"> A Collection of Letters of <persName
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName> , from
                     Numerous Syriac Manuscripts </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">310 [138]-312 [140]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">12</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="44">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the Same From the Letter to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2776">Urban</persName> the Grammarian, Which
               Begins, "When I read the letter of your learning". </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0516" notAfter="0517">516-7</date>
            </dateline>
            <p>In dealing with abstentions with regard to names preserved in the sacred tablets we must in
               fitness duly compare the things of which the sacred Scripture said that, when they fall into
               water that is contained in small vessels, they pollute it, but, when into pools or wells or
               cisterns containing many streams, they cause no stain or pollution. For the law of the divine
               Spirit said thus: "And every drink that ye shall drink in any vessel shall be polluted; and
               everything on which anything from a dead body falls is polluted. However fountains of water and
               pools and cisterns of water shall be pure"<note type="footnote" n="380" resp="#ebrooks">Leviticus xi,
                  25, 26.</note>. This principle then ought to be observed in the present case also. If a man
               separates from many on the ground that they are infected with heresy, or that they communicate
               with those who are infected, let him with all his power maintain abstention from the dead body,
               and not mention even the name of those who are under suspicion and not genuine, lest it fall and
               pollute the <pb n="139"/> purity of the communion. But, if the holding of the orthodox faith,
               and an anathema of every heresy reigns in the churches, and whole countries and provinces<note
                  type="footnote" n="381" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπαρχίας</foreign> (for
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπαρχίας</foreign>).</note>, and populous churches, confess one
               uncorrupted confession, then names which are thought to pollute are inundated by the multitude
               of streams. It is good that no particle of a dead body should be introduced even into a large
               quantity of water; but if perchance<note type="footnote" n="382"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἆρα</foreign>.</note> it in fact happen to be introduced, it is cleansed by the quantity of
               streams, and swamped by the quantity of cleansing<note type="footnote" n="383" resp="#ebrooks">Cf. Select Letters of Severus, p. 289.</note>. We find that in fact the holy fathers also who
               were in former times upholders of the right word managed these things in this way. Show us from
               the compositions of the doctors of the church that, after so large a number had found fault with
               the faith of the 318 at <placeName>Ariminus</placeName> [sic], any question was raised about the names of those who had
               died. And, not to make the letter tedious by using many words, let us pass on in mind to times
               that are near and not far removed. We find that the holy <persName>Timothy</persName>, he who underwent long
               exiles<note type="footnote" n="384" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐξορίας</foreign>.</note>, united with everyone in the Encyclical, and communicated with <persName>Paul</persName>
               bishop of the city of the <placeName>Ephesians</placeName>, and <persName>Peter</persName> who had become prelate of <pb n="140"/> this
               great Christ-loving city of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, while names under suspicion were preserved in the sacred
               tablets; and the holy <persName>Cyril</persName>, when he united with the Easterns after the deprivation<note
                  type="footnote" n="385" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">καθαίρεσις</foreign>.</note> of
               <persName>Nestorius</persName>, when many bishops had died, and had departed under the stain of the Nestorian heresy,
               made no inquiry about names. If therefore those who set great store by strictness in respect of
               such names say that the oblation is not pure, let them know that their strictness also draws its
               origin and existence from such communion, and descends from that source as from a root. For the
               saintly <persName>Timothy</persName>, as we have said, consented to hold communion with those of like opinions in
               company with such names, he whose grandsons they are who now with a boastful front loudly
               proclaim, "You shall not approach me because I am pure". And this we say superfluously, that
               some of the bishops in the cities of the Easterns set even this also straight, and ceased to
               mention all such names: for others found it impossible to set this same thing straight; and it
               was not right for such a reason for them to enter on wrangles<note type="footnote" n="386"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ζυγομάχας</foreign>.</note>, and set themselves in
               array against the enthusiasm of the people of the cities, in order that they might suffer
               shipwreck in the most essential things. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
