<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3196">To Philip the Presbyter and Monk</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Letters I to LXI</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m"> A Collection of Letters of <persName
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName> , from
                     Numerous Syriac Manuscripts </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">326 [152]-329 [157]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">12</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2437">Philip</persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="52">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the Same From the 2nd Letter to the Same <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2437">Philip</persName> the
               Presbyter and Monk<note type="footnote" n="424" resp="#ebrooks">Select Letters of Severus, i, 51
                  (which precedes in our ms.); p. 181, 364; above, p. 104. It is most natural to suppose that
                  this correspondence preceded ep. 34 and Select Letters of Severus, v, 8.</note> About the
               Formation of Man, and That the Monastic Habit Frees From Previous Sins.</head>
            <p>And now I turn to the statement made by your religiousness, that one of those who live an
               ascetic life of philosophic labour, after he had come and presented himself for ordination<note
                  type="footnote" n="425" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>.</note> in
               order that he might officiate as a priest to God, having afterwards come to remember his life,
               and the sins that he had committed in his boyhood, and all the rest of his life, and having
               learned <pb n="155"/> that the canon requires blamelessness, sought to range himself outside the
               priestly ministry, and in a way renounce ordination<note type="footnote" n="426" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>.</note>, and satisfy the canon. How is this
               endurable? tell me; and how is it anything but a result of false modesty? You write that this
               man has lived both with earnestness and according to the ordinances of philosophy<note
                  type="footnote" n="427" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">φιλοσοφία</foreign>.</note>,
               and, to speak in the language of Scripture, looks to himself<note type="footnote" n="428"
                  resp="#ebrooks">2 John 8(?).</note>. If the facts of that great sin which cuts off from the
               priesthood or from the ministry had happened after the profession of monastic life, then there
               would have been reason for modesty to play its part. But, where the facts of the sin happened
               firsthand the enrolling in philosophy followed, how is it right to feel fear where no fear
               is<note type="footnote" n="429">Psalm LII, 6.</note>? We believe, not without the divine Spirit,
               that the holy habit of the monastic life carries forgiveness of sins, and strips off the old man
               'who is corrupted in the lusts of error', and puts on 'the new man who was created in God, in
               righteousness and sanctity of truth'<note type="footnote" n="430" resp="#ebrooks">Ephesians IV, 22,
                  24.</note>, as the wise <persName>Paul</persName> somewhere said in writing. I adduce, although I am addressing
               those who know, in confirmation of what has been stated, <pb n="156"/> the vision which that
               heavenly man the great Antony saw. What in fact does the man who told the story of his life say,
               the divine <persName>Athanasius</persName> who is among the high-priests? "When he was about to eat, and had risen to
               pray at the 9th hour, he felt his consciousness lifted up, and (wonderful to relate!) he felt
               himself standing and seeing himself, as if he had been taken outside him, and as if he were
               being led into the air by some men, and afterwards some grievous and cruel men standing in the
               air and seeking to prevent him from passing. And, when the conductors opposed, these required an
               account to know if he were not liable to them; but, when they sought to make an account from his
               birth, those who were leading Antony prevented it, saying to these: 'What happened from his
               birth the Lord has wiped out; but you may inquire into the time since he became a monk and made
               profession to God'. Then upon their making charges and failing to convict, the road was made
               free and unimpeded before him. And immediately he saw himself standing, as if he had come to
               himself, and that he was again wholly <persName>Antony</persName>"<note type="footnote" n="431" resp="#ebrooks">Vit.
                  Ant., 65.</note>. Guided therefore by this divine command, I have answered the present
               question; and I affirm and say with confidence that that modest man <pb n="157"/> must retain
               the priestly ministry, since with his very scrupulousness and carefulness he has conferred a
               great benefit upon us, and by the wise and modest question has astringed with apostolic salt
               those who gape for priestly offices, and fun after ordinations<note type="footnote" n="432"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονίας</foreign>.</note>, like the pomp<note
                     type="footnote" n="433" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">φαντασία</foreign>.</note> and
               honours of the world, and those whose minds are fixed on pride or on visions of things here, and
               who treat as of no account the judgments which we shall receive for these things, when the day
               of judgment arrives, which will assuredly come, and is spoken of by every one's mouth, but is
               looked for by few as it should be looked for.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
