<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3200">To Caesaria the Hypatissa</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Letters I to LXI</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m"> A Collection of Letters of <persName
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName> , from
                     Numerous Syriac Manuscripts </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">334 [162]-338 [166]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">12</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="56">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF MAR SEVERUS TO CAESARIA THE HYPATISSA, BY WAY OF DEFENCE
               FOR HIS OWN FEAR AND TIMIDITY, AND THAT TO FEAR WHEN IT HAS HAPPENED THAT TRIALS BESET US WORKS
               A REWARD AND IS A MARK OF LOVE OF GOD. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0517" notAfter="0521">519(?)</date>
            </dateline>
            <p>David that king and lover of God and prophet, who was more humble than all men, when Saul had
               twice armed himself against him, with many <pb n="163"/> thousands of armed men and warlike
               soldiers, and, after being in a way caught, he not only escaped in a marvellous manner from the
               danger<note type="footnote" n="444" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >κίνδυνος</foreign>.</note> which surrounded him, but even captured with his hands the man who
               had armed himself against him, and he had it in his power to kill him, mercifully spared him
               twice, that enemy and murderer who was so ferociously set against him. And yet, [after] he had
               received such an experience of God's support and protection, hear what kind of things he
               meditates and says [in] his mind when he is debating with himself. "And David said in his heart,
               'Now shall I [be delivered] one day into Saul's hands and there is nothing good for me, unless I
               escape to the land of aliens, and Saul cease searching for me through the whole border of
               Israel, and I escape from his [hand]'. And David arose and the 600 men who were with him; and he
               went to Achish son of Maacah, [King of Gath]; and David settled with Achish in Gath he and his
               men"<note type="footnote" n="445" resp="#ebrooks">1 Samuel XXVII, 1-3.</note>. Where therefore
               was then Caesaria the strongest of all persons in faith, in order that she might have said to
               David also who was [meditating] and doing such things, "Whither flee you, O prophet? Rather<note
                  type="footnote" n="446" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">μᾶλλον</foreign>.</note>
               <pb n="164"/> you are forgetting God's [high and] constant right hand, which saved you and
               delivered that adversary and foeman into your hands, faithless thoughts have gained control of
               you"; and, "The land of the mightiness of that Exalted one is more worthy of confidence for your
               protection than that of Achish the barbarian. It seems to me that the words escape your memory
               which you yourself <damage><supplied resp="#ebrooks">...</supplied></damage> sing by the Holy Spirit, which, I believe, run:
               'Many are the tribulations of the righteous, and the Lord will deliver them out of them all. The
               Lord preserveth all their bones, and not one of them shall be broken'; and again, 'The Lord will
               deliver the souls of his own bondmen'<note type="footnote" n="447" resp="#ebrooks">Psalm  33:20, 21, 23.</note>"? 
               In answer to these things David would say, "Listen, my daughter, and
               incline thine ear'<note type="footnote" n="448">Psalm 44:11.</note>. I know the purport of the
               spiritual songs that were sung by me better than you: but I also know the God of all, who beyond
               all hope snatches his own peculiar bondmen out of all dangers<note type="footnote" n="449"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κίνδυνοι</foreign>.</note>, and again, exercising them,
               also leaves them to adopt plans derived from human thoughts, and weapons drawn from nature, in
               order that they may also flee and choose to suffer everything, and not betray God, and do aught
               that distresses him. If we trusted to his help and were incapable of falling, not weakening in
               <pb n="165"/> anything of ourselves or contributing anything, the virtue would be without
               reward; or rather<note type="footnote" n="450" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >μᾶλλον</foreign>.</note> there would be no room at all to perform anything whatever, or to
               show any kind of success".</p>
            <p>For this reason therefore Moses the great was afraid of the king of Egypt and fled, and became
               a sojourner in the land of Midian for 40 years, and again he returned to Egypt, and transfers
               the fear to the king, and he chastised that obstinate and disobedient man with plagues by means
               of the marvellous signs. [And the one] was the effect of the virtue of Moses, that is [the
               affair] of the flight by which he fled, in order to bring just help to his countrymen who were
               being oppressed, while the other was the effect of the mightiness of God, the display of the
               great wonders.</p>
            <p>And Elijah the prophet, fearing the threat of Jezebel, the wife of that prodigal<note
               type="footnote" n="451" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄσωτος</foreign>.</note> and
               impious man, was a fugitive, he who bound the clouds for three years and six months, and dried
               up the land with drought, and again by a word brought down rain. But Paul also, the great in
               signs and wonders, was let down from the wall in a basket<note type="footnote" n="452"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">σπυρίδα</foreign>.</note> by the disciples in Damascus
               <pb n="166"/> and fled, when the Jews wanted to kill him; and those who took pleasure in
               hearing his teaching did not say, "Let the teacher stay with us that we may hear his very
               pleasant exposition, by means of which he causes the venomous reptiles to flee like a stag" (I
               mean the demons and evil spirits that are envious and hostile against the salvation of men). <supplied reason="ellipsis" resp="#compiler">(<emph rend="ital">After other things.</emph>)</supplied> And the
               Lord also, the Giver of powers, not being a teacher of timidity, said, "When they persecute you
               in this city, flee ye to another"<note type="footnote" n="453" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew X,
                  23.</note>, wishing us not to trust in our own strength, but rather<note type="footnote"
                     n="454" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">μᾶλλον</foreign>.</note> be anxious about such
               things, and, when at his permission conditions of trial beset us, then indeed we must fight
               bravely.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
