<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3209">To Eupraxius the Chamberlain</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">6 [176]-68 [238]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc><correspAction type="sent"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName></correspAction><correspAction type="received"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName></correspAction></correspDesc></profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="65">
   <head type="number">LXV</head>
   <head type="main" resp="#compiler">FROM THE LETTER OF THE SAME HOLY SEVERUS TO EUPRAXIUS THE
     CHAMBERLAIN<note type="footnote" n="479" resp="#ebrooks">Zach. Rh., iii, 1; P. O., II,
     104.</note>, AND ABOUT THE QUESTIONS WHICH HE ADDRESSED TO HIM.</head>
   <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
    <date notBefore="0508" notAfter="0511">508-11</date>
   </dateline>
   <note resp="#compiler">(And the first question is this, as to how we say that God the Word was
    begotten without beginning by the Father: and the beginning of the letter is this: "You, <pb
     n="177"/> God-loving Eupraxius, are<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">In the heading of the
     extracts at G 8 vo a (p. 180) and G 13o vo b (p. 181) 'being'.</note> smitten with divine
    love": and a little farther on the defence).</note>
   <p>First therefore you seek to learn how we say that God the Word was begotten without beginning
    by the Father. But I from the very appellation 'Father' say that the generation of the Son is
    without beginning. If the Father was from eternity, the Son also, who shows forth the Father,
    existed from eternity: for, if there was a time when the Son did not exist, there was then<note
     type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄρα</foreign></note> a time when the
    Father was not a father. We, because we are a corruptible nature, come into being in time, and
    again pass away from being: therefore also the names applied to us vary; and at one time we are
    sons of certain persons, and after this we cease to be sons, and we become fathers, and we beget
    others. But God is in his nature invariable, and he is as he is from eternity, and he is a
    father from eternity. And the Son became such to eternity, and the Son is a son who is from
    eternity, and he was begotten everlastingly by the Father, and he did not acquire for the Father
    from outside the status of a father, because the Son was begotten by him without beginning and
    without time. If we say that the Son is the wisdom and the power of the Father in accordance
    with the wise Paul's <pb n="178"/> saying, "Christ is the power of God and the wisdom of
     God"<note type="footnote" n="480">1 Cor. i, 24.</note>, how is it not beyond all impiety for us
    to presume to say that the Father ever appeared without wisdom or without power? But, if he is
    wise from eternity, and he is powerful from eternity, then he has also wisdom and power from
    eternity, which is Christ: for he is the ray of the glory of the Father, and the impress of his
     hypostasis<note type="footnote" n="481">Heb. i, 3.</note>. As the sun from which it. shines is
    the cause of the ray, and the sun is a circle and orb, and, so to speak, a composition, and the
    ray that comes from it is the light that is emitted and lightens everything under heaven, the
    land I mean and the sea at the same time, and one can never see the sun without the ray that
    comes from it, but, when you hear of the sun, then you also without separation think of and
    understand the light that comes from it, that which gives light and that which is lightened by
    it, for it is from it, and is not after it, so also from the everlasting and suprasensual light,
    which is the Father, the Son shone forth without beginning and everlastingly, who himself also
    is the suprasensual ray which proceeds from him by generation, and does not appear after him.
    And, as when we hear the divine Scripture calling the Son a ray, <pb n="179"/> we think of the
    Father from whom, he radiated, so, when we hear that he is the Word of God, according to the
    passage, "In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God"<note type="footnote" n="482"
     resp="#ebrooks">John i, 1.</note>, we regularly think of the Father who is the subject of the
    Word, who begot the Son from his own nature without passion, the Word so to speak of a great
    intellect, and the messenger in whom he displays and makes known and on whom he impresses the
    hypostasis of the Father, who is a great intellect, and a mind above all . things. And, as our
    mind begets the word without passion, and makes known the thought that is in the heart, and the
    word is a true image of the mind and an exact likeness, and in conjunction with the word, so to
    speak, there proceeds forth, also the emission of the breath of the mouth, in the same way from
    the essence<note type="footnote" n="483" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
     >οὐσία</foreign>.</note> of the Father also the Son proceeds by way of birth, and the Holy
    Spirit by way of procession. And of the person of the Son who is the wisdom of the Father it is
    written, "I was born before all the mountains"<note type="footnote" n="484" resp="#ebrooks">Pr.,
     viii, 25.</note>, and about the Spirit it is said, "The Holy Spirit which proceedeth from the
     Father"<note type="footnote" n="485" resp="#ebrooks">John XV, 26.</note>. And the divine
    Scripture does not use such words at random, saying that the Son is begotten and the Spirit
    proceeds, <pb n="180"/>
    <note type="footnote" n="486" resp="#ebrooks">In Z this comes in the work of Peter against
     Damian, and, as G (2) has the same version, the compiler must have taken the extracts from the
     Syr. version of Peter's work, not directly from Sev.</note> but that we may not confuse the
    hypostases, and that<note type="footnote" n="487" resp="#ebrooks">The grammar is here
     confused.</note> we may know definitely that the Son is one in his hypostasis, and the Holy
    Spirit another, and that, though they are both from the same essence<note type="footnote"
     n="488" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note>, and from the same one
    Father, one is begotten and the other proceeds: whence it follows that the Holy Spirit is not
    the Son; for he is not begotten but proceeds. But, if anyone say, "How is the Son begotten, and
    how does the Spirit proceed?", we discreetly say that it is as the Father knows that he begot
    and the Son that he was begotten, and the Spirit that he is from the Father; but this even the
    very angels are not allowed to understand, and we too will not contuse ourselves by
    investigating it. But, inasmuch as we are variable, our mind, being subject to variations and
    changes, emits a word that proceeds and is dissolved in the air<note type="footnote" n="489"
     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀήρ</foreign>.</note>, and a breath in the same way
    that as soon as it proceeds is diffused over the same air<note type="footnote" n="3"
     resp="#ebrooks"> </note>. But God and the Father, the living and <pb n="181"/> hypostatic mind,
    being incorruptible and invariable, and everlastingly the same, consequently begets a living and
    hypostatic Word, and emits a living and hypostatic Spirit. And, as the Father is the Creator, so
    the Son is the Creator, and the Holy Spirit: for 'by the word of the Lord were the heavens
    established, and by the spirit of his mouth all the strength of them'<note type="footnote"
     n="490">Ps. xxxii, 6.</note>: and, since they are of the same essence<note type="footnote"
     n="491" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> of the Father, they are
    of necessity<note type="footnote" n="492" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >ἀνάγκη</foreign></note> of the same glory and kingship and eternity; for the fact that they
    are of the same essence<note type="footnote" n="491"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
     >οὐσία</foreign>.</note> brings with it identity in every respect. And, when we hear of the
    Son, we immediately understand that he himself is of the same essence<note type="footnote"
     n="491" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία. </foreign></note> as the Father; for
    every father certainly begets a son of the same essence<note type="footnote" n="491"
     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία. </foreign></note> as himself. Thus also from
    every appellation<note type="footnote" n="493" resp="#ebrooks"> (G [1]) ins. 'concerning God'
     and om. 'about the Son'.</note> we draw <pb n="182"/> God-befitting thoughts about the Son,
    from that of 'ray' the thought of co-eternity with the Father, from that of 'Word' impassibility
    of birth, from that of 'Son' the thought of co-essentiality. It is impossible for us in one
    appellation or illustration to comprehend all the attributes that exist in the divine nature,
    because it is without likeness and without peer: but, when we receive from each of the names
    that which is God-befitting, we dismiss all the other things and let them remain below. When we
    speak of the divine nature, we mean the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, separating the
    hypostases, but <pb n="183"/> uniting the Godhead. And, as the name 'Father' and the fact that
    he is not begotten by anything is the peculiar characteristic of the hypostasis of the Father,
    so also the name 'Son' and the fact that he is begotten by the Father is the peculiar
    characteristic of the hypostasis of the Son: similarly also the appellation 'Holy Spirit' and
    the fact that he is not begotten but proceeds from the Father is the peculiar characteristic of
    the hypostasis of the Holy Spirit. While therefore the hypostases or persons are recognised by
    the peculiar characteristics, and the Father is not converted into the Son or the Holy Spirit,
    nor does the Son pass into the Holy Spirit or the Father, nor yet is the Holy Spirit transformed
    so as to become the Father or the Son, the three are one, in that they are of the same
     essence<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> of
     the<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"> (G (3) L) 'and'.</note> Godhead; for the Father is
    God, and the Son God, and the Holy Spirit God, and, while <pb n="184"/> the hypostases remain
    unconfused, the Trinity is invariable in all points: for its essence<note type="footnote"
     n="494" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> is one, its glory one,
    its everlastingness one, its kingship one, its power one, its will one, its operation one, and
    through it we hold that the Trinity is one God. And, though each appears by himself, yet there
    is one Godhead, in the same essence<note type="footnote" n="495" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>. Here some words seem to have fallen out.</note><damage><supplied resp="#ebrooks">......</supplied></damage>the Son the fact that he is begotten, and the Spirit the fact that
    he proceeds. And these are from the Father as from a root and we refer their Godhead eternally
    and timelessly to one first cause, to the Father, and so the principle of a single first cause
    is preserved. For we do not hold several first causes, but we reject the Jewish poverty also
    which sees little,, and do not confine the Godhead in one person, and at the same time we know
    and think of three hypostases in one essence<note type="footnote" n="494"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note>, and one identity of honour, and do not divide it into
    a trinity of first causes, and shun the polytheism of the pagans. (Of Cyril, from the 12th
    chapter of the Treasure. "As the sun is in the ray that proceeds from it, and the ray in the sun
    from which it proceeded, <pb n="185"/> and in the word is the intellect which begot it, and in
    the river the fount that sent it forth, and in the image the original, so the Father is in the
    Son and the Son in the Father, as he says, 'He who hath seen me hath seen the Father', and, 'I
    and my Father are one', and, 'I am in my Father, and my Father in me', being numerically divided
    into a duality, and being so in hypostases, but in that they are one in nature restricted to one
     Godhead")<note type="footnote" n="496" resp="#ebrooks">Thes. 12 (P. G., LXXV, 181, 184, 185),
     put together from several passages. The fact that this citation is introduced without preface
     makes it very doubtful if it is really part of the letter.</note>. Next the second question,
    'Why and in what way do we say that God the Word was humanized?'. The defence. But now it is
    reasonable to consider why and in what way we say that the only Word, the Son of God, was
    humanized; for this is the second question that you put. But we without going outside the divine
    Scriptures say that the reason for which he shone upon and gave light to this world by the
    coming of his Humanization in the flesh was that, as in Adam we die, so in Christ himself we
    might live<note type="footnote" n="497" resp="#ebrooks">1 Cor. xv, 22.</note>, and, as it is
    said, "By man is death, so also by man is the resurrection of the dead"<note type="footnote"
     n="498" resp="#ebrooks"> Ibid., 21.</note>. Since Adam was condemned to death after the
    transgression which was committed through the deceitfulness of the serpent, and heard the words,
     <pb n="186"/> "Dust thou art and to dust shalt thou return", and, "Cursed is the ground in the
    work of thine hands", and, "In the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat thy bread", and Eve too was
    also condemned with him by hearing the words, "In pains shalt thou bear children"<note
     type="footnote" n="499" resp="#ebrooks">Gen. iii, 16, 17, 19.</note>, so with us also who are
    sprung from them the charges of disobedience have been confirmed, and we ourselves are dust and
    to dust we return, and we are condemned to the curse and are creatures born in pains: and from
    that time we have been in subjection, being subject to lust and to the varied pleasure of this,
    according to the saying of the blessed Paul<note type="footnote" n="500" resp="#ebrooks">Tit.
     iii, 3.</note>. For it was right that against the cunning contriver of evil, the serpent and
    the destroyer of our life, we should contend with him with the same weapons (?)<note
     type="footnote" n="501" resp="#ebrooks">The substantive has perh. fallen out.</note> with which
    he deceived those founders of our race: and, since it was not the part of another power to annul
    the punishment fixed by our Lord himself, he did not send an envoy nor an angel, but, as Isaiah
    cries, the Lord himself saved us<note type="footnote" n="502" resp="#ebrooks">Is. LXIII,
     9.</note>. The only God the Word who is before the ages, the power and wisdom of the Father, in
    whose image he created rational man, became flesh, I mean man according to the words of
     "John<note type="footnote" n="503" resp="#ebrooks">John I, 14.</note>, not that he was changed
    into flesh (far be it!), but, while he remained invariable as God, he himself assumed the whole
    of me by a true <pb n="187"/> and hypostatic union, but still without the sin which had come in
    upon us<note type="footnote" n="504" resp="#ebrooks">Marg. 'everything that is is included in
     that which has past, and in the things that are present and in the things that are
     future'.</note>. For, immediately after Gabriel had made announcement to the Virgin and said to
    her, "Rejoice greatly, thou that art made glad, the Lord is with thee"<note type="footnote"
     n="505" resp="#ebrooks">Luke i, 28.</note>, at the very moment of time, we believe that God the
    Word himself came to dwell in her womb, and was incarnate of the Holy Spirit, and olthe very
    leaven of the holy Virgin, in flesh of our nature possessing an intelligent soul. For he says,
    "That which is born in thee is of the Holy Spirit"<note type="footnote" n="506" resp="#ebrooks"
     >Ibid., 35; Matth., i, 21 (?).</note>, since the Holy Spirit .operatively effected the
    fertilization of the conception, while Mary contributed the birth according to the natural
    manner of mothers. Wherefore also the period of conception was one of nine months (for he says,
    "But, when the days were accomplished that she should bring forth"<note type="footnote" n="507"
     resp="#ebrooks">Luke ii, 6.</note>), and all these things were devoid of phantasy<note
     type="footnote" n="508" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">φαντασία</foreign>.</note>,
    since he who was conceived took the seed of Abraham<note type="footnote" n="509" resp="#ebrooks"
     >Heb. II, 16.</note>: for a descendant of Abraham is the Virgin, who also is of our nature,
    from whom the Lord took flesh and became a babe. For he himself became a babe, and the babe was
    not first formed separately, while he afterwards came to be with him by way of indwelling, as
    those who divide him into two natures say. This unsound opinion is <pb n="188"/> rejected by the
    blessed Paul when he says, "For, since the children partook of flesh and blood, he himself also
    similarly partook of the same, in order that through death he might destroy him who hath the
    power of death, who is the devil" <note type="footnote" n="510" resp="#ebrooks">Heb. ii,
     14.</note>. If then<note type="footnote" n="511" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >ἄρα</foreign>.</note> he partook of flesh and blood similarly to the children and in the same
    way, it is plain that, as the soul of a man is born with its own body, though in its nature it
    is incorporeal, but is nevertheless reckoned to be one with it because of the union, so too he
    who was born is also said to be united to the body that was born that has a rational and
    intelligent soul. And, as you do not say that a man's soul passed into flesh, although it is
    united with the body by an original union, so also no one says that God the Word was changed
    into flesh and endured the process of mingling, because he is hypostatically united to a body.
    Wherefore, when he was born, he made the Virgin the God-bearer, but he did not receive the
    beginning of being God and being held as such from her, but in that he became man. he writes her
    as his mother. But he did not pass from being God, although he took that which he was not; but,
    as he remained that which he is, so also he became truly man. That the body which he united to
     <pb n="189"/> him was not without a soul is certain from the words of the angel: for he said,
    "Rise, take the boy and his mother, and go to the land of Israel, for they are dead who sought
    the boy's soul"<note type="footnote" n="512" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. ii, 20.</note>: concerning
    which he also said, "I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again"<note
     type="footnote" n="513" resp="#ebrooks">John x, 18.</note>. But it was not without intelligence
    and imperfect, according to the statement of the proverbs of Apollinaris, but was in fact
    intelligent, as indeed the very term 'boy' and the fact that he was named 'man' is enough to
    show this same thing: for a boy's soul is not without reason, but it is reasonable because it is
    human. However this very same thing is also clearly shown even by the sacred writings of the
    gospel; for it said of him, "Then he began to be distressed and grieved, and to say, 'My soul is
    sorrowful, even unto death'"<note type="footnote" n="514" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. xxvi,
     28.</note>. But it is plain to everyone that distress and grief happen to a rational and
    intellectual soul. But, if they say that the Godhead of the Only one took the place of
    intellect, this is in truth a thing without intellect, for us to assign the passion of distress
    to the impassible nature of God. Accordingly the Only God the Word became perfectly man, that he
    might:bestow upon us perfect salvation: for, as soon as he was born, he did away <pb n="190"/>
    the punishment laid upon Eve, who was first led astray by the serpent. If Emmanuel had not been
    born, who is the Word of God who took flesh, who according to the saying of the prophet 'removed
    weeping from all faces'<note type="footnote" n="515" resp="#ebrooks">Is. xxv, 8.</note>, the
    curse, "In pains shalt thou bear children"<note type="footnote" n="516" resp="#ebrooks">Gen.
     iii, 16.</note>, would not have ceased: nevertheless it ceased because God was born. Further
    witness is borne to this by the actual unerring words of the gospel also: for it introduces to
    us the angel saying, "I announce unto you great joy, which belongeth to all the world, that
    to-day there hath been born to us a Saviour, who is the Lord Christ, in the city of David"<note
     type="footnote" n="517" resp="#ebrooks">Luke II, 10, 11.</note>. Mark clearly that, if it were
    not that hé who was born was the Lord, the joy that came to all the world, which is also the joy
    of the whole race of men, the curse, "In pains shalt thou bear children", would not have ceased.
    But, if the birth is the cause of the joy, she who bore is also free from the punishment; and
    thenceforth the joy necessarily passes to those who believe in him: for he said, "Those who
    received him he gave them power to become sons of God"<note type="footnote" n="518"
     resp="#ebrooks">John i. 12.</note>, those who attained to the adoption through the Spirit,
    after he became man.</p>
   <p>And next the third question, as to how we should, understand Paul's <pb n="191"/> saying, "In
    him all the fulness of the Godhead dwelleth bodily"<note type="footnote" n="519" resp="#ebrooks"
     >Col. ii, 9.</note>. The defence.</p>
   <p>In the same God-befitting frame of mind let us also understand (and that is what in your third
    question you thought good to ask) the words which the wise Paul wrote and sent to the Golossians
    about Christ, how that in him all the fulness of the Godhead came to dwell bodily; for we do not
    understand the expression 'in him dwelleth' as the supporters of the impiety of Nestorius wish
    to understand it: for these say that the Word came to dwell in Christ by way of indwelling, as
    in one of the prophets. But, lest any man in consequence of the statement that he came to dwell
    decline from the proper opinion and reckon the Incarnation of the Word a mere indwelling, as
    happened in the case of a man, Paul is sufficient to meet this false tenet when he says that it
    came to dwell in him 'bodily', that is hypostatically and naturally, even as the statement that
    he similarly partook with us of flesh and blood<note type="footnote" n="520" resp="#ebrooks">
     Heb., 11, 14.</note> unconfusedly and immutably, in a Unity that is not dissipated, all
    mingling and phantasy<note type="footnote" n="521" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >φαντασία</foreign>.</note> being far from it; for it is alien to a bodiless nature that in
    consequence of its union with a body it should be mingled or changed, a thing which in its
    nature does <pb n="192"/> not touch anything bodily. As to the fact that the word 'dwell' is
    also used of those who are hypostatically united, we have the testimony of the wise Paul
    himself; for in writing to the Corinthians he said, "We know that, even if this our house, our
    tent on earth, is dissolved, we have a building from God, a house not made with hands, that
    abideth for ever in heaven"<note type="footnote" n="522" resp="#ebrooks">2 Cor. v, 1.</note>. As
    we are said to dwell in a body as in a house, so too God the Word is said to dwell in a body, as
    being hypostatically united to a body that has a rational and intelligent soul. But he said that
    all the fulness of the Godhead dwells, that is, not one operation, nor yet a partial grace of
    the Word himself, as took place in the inspiration of the prophets, but the whole hypostasis of
    the Only one, although he is raised above all limitation, he who imparts tens of thousands of
    operations to others, and distributes graces by way of gifts as from a fountain.</p>
   <p>And again the fourth question, as to how it is that, if we say that the Trinity is one nature,
    and also confess one incarnate nature of God the Word, we do not also say that the Father and
    the Holy Spirit became incarnate with the Son. The defence. <pb n="193"/>
   </p>
   <p>Since you have said that this also is impiously said by some men, that, inasmuch as we believe
    that God the Word was united to flesh, the Father also, inasmuch as he is named as being of the
    same nature, is necesarily said to have become incarnate, and the Holy Spirit also, we fitly say
    what we can and what we have believed, fixing our mind on the divine Scriptures, and not crying
    from the earth according to the prophet's saying<note type="footnote" n="523" resp="#ebrooks">
     Is., xix, 3 (?).</note>, nor yet making up things that come from our heart<note type="footnote"
     n="524" resp="#ebrooks">Jer. xxiii, 16.</note>. But this objection has occurred to them in this
    way. If so be that Christ cries in the gospel, "I am in my Father and my Father in me"<note
     type="footnote" n="525" resp="#ebrooks">John xiv, 10.</note>, and Paul again says that the Son
    is the image of the invisible God<note type="footnote" n="526" resp="#ebrooks">Col. i,
     15.</note>, and the Holy Spirit also the image of the Son, in that he said of those who had
    been admitted to the adoption as sons by the Spirit, "they became conformed to the image of his
     Son"<note type="footnote" n="527">Rom. viii, 29.</note>, that it might be shown as following
    from this that the Holy Trinity is one essence<note type="footnote" n="528" resp="#ebrooks"
      ><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note>, when it is said that the Son became
    incarnate, how can we not also allow that the Father and the Holy Spirit too became incarnate,
    inasmuch as they are in the Son and appear in him? This is what these say. But we say with
    intelligence: These, my good men, are the words of those who confuse the hypostases. But, if the
    Father is the Father, he never passes <pb n="194"/> into the Son, and the Holy Spirit also
    remains fixedly and without transformation in his own hypostasis, and does not pass into the
    hypostasis of the Son: but the divine Scriptures have said that the Son became incarnate and
    became man, and it is on account of the co-essentiality that, the Father and the Holy Spirit are
    said to be in him, not in order that we may dissolve and confound the hypostasis of the Father
    and of the Holy Spirit in the Son. But, if the Son is the image of the Father, the very name
    'image' shows that it is understood to be the image of another hypostasis separate from itself:
    for, if it is an image, it is an image of some one, and, because it is an unvarying image in all
    points, it is not therefore the person himself of whom it is an image; for, if it were the
    person himself, it would fail to . be an image, for of whom would it be an image? Suppose a man
    delineates and copies a design and pattern from an original tablet on to another, and draws it
    correctly in all points, and makes the copy like the original, in no <pb n="195"/> point falling
    short of the pattern that was first designed, but makes the colour and form<note type="footnote"
     n="529" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">σχῆμα</foreign>.</note> and stature and size
    and pose of the limbs also alike, and those who see it for the first time do not know, if one
    may so say, which is the original from which it was drawn and designed, on account of the exact
    resemblance of the appearance in both, and after this he takes the copy and fixes it on a wall,
     then<note type="footnote" n="530" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄρα</foreign>.</note>
    will anyone of right understanding say that the original tablet has been fixed on the wall,
    because it is a copy of it and contains all that belongs to the original pattern? So we say that
    the Son became incarnate, the true image of the Father, who has by nature everything that
    belongs to his begetter, and we do not on this account hold that the Father became incarnate,
    who appears in his own special hypostasis or person. <pb n="196"/> What has been said is
    intended as an indication of the subject, in order that the understanding may receive a
    defective and obscure example, because the whole force of the example does not follow in the
    footsteps of the truth, since here the image is without soul and immoveable, and is limited by
    the appearance of colours, but above there is a living and moveable image, suprasensual and
    unlimited and without appearance<note type="footnote" n="531" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">σχῆμα</foreign>.</note>, and possessing immutability by nature. But, if we look
    into the divine Scriptures, we may through the mystery that has been richly revealed in them by
    another example also reįoive an illustration of what is stated. It is everywhere known that our
     speech<note type="footnote" n="532" resp="#ebrooks">Word.</note> is the offspring of our mind,
    and not the offspring only, but also the clear image, which represents the disposition<note
     type="footnote" n="533" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">διάθεσις</foreign>.</note> that
    is in the depths of the mind, and with the speech comes forth also the <pb n="197"/> breath<note
     type="footnote" n="534" resp="#ebrooks">Spirit.</note> of the mouth. The example is defective,
    and is a kind of similitude and shadow of the truth itself for those who are able to listen
    properly and intelligently. However, as our speech comes out through the organ<note
     type="footnote" n="535" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὄργανον</foreign>.</note> of
    the voice and moves the hearing and passes inside him who hears, and no one says that the speech
    which is begotten by the mind, exists hypostatically, the speech which enters into the hearing
    of him who hears, or says that the breath which comes out in the speech through the voice exists
    in hypostasis <note type="footnote" n="536" resp="#ebrooks">I cannot render this otherwise, but
     do not follow the argument.</note>, but only calls it a help to the hearing, so understand also
    with regard to the mystery of God the Word, because he himself alone hypostatically and
    ineffably and as he himself only knows came to dwell in the Virgin's womb and became incarnate
    from her, and neither the Father his begetter nor the Spirit which proceeds shared in this, but
    according to the saying of John, "The Word became flesh, and he was God, and was with God"<note
     type="footnote" n="537" resp="#ebrooks"> John, i, 1, 14.</note>, as one with another, because
    the hypostases exist severally. Since then these things are so, that question of theirs which
    arises from ignorance <pb n="198"/> is superfluous and vain, a question that amounts to actual
    impiety. "If" (they say) "you say that the Trinity is one nature, and say that there is one
    nature of the incarnate Word, how are you not driven to saying that the whole Trinity became
    incarnate?" I am surprised at the cunning rusticity of those men, as shown by the way in which
    they display courage without consideration against the right opinion. We<note type="footnote"
     n="538" resp="#ebrooks">Cf. ep. 6.</note> use the name 'nature' sometimes generally of
     'essence'<note type="footnote" n="539" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
     >οὐσία</foreign>.</note>, and sometimes specifically signifying the hypostasis of a man. We
    term all mankind one nature, as in the text "Every nature of beasts and of birds and of things
    that are in the water is subjected and made subject to human nature"<note type="footnote"
     n="540" resp="#ebrooks">James iii, 7.</note>: and again we call a man 'nature', Paul for
    instance or Peter or James. Where we name all mankind one nature, we use the name 'nature'
    generically in place of 'essence': but, where we speak of one nature of Paul, we employ the name
    'nature' in place of 'individual hypostasis'. So also, when we say that the Holy Trinity is one
    nature, as in the text, "In order that we may be sharers of the divine nature"<note
     type="footnote" n="541" resp="#ebrooks">2 Pet. i, 4</note>, we use the name 'nature' in place
    of the general <pb n="199"/> designation 'essence'<note type="footnote" n="542" resp="#ebrooks"
      ><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note>. And to say that the Holy Trinity is one
    nature is the same as to say that it is one Godhead, as we are in fact accustomed to call all
    mankind one nature. But, when we say 'one incarnate nature of God the Word', we say 'nature' in
    place of an individual designation, and thereby we denote the one actual hypostasis of the Word,
    like that of Paul or Peter or any single man. Therefore also, when we say one nature which
    became incarnate', we do not say so absolutely, but we say 'one nature of the Word himself, and
    clearly denote that it is one hypostasis. But again let no one stain the divine nature that is
    raised above all things with anything lowly taken from the example of Paul and Peter. For,
    although they are of the same essence, they differ not only in hypostases, but also in power and
    operation, and stature and shape, and in the various kinds of impulses that are in men's minds.
    The Holy Trinity however differs by the difference of hypostases only, and in every point is
    unvarying in equality, and in the fact that it is of the same essence. And avoid that poverty of
    the example which is not worthy of the Godhead, and do not conceive of the Word as without
    hypostasis, nor yet of the Spirit as being dissipated in the air<note type="footnote" n="543"
      ><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀήρ</foreign>.</note>. <pb n="200"/>
   </p>
   <p>Next the fifth question, as to how the Only one, who is a quickening blessing, was termed a
     curse<note type="footnote" n="544" resp="#ebrooks">Gal. iii, 13.</note>. The defence.</p>
   <p>We will now go on to give you an answer with regard to the fifth question also, how the Only
    one, who is a quickening blessing, was termed a curse. If he became man to free our race from
    the bonds of former crimes, and took upon him the seed of Abraham, and flesh of our nature, and
    united a human soul to himself hypostatically, therefore he made all the debts of our race to
    which we were liable his own: for we are accursed, and we came under, the penalty of the curse,
    and heard the words, "Dust thou art and to dust shalt thou return", and, "Cursed is the earth in
    the work of thine hands", and, "In the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat bread"<note
     type="footnote" n="545" resp="#ebrooks">Gen. iii, 17, 19. </note>; and he became the
    firstfruits of our nature. For in that he took upon him the seed of Abraham he is consequently
    said to have become<note type="footnote" n="546">We rather require 'been subject to'; but an
     emendation cannot be made without violent alteration. But cf. p. 202, 1. 10. </note> those
    things to which our nature was subject. Nor yet was he subject to these things for a moment of
    time, but rather after they had been vainly applied to him he destroyed them. Just as the sun
    when it shines in a gloomy and dark house, as soon as it puts forth its ray, dispels the
    darkness, since it itself is not affected <pb n="201"/> by darkness, in the same way also the
    Only God the Word, the Sun of righteousness, as soon as he approached our nature, also dispelled
    the curse. For the holy Virgin, who conceived with the divine and incorruptible conception,
    immediately heard from Elizabeth who had been divinely moved, that is the servant of the
    Baptist, the words, "Blessed art thou among women, and blessed is the fruit of thy womb. And
    whence is this to me, that the mother of my Lord should come to me?"<note type="footnote"
     n="547" resp="#ebrooks">Luke i, 42, 43.</note>. If she had not known that it was the Lord who
    was conceived of the God-bearer Mary, she would not have cried, "Blessed is the fruit of thy
    womb". In agreement with this our Lord himself also in his words dispelled the curse, that the
    earth might no more be 'cursed in the work of thine hands', saying, "Work not the food that
    perisheth, but the food that abideth in eternal life, which the Son of man will give you", and
    not, "In the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat thy bread", but, "I am the bread of life which
    came down from heaven, and if any man eat of this bread he shall live for ever", and no more,
    "Dust thou art and to dust shalt thou return", but, "This is the will of my Father, that
    everyone who seeth the Son and believeth on him shall have eternal life, and I will raise him up
    at the last day"<note type="footnote" n="548" resp="#ebrooks">John vi, 27, 40, 51.</note>. You
    see that on all points by <pb n="202"/> being himself made a curse he becomes a dispeller of the
    curse, and this curse he takes up on to the cross, and thence puts it to flight: for it was
    overcome by the law which said, "Cursed of God is everyone who shall be hanged upon wood"<note
     type="footnote" n="549" resp="#ebrooks">Deut. xxi, 23. </note>. And he himself underwent the
    accursed death that was for our sake, and thence blessed the whole human race; and the blessed
    Paul bears witness who writes to the Galatians and says, "Christ redeemed us from the curse of
    the law, and became a curse for our sake, because it is written, 'Cursed is everyone who is
    hanged upon wood', in order that the blessing of Abraham might be among the nations in Jesus
     Christ"<note type="footnote" n="550" resp="#ebrooks">Gal. iii, 13, 14.</note>. So also he is
    said to have become sin<note type="footnote" n="551" resp="#ebrooks">2 Cor. v, 21.</note>,
    because he endured the death that was the due of sinners; for, while he is himself the pure
    justice of the Father, he is crucified between two robbers; but these on account of their
    offences, and in accordance with the passage in the Gospel of Mark who says, "And with him they
    crucified two robbers, one on the right hand and one on the left, and the Scripture was
    fulfilled which saith, 'He was numbered with the unjust'"<note type="footnote" n="552"
     resp="#ebrooks">Mark xv, 27, 28.</note>. So he became sin to remit the sins of others: so also
    he paid the debt that was incurred for us, and we ourselves became righteousness in him; for
    those who have been freed from debts are righteous, and <pb n="203"/> are not termed liable.
    And, because during the time of his Humanization he did no sin, therefore also iniquity was not
    found in him, but he showed himself righteous, that is, he is righteousness; and, when he became
    flesh, all our nature again was justified in him as in firstfruits; and this is what the wise
    Paul said to the Corinthians about the Father, "He made him sin for our sake, who knew no sin,
    that we might be the righteousness of God in him"<note type="footnote" n="553" resp="#ebrooks">2
     Cor. v, 21.</note>. This too was carried out in the ritual of the law also; for the two goats
    on whom lots were laid were a type of Christ our Saviour, who is made up of two elements, the
    perfect Godhead I mean and the manhood: and the one, on whom the Lord's lot fell, was
    slaughtered, while the other was dismissed into the wilderness that is not passed,, who also was
    named 'the dismissible', who gained the appellation also from the fact itself; for he was
    dismissed, but was hot simply dismissed, but in the manner which Scripture mentioned; for it
    said as follows: "And thou shalt bring the living goat, and Aaron shall lay his two hands on the
    head of the living goat, and shall confess over him all the sin of the sons of Israel, and all
    their wickedness and their iniquity, and shall lay them on the head of the living goat, and
    shall dismiss him by means of a man who is ready into the wilderness; <pb n="204"/> and the goat
    shall take upon him all their iniquity"<note type="footnote" n="554" resp="#ebrooks">Lev. xvi,
     20-22.</note>. This therefore was thus performed in the case of the two goats also, that the
    one was slaughtered and the other dismissed. We clearly see the hidden meaning which relates to
    the Cross: for the type denotes that the same one Christ suffered in the flesh, but remained
    without suffering in that he is considered to he true God. For the same person both is separated
    by lots to the Lord and slaughtered (for 'he delivered himself for our sake as an offering and a
    sacrifice to God the Father for a sweet savour'<note type="footnote" n="555" resp="#ebrooks">
     Eph., v, 2.</note>), and goes away without suffering bearing the sins of all Israel, which in
    the type of Aaron were confessed over the head of the goat: for he clearly displays himself as
    being himself true God, over whom we confess our sins according to law; for "I will make
    confession", he saith, "unto thee, Lord, concerning my sins, and thou wilt forgive the
    wickedness of my heart"<note type="footnote" n="556" resp="#ebrooks">Ps. xxxi, 5.</note>; for,
    though 'he was led as a lamb to the slaughter', yet, 'who shall tell his generation, because his
    life is taken away from the earth?'<note type="footnote" n="557" resp="#ebrooks"> Is., LIII, 7,
     8.</note>, for he is without descent as God, and he is life in his nature, for he was taken
    away and lifted up from the earth. Truly is it said of him in reference to the type that he
    shall be dismissed into the wilderness that is not passed; for that country is impassable to all
    outside <pb n="205"/> nature, and is passable to him who became incarnate only, I mean the
    throne of the kingdom, on which he sits at the Father's right hand, bearing our sins; for so too
    John also the loud-voiced preacher and ambassador of the Word himself cried and said, "Behold!
    the Lamb of God who beareth the sin of the world"<note type="footnote" n="558" resp="#ebrooks"
     >John i, 29.</note>. For the same person is termed at one time a goat, at another a lamb; and
    he shows that he came to suffer not only for the sake of sinners, but also for the sake of the
    righteous; for death reigned 'even over those who had not sinned' also, as Paul also said<note
     type="footnote" n="559" resp="#ebrooks">Rom. v, 14.</note>. Accordingly the lamb is the type of
    the righteous, and the goat of sinners; for the righteous stand as lambs on the right hand, and
    the sinners as goats on the left. Let no one think- that through the symbol of the two goats he
    shows us two Christs, one passible and the other impassible, but one and the same, passible in
    the flesh, but impassible in his Godhead. For indeed one goat only was not sufficient to signify
    what was signified with two (how was it possible for the same to be slaughtered and not
    slaughtered?), to show that Christ tasted death in the flesh, and in his Godhead is raised above
    suffering. Is it not plain therefore that another goat is necessarily taken, in order that the
    one fact may be perfectly revealed symbolically in <pb n="206"/> the two? Just as a painter,
    when he depicts the story of Abraham, depicts him several times, now hearing God saying to him,
    "Offer thy son to me as a burnt-sacrifice", now cutting faggots, now again binding Isaac and
    laying him on the faggots, now with his hand armed with the knife and stretched out to slay and
    held back by the heavenly voice coming from above, and we do not think the one Abraham to be
    many because the same person was depicted many times, and indeed one picture was not sufficient
    to tell the whole story, so also for the shadowy representation of the symbol, for the sake of
    perfectly setting forth the fact, two goats were taken, and we do not divide the one Christ into
    two, but we declare him to be one out of two natures, the perfect Godhead and the manhood,
    according to the faith of the divine Scriptures, and the words of the fathers that are inspired
    by the Spirit, from which sources we also speak these things. That the two goats symbolized the
    one Christ is plain from the allegory of the lots; for the priest Aaron did not select one of
    the goats at haphazard to be slaughtered, but committed the matter to the uncertainty of lots,
    that by this he might show the primary unity of God the Word and his flesh. As he is himself God
     <pb n="207"/> impassible and free, but by reason of the union with a body possessing a rational
    soul was condemned to death, though in his nature he is immortal, so also the one goat who was
    to be dismissed to the wilderness symbolized the impassibility of the Godhead of the Only one,
    and was under the decree of slaughter; for the lot cast over him, whether he was to be
    slaughtered or dismissed, was uncertain. Accordingly it is plain that the two goats signify the
    one Christ, and that the same suffered in the flesh, and, in that he is God, remained raised
    above sufferings. Nor yet let anyone, imitating the madness of the heathen, imagine that the
    dismissed goat was set apart and dismissed to the wilderness for some demon; for this is a
    departure from the laws of Moses, inasmuch as he said, "Hear, Israel. The Lord thy God is one
    Lord", and again, "Thou shalt fear the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve, and to him
    shalt thou draw near, and in his name shalt thou swear", and, "Thou shalt not go after other
     gods"<note type="footnote" n="560">Deut. vi, 4, 13, 14.</note>; and again in another place,
    "And ye shall not make mention of the name of other gods, and it shall not be heard from your
    mouth"; and again, "Thou shalt not worship their gods, nor serve them, nor do according to their
    deeds, but shalt utterly overturn them and destroy their pillars, and shalt serve the Lord <pb
     n="208"/> thy God only"<note type="footnote" n="561" resp="#ebrooks">Ex. xxiii, 13, 24,
     25.</note>. How then should he in the same mind break in pieces and overturn their pillars (and
    he did not allow the name of other gods to be mentioned at all beside the one Lord God), and on
    the other hand separate the goat to another beside him as to some evil fiend, and propitiate
    this fiend in this way? But it is plain that the two goats were offered in order to honour one
    God only, and completed the symbolic allegory which we have already mentioned, and two lots were
    cast, and one was slaughtered to the Lord, and the other was dismissed after the manner of the
    separation of the lots, and therefore he was called 'the dismissible'. If he had said, "One goat
    to the Lord, and one goat to the dismissible", perhaps their charge would have derived some
    plausibility from the divine Scripture, because it said, "One lot to the Lord, and one to the
    dismissible"; for it is plain that the one was separated for the purpose of slaughter, and the
    other was dismissed to the Lord, not to another different from him; for this is what the divine
    Scripture said, "And he shall set' the living one before the Lord, in order to dismiss him in
     dismissal"<note type="footnote" n="562" resp="#ebrooks">Lev. xvi, 10. I do not follow the
     argument in this passage.</note>. But some of the learned Hebrews, that is rather those who are
    earlier than those who are of the Hebrews, said <pb n="209"/> "One lot to the Lord, and one lot
    to him that was dismissed"<note type="footnote" n="563" resp="#ebrooks"> I do not know the
     source of this quotation.</note>, in order that in all points and that even from the very
    imagination of the heathen, or, to speak fittingly, from their lack of instruction, it might be
    seen that their charge against the holy laws of Moses is without plausibility. For those who
    after the Christian religion were lifted up in philosophy, and endeavoured to adorn
    demon-worship in a reverend fashion<note type="footnote" n="564" resp="#ebrooks">Julian
     (?).</note>, as they themselves say on behalf of others, say of their god who is called
    'mblkhywn, "We should not sacrifice to the gods, but by purity of mind propitiate and honour
     them"<note type="footnote" n="563" resp="#ebrooks">I do not know the source of this
     quotation.</note>: but men who were fettered in the same chain as they said that men should
    sedulously offer sacrifices to the evil spirits who delight in blood, not that they may help,
    but that they may not injure<note type="footnote" n="565" resp="#ebrooks">Porphyry, De Abstin.,
     ii, 37 ff.; De sacrificiis et diis atque daemonibus, ap. Iamblichum, ed. Ficinus (1577), p.
     317. </note>. If then Moses separated and dismissed one of the goats to a demon, according to
    the madness of those men he ought to have ordered this goat to be slaughtered to the demon, and
    he who is pleased by blood ought to have rejoiced in his blood. But now the exact contrary is
    the case: the one who was set apart to God Most High was slaughtered, while the other, the
    dismissible, or, as they wish to say. the one who was separated to an evil <pb n="210"/> demon,
    was dismissed into the wilderness without blood and without sacrifice. By all these arguments
    the ingenious madness of the heathen has been refuted, who wished to stain the divine Scripture
    with the blame of their cults of many demons, men who did not shrink from calling the usual
    sacrifices to their idols 'dismissible', in order to substantiate their error by a plausible
    identity of name. These things we have stated shortly in the desire to show how Jesus became sin
    for us, that we might in him become the righteousness of God. He endured a death that was for
    our sake, he who for the sins of us all became one that is subject, he who knows not sin, for
    according to the prophet's saying, "He came to death for the sins of my people, and for our sake
    he suffered pain, and was smitten, and he endured sickness for our iniquity"<note
     type="footnote" n="566" resp="#ebrooks">Is. LIII, 5 (loose quotation).</note>. So also Paul
    wrote to the Hebrews and said, "Christ was offered once, that he might bear the sins of many" ,
    and he says that 'by his sacrifice he hath been revealed once for all at the last for the doing
    away of sin', and 'he offered one eternal offering for our sins'<note type="footnote" n="567"
     resp="#ebrooks">Heb. ix, 26, 28; x, 12. </note>: and Peter the eminent among the apostles said,
    "The same carried up our sins in his body on to the cross, that we, being freed from sins, might
    live in righteousness"<note type="footnote" n="568" resp="#ebrooks">1 Pet. ii, 24.</note>.</p>
   <p>And again the sixth question, as to how we say that the same suffered in <pb n="211"/> the
    flesh, and in his Godhead remained without suffering, and, while we do not make him alien to
    suffering, we keep him without suffering. The defence. Now we will give a sufficient answer to
    that question also, how we say that the same suffered in the flesh, and did not suffer in the
    Godhead, and, while we do not make him alien to suffering, we keep him without suffering. On the
    same subject we will lay before you an example which has come to us from our fathers. The force
    of examples is in truth small, and far removed from the truth; nevertheless, if only in some
    thin and shadowy phantasies<note type="footnote" n="569" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >φαντασίας</foreign>.</note>, it offers to the understanding a beginning of conceptions. As,
    when iron or another similar substance<note type="footnote" n="570" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">ὕλη</foreign>.</note> is abundantly warmed by fire, and is heated by flame, we
    know that, while the iron does not pass out of its own nature, the iron which has passed into a
    complete flame, and has been made to hiss and to glow by it, it appears to be all fire, and,
    while it is in this state, blows are applied to it, it being smitten by a hammer or by means of
    other kinds of strokes, but the iron is exposed to the blows themselves, being expanded and
    narrowed at the same time, while the nature of the fire is in no way injured by the smiter, so
    must we also understand the mystery <pb n="212"/> concerning Christ also, even although all the
    power of speech shrinks, from the glory of the fact. He was hypostatically united to a body with
    a rational and intelligent soul, but he permitted it to suffer naturally from the blows of
    pains, I mean on the cross, when he might have deadened these also as God, but he was not
    desirous of this, for it was not for himself, but for our race, that he was purchasing the
    successes of victory. Therefore he permitted his body to suffer, while even he himself also was
    not alien from suffering, for he was united to a suffering body, and, as it is his body, so also
    it is called his suffering; nevertheless as God he remained without suffering, for God is not
    touched by suffering. He is said also to have tasted death for us, in that his soul was
    separated from his body; not that his soul was cut away from his Godhead, or his body left
    without Godhead; but he showed that he was in both without separation, for neither was his soul
    left in Sheol, nor did his flesh see corruption<note type="footnote" n="571" resp="#ebrooks">Ps.
     xv, 10.</note>, according to the saying of the Psalmist. For he was not separated from his body
    that was buried, and therefore he annihilated corruption; for, if it had been separated from him
    who is life and incorruption, perhaps it would have been constantly <pb n="213"/> attacked by
    corruption also. For he went down into Sheol with his soul also, the whole of him being in it,
    and the whole of him in his body without separation, as one that is incorporeal and is able to
    fill everything as one that is infinite. It was necessary for him to give light even to the
    lower regions also, and to have mercy on the souls there imprisoned, and, according to the
    saying of the prophet, "to say to those that are in bonds, 'Come forth', and to those also that
    are in darkness, 'Be revealed'"<note type="footnote" n="572" resp="#ebrooks"> Is., XLIX,
     9.</note>. This he accomplished in action. The gates of Sheol which saw him trembled, and he
    broke the bars of iron and gates of bronze<note type="footnote" n="573" resp="#ebrooks">Ps. cvi,
     16.</note>, and opened Paradise which was shut, and "many bodies of just men among those who
    had fallen asleep came out of their graves after his resurrection, and went into the holy city,
    and appeared to many"<note type="footnote" n="574" resp="#ebrooks"> Matth., xxvii, 53.</note>.
    Very properly the evangelist added, 'after his resurrection'; for it was necessary that he who
    is life in his nature should himself first begin the resurrection, and that the very one who was
    able to dissolve the power of death should himself tread the way for the rest who came after
    him. He did not deal arbitrarily with the devil, the same who led the first man astray, when he
    was defeated as by God, but, as one who is just and 'taketh the wise in their craftiness'<note
     type="footnote" n="575" resp="#ebrooks">Job, v, 13.</note>, he brought the <pb n="214"/> crafty
    one into subjection by means of his devices. He who led Adam astray and said to him, "You will
    be a god, if you transgress the law", fell by the device of craft. He fought with the second
    Adam who is Christ, and found him to be God and man at the same time; and he won a just victory
    over him; and henceforth we confidently sing songs of praise for his victory over death and say,
    "Where is thy victory, death? and where is thy sting, Sheol?" For Paul says that 'the sting of
    death is sin'<note type="footnote" n="576" resp="#ebrooks">I Cor. xv, 55, 56.</note>.</p>
   <p>Next the seventh question, why the law was given to the fathers that they should circumcise
    their foreskin. The defence.</p>
   <p>Now we pass on to discuss the subject of circumcision. This<note type="footnote" n="577"
     resp="#ebrooks">This passage to 'kin' (p. 215,1.1) is published in Greek in Cramer, Cat. in
     Act. Apost., p. 108.</note> is what you ask, "Why was the law given to the fathers that they
    should circumcise their foreskin?" Some have simply and easily handed down a reason like this.
    They say, "Because Abraham migrated from the land of the Chaldees, and the Chaldees were
    permitted (and the same was the case too with the Medes and Persians also) according to the
    custom of their fathers to have intercourse with their mothers and sisters, for this reason
    therefore he circumcised his foreskin, that he might shun kindred flesh, <pb n="215"/> and
    renounce marriage with those of his kin, and on this account God gave the law to the sons of
    Israel through Moses and said, 'A man shall not go in to any that is related to him in the flesh
    to uncover his shame'<note type="footnote" n="578" resp="#ebrooks">Lev. XVIII, 6. What follows
     to 'ever' (1. 6) is in Cramer, l. c., headed <foreign xml:lang="grc">μετ᾽
     ὀλίγα</foreign>.</note>". And others say that the reason why Abraham was commanded to
    circumcise his progeny also besides was that it might be plain that Christ should come of them
    in the flesh who is God over all for ever and ever. But, if you please, we will pass from these
    reasons; for it is known that the Egyptians also as well and other nations circumcise their
    foreskin, even although they imitated the Hebrews; and we state that which is true and befits
    God the lawgiver, and that is very sublime and to which testimony is borne by the Scriptures,
    that circumcision promises renunciation of fleshly birth, and acquisition of the adoption of the
    Spirit, by which we are called sons of God; for it is written, "Thus saith the Lord, 'Israel is
    my son, my firstborn'"<note type="footnote" n="579" resp="#ebrooks">Ex. iv, 22.</note>. After
    the fall from Paradise and the' destruction of immortality, Adam knew Eve, and she conceived and
    bare; and this unstable intercourse, intercourse befitting beasts, was given for the propagation
    of our race, it being a kind of healing of the sickness, that the race of men might <pb n="216"
    /> not be cut off through death. The woman was not at first given to Adam for the sake of the
    procreation of children, but that she might be a helper to him; for the Lord God said, "It is
    not good for Adam to be alone; let us make him a helper like to him"<note type="footnote"
     n="580" resp="#ebrooks">Gen. II, 18.</note>. He did not say from the beginning that he would
    make her be fruitful and multiply, in order that by means of fertility the race might go on to
    multiplication; for God might have done this even without the intercourse of marriage, and have
    made our race increase and multiply like the myriads of angels, as the Lord himself actually
    said in a place in the gospel, "In the resurrection there is no marriage, nor yet are they
    joined in marriage, but they will be as the angels in heaven"<note type="footnote" n="581"
     resp="#ebrooks">Matth. xxii, 30.</note>. If anyone says, "What is the help that the woman was
    to give the man?", we easily say: In the worship in Paradise and in the keeping of the law; as
    Solomon also said of a similar woman, "Who can find a manly woman?"<note type="footnote" n="582"
     resp="#ebrooks">Pr., xxix, 28.</note>, and again another wise man says, "A manly woman
    gladdeneth her husband", and, "A good woman is a good portion<note type="footnote" n="583"
     resp="#ebrooks">Sir., xxvi, 2, 3.</note>": and for this reason they also received the law in
    common, that through union and conjunction of breath<note type="footnote" n="584">This probably
     represents some Greek compound (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁμοπνοία</foreign>?).</note> they might
    be cautious, and not liable to be overcome by the <pb n="217"/> deceit of the serpent; for he
    said to them, "Of the tree of knowledge of good and evil ye shall not eat of it; but in the day
    in which ye shall eat of it ye shall die"<note type="footnote" n="585">Gen. ii, 17.</note>. For,
    as long as they kept the law, and rejoiced with one another without passion, and did not
    perceive one another's nakedness, and also did not think of their union in marriage, they
    enjoyed the blessed life in Paradise itself. But, when the woman gave up the duty of help, and
    like a weak person out of simplicity accepted the deceitful counsel of the serpent, then she
    herself also became an evil counsellor to the man, and immediately they were alien to God, and
    also to the life in Paradise, and by means of death were condemned; and Adam knew his wife, and
    she becomes a helper to him in the second line, through the procreation of children<note
     type="footnote" n="586" resp="#ebrooks">Cf. ep. 63.</note>. And at first she was given him as a
    helper in the worship in Paradise; for such is God's care for us that, even when we change, he
    continues to help us: for he made man his own master, and to honour that which is good; and,
    having foreseen that he would change, he provided a helper for him beforehand. Therefore also
    Adam by the grace of God, as soon as the woman was created, foretold that a man should 'leave
    his father and his <pb n="218"/> mother, and cleave to his wife, and they two should be one
     flesh'<note type="footnote" n="587" resp="#ebrooks">Gen. ii,24.</note>. This bodily birth
    circumcision renounces, which was given after the fall from the life in Paradise in the
    character of a remedy, and causes us to approach to the impassibility which existed during the
    residence in Paradise; by which we are named sons of God, inasmuch as it slays our members upon
    the earth, and puts off from us the old man. The truth itself, of which circumcision is a type,
    testifies to us; for Paul wrote to the Colossians and said that circumcision in Christ is
    baptism, whereby we put away from us our old man, and the mortality wherein we died after our
    fall from Paradise, and we also cut away the bodily desire as it were a kind of foreskin, and
    bury it in the waters which slay sin, and in the same way we are buried with Christ, and rise as
    new men and born afresh, and hasten to the new and; passionless life; for this is what Paul
    wrote: "In whom ye were circumcised with a circumcision not made with hands, by stripping off
    the body of your flesh, by the circumcision of Christ, and were buried with him in baptism, and
    rose in him through faith in the operation of God who raised him from the place of the dead; and
    you also, who had died in your sins and in the foreskin of your flesh, he quickened <pb n="219"
    /> with him, and he forgave you all your sins"<note type="footnote" n="588" resp="#ebrooks">Col.
     ii, 11-13.</note>. You see that circumcision is the destruction of the foreskin, and contains a
    renunciation of fleshly birth and of the body's pleasure in mortality; for it confesses the
    passionless and new-fashioned life, as the actual truth of baptism showed, of which circumcision
    is a type, which in a shadow cuts away the foreskin of the flesh, while baptism cuts away the
    foreskin of the soul, and, so to speak, destroys its excessive wickedness. Such was the legal
    ceremony, and the covenant with Abraham, and of<note type="footnote" n="589" resp="#ebrooks">Sic
     Syr.</note> his descendants, which by the ancients was carried out in a bodily and sensual
    fashion, but signified beforehand the allegorical conceptions, which the spiritual and
    suprasensual ceremony in Christ revealed and brought to pass, for through baptism we are
    circumcised with a suprasensual circumcision, and receive in our mind the privilege of being no
    longer sons of the flesh, for we are named sons of God. Hear what John the thunder and trumpet
    of the divine words says, "For those who received him he gave them power to become sons of God,
    those who believed on his name, who were born not of blood, nor of the will of man, but of
     God"<note type="footnote" n="590" resp="#ebrooks">John i, 12, 13.</note>. Joshua<note
     type="footnote" n="591" resp="#ebrooks">Syr. 'Jesus'.</note> also the son of Nun, who typified
    Jesus who is God and our Saviour, shows this clearly, that circumcision is the baptism which is
     <pb n="220"/> perfected in Christ, and was given to the sons of Israel as to a kind of sons
    without passibility; but, because they had lived forty years in the wilderness, it happened that
    the sons who were begotten by them remained uncircumcised, though it was possible for them to
    circumcise. But this did not happen by chance, but because God was directing this matter in
    order to reveal the future mystery; and neither did Moses circumcise them, the exact observer of
    the fathers' customs, who ordered that anyone who collected sticks on the sabbath-day should
     die<note type="footnote" n="592" resp="#ebrooks">Num. xv, 32-35.</note>, who knew all things
    beforehand, and among them the threat pronounced by God who said, "Whoever is not circumcised in
    the flesh of his foreskin on the eighth day, that soul shall perish from among its people,
    because it hath set at naught my covenant"<note type="footnote" n="593" resp="#ebrooks">Gen.
     xvii, 14.</note>; nor yet did Joshua<note type="footnote" n="594" resp="#ebrooks">Syr. '
     Jesus'.</note> again, who succeeded to the government after Moses, circumcise them before they
    crossed Jordan; but, after they had crossed Jordan, then he took knives of rock and cut away
    their foreskins from them. And this is plain, that he who has crossed Jordan and by the laver is
    admitted to regeneration is circumcised with a rock-knife, which is Christ: for "the <pb n="221"
    /> Word of God is living, and effectual and sharp beyond a two-edged knife"<note type="footnote"
     n="595" resp="#ebrooks">Heb. iv, 12.</note>; and according to Paul's saying Christ also is a
     rock<note type="footnote" n="596" resp="#ebrooks">1 Cor. x, 4.</note>. Let no one hold the
    unreasonable supposition that they had no iron-knives in the wilderness; for they were armed,
    and slew those who opposed them. Mark again the same type in other mysteries also; for the
    blessed Paul said, "Those who were baptized in Christ were baptized in his death"<note
     type="footnote" n="597" resp="#ebrooks">Rom. vi, 3.</note>, and. Joshua<note type="footnote"
     n="598" resp="#ebrooks">Syr. 'Jesus'.</note> the son of Nun presents the same figure, for he
    provided that the knives with which he circumcised the sons of Israel should be buried with him,
    that thereby he might show that those who are baptized in the name of Jesus the true God with
    the baptism that is completed in his death are by it circumcised. And, when we examine the sense
    of Scripture, we find an unlimited abundance of thoughts, and a primary union and agreement of
    the types with the truth, and praise the one God, the giver of the two covenants<note
     type="footnote" n="599" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">διαθήκας</foreign>.</note>.
    And, as to the manner again in which we on being admitted to the divine laver and regeneration
    and putting off from us our old man are both invited by Christ to the mystic table and eat the
    angelic heavenly bread, Joshua the son of Nun himself again showed us this mystery. For, <pb
     n="222"/> after they had crossed the Jordan and been circumcised with knives of rock, then for
    the first time those who were circumcised ate of the wheat of the land of promise, and
    celebrated the Passover, not with the old leaven, but with the pure true leavens: and, as, when
    Jesus Christ ate the legal Passover with his disciples, and thereby fulfilled the law, and took
    the bread of thanksgiving in the midst, and blessed<note type="footnote" n="600" resp="#ebrooks"
     > (G (2) L) 'blessed in the midst the eucharistia and'.</note> the cup, and put an end to the
    legal Passover, the new<note type="footnote" n="601" resp="#ebrooks">A.v, (G (1))
     'spiritual'.</note> suprasensual sacrifice received a beginning and entrance, so also, when
     Joshua<note type="footnote" n="602" resp="#ebrooks">Syr. 'Jesus'.</note> the son of Nun as in a
    kind of prefigurement and type kneaded<note type="footnote" n="603" resp="#ebrooks">A. v. (G
     (1)) ins. 'and made'.</note> unleavened loaves out of new wheat and kept the Passover, the old
    eating of manna ceased, and on that same day came to an end. Thus in every single point the type
    set forth the truth, It is proper also for us to hear the actual words of divine Scripture: <pb
     n="223"/> "And the sons of Israel celebrated the Passover on the fourteenth day from the
    evening, to the west of Jericho, beyond Jordan in the plain. And they ate of the produce of the
    land, and the next day they ate of the unleavened loaves of the Passover. And that same day the
    manna was taken away, after they had eaten of the wheat and the fruits of the land, and the sons
    of Israel had no longer manna"<note type="footnote" n="604" resp="#ebrooks">Josh. v,
     10-12.</note>. The fact again that he who was bom was circumcised on the eighth day shows
    clearly that that circumcision is a type of the life of impassibility in which we truly live,
    not the life that is spent by those who are bom to destruction; "for in the resurrection there
    is no marriage, nor yet persons given in marriage, but they are as the angels in heaven"<note
     type="footnote" n="605" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. xxii, 30. </note>: for the eighth day itself is
    the beginning also on which our Lord rose, when he became firstfruits for our resurrection. He
    who is circumcised on the eighth day, which is the beginning of the future world<note
     type="footnote" n="606" resp="#ebrooks">Cf. ep. 79, 80.</note>, is raised above this world, for
    the rest of which the seventh day was appointed, the end of which brings us to that day which is
    the beginning and the eighth, on which is the impassible life, and he does not know the words,
    "Be fruitful and multiply"<note type="footnote" n="607" resp="#ebrooks">Gen. i, 28.</note>.
    These, we think, are the <pb n="224"/> things which through circumcision were given to the sons
    of Israel. But you perhaps, conversant as you are in divine things, can think of something else
    that is greater and more sublime.</p>
   <p>And next the eighth question, how we ought to understand the saying of our Saviour in the
    gospel, "Agree with thine adversary quickly, while thou art in the way with him"<note
     type="footnote" n="608" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. v, 25.</note>. The defence.</p>
   <p>It agrees with the order of your questions that we should also shortly refer to your other
    question about the words spoken by our Saviour in the gospel by way of persuasion and advice,
    "Agree with thine adversary quickly, while thou art in the way with him, lest thine adversary
    deliver thee to the judge, and the judge deliver thee to the officer, and thou be cast into
    prison, and thou shalt not come out thence till thou pay the last mite"<note type="footnote"
     n="609">Ibid., 25, 26.</note>. This commandment is almost the same which says, "He that will
    sue thee and take away thy tunic, let him have thy coat also"<note type="footnote" n="610"
     resp="#ebrooks">Ibid., 40.</note>. However this needs a great effort in order that we may
    restrain and cut away the corruptions of sin. For what he said is like this. "If you are
    standing in the <pb n="225"/> court that is trying the case itself, and are prosecuting before
    the judge, and are altogether wrapt up in the court, rouse yourself on the way, and change from
    enmity towards your adversary to agreement, considering the uncertainty of the issue, lest you
    have to submit to an adverse verdict, and the adversary on the contrary part deliver you to the
    judge as one that is guilty, and you fall some time under sentence, and the judge deliver you to
    the officer, and so you be chastised until you pay the last mite" (it is the custom to term the
    bronze coin that is the smallest a mite). Luke also clearly confirms this sense, and for perfect
    understanding it seems to me sufficient to cite his actual words: "But why dost thou not of
    thyself judge righteously? But, when thou art going with thine adversary on the way to the
    judge, make it thy business to be quit of him, lest he deliver thee to the judge, and the judge
    deliver thee to the exactor, and the exactor cast thee into prison. And verily, verily I say
    unto thee that thou shalt not come out thence till thou pay the last mite"<note type="footnote"
     n="611" resp="#ebrooks">Luke xii, 57-59.</note>. To strip off your cloak also for the man who
    has a suit with you about your tunic and with great power overcome the rapacity of him who is
    contending with you is an act of sublime and exalted wisdom. Think only of getting rid of the
    running to, the judge <pb n="226"/> and duly preventing it during the time that is pressing upon
    you, when<note type="footnote" n="612" resp="#ebrooks">We rather require 'before'. There is
     probably some error in this sentence.</note> you are not master of yourself, either to ruin
    your enemy or to reconcile him; and this needs the labour and toil of philosophy. For he
    commands us not only not to become adversaries, but to agree with our adversaries, and by
    watchfulness to keep guard over and restrain wrath, and quickly assuage the fire of enmity, and
    reconcile our present enemies by agreement. This is the simple conclusion of this in the form of
    exposition; for some have taken this saying in a higher sense. They say that a man's adversary
    is the reminder that comes from his conscience, and our Lord says this: "When you sin or wish to
     sin<note type="footnote" n="613" resp="#ebrooks"> (G) 'your neighbour offends against
     you'.</note>, agree with your adversary"; that is, accept the admonition that comes from your
    conscience, when it reminds you and blames you, if you have sinned or wished to sin; and, if you
    neglect the reminder from your conscience, and do not obey nor restrain yourself<note
     type="footnote" n="614" resp="#ebrooks">3: (V) 'be admonished'.</note>, you do not agree <pb
     n="227"/> with your adversary, but rather use force against your adversary. So also is it
    written in the prophet Hosea: "Ephraim used force against his adversary and forgot judgment,
    because he began to go after vanity"<note type="footnote" n="615" resp="#ebrooks">Hos. v,
     11.</note>. So also Paul wrote to the Romans and said: "Our conscience beareth witness, or
    maketh defence, on the day on which God shall judge the secrets of men"<note type="footnote"
     n="616" resp="#ebrooks">Rom. ii, 15, 16.</note>. The words, 'as long as thou art in the way
    with him', have this meanmg, 'as far as this world extends', and the way is trodden by all men:
    and this is what he said: "While you are walking in this world as on a way, <note
     type="footnote" n="617" resp="#ebrooks"> (G) om.</note> accept the reminder that comes from
    your conscience and do not refuse it. If you refuse it and pass out of this world without having
     agreed<note type="footnote" n="617" resp="#ebrooks">In another version (G) om.</note>, the
    conscience will take the place of an adversary and accuse you before the judge and place you
    under his sentence, and the judge will deliver you to the torture<note type="footnote" n="618"
     resp="#ebrooks"> (G) 'you will be delivered to unending judgments'.</note>; <pb n="228"/> and
    these things would not have befallen you if you had made union with your adversary in this way
    of the world, when admonition was offered to you, and you did not accept this in agreement. This
    John the Evangelist also wrote in an epistle and said: "If our conscience condemneth us not, we
    have confidence towards God"<note type="footnote" n="619" resp="#ebrooks">1 John iii,
    21.</note>.</p>
   <p>And next the ninth question, as to how we ought to understand the words used by Paul in the
    first epistle to the Corinthians, "Every sin that a man may sin is outside his body; but he who
    committeth fornication sinneth against his body"<note type="footnote" n="620" resp="#ebrooks"> 1
     Cor. vi, 18.</note>. The defence.</p>
   <p>Since you wished to have that other saying of the wise Paul also explained to you which is
    made in the first epistle to the Corinthians, "Every sin that a man may sin is outside his body,
    for he who committeth fornication sinneth against his own body", examine the explanatory and
    easy exposition of our holy fathers, who take this as a decree. Some say that Paul's <pb n="229"
    /> intention was this, to show the offence of fornication to be something greater than all other
    sins, and therefore he frightens those that are weak in order that they may rise to reformation,
    and by way of deterrent says that fornication is a sin of the body, and as if the other sins are
    outside the body, and, though a murderer defiles his hand with blood, and sins against his own
    body, and a slanderer immerses his tongue in calumny as in blood, yet he who commits
    fornication, he says, dips his whole body in the mire of sin, and lets it down as into a pot
    that is fall of putrid matter; therefore too he who commits fornication also, in that he thinks
    that the whole of him has been defiled and polluted, runs to the laver in order to wash off the
    stain itself of the pollution, which a slanderer or a robber or a thief never does, for they do
    not think that their body is polluted and defiled by the sin: for Paul, wishing to show that the
    offence of fornication is higher than the other sins, used this expression and said, "The other
    sins are outside the body; for he who commits fornication sins against his body". But certain
    others say that this is the meaning of the saying that he who commits fornication sins against
    his own body, that is, that he offends against the structure of the body, and, so to speak,
    against the very formation of man, <pb n="230"/> and the very mystery of the beginning of birth
    (for it is indeed an ineffable and all-glorious mystery and is known to God alone, how from the
    emission of a small seed this great and rational animal, that is to say man, takes a beginning);
    and this, they say, is the meaning of the words 'sins against his body': "and abstain, I pray
    you, so to speak, from doing despite to the formation of nature, from which your body too also
    sprang, by unlawful intercourse; for you forget that you are acting madly against yourself, for
    this act is in truth one of madness and drunkenness".</p>
   <p>This is what these say. But others say better, as I also judge their interpretation to be the
    highest, that is the nearest to the apostle's meaning. Paul desired, so to speak, to show that
    the sin of fornication is beyond forgiveness; and above this he says, "Know ye not that your
    bodies are members of Christ?", and he turns reprovingly and says, "Shall I <note
     type="footnote" n="621" resp="#ebrooks"> (G) 'Wilt thou'.</note> then take a member of Christ
    and make it a member of a harlot<note type="footnote" n="622" resp="#ebrooks"> (V) 'fornication.
     Far be it'. </note>?"<note type="footnote" n="623" resp="#ebrooks">1 Cor. vi, 15.</note>: and
    by this he <pb n="231"/> showed that he who commits fornication offends against the members of
    Christ; and so he goes on to say, "Every sin that a man may sin is outside the hody, but he who
    commits fornication sins against his own body". A slanderer or a thief or a robber or a covetous
    man sins against a man by slandering him or by stealing his property or by desiring his goods;
    but he who commits fornication sins against his own body, that is against a member of Christ.
    Every sin distresses God, and men are reckoned to have sinned against him. These however are
    human sins, and have been committed as it were against men. But blasphemy or idolatry, and
    contempt and neglect of the sacred service, and things like these, are, we say, acts of impiety
    against God, and they are believed, so to speak, to be without <pb n="232"/> forgiveness, as
    also Eli the priest and old in days who was negligent concerning his sons, who were evil men as
    it is written and unlawfully offended against the divine service; for<note type="footnote"
     n="624" resp="#ebrooks">Sic Syr.</note> he testified to them and said, "If a man sin against a
    man, they shall pray to the Lord for him: but, if he sin against the Lord, to whom shall they
    pray for him?"<note type="footnote" n="625" resp="#ebrooks">1 Sam. ii, 25.</note> So therefore
    Paul also wishes to make it appear that the sin of fornication is committed against Christ
    himself: and just as, if a man take a harlot and bring her into the holy temple of the Saviour
    of all, and there commit fornication, he will not merely be called to account for fornication,
    but also judged for impiety as having polluted the illustrious and holy place, so also he who
    commits fornication before believing: in Christ and writing him as his leader commits
    fornication <pb n="233"/> only; but, when he has through adoption been inserted in Christ's
    body, he is not only charged on account of fornication, but is also accused of impiety, as doing
    despite to the members of Christ<note type="footnote" n="626"> (V) 'taking a member of Christ
     and making it a member of fornication'. </note>. Therefore it is with this meaning that Paul
    says, "He who commits fornication sins against his own body". Immediately without any
    intervening words he went on to say, "Know ye not that your body is the temple of the Spirit
    that is in you, which ye have from God? And ye are not your own, for ye were bought with a
    price. Praise God therefore in your body"<note type="footnote" n="627" resp="#ebrooks">1 Cor.
     vi, 19,20.</note>. Accordingly it is plain that through the adoption of the Spirit, which is
    the Spirit of Christ, we both become a temple of God, and, as it is said, "Christ dwelleth in
    our hearts"<note type="footnote" n="628" resp="#ebrooks">Eph.iii, 17.</note>; and let no one say
    that he who slanders and he who robs pollutes the one the tongue, the other the hand only; for
    the pollution is not the same, nor are the stain and the mire the same; and, even if we allow it
    to be the same, yet the pollution does not affect the whole body equally, nor is the whole
    temple of God so to speak defiled. For he who commits fornication with a woman who commits
    fornication intertwines his whole body. <pb n="234"/> This objection the blessed Paul demolished
    beforehand by having recourse to the divine Scriptures and saying, "They two shall be one
     flesh"<note type="footnote" n="629" resp="#ebrooks">1 Cor. vi. 16.</note>. That the sin and
    pollution of the other sins and those of fornication are not the same, but that the sin that
    arises from fornication is far removed from these, because it renders the man who commits
    fornication with his body, or with the temple of God, suddenly void of divine grace, this is
    clearly signified by the story of Samson. He even before his conception received a commandment
    by the voice of an angel, his mother being barren and his father Manoah<note type="footnote"
     n="630" resp="#ebrooks">Sic Syr.</note>; and, when he had been conceived and grown up, his
    affairs were determined according to the commandment of the angel who appeared; for he said,
    "Thou shall observe and not drink either wine or strong drink, and thou shalt not eat aught that
    is defiled; for lo! thou shalt conceive and shalt bear a son, and iron shall not go up upon his
    head, because the boy is a Nazirite unto God from thy womb"<note type="footnote" n="631">Jud.
     xiii, 4, 5.</note>. And he grew up and became very great, and he was blessed by the Lord, and
    the Spirit of God was upon the boy, through whom he wrought marvellous and glorious deeds. But,
     <pb n="235"/> when he began to transgress the law of the Lord, the other sins were worthy of
    forgiveness, and the grace of the Spirit did not yet depart from him; but the sin of fornication
    rendered him bereft of the grace of the Spirit. First he transgressed against the law which
    commands the sons of Israel that it is not right to take in marriage women alien to their
    tribes, who<note type="footnote" n="632" resp="#ebrooks">Some words have perhaps fallen out. The
     pronoun in masc.</note> were the peoples round them whose land they inherited. For Samson said,
    "I have seen a beautiful woman in Timnath, of the daughters of the Philistines: now, take her
    for me to wife". And his father said to him, "Is there not a woman in the house of thy brethren
    of thy people to take, that thou goest to the uncircumcised Philistines to take thee a
     wife?"<note type="footnote" n="633" resp="#ebrooks">Jud. xiv, 2, 3.</note>: however, they did
    not persuade him, but on the contrary even went with him to make the unlawful betrothal. And God
    suffered this wickedness to be carried out, in order that he might requite the Philistines, even
    against the wish of the sons of Israel; for Samson's going down became an occasion for their
    destruction. But, as they were going along and were bent on making the betrothal, he turned a
    little out of the way, and he came upon a lion and killed him as a man might kill a little kid.
    And the divine Scripture states that the Spirit of the Lord worked mightily upon him', or
    according to the text <pb n="236"/> contained in other manuscripts, 'the Spirit of the Lord
    prospered his way'<note type="footnote" n="634" resp="#ebrooks">Jud. xiv, 6.</note>; and, though
    he opposed himself to God's laws, the grace of the Holy Spirit did not abandon him. However it
    was not fornication on which they were bent, but marriage. And again at the wedding-feast he
    composed a certain question, or rather<note type="footnote" n="635" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">μᾶλλον</foreign>.</note> a riddle, and asked it of those Philistines, fixing
    gifts for them and promising them so many garments and articles of clothing, if they told him
    the solution of that riddle; but, if they failed to find the origin of it and did not tell it,
    on the other hand he appointed a similar present for them to give. So much for what he did: but
    they could not find the interpretation of the question; but they persuade the woman who had been
    united to him to get the answer to the riddle from him by a trick, and make this known to them,
    as was in fact done. And thereupon those garments had to be exacted from him; for the holy
    Scripture said, "The spirit of the Lord came mightily upon him; and he went down to Ascalon, and
    there killed thirty men; and he took their spoils, and gave their garments to those who
    interpreted the riddle to him"<note type="footnote" n="636" resp="#ebrooks">Jud. XIV,
    19.</note>. Now mark here again also how it said that the spirit of the Lord came mightily upon
    him, because he killed men alien to his race in fight, since God, as we have said, permitted
    this <pb n="237"/> same thing, that these men should perish, as men who had oppressed Israel:
    and at every great and wonderful and glorious deed that he did Scripture stated and said that
    the Spirit of the Lord came mightily upon him<note type="footnote" n="637" resp="#ebrooks">Jud.
     xv,14.</note>. And, after he had gone down to Gaza as is written<note type="footnote" n="638"
     resp="#ebrooks">Id., xvi, 1.</note>, and had there seen a harlot and gone in to her, he shone
    with the same brilliant deeds and was resplendent with the same good successes, and with great
    power advanced to such acts, God instigating him to these. Nevertheless after the fornication on
    the occasion of the successes gained by him the divine Scripture no longer stated that the
    spirit of the Lord came mightily upon him; for the sin of fornication which is committed against
    the body, that is which is a sin against God, is of such a kind as to drive away the Holy
    Spirit. Wherefore also the wise Paul too says, "He who commits fornication sins against his own
    body", not as if the other sins were not objects of condemnation, for all of them contain a
    falling from the kingdom, but for the reason that was stated he was desirous to show that
    fornication is evil, and he wished to eradicate the passion itself from every man, as from some
    root; because the <pb n="238"/> Corinthians sinned wickedly in this respect; for he said, "Such
    fornication is reported among you, and fornication of such a kind that is not even named among
    the peoples, that a man should have his father's wife"<note type="footnote" n="639"
     resp="#ebrooks">1 Cor. v, 1.</note>. He began with an accusation of this kind, founded upon the
    particular unlawful intercourse, and he went on to use the spiritual knife against all
    fornication; and he raised a charge of this kind to a height. Look at the strict mercifulness of
    God, as in the history of Samson. As soon as he had committed fornication, the grace of the
    sanctifying power of the Spirit departed from him, but it was nevertheless poured out upon him
    in the power and operation of the successes obtained by him, giving an opportunity for
    repentance by means of which every sin is overthrown and cast out, unless we throw ourselves
    into the pit of despair<note type="footnote" n="640" resp="#ebrooks">A Greek extract <foreign
      xml:lang="grc">ἐκ τῶν πρὸς Ε. κουβικουλάριον ἀποκρισέων</foreign> is published in Cramer, Cat.
     in Luc et Jo., p 255, but the passage is not in our text.</note>.</p>
  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
