<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3125">To Anastasia the Deaconess</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">75 [245]-104 [274]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="69">
   <head type="main" resp="#compiler">THE LETTER OF THE HOLY MAR SEVERUS, PATRIARCH OF ANTIOCH, TO
    ANASTASIA THE DEACONESS<note type="footnote" n="664" resp="#ebrooks">Ep. v, 1 after exile (see
     text, p. 249). A so-called life of Anastasia (there called 'patrician') exists in Add. 14649
     (f. 99v), but is historically worthless. This letter was written after the work against Julian
     of Halicarnassus (p. 272), but the allusion to Isaiah (ibid.) forbids a late date.</note>. </head>
   <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
    <date notBefore="0522" notAfter="0526">522-6</date>
   </dateline>
   <p> While walking in the way of righteousness (I mean that of asceticism), and the monastic life,
    you meditate on the sublime thoughts of the God-inspired Scriptures, and gather benefit from
    them, and shun lack of knowledge and the poverty arising therefrom as something alien to the
    commandments of religion, and for this disposition therefore you are an object of praise. For
    the book of Proverbs also somewhere said, "The lips of the <pb n="246"/> righteous know high
    things, but fools die in scarcity". For this reason it has decreed for you a blessing from
    above, and a life that is without sorrow and blessed: for it adds, 'The blessing of the Lord
    upon the head of the righteous, this maketh rich, and sorrow in heart shall not be added unto
     it"<note type="footnote" n="665" resp="#ebrooks">Proverbs x, 21, 22.</note>. It is therefore known
    beforehand that to me too you bring freedom from sorrow through your God-loving questions,
    inasmuch as you cause me to enjoy the pleasure of spiritual thoughts. Accordingly I will readily
    try to give an elucidation of the rest<note type="footnote" n="666" resp="#ebrooks">See p. 274,
     n. 2.</note> of your questions also. You are pleased to ask me what our Lord Jesus Christ
    wishes to make known to us by that parable which Luke the Evangelist recorded as follows: "Who
    among you shall have a friend, and he shall go unto him at midnight and say to him, 'My friend,
    lend me three loaves, for a friend hath come to me from a journey, and I have not wherewith to
    set before him', and he from within shall answer and say, 'Trouble me not. Lo! the door is shut,
    and my children with myself are in bed. I cannot rise and give to thee'? I say unto you that, if
    he will not rise and give to him because he is his friend, because of his importunity he will
    rise and give him as much as he needeth". For<note type="footnote" n="667" resp="#ebrooks"> This
     passage down to the citation is published in Greek in Mai, Class. Auct., X, 431, under the
     heading <foreign xml:lang="grc">Σ. εἰς τὸ κατά Λουκᾶν</foreign>.</note>, us to find the reason
    of this parable from outside is foolish and senseless, <pb n="247"/> since our Saviour himself
    plainly added by his own words and declared that he brought this forward to convince us that we
    ought to pray and make requests without ceasing and at all times, readily<note type="footnote"
     n="668" resp="#ebrooks">Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">συνεχῶς</foreign>.</note> and without ever
    growing slack or weak from the constant habit<note type="footnote" n="669" resp="#ebrooks">Gr.
     om.</note>: for he added, "I also say unto you, Ask, and it shall be given unto you. Seek, and
    ye shall find, knock, and it shall be opened unto you. For everyone that asketh receiveth; and
    he that seeketh findeth; and to him that knocketh it shall be opened unto him"<note
     type="footnote" n="670" resp="#ebrooks">Luke 11:5-10.</note>. In what precedes he delivered to
    the disciples the form of that divine prayer which begins, "Our Father which art in heaven"<note
       type="footnote" n="671" resp="#ebrooks">Luke 11:2.</note>; and so he added to it the parable
    given above, so that on all sides the object'is clear. But, since you have thought to yourself
    that there is some spiritual, sublime, lofty allegory<note type="footnote" n="672"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">θεωρία</foreign>.</note> contained in the words of the parable, and ask what
    those three loaves are, we ourselves also find it quite impossible not to be uplifted with your
    instruction-loving and inquiring mind, and to state the partial result which we have reached;
    for assuredly we must not force the parables into an allegory<note type="footnote" n="673"
     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">θεωρία</foreign>.</note> in every point. These<note
     type="footnote" n="674" resp="#ebrooks">This passage to the end of the paragraph is in Mai, p.
     430, 456 (cf. Corderius, Cat. in Luc., p. 321). Here the sentences are in a different order,
     and are sometimes shortened.</note> three loaves I consider to be faith in <pb n="248"/> the
    Father and in the Son and the Holy Spirit; to which it is reasonable to suppose that our Lord,
    the ' one of the Trinity ' is urging all men through these words; because indeed, as the apostle
    said, he ' wisheth all men to be saved, and to come to the knowledge of the truth'<note
     type="footnote" n="675" resp="#ebrooks">1 Timothy ii, 4. What follows is in the Gr. put into
     Christ's mouth.</note>. Since therefore some have wasted all their life in negligence, and
    taken no account of the faith, and at last towards the end of life come to a perception of their
    sins, and rush to the faith, the merciful one says this: "Even men of this kind, who come and
    knock at my door at an untimely hour of night, I will hear, not for the sake of justice, but
    because of their importunity<note type="footnote" n="676" resp="#ebrooks">Gr. ins. <foreign
      xml:lang="grc">ἀναίδειαν δὲ ἐνταῦθα τὴν ὑπομονὴν φησὶν κ. προσεδρείαν</foreign>.</note>, and I
    will hand to them the loaves of faith, which is the confession of the Holy Trinity". The friend
    therefore, the master of the house, is the God and Saviour Jesus<note type="footnote" n="677"
     resp="#ebrooks">Gr. ins. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁ Χριστός</foreign>.</note>, who loves every
    man, even those who have not yet believed on him, and thirsts for their salvation. But he who
    asks for the three loaves in the middle of the night is he who comes to the faith late. But the
    friend who came from a journey and was received by him we should afterwards rightly understand
    as the angel or angels who come at the end of life to take us and <pb n="249"/> conduct us on
    the last journey; for they themselves also love us, and make our salvation a subject of
    rejoicing, according to the testimony of our Lord which says, "Joy ariseth before the angels of
    God over a sinner who repenteth"<note type="footnote" n="678" resp="#ebrooks">Luke xv,
     10.</note>. But the children who are resting in the bed are those who have been brought up as
    children, and have believed the gospel with a simple heart, and have been judged worthy to rest
    with our Lord. For the lying on the bed also is a sign of rest, as our Lord himself again says
    in the Gospel of Matthew: "Many shall come from the east and from the west, and shall recline
    with Abraham and Isaac and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven"<note type="footnote" n="679"
     resp="#ebrooks">Matthew viii, 11. The Gr. adds: <foreign xml:lang="grc">Τάχα δὲ κ. προφηρεία
      ἐστὶ περὶ τῆς συντλείας, ὅτε διὰ τὸ πληθυνθῆναι τὴν ἀνομίαν ψυγείσης τῆς ἀγάπης τῶν πολλῶν ἡ
      θύρα κέκλεισται, τά δὲ παιδία μετὰ τοῦ Χ. ἐστίν· ὅτε οὐ τοσοῦτον διὰ τὸ εἶναι φίλος λαμβάνει
      τις ἄρτον, ὅσον διὰ τὴν τοῦ αἰτεῖν τρεῖς ἄρτους ἀναίδειαν</foreign>.</note>.</p>
   <p>The words spoken by our Saviour to the Jews, "In order that upon you may come all the blood,
    of righteous men that has been shed upon the earth, from the blood of Abel the righteous to the
    blood of Zacharias<note type="footnote" n="680" resp="#ebrooks"> (E) ins. 'son of Barachias'.
    </note> whom ye <pb n="250"/> slew between the temple and the altar"<note type="footnote"
     n="681" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew xxiii, 51.</note>, have been variously understood by those who
    have interpreted, because concerning this matter nothing is plainly stated by the God-inspired
    Scripture. But, since our Saviour's purpose requires that he should unite and comprise in the
    saying all the blood of righteous men that was unjustly shed, from Abel down to the day on which
    he himself said these things to the Jews, and lay the responsibility for this upon them and upon
    their ancestors, it<note type="footnote" n="682" resp="#ebrooks">This passage to 'them' (p. 252,
     1. 2) is in Mai, p. 432.</note> is a right and reasonable thing, as it seems to me, to
    understand that he referred to Zacharias the priest, who begot for us the holy<note
     type="footnote" n="683" resp="#ebrooks"> (AG) 'Theologian'; Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >θεσπέσιον</foreign>.</note> John the Forerunner and Baptist, whom a tradition not contained
    in Scripture relates that the Jews slew between the temple and <pb n="251"/> the altar, because
    he plainly prophesied or rather<note type="footnote" n="684" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">μᾶλλον</foreign>.</note> showed the God-bearer to be a virgin<note
     type="footnote" n="685" resp="#ebrooks"> (AG) 'Virgin to be the God-bearer'.</note>, and him
    that is born of her, the great God and Saviour Jesus Christ, like some King and chief and Lord
    over their people, and did not remove the holy Virgin herself after the incomprehensible
    conception by the Holy Spirit from the virgins' place in the temple, between the temple and the
    altar, as one that was married, but knew her to be still a virgin, and allowed her to stand in
    the same<note type="footnote" n="686" resp="#ebrooks">A. v, (AG) ins. 'time and'; Gr. om.
    </note> accustomed place as usual. For this reason (they say) those who heard of it fell into a
    rage and took weapons in their hands against him, fearing the king who was expected from his <pb
     n="252"/> prophecy, who was to exercise sway over them and lay the yoke of bondage upon them.
    And these things Gregory the wise in divine things, the brother of Basil the great, and bishop
    of Nyssa, in the sermon on the Nativity of our Saviour, states thus: "But, if we are not
    straying a long way from the subject, it would perhaps not be inopportune to adduce Zacharias
    also who was slain between the temple and the altar to testify to the undefiled mother. This
    Zacharias was a priest, but not a priest only, but possessing also the gift of prophecy, and the
    power of prophecy is proclaimed in the book of the gospel as inevitable<note type="footnote"
     n="687" resp="#ebrooks"> (E) 'unblamed'; Greg. (ed.) <foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >ἀνάγραπτος</foreign>;(l. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀναγκαῖος</foreign>? Luke, i, 67?).</note>,
    in that the divine grace makes a way for men beforehand, that they may not think the birth from
    a virgin incredible, and, training the assent of those who did not believe beforehand by small
    miracles, a child <pb n="253"/> is born to her that is barren and past age<note type="footnote"
     n="688" resp="#ebrooks">The grammar is confused in both versions and in the text of Greg.
    </note>. This is the beginning of the miracle that is performed in the Virgin<note
     type="footnote" n="689" resp="#ebrooks">Greg. <foreign xml:lang="grc">κατὰ τὴν
      παρθενίαν</foreign>.</note>. For, as Elizabeth does not become a mother by the power of
    nature, inasmuch as she had grown old in the world<note type="footnote" n="690" resp="#ebrooks">
     (A) 'her life had grown old'. </note> without bearing, but the boy's birth is referred to the
    divine will, so also the incredibility of the virgin birth-throes obtains belief by reference to
    the deity. Since therefore the son born of the barren woman, who at the voice of her that had
    conceived the Lord, before he came forth to the light, leaped in his mother's womb, preceded the
    son born of the virgin, immediately on the forerunner of the Word coming forth to birth, then
    the silence of Zacharias is dissolved, by the prophetic indwelling, and all things that
    Zacharias utters were a prophecy of the future. This man therefore who was being led by the
    spirit of prophecy to the knowledge of hidden <pb n="254"/> things, having understood the
    mystery of virginity in the undefiled birth, did not exclude the unmarried mother in the temple
    from the place which according to the law was assigned to the virgins, teaching the Jews that
    the Maker of the things that are and Ring of all creation has human nature under his rule with
    all things, and by his own will leads it to that which pleases him, and is not himself
    controlled by this nature, so that it is in his power to make a new form of birth which will not
    cause her who has become a mother to cease from being a virgin. Therefore he did not exclude her
    in the temple from the ranks of the virgins; and this place was a space between the temple and
    the altar. Since therefore they heard that the King of creation was coming forth<note
     type="footnote" n="691" resp="#ebrooks">Greg. <foreign xml:lang="grc"
     >προελθεῖν</foreign>.</note> by dispensation to human birth, in fear of being under a king's
    rule they slew the man who testified these things <pb n="255"/> concerning the birth,
     sacrificing<note type="footnote" n="692" resp="#ebrooks">Greg, (ed.) ἱ<foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >ερουργήσαντα</foreign> (l. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἱερουργήσαντες</foreign>).</note> the
    priest at the very altar"<note type="footnote" n="693" resp="#ebrooks">P. G., XLVI,
    1136.</note>. But of the Zacharias who was one of the twelve prophets we cannot reasonably
    understand the passage quoted, since it is not related that he was killed, but he departed from
    life by the ordinary end of human life. Wherefore also in the times of the pious king Theodosius
    the grandson of the elder Theodosius his holy body was found by revelation in the territory of
    Eleutheropolis, when it had not been in the least corrupted but was found as if it had been
    buried yesterday, at a place at which an oratory is now to be seen, and a temple which was
    consecrated to God in his name; and it is known and honoured by all who pass by that way. This
    is related by a certain Sozomen who wrote ecclesiastical histories<note type="footnote" n="694"
     resp="#ebrooks">ix, 17.</note>. Some have supposed that in the above-quoted passage our Saviour
    referred to Zacharias the son of Jehoiada who was put to death by Joash, king of the Jews. But
    this explanation is futile, and is refuted by the facts themselves. For it is not the case that
    the foul murder of prophets and priests, the murder which it is the intention of the <pb n="256"
    /> evangelic saying of our Saviour to set forth, was perpetrated down to his time and then
    ended: for after Joash other kings of the Jews also reigned who turned aside to idolatry, and,
    as is natural, were ill-disposed towards those who pleased God; among whom Manasseh is said to
    have put Isaiah the great among prophets to death with a saw. But besides these things we should
    know this also, that the man who was put do death by Joash was called Azarias and not Zacharias,
    though in certain copies some men have changed the name, and by a slight change have written
    'Azarias' as 'Zacharias'<note type="footnote" n="695" resp="#ebrooks">2 Chronicles xxiv, 20.</note>.
    Accordingly for all these reasons it seems to be a just conclusion that we must consequently
    understand our Saviour's saying of the father of John the Baptist, as the holy Gregory said.</p>
   <p>Of the passage written by the wise Paul in the first epistle to the Corinthians, "He that
    speaketh with tongues edifieth himself, but he that prophesieth edifieth the church<note
     type="footnote" n="696" resp="#ebrooks">1 Corinthians xiv, 4.</note>", this is the elucidation. In the
    times in which the apostles were "propagating the saving preaching of the gospel in the <pb
     n="257"/> world, many of those who believed worked signs and prodigies, in order to bring
    unbelievers to accept the truth. For it is for this cause that miracles are numerous among
    unbelievers, and not among those who have already believed, according to the saying of the same
     Paul<note type="footnote" n="697" resp="#ebrooks">1 Corinthians xiv, 22.</note>. For this very same
    reason the gifts of the Spirit were given with greater liberality, and more openly, to these who
    were being brought to the faith. And those who were baptized often spoke with tongues
    immediately, and some were thought worthy to receive prophetic inspiration, while certain others
    even enjoyed the possession of both, as is written in the book of the Acts about some men who
    were baptized by Paul at Ephesus, as follows: "But, when they had heard it, <pb n="258"/> they
    were baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus. And, when Paul had laid his hand upon them, the
    Holy Spirit came upon them, and they spake with tongues and prophesied"<note type="footnote"
     n="698" resp="#ebrooks">Acts XIX, 5, 6.</note>. This grace therefore flourished among the
    Corinthians also at that time, and some used to speak with tongues, while others were thought
    worthy to prophesy. And the form of prophecy was such that it was made known not only by
    foretelling the future but also by the commingling of words of instruction which corrected
    morals, as the God-clad doctors such as Athanasius the great and Basil, and such as Gregory and
    John, and all who were like these, gained renown at one time and another in the churches. Since
    therefore certain men at Corinth were puffed up and thought much of themselves because they
    spoke with <pb n="259"/> tongues, while others prophesied and taught things useful and
    beneficial, Paul, wishing to bring down their high looks, says this: "He who speaks with the
    tongues of the nations edifies himself, that is, establishes his own reputation, and is admired
    only, but does not benefit the soul of the hearers by reforming morals: but he who prophesies
    and weaves a web of moral teaching, and reproves secret things of the heart, and purifies the
    souls of the hearers from shameful passions, edifies the church, and acquires the gift of
    prophesy or of teaching for others rather<note type="footnote" n="699" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
      xml:lang="grc">μᾶλλον</foreign>.</note> than for himself".</p>
   <p>The meaning of Job's saying, "May the blessing of him that hath perished come upon me"<note
     type="footnote" n="700" resp="#ebrooks">Job, xxix, 13.</note> is plain to those who read with
    intelligence and not carelessly from the fact that it follows the words which precede, and from
     <pb n="260"/> the words which next follow. This is what he says: "Often have I seen a man
    suffering extreme tortures, and just on the point of perishing, as perhaps when enemies were
    upon him, or violent men, and have rescued him from distress<note type="footnote" n="701"
     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀνάγκη</foreign>.</note> and saved him; and such a one
    has blessed me, because against all hope he had been delivered from the destruction that was
    impending over him<note type="footnote" n="702" resp="#ebrooks"> (E) 'hope had been found for
     him who was without hope, and through the same he had been saved'.</note>. May that blessing
    therefore come upon me, and may God bring it to effect"<note type="footnote" n="703"
     resp="#ebrooks">H ins. 'And this applies also to those who are sent and go down into the
     world'.</note>. That this is so the words which follow will prove as I said before. What in
    fact does he say? "For I delivered the poor from the hand of the powerful, and I helped the
    orphan who had no helper. May the blessing of him that hath perished come upon me; and the mouth
     <pb n="261"/> of the widow hath blessed me"<note type="footnote" n="704" resp="#ebrooks">Job,
     xxix, 12, 13.</note>. But one may also understand this in a higher sense as a parable. For our
    Lord also says in the gospels about those who mortify their soul to the world, and give up their
    body to the arena<note type="footnote" n="705" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >στάδιον</foreign>.</note> of martyrdom, or to labours of asceticism, and are thereby thought
    to be destroying and slaying their soul, because they are deprived of worldly pleasure: "He that
    destroyeth his soul for my sake shall find it"<note type="footnote" n="706" resp="#ebrooks"
     >Matthew x, 39; Luke, ix, 34.</note>. The prayer and blessing therefore of a man who has thus
    perished according to our Saviour's saying and finds his soul is a great thing: and any
    right-minded man will pray that this may come upon him, and will wisely say the words, "May the
    blessing of him that hath perished come upon me".</p>
   <p>As to what is written at the end of the book of Job, that he took an Arabian<note
     type="footnote" n="707" resp="#ebrooks"> (AH) '.'Arbakitha'; so below.</note> wife, it is
    unnecessary for us to inquire much who this is, <pb n="262"/> whether this is another wife by
    whom he had other children after the calamity, or the former one, who under the magnitude of the
    afflictions that came upon him gave way and stumbled, and advised him to utter some blasphemous
    speech and depart from his pains. However it is reasonable for us to understand that the wife by
    whom the children after the calamity were born was some other one different from her. For it is
    as if adding something new that the writer uses the words: "Having taken an Arabian wife he
    begets a son"<note type="footnote" n="708" resp="#ebrooks">Job, XLII, 17c.</note>. For it would
    have been far from just that she should share in the good things, who shrank in the time of the
    struggle, and tried to bring the combatant<note type="footnote" n="709"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
      >ἀθλητής</foreign>.</note> down from the highest summit of endurance. <pb n="263"/>
   </p>
   <p>The words that were written by the writer in the book, and these also about Job, of whom it is
    written that he also 'shall again rise with those whom the Lord raiseth'<note type="footnote"
     n="710">Job 42:17a.</note>, we must suppose to have been composed with this meaning. In
    consequence of so great a trial he had in a sense gone down to Sheol and final destruction, so
    that even his name should thenceforth be extinguished, as he himself said when he was being
    tormented by the pains <note type="footnote" n="711" resp="#ebrooks">Job 19:14.</note>, and
    suddenly he arose as from the dead, and put off the unsightliness of the sores, and he was
    comely in body, as in the bloom of youth, and everything ended for him in a change to the best
    fortune. Therefore, lest any think that the prize of virtue ends with these things, and lest we
    who read imagine that we shall receive the rewards for the labours <pb n="264"/> of virtue in
    this world, for this reason the writer recorded the words that are written, "He shall again rise
    with those whom the Lord raiseth"; that is, lest any think that his rewards are completed and
    ended with present things: for these were given as an earnest for the things that are future and
    are expected by us all. For he shall rise with those whom the Lord raiseth, viz. those who have
    conducted themselves after the same pattern, of whom Paul also in writing to the Hebrews says
    that all those who have borne testimony through faith 'did not receive the promises, God having
    provided some better thing for us, that they might not be made perfect without us'<note
     type="footnote" n="712" resp="#ebrooks">Hebrews XI, 39, 40.</note>. By the words which he used
    (and it is written, "He shall <pb n="265"/> again rise with those whom the Lord raiseth") the
    writer is thought to be explaining this also, that he endured such pains, not because he looked
    to the things that were given him in this.world, but to the hope of the great and wonderful
    resurrection, concerning which also he said, "I will endure for thee until I shall again
     be"<note type="footnote" n="713" resp="#ebrooks">Job 14:14.</note>; and again, "For I know
    that he ever floweth who shall release me upon the earth. He shall raise my skin which endureth
    these things"<note type="footnote" n="714" resp="#ebrooks">Job 19:25, 26.</note>. The words
    which are before us for the purpose of interpretation were used by the author with reference to
    the general resurrection which is expected by everyone (and the words are "He shall again rise
    with those whom the Lord raiseth"), and not, as your religiousness has supposed, to that by
    which some of the saints rose, <pb n="266"/> when our Lord took the saving Cross upon him for
    our sakes, and the Good Shepherd laid down his soul for the sheep. For this the holy<note
     type="footnote" n="715" resp="#ebrooks"> (A) 'Theologian'.</note> Matthew the Evangelist
    recorded in these words: "But Jesus, when he had cried with a loud voice, gave up the ghost. And
    lo! the veil of the temple was rent in two, from the top to the bottom, and the earth quaked,
    and the rocks were rent, and the graves were opened, and many bodies of the saints who slept
    arose, and came out from the graves, and after his resurrection went into the holy city, and
    appeared to many"<note type="footnote" n="716" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew xxvii, 50-53.</note>.
    Since then the Evangelist stated indefinitely that many bodies of the saints who had fallen
    asleep rose, it is unnecessary for us to inquire who these were, and if Job was among them. For
    the reason why he said 'many', and not 'all the bodies of the saints' is because the
    resurrection which is expected by everyone is not that one, <pb n="267"/> but the one at the
    second coming of our Saviour Christ. For then, I mean at the time of the revered Gross, it was
    only in order to demonstrate the power of our same Saviour, who in that the soul separated from
    the body went down to Sheol, that certain men rose by a divine manifestation, showing that in
    the places beneath the earth there was perception of the God-befitting illumination. And these
    were prophets and some of those who lived after the same manner as they, who were well-known
    from the Holy Scriptures among the inhabitants of Jerusalem. This is stated also by the God-clad
    Ignatius, who adorned the throne of the Antiochenes, immediately after the apostolic
     administration<note type="footnote" n="717" resp="#ebrooks"> (A) 'coming'.</note>, and the
    first see of the chief of the apostles Peter, and was perfected with a crown of martyrdom. In
    writing-to those at <pb n="268"/> Magnesia he wrote as follows about our Saviour Christ: "How
    shall we be able to live without him? whom the prophets also, being his disciples in the spirit,
    expected as a teacher; and for this reason he whom they rightly awaited when he came raised them
    from the dead"<note type="footnote" n="718" resp="#ebrooks">Ad Magn., 9.</note>. But that we
    should think that those who rose then, at the time of the saving Cross, remained to this day the
    words of the gospel do not permit; for they cry plainly, "They went into the holy city and
    appeared to many". The word 'appeared' plainly denotes a temporary appearance, for the purpose
    of confirming, as we<note type="footnote" n="719"> (E)'they'.</note> said, the power of our
    Saviour, who broke the gates of bronze, and the bars of iron<note type="footnote" n="720"
     resp="#ebrooks">Psalm cvi, 16.</note> from which there is no escape, of the places <pb n="269"/>
    beneath the earth. After therefore those who rose had shown themselves at that time, they again
    laid their bodies aside and departed to their places, awaiting the general resurrection which is
    expected by everyone. That this is so, the holy John bishop of Constantinople also testifies in
    the fourteenth note of the second part of the commentary on the first epistle to the
    Corinthians, where he wrote thus: "But if any be in doubt why, when speaking about the
    resurrection, he did not here introduce the bodies which rose in our Lord's time, we will say
    this, that this is not speaking about the resurrection. For to show that those who rose die
    again was alien to the purpose of one who is showing that death is finally destroyed. For it is
    for this reason also that he said that it is the last thing to be destroyed, in order that you
    may no longer fear that it will rise. For, when evil is <pb n="270"/> done away, much more shall
    death be annihilated"<note type="footnote" n="721" resp="#ebrooks">In Ep. I ad Corinthians Hom. XXXIX,
     30 (ed. Field).</note>. And in the fifteenth note which follows, when speaking about saving
    baptism, and explaining why a man who is about to be baptized, when he repeats<note
     type="footnote" n="722" resp="#ebrooks"> (E) 'learns'.</note> the baptismal confession, is
    baptized into the remission of sins and the resurrection of the dead, and eternal life, he says
    this: "For, since sin brought in death, the root being dried up, we must no longer dispute in
    any way about the: destruction of the fruit. Therefore after first saying 'the remission of
    sin', he then confesses<note type="footnote" n="723" resp="#ebrooks">Jo. Chrys. <foreign
      xml:lang="grc">ὁμολογεῖς</foreign> (v. l. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁμολογεῖ</foreign>).</note>
    also the resurrection of the dead, being led from this to that also. And afterwards, since the
    name 'resurrection' does not suffice to set forth everything (for many after they had risen
    departed again,' as <pb n="271"/> those in the Old Testament, as Lazarus, as those at the time
    of the Cross) you are bidden<note type="footnote" n="724" resp="#ebrooks">A., v. (E) 'he bids';
     Jo. Chrys. <foreign xml:lang="grc">κελεύει</foreign>.</note> to say, 'and in eternal life',
    that none may any longer fear death after that resurrection"<note type="footnote" n="725"
     resp="#ebrooks">Op. cit., XL, 4.</note>.</p>
   <p>We have now discharged, as you see, all the God-loving debt of your, esteemed questions,
    according to our feebleness, and according to the small measure of knowledge which has come to
    us; and we pray that there may fall to you the glorious part of Mary, who never tired of bending
    her instruction-loving ear to the saving teaching of Jesus, and upon whom that testimony was
    given which said, "For Mary hath chosen for herself the good part, which shall not be taken from
     her"<note type="footnote" n="726" resp="#ebrooks">Luke x, 42.</note>. But, whereas in the
    previous letter to us you stated how your religious brother Innocent and the sisters stand in
    the faith, and after writing this about them, as if you had done something contrary to the
    profession of philosophy, you then added that you take no "thought for them, know clearly that
    it is not a thing unworthy of your perfection that as regards the faith and in fitting spiritual
    matters you should take thought for those who are related to you, and perform all that is in
    your power, and give assistance with counsels and <pb n="272"/> prayers. For in these things our
    duty consists; and to this also the apostolic saying extends, "If any man taketh no thought for
    his own and especially those of the house, he denieth the faith, and is worse than an
     unbeliever"<note type="footnote" n="727" resp="#ebrooks">1 Timothy v, 8.</note>. And that we
    should take thought for their worldly opulence, or for anything else that is pleasant, is the
    part of those who are not philosophers. This distinction therefore I too made, and asked the
    love of God that is in you to write to me about them; and you have done well in telling
    everything both wisely and in accordance with truth; and it is proper that the distinction in
    this point also should not escape you. Upon another matter you have asked me questions of this
     kind.<note type="footnote" n="1" resp="#ebrooks"> </note> have heard that Isaiah<note
     type="footnote" n="728" resp="#ebrooks">Select Letters of Severus, pp. 232, 473; P. G., LXXXVI,
     45.</note> the unlawful, like Dathan and Abiram, has risen against the laws of the priesthood,
    and has trampled upon everything like a hog, with foul, disorderly, uncanonical feet; and that,
    having gone to Pamphylia, he has thought fit to whisper lies about me, and to say that in what I
    wrote about the incorruptibility of the body of God and our Saviour Jesus Christ<note
     type="footnote" n="729" resp="#ebrooks">In the treatise against Julian of Halicarnassus (Add.
     17200; Vat. Syr. 140, 255).</note> I proclaimed the faith, and said that the body was corrupted
    and dissolved during the three days' burial, and certain similar blasphemies which are not
    plausible, which wound the ears, and disturb the souls, of those who listen without
    intelligence: and it <pb n="273"/> is therefore in my mind to send a man there carrying all that
    has been written by me, in order to establish the truth. If then you also have heard of any
    similar report that has been whispered there, since some persons have perhaps written and told
    you, tell me. The statement on which you have dilated in the letter, as to how you have loved
    and still love my humility with peculiar warmth, I read with great pleasure, and I rejoiced with
    spiritual joy on learning the fervour of the love that is in you, the God-befitting and pure
    love, wherewith rational souls are smitten towards one another, even among those with whom you
    associate in the blood of Christ. But I believe of you that, even if you write at very great
    length in every letter, you will not be able to express even a small portion of the love and
    confidence that you have towards me, who am unworthy and fall far short of this. But I pray that
    for this perfect love you may receive rewards both in this world, and in the future and endless
    life.</p>
   <trailer resp="#compiler">The end of the letter to Anastasia the deaconess<note type="footnote"
     n="730" resp="#ebrooks">A letter to Anastasia which is probably this exists also in Coptic in
     Vat. Copt. 11 (Assem., B. O., I, 618).</note>. <pb n="274"/></trailer>
  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
