<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3100">To Anastasia the Deaconess</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">107 [277]-117 [287]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="71">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE SAME FROM THE 8th LETTER OF THE 2nd BOOK OF THOSE AFTER
               EXILE, WHICH WAS ADDRESSED TO ANASTASIA THE DEACONESS. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0522" notAfter="0526">522-6</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> As to the words therefore which the Evangelist Matthew wrote that our Lord and God and
               Saviour Jesus Christ used: "Pray that your flight be not in the winter nor on the sabbath"<note
                  type="footnote" n="739" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew XXIV, 20.</note>, know that they have a double
               meaning, and as a historical fact this has already happened to the Jews at the time <pb n="278"
               /> of the captivity at the hands of the Romans<note type="footnote" n="740" resp="#ebrooks">In
                  another version (EK) om.</note>, but in a higher sense it is expected to take place at the end
               of the whole world. In fact after the outrage on the cross the judgment of God-slayers was
               exacted from them when the Romans took arms against them, and encamped over all Judaea and over
               the country round for whole years, and during the winter-seasons the evil consequences of war
               prevailed, and these especially in the winter when the fighting-men were idle; and not so only,
               but on the sabbath also they were slaughtered, because on account of the cessation of the
               sabbath they could not take arms in their hands and exact vengeance from those who were fighting
               with them. And this is often recorded by those who described the calamities of those men, that,
               by reason of the distress of the calamities which came upon them, they disregarded even the
               cessation of the sabbath, and took arms against their adversaries: nevertheless even so they
               fell with a complete and lamentable fall, and endured utter ruin. But, when our Saviour's words
               in respect of this prophecy are raised in meaning so as to refer to the time of the end and of
               Antichrist, it induces believers <pb n="279"/> always to persevere in works of virtue, and
               strive not to be caught by the winter or by the sabbath, at the time of the end, or the
               departure of every soul and its separation from the body, the winter signifying absence of
               fruit, and the sabbath cessation from virtue: for we know that the winter is unproductive as
               regards the production of fruit, and that the sabbath signifies cessation. For the winter, in
               which there is much rain and falls of snow, and gathering of clouds and a murky atmosphere<note
                  type="footnote" n="741" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀήρ</foreign>.</note>, and
               scarceness of pure air<note type="footnote" n="741" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >ἀήρ</foreign>.</note>, may denote confusion. The intention of the saying therefore is that
               our souls should be active and fruitful, and free from confusion as regards readiness and
               preparation for acts of religion, as in the words sung by David the prophet, "I was made ready
               and was not confounded"<note type="footnote" n="742" resp="#ebrooks">Psalm CXVIII, 60.</note>. In
               the same way should also be interpreted the saying, "Woe to them that are with child and to them
               that suckle in those days"<note type="footnote" n="743" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew XXIV, 19.</note>.
               For this also occurred as a historical fact throughout Judaea, when the hand of the Romans
               fought with them, so that the women who were with child and those who were <pb n="280"/>
               suckling were pitifully slain with their children themselves, either while they were yet in the
               womb or while they were being nourished at the breast. And in a higher sense on the last day the
               souls are to be reckoned as objects of pity which received in the mind the practice of virtue
               and bear it as in a womb, and began to hold the seed of the word of religion, which was with
               difficulty conceived in them, which bring forth to the light and as it were give birth, but
               produce the thing itself in very imperfect form, like women who are unable to give perfect
               nourishment to their babies. For those who cultivate virtue must according to the parable that
               is in the gospel bear the full measure so as to rise to the number of 100, or produce fruit of
               the measure of 60, or at least of 30; for what is less than this should like an
               incompletely-formed and unnourished babe be reckoned as nothing.</p>
            <p>But the saying "Where the corpse is, there will the eagles be gathered together"<note
               type="footnote" n="744" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew xxiv, 28.</note> is spoken as a kind of simile
               and proverb and illustration. As, when a dead body is found lying anywhere, both eagles and
               other birds of <pb n="281"/> prey come from different quarters from very lofty heights, suddenly
               and unexpectedly, in order to be fed, 'in the same way' (he says) 'shall be also the coming of
               the Son of man' <note type="footnote" n="745" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew xxiv, 27.</note>, for, when
               he shall again appear upon the earth, at the glorious second coming to judge the world, and
               shall appear with armed ranks of angels, all the saints also, rising 'suddenly and in the
               twinkling of an eye at the last trump'<note type="footnote" n="746" resp="#ebrooks">1 Corinthians xv,
                  52.</note>, as the apostle said, shall suddenly all appear like some swift eagles of rapid
               motion. And very rightly were they compared to eagles, because they had high and heavenly
               thoughts, and lived in a manner worthy of the kingdom of heaven. But some have tried to
               interpret this saying in the following way, and have said that at the Lord's second coming all
               those who have lived a righteous life, and were like high and heavenly eagles in their mind,
               shall receive Paradise, and shall be gathered in the same place where Adam's fall<note
                  type="footnote" n="747" resp="#ebrooks">Sc. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πτῶμα</foreign>, the word
                  which is used for 'corpse'.</note> was, and the disobedience through which he fell into sin. Of
               the words, "Two men shall be at that time m the field, one is taken away and one left, two women
               shall be grinding <pb n="282"/> in the mill, one is taken away and one left"<note
                  type="footnote" n="748" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew 24:40, 41.</note> this is the explanation.
               The field is the world, according to what was said by our Saviour, "He that soweth the good seed
               is the Son of man; but the field is the world"<note type="footnote" n="749" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew 13:37, 38.</note>. Those therefore who have received the seed of the gospel, and the word of
               religion, while they are in the field and at work, either are taken into the kingdom because
               they are working and acting strenuously, or are left and remain as men who are indolent and
               slothful and lax. And the mill after the same model is this world, in which we pass our<note
                  type="footnote" n="750" resp="#ebrooks">In another version (V) 'men pass their'.</note> time as
               at a mill, eating bread by labour and toil; and some strenuously undergo hardship and exertion
               in works of righteousness, while others spend their time in vain acts which pass away like a
               shadow. And on account of those things<note type="footnote" n="751" resp="#ebrooks"> (V) 'of
                  these also'.</note> therefore it is <pb n="283"/> manifest that some are taken and others left.
               But the very wise Luke the Evangelist wrote this passage in the following form: "In this night
               there shall be two in one bed; the one shall be taken and the other left. There shall be two
               women grinding together; the one shall be taken away but the other left"<note type="footnote"
                  n="752" resp="#ebrooks">Luke xvii, 34, 35.</note>. And these things are brought about
               beforehand by each act, of the rich that is and of the poor, some of whom because they have done
               deeds worthy of the kingdom of heaven shall be taken, while others who have been negligent shall
               be left. For indeed even those who are in bed, those that is to say who enjoy ease in this
               world, and are in the portion of the rich, who<note type="footnote" n="753" resp="#ebrooks">Sic
                  Syr.</note>, if they administer the riches well, shall earn the privilege <pb n="284"/> of the
               kingdom of God, but those who spend this on vanities will justly be despised and put to
               contempt. But by the work of the mill those again are denoted who live in poverty and contempt,
               according to what is said in Exodus, "And all the firstborn shall die in the land of Egypt, from
               the firstborn of Pharaoh who sitteth on his throne down to the firstborn of the bondwoman who is
               in the mill-house"<note type="footnote" n="754">Exodus xi, 5.</note>; so that from this it is
               manifest that the name of [mill-house or<note type="footnote" n="755" resp="#ebrooks">These
                  words must have been inserted by the translator in ref. to Pesh. <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                     ><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܝܬ ܪܚܝܐ</foreign></foreign>. LXX <foreign xml:lang="grc">παρὰ τὸν
                        μὐλον</foreign>.</note>] mill signifies the utter contempt and poverty of those who continue
               in such service for the sake of daily sustenance. Accordingly our Lord's saying in the gospel
               signifies that both from among the rich who enjoy ease upon beds, and from among the utterly
               poor who are occupied in contemptible employments on the last day some shall be found, of whom
               <pb n="285"/> some will be saved, while others will perish, and neither poverty nor riches
               are<note type="footnote" n="756" resp="#ebrooks">Sic Syr.</note> impediments to him who seeks
               to live in the fear of God, in order to earn the kingdom of heaven. But some have said that the
               words "Two women shall be grinding in the mill, one is taken and one is left" were meant by our
               Saviour to refer to those who teach in the church. For those men grind the word of teaching as
               in a mill for those who learn, and lay rational bread before them, suprasensually feeding the
               souls. Wherefore also they say that what is written in Deuteronomy, "Thou shalt hot take a
               millstone nor an upper millstone in pledge, because this man taketh a soul in pledge"<note
                  type="footnote" n="757" resp="#ebrooks">Deuteronomy xxiv, 6.</note>, was meant to refer to teaching,
               that a teacher must not lay them under any debt and bond of debt, since the souls of those who
               are <pb n="286"/> taught are taken in pledge, and made void<note type="footnote" n="758"
                  resp="#ebrooks">In another version (E) 'and pass away from the teaching which takes the
                  souls<damage><supplied resp="#ebrooks">......</supplied></damage>taught in pledge, and fails'. </note> in respect of the
               principles of religion and the hope that arises thence. And this holy Scripture signifies in
               Koheleth also, saying of the time of the end, "And the grinding-women ceased because they had
               became few"<note type="footnote" n="759" resp="#ebrooks">Eccl., xi, 3.</note>. Then accordingly
               all teaching shall be silent, and labour and toil, when those who have previously performed
               shall receive rewards: for neither is it time then for them to teach or perform. Therefore Paul
               in writing to the Galatians said: "Therefore then while we have time let us work that which is
               good"<note type="footnote" n="760">Galatians vi, 10.</note>. This then is what our Saviour said:
               "Then shall there be two women grinding" (and that means souls occupied in teaching), "one is
               taken and one is left": and he who has taught the things that belong to religion, and has set
               the sound word without detraction and accurately before the rational sheep is taken <pb n="287"
               /> into the kingdom, but he who has detracted from<note type="footnote" n="761" resp="#ebrooks">
                  (V) ' debased'.</note> the teaching by heretical doctrines and deceived many, who by his own
               deceit has injured some, shall be left and sent outside the kingdom, having extreme judgments
               exacted from him on account of the wrong that he has done. Those again upon the roof they
               interpreted as those who have stood at the height of eminence.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
