<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3221">To John</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">132 [302]-138 [308]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2681">John of Bostra</persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="83">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName> to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2681">John</persName><note type="footnote" n="809"
               resp="#ebrooks"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2681">John</persName> of Bostra (ep. 81) (?).</note>, That, According to the Letter, Both <persName>Christ</persName>
               and <persName>Paul</persName> Abolished the Law, but, According to the Spirit, They Confirm It. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0538">519-38</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> We say that according to the letter the law was abolished through <persName>Christ</persName>, but that in the
               spirit it was much more fully brought to confirmation. But what were the things of the letter?
               Sacrifices, sprinklings, various temporary cleansings repeated at stated times, and other
               similar things, which were different from heathen demon-worship, but prefigured the truth as in
               a shadow, as <persName>Paul</persName> also says: "For the law contained a shadow of the future good things, not the
               very image of the facts"<note type="footnote" n="810" resp="#ebrooks">Hebrews x, 1.</note>. In the
               <pb n="303"/> same way <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/511">Gregory</persName> the Theologian<note type="footnote" n="811" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">θεολόγος</foreign>.</note> also in the homily on the Holy Spirit
               wrote thus: "The first, when it cut away idols conceded sacrifices: the second, when it caused
               sacrifices to pass away, did not forbid circumcision. But afterwards, when they had once
               accepted the suppression, they conceded even what had been conceded, the one sacrifices, the
               other circumcision; and they became instead of Gentiles Jews, and instead of these Christians,
               having by a gradual change of position been brought near to the gospel. Let <persName>Paul</persName> persuade you of
               this, who from circumcising and being purified was brought to say: 'But as for me, my brethren,
               if I still preach circumcision, why do I continue to be persecuted?' The one is a matter of the
               dispensation, the other of perfection"<note type="footnote" n="812" resp="#ebrooks">Or. Theol.
                  v, 25.</note>.</p>
            <p>That God permitted sacrifices in order to lead men to shun idolatry, <persName>Moses</persName> also testifies,
               since in Leviticus he wrote thus, after he had said that those of <placeName>Israel</placeName> were not allowed to
               perform any kind of sacrifice in another place besides the tent of witness: "And they shall no
               longer perform their own sacrifice to the vanities after whom they themselves go a 
               whoring"<note type="footnote" n="813" resp="#ebrooks">Leviticus XVII, 7.</note>. When therefore we say that
               the enactments which were laid down for that infant people, who were incapable of rising to the
               perfect service of God, <pb n="304"/> that I mean which is performed through the spirit, when
               the perfection came, which is <persName>Christ</persName>, were in the bodily form done away, we do not sin<note
                  type="footnote" n="814" resp="#ebrooks">Sc <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἁμαρτάνομεν</foreign> (err):
                  cf. p. 77, n. 3.</note>. Let me, as if dealing with a hypothesis<note type="footnote" n="815"
                     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπόθεσις</foreign>.</note>, test the matter. Various
               animals were formerly sacrificed for sin, and the blood of these was brought into the sanctuary
               by the high-priest, while, their bodies were delivered to be burnt outside the camp. This kind
               of sacrifices therefore symbolized beforehand the great sacrifice which balances the great sin
               of the world, as <persName>Paul</persName> also says: "For, as for the animals whose blood was brought into the
               sanctuary because of sins by the high-priest, the bodies of these were burnt outside the camp.
               Therefore <persName>Jesus</persName> also, in order to sanctify the people by his own blood, suffered outside the
               gate"<note type="footnote" n="816" resp="#ebrooks">Hebrews xiii, 11, 12.</note>. Since then <persName>Christ</persName>
               the Saviour of all was sacrificed in the original model on the cross, and is also slaughtered so
               to speak every day on the altar, and is distributed to the believers limb by limb by the hand of
               the priests, who is so mad, and so exceedingly uninstructed in the greatest matters, as to dare
               to deny that the type was abolished in the letter, that is according to the bodily form, and the
               <pb n="305"/> sacrifice of animals ceased, but the intellectual meaning<note type="footnote"
                  n="817"><foreign xml:lang="grc">θεωρία</foreign></note> was also preserved according to the
               spirit, in which the truth was prefigured through it? After the same manner also the eating of
               unleavened bread was abolished according to the letter, but according to the spirit it is still
               maintained, in that we 'keep the feast not in the leaven of wickedness and bitterness, but in
               the unleavened bread of purity and truth'<note type="footnote" n="818" resp="#ebrooks">1 Corinthians v,
                  8.</note>. <supplied reason="ellipsis" resp="#compiler">(<emph rend="ital">A little farther
                     on.</emph>)</supplied> But we will grant if you wish that the wax represents the letter, and the
               bronze that has been melted is the perfection in the spirit. If then it is the fact that, when
               the bronze is brought to the fire, it is reduced to non-existence, and the wax, when liquefied,
               gives to the bronze the shape only of that which was fashioned, explain if you have any abundant
               store of wisdom. But, if the wax has been dissolved and liquefied, the letter will be dissolved,
               but the spiritual meaning<note type="footnote" n="819"><foreign xml:lang="grc">θεωρία</foreign>.</note> of the law will remain, preserving the form<note type="footnote"
                  n="820" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">σχῆμα</foreign>.</note> of the letter. or <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/430">Cyril</persName>
               teaches and says: "We have not relegated the types to utter desolation(?), though certainly to
               partial desolation, I mean since the letter of the bodily observances ceases"<note
                  type="footnote" n="821" resp="#ebrooks">I do not know the source of this citation.</note>.
               Listen to the expressions of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/511">Gregory</persName> <pb n="306"/> the Theologian<note type="footnote" n="822"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">θεολόγος</foreign>.</note>, and let the words of that
               man and his thoughts be a law to you, and a fixed ordinance, since they are indeed such to all
               Christians. When in the homily on the Passover he discussed the meaning<note type="footnote"
                  n="823">The word <foreign xml:lang="grc">θεωρία</foreign> is here preserved.</note> of all the
               rites performed at the old Passover, he also caused the hearer to pass from the letter to the
               spirit: for, when he came to the staff, and solved the riddle of this, he commanded the man who
               eats this our Passover in truth to lean upon the staff of faith, using these words: "Stand
               firmly, with feet strongly planted, being in no point shaken by the adversaries, nor carried
               away by words of plausibility. These things <persName>Christ</persName> fulfilled, the subverter of the letter, the
               fulfiller of the spirit"<note type="footnote" n="824" resp="#ebrooks">Or. XLV, 19, 21.</note>.
               If 'the letter killeth, but the spirit giveth life'<note type="footnote" n="825" resp="#ebrooks">2 Corinthians III, 6.</note>, and <persName>Christ</persName> is life as it is written, "When <persName>Christ</persName> our life shall be
               revealed"<note type="footnote" n="826">Colossians iii, 4.</note>, how can it be that when the life
               came that which slew was not abolished? since, if you deny that the law was abolished in the
               letter, but brought to confirmation in the spirit, <persName>Paul</persName> also will be seen to say contradictory
               things, writing in one place that he 'annulled the law of commandments in teachings'<note
                  type="footnote" n="827" resp="#ebrooks">Ephesians ii, 15.</note>, and saying in another, "Do we
               therefore annul the law through faith? For be it. Nay we establish the law"<note type="footnote"
                  n="828" resp="#ebrooks">Romans iii, 31.</note>, recognising the <pb n="307"/> commandment as
               'holy and just and good'<note type="footnote" n="829" resp="#ebrooks">Romans viii, 12.</note>, and
               in another sorrowfully crying to those who chose after recognition of the truth to live by the
               law, "Ye who are justified in the law have been annulled from <persName>Christ</persName>, ye have fallen from
               grace"<note type="footnote" n="830" resp="#ebrooks">Galatians v, 4.</note>. It is a thing impossible
               that of the same object he should say that it has been annulled and openly confess that it has
               been established, and that he should admire it as just and good, while he rejects those who are
               justified in this and asserts that they have fallen from the grace that is in <persName>Christ</persName>. For it
               seems to some extent likely that we [shall remove] the enigma<damage><supplied resp="#ebrooks">.....</supplied></damage> from
               doubt if we look carefully at the words of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/511">Gregory</persName> the Theologian<note type="footnote" n="831"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">θεολόγος</foreign>.</note>; for he called <persName>Christ</persName> 'the
               subverter of the letter, but the fulfiller of the spirit'. Let us therefore cleave to the law
               inasmuch as it has been fulfilled, but let us neglect it, let us make haste to eradicate it with
               the swift foot of the word inasmuch as it has been abolished, rightly treating its bodily
               observances with contempt. Nay, you say, but that holy man says that the letter was abolished,
               while you say the law, inasmuch as you said that <persName>Paul</persName> is a subverter of the law. Rather <damage><supplied resp="#ebrooks">.....</supplied></damage> from what we have said you have the certain truth which <pb n="308"
                  /> was before likely. When <persName>Paul</persName> says that the law of commandments was annulled, we say that he
               means that according to the letter it was annulled, trusting to the words of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/511">Gregory</persName>; and there
               is therefore nothing that prevents me also from calling the letter the law. However<note
                  type="footnote" n="832" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܪܡ ܐܠܐ</foreign> here
                  represents <foreign xml:lang="grc">πλὴν ἀλλά</foreign>.</note>, if you desire to hear one of
               the fathers saying that the law was abolished when he should have said the letter, we will
               readily produce this citation also for you.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
