<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3126">To Constantine, Bishop of Laodicea</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">158 [328]-169 [339]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="91">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE HOLY SEVERUS PATRIARCH OF ANTIOCH, FROM THE 15th LETTER
               OF THE 5th BOOK OF THOSE AFTER BANISHMENT, WHICH WAS ADDRESSED TO MAR CONSTANTINE BISHOP OF
               LAODICEA. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0538">519-38</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> But the next point to which I will apply myself is the words found in the Book of Genesis
               that were spoken by God, when he was about to bring <pb n="329"/> the flood in the days of Noah,
               "My spirit shall not dwell among those men forever, because they are flesh; but their days shall
               be 120 years"<note type="footnote" n="891" resp="#ebrooks">Genesis 6:3.</note>. You ask how it is
               that, when a space of 120 years had been granted, he is seen to have carried out the same threat
               after 100 years, and flooded the whole earth together. For Noah was 500 years old on the day on
               which he granted him the space; and the divine Scripture said, "And the waters of the flood came
               upon the earth in the 600th year of the life of Noah, in the 2nd month on the 27th day of the
               month"<note type="footnote" n="892" resp="#ebrooks">Genesis 7:11.</note>. Upon this, being
               directed to the truth by the divine Scripture itself, we say that the term of 120 years was
               given in mercifulness, in order that those who were living an evil life might change for the
               better in fear of the threat. But they came to the utmost limit of wickedness, and treated the
               divine long-suffering with contempt, and accordingly God brought the punishment immediately; not
               as if he did not know what was to happen, but to show by the long term the abundance of his own
               long-suffering, and to establish also the greatness of those men's wickedness, who so much
               increased their impiety, and went down to the very end and bottom of wickedness, so as to call
               the sentence quickly down upon them. <pb n="330"/> Therefore he further also said to the
               righteous Noah, "The end of all flesh hath come in before me, because the earth hath been filled
               with iniquity by them"<note type="footnote" n="893" resp="#ebrooks">Genesis 6:13.</note>. For it
               is his custom to change his own sentences in the direction of fury and goodness according to our
               change, either towards wickedness or towards virtue. And this he stated plainly through Jeremiah
               the prophet: "If I speak a determination against a people or against a kingdom to root it out
               and destroy it, and that people turn from their evil deeds, I will repent concerning the evil
               things which I spake to do to them. And, if I speak a determination against a people and against
               a kingdom, that it be built and planted, and they do evil deeds before me, and hearken not to my
               voice, I will repent concerning the good things which I spake to do to them"<note
                  type="footnote" n="894" resp="#ebrooks">Jeremiah xviii, 7-10.</note>. And that these things are so
               is laid down by the very wise John also who became bishop of Constantinople, when he is
               interpreting the 104th Psalm and writing thus, and contending as against the Jews, who adduced
               the promises to their fathers: "But, if the Jew argues against these things, and holds to the
               promise that was made to them, I learn that many such promises were indeed made in the Old
               Testament also. He promised to give the land <pb n="331"/> from the river of Egypt to the
               Euphrates, and did not give it. He promised Adam to lay the fear and dread of him upon the
               animals, and the promise was not brought to completion. He promised that the life of men should
               be 120 years, and he brought the punishment before the term. And in the opposite cases the same
               things are to be seen. He threatened Hezekiah with death, and turned it away. He threatened the
               Ninevites with overthrow, and dispelled the wrath, showing that neither good things nor painful
               things depend on him only, but also on the recipients. For, if he threaten something grievous,
               and those who receive the threat change, they repel the wrath from them. But, if he promise
               something good, and they show themselves to be unworthy, they will be deprived. Therefore he
               says, ' I will speak a determination against a people and against a kingdom, to build and to
               plant', but, 'if he says 'they are seen to be unworthy, I will not bring these things'. Let them
               not therefore bring God's promises before us, but let them show if they were seen to be worthy
               of these. But they cannot show it: therefore they passed to others. For we nowhere find that
               they are able to show that the words 'In thy seed shall all the nations be blessed'<note
                  type="footnote" n="895" resp="#ebrooks">Genesis xxii, 18.</note> 'were fulfilled of them"<note
                     type="footnote" n="896" resp="#ebrooks">The commentary on Psalm CIV is lost.</note>. It is the
               same difficulty and elucidation <pb n="332"/> to which the words' also relate which the holy
               Cyril wrote in the 12th book of the commentary on the Gospel of John, as follows: "But,
               because<note type="footnote" n="897" resp="#ebrooks">Cyr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὅτι</foreign>, which the translator has misunderstood.</note>, though he often promised to
               do many things at the fitting time, he nevertheless did them even before the time appointed, for
               the purpose of persuading us, in order that we may truly believe that even under all
               circumstances the things said by him will come to effect, we will show from the following. He
               promised to raise the dead, and to bring back to life those who are laid in the earth and dust.
               For, 'there cometh', he saith, 'an hour, wherein the dead shall hear the voice of the Son of man
               and come forth, they that have done good deeds to the resurrection of life, but they that have
               done evil deeds to the resurrection of judgment'. And that he will easily make this good, and
               will hasten to persuade<note type="footnote" n="898" resp="#ebrooks">Cyr. <foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">πληροφορεῖν ἐπειγόμενος</foreign>.</note> he taught by saying, ' I am the
               resurrection and the life'. And, because he would not make the greatness of the thing that the
               dead should rise at that time so to speak incredible, for a useful purpose the time of the
               resurrection is hastened<note type="footnote" n="899" resp="#ebrooks">Cyr. <foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">ἡ τοῦ πράγματος ὑπερβολὴ τὸ ἀναβιώσεσβαί ποτε τοὺς νεκροὺς πως ἐτίθει φθάνει
                  χρησίμως τον τῆς ἀναστασέως καιρόν</foreign>.</note> and he shows the sign in that he raised
               Lazarus and the widow's son, and Jairus' daughter. And what else besides these things? He says
               that the resurrection of the <pb n="333"/> saints shall be something exceedingly glorious.
               'Then', he says, 'the righteous shall shine in their Father's kingdom', that he may again be
               believed as one who speaks truly, in that he saw the disciples beforehand and gave the sight of
               this<note type="footnote" n="900" resp="#ebrooks">Cyr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόωρον τοῖς
                  μαθηταῖς κ. τὴν τούτου θέαν ἐχαρίζετο</foreign>.</note>. For 'he took Peter and James and
               John, and went up into a mountain, and was transfigured before them; and his face shone as
               lightning, and his raiment became white as snow'"<note type="footnote" n="901" resp="#ebrooks">In Jo. Ev., ed. Pusey, III, 136.</note>. But in the above-mentioned commentary on the 104th
               Psalm we find the holy John bishop of Constantinople solving the point in Exodus that seemed
               doubtful; and the point that seemed doubtful is, you said, as follows: "How is it that, after
               Moses had turned all the water in Egypt into blood, Scripture said that the magicians were able
               to show the same sign against that? For, since all the water had been changed, how was it
               possible for pure water to be found in which these men were to show the sign?" Some have said
               that it was possible for sea-water to come, since the sea was not at a great distance, in order
               that they might change this by magic skill; while others have said that it is not incredible
               that Moses himself, after the change to blood, turned <pb n="334"/> the water back to its own
               appearance and nature, in order that the magicians might show their own skill on the other side.
               But the wise doctor John, since he understood the divine power as is right and in very
               discerning fashion, said that, as in the case of the darkness the Egyptians had that darkness,
               while the sons of Israel had light, and, as in the matter of the herds, and in the case of the
               yoke-animals when they died, those belonging to the Israelites remained unharmed, and, in the
               case of the plague of hail, where the sons of Israel were in the land of Goshen no hail fell, in
               the same way you should understand as regards all the plagues too, among which that change from
               water to blood was also included, and it must be believed that in the land of Goshen, and where
               the sons of Israel were, the water remained for the sons of Israel in its own nature without
               change, in which it was possible for the magicians to show the performances of their own skill.
               Among the words uttered by the doctor is contained the following passage by way of summary: "'
               He sent darkness and made it dark'<note type="footnote" n="902" resp="#ebrooks">Psalm CIV,
                  28.</note>; and it was a very glorious fact that, while the ray shone everywhere, in, Egypt
               darkness appeared; and there not throughout, but only where the Egyptians were. For, lest any
               one should say that what happened was an eclipse<note type="footnote" n="903" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔκλειψις</foreign>.</note>, <pb n="335"/> that is a disappearance of
               the moon, nor<note type="footnote" n="904" resp="#ebrooks">Sic Syr.</note> the course of nature,
               the Hebrews who were living in the same country with them were not affected by this plague, a
               thing which happened in the other plagues". After a similar manner Gregory also bishop of Nyssa,
               who was great in the knowledge of divine things, in the treatise which he composed about virtue
               said these things: he said: "For then all the nature of the waters in Egypt was in accordance
               with Moses' command turned to blood, and the fish were destroyed, because the water was
               converted to fleshlike density; but the Hebrews, when they drew the blood, had water<note
                  type="footnote" n="905" resp="#ebrooks">Greg. <foreign xml:lang="grc">τοῖς Ἑβρ. ἀρυομένοις
                     μόνοις ὕδωρ τὸ αἷμα ἦν</foreign>.</note>. Therefore there arose an occasion for the display of
               skill, that with the water found among the Hebrews they might in a defective manner contrive to
               produce the appearance of blood"<note type="footnote" n="906" resp="#ebrooks">P. G., XLIV,
                  308.</note>. The words used in the 1st Book of Kingdoms to Ahimelech the priest by the holy
               David, "Is the journey itself also profane?<note type="footnote" n="907" resp="#ebrooks">The
                  ambiguity between affirmative and interrogative (see below) cannot be preserved.</note> because
               it will be hallowed to-day by means of my implements", if it is very carefully and clearly read,
               is seen to be much plainer than the sun, and to be free from all obscurity. David asked for
               bread to eat; and the priest answered and said, "There are no profane loaves under my hands; but
               there are holy <pb n="336"/> loaves. If the slaves have refrained, at least from a woman, they
               shall eat". And David answered and said, "But we have kept away from a woman since yesterday,
               and since the third day. Since I set out on the journey, all the slaves have been pure". And,
               these things having been so stated first, what follows should be read as a question, "Is the
               journey itself also profane?"<note type="footnote" n="908" resp="#ebrooks">1 Samuel xxi, 4,
                  5.</note>; and thereupon the addition will give the reason for which the journey is not
               profane; and the addition runs, "Because it will be hallowed to-day by means of my implements",
               that is to say, 'Will anyone call the same journey a profane thing, a journey which has been
               hallowed by means of my implements?', viz 'by means of my armour, and the burden of my
               implements, and by my going to war'. And from this it is manifest that, inasmuch as the slaves
               were accustomed to carry his implements and arms, when he went out to war, they were purified.
               And, that slaves again used to march after generals or commanders, as armour-bearers, this is
               manifest from many instances; for the present from the end of the 1st Book <pb n="337"/> of
               Kingdoms, in which it is stated that Saul said to his weapon-carrier, "Draw thy sword and
               transfix me with it"<note type="footnote" n="909">I Samuel 31:4</note>. And towards the end of
               the 2nd book he says, in the numeration and reckoning of the generals or commanders of the
               divine David. "Naharai the Berothite, weapon-carrier of Joab the son of Zeruiah"<note
                  type="footnote" n="910" resp="#ebrooks">2 Samuel 23:37.</note>. This then is what David here
               said, "Even the slaves themselves are pure, because they are weaponbearers"; and this now when
               he had fled from Saul, and was not carrying arms. Wherefore also he asked the priest saying,
               "See if there be here under thine hand a spear or a sword, because I did not take my sword and
               my weapons in mine hand, because the king's word was pressing"<note type="footnote" n="911"
                  resp="#ebrooks">1 Samuel 21:8.</note>. And from what is here stated especially it is manifest
               that those who went out for the purpose of being ranged in order of battle were purified. And
               this is very clearly recognised also from the commandments given in Deuteronomy; for he says:
               "If thou go out against thine enemies, keep thyself from every evil action. And, if there be
               among thee a man who is not pure from his discharge at night, he shall go outside the camp and
               shall not' come into the camp. And it shall be that towards evening he shall bathe his body in
               water, and, <pb n="338"/> when the sun hath set, he shall go into the camp. And thou shalt have
               a place outside the camp, and he shall go out there without. And thou shall have a peg on thy
               loins, and it shalt be that, when thou sittest outside, thou shalt dig with it, and shalt turn
               and hide thy shame with it; because the Lord thy God walketh in thy camp, to rescue thee, and to
               deliver thine enemies into thine hands; and thy camp shall be holy; and the shame of an act
               shall not be seen in thee and shall turn away from thee"<note type="footnote" n="912"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Deuteronomy 23:10-14 (text of AF).</note>. And in the 2nd Book of Kingdoms Uriah
               too also manifests this same sentiment. When he had returned from the lines, and was about to go
               to them, David ordered him to go down to his own house after supper; and he answered and said,
               "If the ark and Israel and Judah dwell in tents, and my lord Joab and my lord's bondmen are
               encamped upon the face of the field, shall even I go into mine house and eat and drink and sleep
               with my wife? how? As my soul liveth, I will not do this thing"<note type="footnote" n="913"
                  resp="#ebrooks">2 Samuel xi, 11.</note>. These are the conclusions at which we for our part have
               arrived on the questions that were presented to me by your saintliness according to the capacity
               that our meanness possesses. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
