<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3089">To Archelaus the Reader</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">170 [340]-177 [347]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="93">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE SAME FROM THE 5th LETTER OF THE 9th BOOK OF THOSE
               WRITTEN WHILE HE HELD THE BISHOPRIC, WHICH WAS ADDRESSED TO ARCHELAUS THE READER<note
                  type="footnote" n="917" resp="#ebrooks">Of Tyre (Select Letters of Severus, vi, 2). A Greek
                  extract from a letter to him is published in Mai, Class. Auct., X, 440 (of. 457).</note>. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0513" notAfter="0518">513-8</date>
            </dateline>
            <p>For you write to the effect that certain men said about the holy John the Evangelist that he
               did not undergo the common end, but still continues even now to exist without death, like Enoch,
               of whom the apostle said that he 'was translated that he might not see death'<note
                  type="footnote" n="918" resp="#ebrooks">Heb. XI, 5.</note>, and Elijah of whom it is written
               that he 'was carried up in a whirlwind toward heaven'<note type="footnote" n="919"
                  resp="#ebrooks">2 Kings II, 11.</note>. I am astonished at the crassness of the ignorance of
               those who said this and their lack of information. As the evangelist manifestly corrects the
               supposition of many and says, "Jesus did not say to him 'He shall not die', but 'If I will that
               he tarry till I come what is it to thee?"<note type="footnote" n="920" resp="#ebrooks">John XXI,
                  23.</note>, where is there room for us to speak in opposition to the divine Scriptures and say
               that he who said these things remained immortal? The disciples above all, they who were the
               preachers of the resurrection, were bound to undergo the common <pb n="341"/> end, in order that
               all who received the preaching of the gospel might learn that all the chances of their
               blessedness rest in the future life, and that we must despise the life here, and willingly
               hasten to death. Such wonderful things were done in the times of the old covenant<note
                  type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">διαθήκη</foreign>.</note>, when men
               were not yet in a perfect condition, and were deficient in faith, and were unable to receive the
               teaching of the resurrection, and firmly to believe that, after the separation of soul and body,
               it is possible for those who have once died to come back again to life. As to the fact that John
               the Evangelist underwent the common end, it is not we only who admit this, but men also who are
               highly distinguished among the fathers, and guides to the mysteries<note type="footnote"
                  resp="#ebrooks">This phrase represents <foreign xml:lang="grc">μυσταγωγοί</foreign>.</note> and
               doctors of the holy church. And John, who became bishop of Constantinople, in the commentary on
               the Gospel of John, when commenting on the very place from which those who are blind towards
               what is manifest and plain draw the erroneous inference, says thus: "For, because Peter was
               always confident and forward in asking such questions, it was again by way of cutting away his
               impetuosity and teaching him not to make any further inquiry that he said this. Therefore the
               report went out among <pb n="342"/> the brethren that that man should not die. And he did not
               say, 'He shall tarry till I come', but, 'If I will that he tarry'. 'For do not suppose either',
               he says, 'that I manage your affairs in one way only'. But this he did because he wished to
               detach them from excessive love towards one another. For, since they were to receive the charge
               of the world, it was not right for them any longer to be bound up with one another: for, if this
               had been so, this would have been a great loss to the world. Therefore he says thus<note
                  type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"> The translator therefore read <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                     >οὕτως</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">αὐτῳ</foreign>.</note>: 'You have had a work
               entrusted to you, look to it, and act and fight like a combatant. For what even though I will
               that he tarry here? look you to your own affairs, and concern yourself about them'. But do you
               observe, I pray, even here also the unassuming character of the evangelist. For after mentioning
               the belief of the disciples with regard to this matter he corrects it on the ground that they
               had not noticed what he said. For neither did Jesus say, 'He shall not die', but, 'If will that
               he tarry'<note type="footnote" n="921" resp="#ebrooks">In. Joh. Hom. LXXXVIII, 2 (ed. Par. 2a,
                  VIII, 60).</note>. And the very wise Cyril, while inserting a mention of the interpretation of
               this saying, writes thus: "When Peter therefore saw this man, he tried to be curious, and begged
               to learn to what and what kind of <pb n="343"/> dangers he also would after these things be
               exposed, or to what the end of his life also would come. But the question was manifestly beyond
               the limits of due reason, and that act was one of inquisitiveness rather; not of useful
               learning, that, having obtained knowledge about himself, he should inquire into the things that
               were coming upon others. For this reason, as I think, the Lord answered and said something,
               though not a direct answer to, the things asked or inquired about, but he turns in a way the
               purpose of the questioner to other things, so that he does not say 'John shall be immortal' but
               'If I will that he be alive till I come, what then is it to you yourself?': 'therefore', that
               is, 'you have heard, O Peter, the things that concern you, and why are you curious about things
               that concern others? and why do you probe into the knowledge of the divine judgments out of
               season? For, if he had actually said that he should never die<note type="footnote" n="922"
                  resp="#ebrooks">So Syr. meaninglessly; Cyr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἰ γὰρ καὶ μηδόλως τελευτῴη
                     ἄησιν</foreign> #check transcription#.</note>, how then will this comfort your anxiety?'"<note
                        type="footnote" n="923" resp="#ebrooks">In Jo. Ev., ed. Pusey, III, 168.</note> And Athanasius
               patriarch of Alexandria in the 41st exposition spoken at a festival on the 3rd of the month of
               Farmenothi said these words: "And the graves of all these exist to this day, and we have
               ourselves seen them, as that of Peter and that of Paul at the great Rome, <pb n="344"/> and that
               of John at Ephesus"<note type="footnote" n="924" resp="#ebrooks">This work is not
                  extant.</note>. And Eusebius Pamphili in the 3rd book of the Ecclesiastical History plainly
               wrote that John the theologian-apostle and evangelist underwent the common end of all men, and
               that he awaits the true and long life that has no ending which is after the resurrection: and in
               the 68th chapter<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >κεφάλαιον</foreign>.</note> of the book which we have mentioned he says; "It is related that
               John, the apostle and evangelist at the same time, was still living in the world, and on account
               of the testimony concerning God the Word<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">Eus. <foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">τὸν θεῖον Λόγον</foreign>.</note> was condemned to live in the island of
               Patmos"; and again in the 23rd chapter<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">κεφάλαιον</foreign>.</note> he writes thus: "In these times there had been left
               in the world in Asia the actual man whom Jesus loved, John the apostle and evangelist at the
               same time, and he was governing the churches there, having returned from the island in which he
               had been exiled after Domitian's death"; and in the 31st chapter<note type="footnote"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">κεφάλαιον</foreign>.</note> he immediately adds these
               things about him: "But the chronology of John's life we have already mentioned, but the locality
               of his body is shown from the letter of Polycrates (he was bishop of the region<note
                  type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">χώρα</foreign> (Eus. <foreign
                     xml:lang="grc">παροικίας</foreign>).</note> of Ephesus), in writing which to Victor bishop of
               the Romans <pb n="345"/> he mentions him and Philip the apostle at the same time and the
               latter's daughters as follows: 'In Asia also sleep great lights who shall rise at the last day
               of our Lord's coming, in which he comes with glory from heaven and shall search out all the
               saints, Philip who was of the 12 apostles, who also sleeps in Hierapolis, and his two daughters
               who had grown old in virginity; and his other daughter, who lived her life in the Holy Spirit,
               fell asleep in Ephesus. Moreover John also as well who fell upon our Lord's breast, who became a
               priest, having put on the crown, and martyr<note type="footnote" n="925" resp="#ebrooks">Or
                  'witness'.</note> and doctor, he sleeps in Ephesus'. So much we have said concerning these
               persons' death"<note type="footnote" n="926">H. E., III, xviii, 1; xxiii, 1; xxxi, 2-4.</note>.
               But that other argument also besides is one of great madness and of uninstructed understanding,
               which confirms the erroneous supposition from the gospel saying which was spoken by our God and
               Saviour Jesus Christ to his disciples in this way: "Verily I say unto you; there are some
               standing here who shall not taste death till they see the Son of man coming in his kingdom"<note
                  type="footnote" n="927" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. xvi, 28.</note>. It is time for those who thus
               err to say also of which of the other disciples they suppose that together with John himself
               they did not taste of death, but that they have remained immortal to this day; for the <pb
                  n="346"/> saying is expressed in the plural, for Christ did not say 'someone who shall not
               taste death till he see the Son of man coming in his kingdom'. What answer will the men who
               speak all their words without examination give to this? It was not in reference to immortality
               in this world that our Saviour himself spoke these things to his own disciples, but because he
               wished to supply confirmation in the matter of the promise of the future life, and of the glory
               that is in it; for in fact a little before he said, "The Son of man shall come in the glory of
               his Father with his angels, and then shall he reward every man according to his works"<note
                  type="footnote" n="928">Matth. xvi, 27.</note>. It was because he wished, as I have said, to
               raise their mind which still saw little and was confined to the lowliness of the dispensation
               and had no God-befitting thoughts to the height of that hope that he immediately added the
               saying, "Verily I say unto you that there are some standing here who shall not taste death till
               they see the Son of man coming in his kingdom", and because he was about to take the three
               disciples, Peter, James, and John, up into the mountain, and to show them a phantasm<note
                  type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">φαντασία</foreign>.</note> and very
               obscure picture of the future kingdom and of his own glory, and as on a stage give to that which
               was immediately <pb n="347"/> duly to appear the future exalted and God-befitting greatness
               which our mind cannot grasp. For after these words in immediate sequence the evangelist added,
               "After six days Jesus took Peter and James and John his brother, and led them up into a high
               mountain alone and was transfigured before them, and his face shone like the sun, and his
               raiment became white like the light"<note type="footnote" n="929" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. xvii.
                  1, 2.</note>. Let no one again from the statement that the Son of man shall come in his kingdom
               refer the saying to the second coming of our Saviour; for the name 'coming' may be used not only
               to signify a bodily coming, but also for the glory and light of the divine revelation. This is
               shown by the divine saying of our Saviour when he says in the Gospel of John to his disciples,
               "If a man loveth me, he will keep my words, and my Father will love him, and we will come to
               him, and make an abode with him"<note type="footnote" n="930" resp="#ebrooks">John xiv,
                  23.</note>. Here the expression 'we will come'manifestly denotes not a bodily coming, but a
               revelation as we have said of God-befitting glory and brightness. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
