<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3024">To Solon, Bishop of Isauria</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">181 [351]-193 [363]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="96">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE HOLY SEVERUS THE 22nd LETTER OF THE 2nd BOOK OF THOSE
               WRITTEN DURING EPISCOPACY, WHICH WAS ADDRESSED TO SOLON BISHOP OF ISAURIA<note type="footnote"
                  n="939">See p. 132, n. 3.</note>.</head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0514" notAfter="0517">514-7</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> After we had held the love of God that is in you much to blame for sending the religious
               bishops Epiphanius and Symbatius<note type="footnote" n="940" resp="#ebrooks">Select Letters of
                  Severus, p. 75.</note>, who are under your authority by right of the metropolitan dignity,
               without a letter, the well-tried Basil arrived, bringing us a letter written by you, and, after
               gladly seeing this, we believed it to be a defence to the same charge, since we perceived that
               by means of it the reason for which the bishops came to the city of Antiochus is made clear. And
               the contents of the letter were concerned with other matters: for among these there was a query
               concerning a certain scriptural problem; and it seemed to me difficult and evidence of great
               ignorance for us to return an answer to the question while I am distressed in my soul on account
               of the division in the faith which has prevailed among you because of our sins. For we remember
               one of those wise in divine <pb n="352"/> things who says, "Instruments of music at a time of
               mourning are a tale out of season"<note type="footnote" n="941" resp="#ebrooks">Sirach xxii,
                  6.</note>. However, since by the other letter<note type="footnote" n="942" resp="#ebrooks">The
                     Greek must have meant 'rest of the letter'.</note> we were released so to speak from the
               mourning of sorrow, I considered it right on account of the great honour maintained towards your
               excellence to write a few words in answer to that query, such as have come into my mind, and
               words which are drawn from the Scriptures composed by the Spirit and the fathers who with the
               help of the Spirit expounded these, little as we have understood. Since you have set. down in
               your letter (therein acting rightly) the points raised by every kind of understanding or by
               impulsive eloquence, I have determined not to extend this letter to a great length; for I myself
               also have believed that the enjoyment of the good things that are promised us in the kingdom of
               heaven is not sensual, nor yet does it consist in eating and drinking. Since the man who
               propounds the contrary argument is vehement, and everywhere introduces the restoration to the
               primitive state and the enjoyment in <placeName>Paradise</placeName>, I pass over the theory which raises the enjoyment
               and the trees and the ends of the branches to an allegory<note type="footnote" n="943"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">θεωρία</foreign>.</note>, and come to a matter which is
               free from dispute, and simple, and one which draws its defence <pb n="353"/> from the truth
               only. That Christ by means of his Incarnation raised or raises us to these primitive conditions
               is certain. But this must be understood as far as concerns in corruption arid the abolition of
               death, to which the bitter taste enjoyed by disobedience gave birth. That Emmanuel invites us to
               prizes and crowns that surpass the primitive state, making our right actions means of support
               for further assistance, and that he does not raise us to <placeName>Paradise</placeName> again, but introduces us in a
               new fashion into the kingdom of heaven, is manifest and is never a matter of doubt, not even to
               those who are very perverse. And, in order that we may not be thought to be rousing the hearer
               to maintain the contrary argument by using our own inventions, we will as a superfluity cite the
               laws of the God-clad guides to the mysteries<note type="footnote" n="944" resp="#ebrooks">This
                  phrase represents <foreign xml:lang="grc">μυσταγωγοί</foreign>.</note> of the church, which
               suffice to bring before our eyes the meaning of the divine words. Gregory the Theologian in the
               homily on the divine Epiphany in speaking about the Incarnation wrote thus: "This is more
               godlike than the former. This to those who have intelligence is higher"<note type="footnote"
                  n="945" resp="#ebrooks">Or. xxxviii, 13.</note>. But, if there is more likeness to God, and it
               is higher than a new creation, it is manifest that it leads those who are formed anew to a
               higher and more divine <pb n="354"/> condition<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">κατάστασις</foreign>.</note>. And John the holy bishop of Constantinople in the
               homily entitled 'Why that tree was called the tree of good and evil', and 'What is the meaning
               of the words "To-day thou shalt be with me in <placeName>Paradise</placeName>"', laying down clear teaching on this
               matter, said these words: "The robber entered <placeName>Paradise</placeName>. And what is this? Are these the good
               things which God promises us? Do you not hear Paul saying, 'These good things eye hath not seen,
               and ear hath not heard, and they have not gone up into man's heart'. But <placeName>Paradise</placeName> both eye has
               seen, that of Adam, and ear has heard, and man's heart has received, for indeed we have been
               speaking about it for so many days. How then did that robber receive them? For God does not
               promise to bring us into <placeName>Paradise</placeName>, but into heaven itself; and he did not proclaim a kingdom of
               <placeName>Paradise</placeName> but a kingdom of heaven. For 'he began to proclaim and to say, "Repent, for the kingdom
               of heaven hath drawn near""<note type="footnote" n="946" resp="#ebrooks">In Genesis Hom. vii, 4, 5
                  (ed. Par. 2a IV, 788). A similar passage is published in Greek from Severus with no mention of Jo.
                  Chrys. in Mai, Class. Auct., X, 444.</note>. Since these things therefore have been thus stated
               by the holy doctors, it is good to add Paul's words as a head and confirmation to what has been
               stated; for he <pb n="355"/> said, "The kingdom of heaven is not food and drink, but
               righteousness and peace, and joy in the Holy Spirit"<note type="footnote" n="947"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Romans xiv, 17.</note>. For the saying, "Blessed are the lowly, for they shall
               inherit the earth"<note type="footnote" n="948" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew v, 5.</note>, must on no
               account lead us to the notion that after release from this world and the future life we shall
               enjoy sensual things. For even the holy John also whom I mentioned a short time ago stated how
               Christ, following the custom of the Old Testament<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">διαθήκη</foreign>.</note>, which promises a land of promise flowing with milk
               and honey, himself also similarly promised to the lowly after this model abundance of days in
               this world, and a share in the good things of the earth, writing thus in the commentary on the
               Gospel of Matthew: "For he does not incite from future good things only, but also from present
               ones, and that on account of the more dense among the hearers, who seek these things before
               those that are future"; and a little farther on: "And in another way also, because in the Old
               Testament the prophet says, 'For the lowly shall inherit the earth', he therefore weaves the
               sentence together out of words that had grown up with them, in order that they may not
               everywhere hear strange things"<note type="footnote" n="949" resp="#ebrooks">Serm. in Matthew xv,
                  8 (ed. Par. 2a, VII, 216, 217).</note>. And the saintly Gregory bishop of Nyssa in the work
               entitled 'About the <pb n="356"/> Beatitudes' said thus: "But, if we soar in language and stand
               above the arch of heaven, we shall find there the supracelestial earth also, which is kept as an
               inheritance for those who have lived in virtue, so that the order of sequence of the blessings
               may not seem to be at fault, in that heaven was first set before us by God and afterwards a
               promise of earth"<note type="footnote" n="950" resp="#ebrooks">P. G., XLIV, 1209.</note>. But,
               if any man, having regard to his belly and occupying himself with foods that please the throat,
               turn against these things also, saying, "Why therefore shall we make use of the earth?", then we
               must say to him; If we look for a new heaven and a new earth according to his promise, as the
               divine Scripture said<note type="footnote" n="951" resp="#ebrooks">Revelation XXI, 1.</note>, how is
               it anything but inconceivable that we should introduce the old custom into the renovation of the
               elements? When the earth is new, the life also as well: will assuredly be new, a life that on
               every point lies outside this one and differs from it; for we may hear the Psalmist saying, ,
               "The voice of praise and salvation is in the tent of the righteous"<note type="footnote" n="952"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Psalm cxvii, 15.</note>. And this a man will say is the food of those who are
               about to live the expected life, continual songs of praise and the sublime contemplation<note
                  type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">θεωρία</foreign>.</note> on which the
               angels also feed, and joy and inexplicable exaltation, in life that does not <pb n="357"/> end.
               For those whose throat gapes for sensual enjoyment, being involved in the same empty-mindedness
               as those men, make use of senseless fatuities and say, "For what purpose then shall we make use
               of teeth, or the other members by which the perception of the things that please is received?"
               To these it is obvious to answer that, since the soul receives the body in perfection at the
               time of the resurrection, those who rise not being devoid of genital members, and this though
               the book of the gospel cries, "In the resurrection they marry not, nor are given in marriage,
               but they are as the angels that are in heaven"<note type="footnote" n="953" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew xxii, 30.</note>, after the same fashion they will have also <pb n="358"/> teeth and
               all the members of the body, that, as they have together with the soul practised habits of
               virtue, they may also partake of the glory; for it is not in order that they may make use of
               these according to the ancient custom. If we crave for and need sensual food in the future
               painless life, it is then time to desire also clothes made of wool, and the other things which
               this life shows to be necessary, in the summer and in the winter which comes round in the
               succession of the other seasons. But it is very certain that the expected life is free from all
               these things, since the seven days' circle which makes up the existing time ceases, and there is
               one day the eighth<note type="footnote" n="954" resp="#ebrooks">See ep. 79, 80.</note>, one
               which has none to succeed it and is without evening. If then there is a new heaven and a new
               earth and a new course of time expressed in one endless day and not divided into days and
               nights, how is it anything but reasonable to expect that the new life which is unknown to us and
               is not <pb n="359"/> even comprehended by the mind is severed from sensual foods, just as the
               life of the angels is far removed in comparison with the present life of men? But I for my part
               say this also, that, since Christ became a beginning for us in all things, it is manifest that
               the conditions of our resurrection also bear a resemblance to the same beginning. If then Christ
               after the Resurrection from the place of the dead is<note type="footnote" n="955"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Mss. ins. 'not'.</note> made known in flesh as it is written<note
                     type="footnote" n="956" resp="#ebrooks">Luke xxiv, 39.</note>, having, as he had, that body and
               no other, but no longer susceptible of hunger, or of any similar thing, nor yet one sustained by
               foods, it is assuredly necessary that our bodies also should not want anything; for Paul said,
               "As we were clad in the image of the earthy, so shall we also be clad m the image of him that is
               from heaven"<note type="footnote" n="957" resp="#ebrooks">1 Corinthians xv, 49.</note>. For the fact
               that he ate and drank with the disciples as it is written<note type="footnote" n="958"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Acts x, 41.</note> and received food should be ascribed to dispensation;
               because he did this same thing in order to confirm the nature of the body that had risen and
               cast out the supposition of phantasy. But, even though in conflict with the beginning of the
               argument, I say this also, guiding my opinions by the labour of the God-clad guides to the
               mysteries<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">This phrase represents <foreign xml:lang="grc">μυσταγωγοί</foreign>.</note>, <pb n="360"/> that, even if we expect the kingdom of heaven,
               and an end that is greater than the life of <placeName>Paradise</placeName>, we are not debarred from expecting a fresh
               return of the primitive state; for Basil the great said in the homily entitled ' God is not the
               cause of evils' that, if Adam had kept the commandment and not transgressed, suprasensual prizes
               and crowns and such as raise to an equality of honour with the angels were prepared for him; for
               he wrote as follows: "It was not fitting that he should have clothes either from nature or from
               craftsmanship, but there were others prepared for the man, if he displayed virtues, clothes such
               as by God's grace glistened and were to flash, shining garments, as those of the angels also
               are, surpassing the varied hues of the flowers, and excelling the light of the stars. For this
               reason therefore the garments were not immediately forthcoming, because they were prizes of
               virtue reserved for the man, to which by Satan's fraud he did not receive permission to
               attain"<note type="footnote" n="959" resp="#ebrooks">P. G., XXXI, 349.</note>. For us to adduce
               the food of the angels who were <pb n="361"/> entertained by Abraham is very much beside the
               point; for how can those who appeared as in a vision and a symbol be patterns for the things
               that are expected by us in reality? Shall we say that these three, who appeared to the,
               patriarch in the likeness of men, and signified the Holy Trinity (for the sacred Scripture said
               that God himself was manifested to Abraham<note type="footnote" n="960" resp="#ebrooks">Genesis
                  xviii, 1.</note>), ate of that unleavened bread and partook of that calf in such a way that
               these things actually passed into the digestion and the material exits, and not rather that they
               were invisibly consumed in a manner which God understands, who brought about these things? But
               how is it anything but foolish and an act of great madness for us here to think of the
               phantasy<note type="footnote" n="961" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">φαντασία</foreign>.</note> of Eutyches? Eutyches by comparing our Saviour's dispensation in
               the flesh, by means of which the word of God shared our nature, to earlier utterances and
               revelations of <pb n="362"/> God both to prophets and to patriarchs, which were described in
               symbols and adumbrations as being of God, missed the right principle. But we, who follow the
               apostolic teachings, who know that a vision shown in a symbol is one thing, and the truth of the
               fact another, pronounce that the coming of the Word in the flesh is quite distinct from the
               earlier manifestations which were made as in a dream and an adumbration. For we also hear of
               revelations coming from God which say to Aaron and Miriam, "If there shall be among you a
               prophet to the Lord, I will be made known to him in a vision and will speak to him in a
               dream"<note type="footnote" n="962" resp="#ebrooks">Numbers XII, 6.</note>, and cry in Hosea the
               prophet, "I for my part multiplied visions, and by means of prophets was I likened"<note
                  type="footnote" n="963" resp="#ebrooks">Hosea XII, 10.</note>. But he who multiplied visions and
               was variously likened by means of prophets became man for our sake truly and without variation,
               and in a new way. As therefore the shadowy and primitive symbols in no way impair by comparison
               the fact that our Lord and God Jesus Christ became in truth man invariably, so we do not on
               account of his true Incarnation refuse to hold the earlier symbols and obscure revelations given
               as in a dream and visions to be <pb n="363"/> adumbrations, since the Holy Scriptures cry this
               out with loud voice. Since then these things are so, we must shun the false opinion of those who
               think that the enjoyment promised in the kingdom of heaven consists in some sensual foods, an
               opinion into which Irenaeus bishop of Lyons in Gaul fell, who through the books of Papias
               departed from the truth, as Eusebius, who composed the Ecclesiastical<note type="footnote"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐκκλησιαστική</foreign>.</note> Histories for us,
               wrote<note type="footnote" n="964" resp="#ebrooks">H.E., III, XXXIX, 12, 13.</note>. Those who
               so hold, and expect a kind of recurrence of a cycle, are of a folly which even madmen do not
               possess; into which the witless Apollinaris also fell. This is as much as we are able to write
               on the present question, according to our small capacity. But it is the duty of your saintliness
               after the reading of these things to acquaint us by letter what was the frame of mind of those
               who disputed about this; for we shall think this a reward for our labours, to know clearly if
               after what has been written the supporters of the contrary opinion were helped. The other thing
               also do not forget, that, if after reading these things they retain any contrary opinion in
               their mind, we shall perhaps not be wanting in the needed medicines for this also. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
