<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3118">To Caesaria the Hypatissa</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">194 [364]-199 [369]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="97">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE SAME FROM THE 74th LETTER. OF THE 3rd BOOK OF THOSE
               AFTER EXILE WHICH WAS ADDRESSED TO CAESARIA THE HYPATISSA WHICH BEGINS, "The various
               communications addressed to me by your highness". </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0538">519-38</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> And the other thing also which you ask is a question of the Phantasiasts<note type="footnote"
               resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">φαντασιασταί</foreign></note> who hold the opinions of
               the Manichees, since they think that they are propounding and saying something against which it
               is impossible to argue: "If our Lord underwent the circumcision required by the law, 'when', as
               the gospel says, 'eight days were accomplished for circumcising him, and his name was called
               Jesus'<note type="footnote" n="965" resp="#ebrooks">Luke II, 21.</note>, what happened to his
               foreskin?"; for those wretched men think that they are driving us into a corner, and do not
               understand that it would be an act of their own godless lack of intelligence <pb n="365"/> for
               us to refuse to acknowledge things that are written on account of things that are not written.
               It is not the gospel only which testifies through these words which have been cited that Christ
               was circumcised according to the law, but Paul also, who in writing to the Romans says, "For I
               say that Christ became a minister of circumcision on behalf of the truth of God, that he might
               confirm the promises made to the fathers"<note type="footnote" n="966" resp="#ebrooks">Romans xv,
                  8.</note>. For to Abraham and Isaac and Jacob our fathers both the covenant<note
                     type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">διαθήκη</foreign>.</note> of
               circumcision was given, and the promise was made, "In thy seed shall all the families of the
               nations be blessed"<note type="footnote" n="967">Genesis xxii, 18; xxvi, 4; xxviii, 14.</note>; for
               Christ was their seed. Therefore also in writing the epistle to the Galatians he says, "But to
               Abraham were the promises made and to his seed; for he saith not 'and to seeds' as to many, but,
               as to one, 'and to thy seed', which is Christ"<note type="footnote" n="968">Galatians iii,
                  16.</note>. In order to carry out the accomplishment of those promises therefore Christ came,
               and truly to endure <pb n="366"/> circumcision in the flesh, and to carry out the dispensation
               that consists in this; for the whole principle of the dispensation is dispensation and service;
               and so he caught all the nations by faith in him and made them Abraham's sons. Since therefore
               the God-inspired Scripture says that he was circumcised in reality, who is he who presumes to
               say that he did not undergo circumcision? a thing which those who teach the phantasy<note
                  type="footnote" n="969" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">φαντασία</foreign>.</note> seek
               to deny along with the other things. Because nothing is written about the portion of himself
               that was cut off (I refer to the foreskin), we will not therefore refrain from confessing that
               he was circumcised in reality, he who said, "For so it becometh us to fulfil all justice"<note
                  type="footnote" n="970" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew iii, 15.</note>, and was in everything made like
               unto us except sin<note type="footnote" n="971" resp="#ebrooks">Hebrews ii, 17; IV, 15.</note>.
               Perhaps indeed some God-befitting miracle was performed with regard to the portion that was cut
               off, which Scripture left unknown to us; and for us to guess about unknown matters is a thing of
               great danger<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >κίνδυνος</foreign></note>. But what <pb n="367"/> is assuredly already known is this, that,
               when he rose from the dead, he took that also, inasmuch as it is a portion of the whole body,
               and he preserved it with this without corruption according to ineffable methods which he
               understands. For we also shall receive our own body complete at the resurrection, not carrying
               the diminution caused by sores or other injuries, but whole and perfect. It is a good thing to
               ask the impious men, who think that by such questions they frighten those who believe rightly,
               so as to reduce us not to acknowledge<note type="footnote" n="972" resp="#ebrooks">A.v. (K) 'and
                  they will be caught not acknowledging'.</note> that our Lord suffered real sufferings in the
               body, what they themselves say about the blood which came out from the pure rib mixed with
               water. Did it reach the earth? For this also is <pb n="368"/> not declared by the holy Scripture
               of the gospel. But let them themselves be frightened by the fear of loss; and it is consistent
               for them to say that the blood was poured, out in semblance only, and did not flow in reality.
               But John, who became bishop of Constantinople and was a preacher of the true dispensation with
               boldness<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >παρρησία</foreign>.</note>, in the homily entitled 'Concerning the cross and concerning the
               robber, and concerning the fact that we should frequently pray for enemies' was not frightened
               by the fear of these impious men, but said that the blood dropped upon the earth and purified
               the whole of it, inasmuch as he wrote thus: "But why is he slaughtered at the height of the
               tree, and not under a roof? In order to purify the nature of the air, therefore it is done high
               up, without a roof above him, but heaven. For <pb n="369"/> the air was purified by the sheep
               being sacrificed high up. But the earth also was purified; for the blood dropped from the rib
               upon it"<note type="footnote" n="973" resp="#ebrooks">Ed. Par. 2a, II. 477.</note>. Accordingly
               therefore, if on this analogy the foreskin that was cut off touched the earth, it assuredly also
               sanctified it, and by methods which he himself understands who was voluntarily circumcised, he
               assuredly, as I said before, preserved it; and at the time of the Resurrection he rose with the
               whole body complete and without corruption, having this portion also undiminished, although he
               showed the scars of the nails and the lance; with which he will also appear to those who pierced
               him, according to the unerring words of the God-inspired Scripture<note type="footnote" n="974"
                  resp="#ebrooks"> John, xix, 37.</note>. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
