<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3122">To Caesaria the Hypatissa</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">213 [383]-229 [399]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="99">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE SAME FROM THE 57th LETTER OF THE 4th BOOK OF THOSE
               WRITTEN AFTER EXILE, WHICH WAS ADDRESSED TO CAESARIA THE HYPATISSA<note type="footnote" n="1040"
                  resp="#ebrooks">In the heading of the fragment in U 110vb (p. 394) it is called the 16th letter
                  to Caesaria.</note>. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0538">519-38</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> "But in the fourth watch of the night Jesus came to them walking on the sea"<note
               type="footnote" n="1041" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. xiv, 25.</note>. Know therefore that it is the
               custom in a city for the sake of <pb n="384"/> precaution against housebreakers and thieves, as
               well as in military camps for the sake of precaution against an attack upon them by their
               enemies, to keep ward by night and watch in turns; and some watch during the first portion of
               the night, and go round the city or the camp, and some during the second portion and some during
               the<note type="footnote" n="1042" resp="#ebrooks">Ms. om.</note> third, and others during the
               fourth, and others at the very appearance of dawn, those who follow in succession coming in in
               order after the previous ones are tired. And this is recorded even in the Old Testament<note
                  type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">διαθήκη</foreign>.</note> Scriptures
               also. When Gideon was ordered to attack a city by night, I mean the camp of the Midianites, the
               divine Scripture said: "And Gideon went in and the 100 men who were with him into a part of the
               camp when they had begun the middle watch, when those who set the guards had just set them, and
               they sounded the horns"<note type="footnote" n="1043">Jud. VII, 19.</note>. And in the 2nd book
               of Ezra, when the walls of Jerusalem were being built, and the barbarians who lived near the
               country wished to assail them and stop the work, it is written thus: "And I prayed to our God,
               and we set guards over us day and night against them"; and again, "At that time I said to the
               <pb n="385"/> people, 'Every man with his slave shall go up and down in the midst of Jerusalem,
               and let us take night for the first watch, and day for the work'"<note type="footnote"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Neh. XIV (IV), 9, 22.</note>. Accordingly therefore the evangelist desired to
               signify the very time of night at which Jesus, who is God appeared to his disciples when
               distressed in the boat walking on the sea<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">The sentence is
                  published in Greek in Cramer, Cat. in Matth. et Marc., p. 118.</note>.</p>
            <p><supplied reason="ellipsis" resp="#compiler">(<emph rend="ital">And after other things.</emph>)</supplied></p>
            <p>But that which is written in the divine gospels about the cloak<note type="footnote"
               resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">χλαμύς</foreign>.</note> with which the Romans at the
               time of the Passion and of the voluntary saving Cross sought to clothe our Lord and God Jesus
               Christ, and indeed did actually clothe him, for the purpose of mockery contains no discrepancy,
               because Matthew related as follows: "And, when they had stripped him, they put on him a cloak of
               scarlet"<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. XXVII, 28.</note>, and Mark, "And they
               clothe him in purple robes"<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">Mark XV, 17.</note>, and John,
               "And they covered him with a purple garment"<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">John XIX,
                  2.</note>. You should understand that the rascally company of soldiers<note type="footnote"
                     resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">στρατιῶται</foreign>.</note>, by way of prolonging the
               mockery and ridicule and derision for him, first clothed him with the cloak<note type="footnote"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">χλαμύς</foreign>.</note> of scarlet, that is red, and
               after this with the purple one, <pb n="386"/> thinking by the change of attire<note
                  type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">σχῆμα</foreign>.</note> to increase the
               mockery. That they did this for the sake of mockery is plainly signified by the story told by
               Luke also, for he said that, when Pilate learned that Jesus was from Galilee, he sent him to
               Herod, on the ground that the supremacy and authority was by right his, and he was glad to see
               him; and when he did not hear any word from him, or see any sign done by him, but found him
               silent, 'having set him at naught' (he says) 'with his soldiers and made fun of him, having clad
               him in splendid robes, sent him to Pilate'<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">Luke XXIII.
                  11.</note>. But, if one considers the matter carefully and minutely, one may say that there is
               one cloak<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">χλαμύς</foreign>.</note>,
               of purple, but of purple which contains some inferior dark tincture, so that it disavows the
               true purple, and changes its appearance to one that is redder, and appears to hold a position
               approximating to both colours, and to be each of them, and in strictness is neither of them.'
               Accordingly the evangelists looked one at the one colour and the other at the other, so as to
               mention each of them both with the same meaning and in different terms. Since it was the purpose
               of those blasphemers against God to pile up the whole mass <pb n="387"/> of insult and increase
               the mockery, for this reason they found even the very dress which, as they thought, would excite
               much mockery; but the mystery contained in it which was hidden was shown by each of the colours,
               in order that the purple colour might show the King of kings and Lord and God, who was of his
               own will coming to the Passion, while the scarlet and red showed the fact that he himself took
               the whole of our sin, so that he was clad in the crimson cloak of blood, and nailed this to the
               saving Gross. For he suffered who knows not sin, not on his own behalf (may we never say this!),
               but rather on behalf of our sins. This therefore John also the ambassador said: "Behold! the
               Lamb of God who beareth the sin of the world"<note type="footnote" n="1044" resp="#ebrooks"
                  >1044. 1. John, i, 29.</note>. And Peter the chief of the apostles wrote in his epistle: "He
               took up our own sins in his body on to the tree, in order that being separated from the sins we
               may live in righteousness"<note type="footnote" n="1045" resp="#ebrooks">1 Pet. ii, 24.</note>.
               And the wise Paul wrote to the Corinthians about God and the Father, who wishes with him that he
               should suffer for for the sake of the salvation of the race of all men: "Him who knew not sin he
               made sin for our sake, that we in him may become righteousness unto God"<note type="footnote"
                  n="1046" resp="#ebrooks">2 Cor. V, 21.</note>. </p>
            <pb n="388"/>
            <p>For there is also another further question which you ask, as to how we should understand the
               statement made by Gregory the Theologian in the 2nd peace-making homily about the Holy Trinity
               in the following words: "A perfect Trinity of three perfect ones, Unity having been moved on
               account of wealthiness, while duality was passed over on account of the material and the form of
               which bodies consist, and a Trinity was fixed on account of perfection, for it first passes the
               composition of a duality, in order that the Godhead may not remain narrow, nor be diffused into
               infinitude; for the one is mean, and the other disorderly, and the one is utterly Jewish, and
               the other heathen and polytheistic"<note type="footnote" n="1047" resp="#ebrooks">Or. xxiii,
                  8.</note>. This abominable notion must therefore first be removed from our mind, that we should
               not<note type="footnote" n="1048">Sic all versions.</note> think that the Father first existed
               in his own sole hypostasis, and was moved as if by some <pb n="389"/> afterthought to put forth
               another hypostasis, that of the Son, and similarly further conceived the thought of putting
               forth a third hypostasis also from himself, that of the Spirit, in order that he might exist in
               a Trinity. On this theory it will result that the Son and the Holy Spirit are not ever-existing
               but were afterwards added to the Father, and we shall give occasion for the blasphemy of Arius
               who says, "There was once when the Son and the Holy Spirit were not". But this is abominable;
               for one who was acquired later and came into being afterwards is not God; for the Holy Trinity
               is of equal everlastingness, and it is therefore understood and acknowledged to be one God truly
               in three hypostases. The words used by the doctor we should therefore understand in the same way
               as that which is stated in Wisdom, "From the greatness and beauty of created things the causer
               of their birth <pb n="390"/> is inferentially seen"<note type="footnote" n="1049"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Sap., XIII, 5.</note>; and from formed creation and this visible world we may
               conceive not only of the wisdom and power of him who created them, but also of the very
               peerlessless of his Godhead in regard of creation, and its distance in all points and lack of
               similarity. We see that all the bodies which make up the world are composed of material<note
                  type="footnote" n="1050" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὕλη</foreign>.</note> and
               form, and arise from a duality; but what material<note type="footnote" n="1050" resp="#ebrooks"
                  ><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὕλη</foreign>.</note> and form are we will state in the form of an
               example. For instance the potter's material<note type="footnote" n="1050" resp="#ebrooks"
                  ><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὕλη</foreign>.</note> for the craft is the clay, but he adds the form
               to the material<note type="footnote" n="1050" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >ὕλη</foreign>.</note>, that is to say, that which belongs to the fashioning of the vessel
               that is being manufactured, a jar or a pot or anything of the kind. But in this case the potter
               is the maker of the form only, and he borrows the material<note type="footnote" n="1050"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὕλη</foreign>.</note>. But God, the Maker of all and
               perfect in craftsmanship, both brought the material<note type="footnote" n="1050"
                  resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὕλη</foreign>.</note> of every body from that which did
               not exist and added the form; and, if you speak of fire or of earth, or <pb n="391"/> of
               air<note type="footnote" n="1051" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀήρ</foreign>.</note>
               or of water, or of the sky and the sun and the moon and the other stars, he both formed the
               material<note type="footnote" n="1052"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὕλη</foreign>.</note> of all of
               them out of non-existent things, and the form was devised for them in different ways at the
               moment that they came into being, and he is both the Maker and the adorner of the shapeless
               material<note type="footnote" n="1052" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >ὕλη</foreign>.</note> of the bodies, in that he differentiated it into the various forms of
               the bodies. And this Wisdom also states, when it declares concerning Pharaoh and the Egyptians,
               who were vexed by the serpent and the vile reptile: "For neither was thine almighty hand, which
               created the world out of shapeless material, at a loss to send against them either a multitude
               of wolves or fierce lions"<note type="footnote" n="1053" resp="#ebrooks">Sap., XI, 17.</note>.
               Therefore our mind, seeing that the bodies in this tangible world consist as we have said of
               material<note type="footnote" n="1052" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >ὕλη</foreign>.</note> and form, <pb n="392"/> and that they arise from a duality, and being
               instructed by the sacred Scriptures that there is one Godhead in a Trinity, wonders and is
               amazed at the profoundness of the theology<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">θεολογία</foreign>.</note>, since it sees a corresponding fact in creation, and
               is as it were initiated into a mystery and learns from creation the inaccessibility of the
               Trinity and its lack of likeness to and community with creation, and reflects in itself and
               says: The reason then<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >ἄρα</foreign>.</note> why the Godhead does not exist in one hypostasis is that it may not be
               inferior to the bodies, falling short in the restriction of number. And it does not again exist
               in a duality, because it shuns similarity to the bodies, which arise from a duality, but it only
               appears in a Trinity and as plural, which is admirable; for in the Trinity is completed the
               unique number which follows two. Therefore also, when Moses said to him, "Show me thyself, let
               me see thee plainly", he refused this, saying, "Thou wilt not be able to see my face, for a man
               shall not see my face and live"; but he added, "Thou shalt see my back parts, <pb n="393"/> but
               my face shall not be seen by thee"<note type="footnote" n="1054" resp="#ebrooks">Ex. XXXIII,
                  18-23.</note>; signifying that by the very essence<note type="footnote" n="1055"><foreign
                     xml:lang="grc">οὐσία</foreign>.</note> and by the sight, as one may say, of the face no man
               can comprehend God, but from his back parts a man shall know the things that pertain to him. out
               his back parts are created things which came into being afterwards, through which he is
               inferentially seen as the causer of their birth, as our father the Theologian himself also said
               in the 2nd theological homily: "These are God's back parts, all things which, being after him,
               make him known, like the shadows and reflexions of the. sun upon waters, which show the sun to
               weak eyes, because they cannot look at it, since by the purity of the light <pb n="394"/> it
               overcomes the perception"<note type="footnote" n="1056" resp="#ebrooks">Or. Theol. ii,
                  3.</note>. And therefore in the passage now before us for interpretation he applied the
               expression 'movement of the Unity towards a duality' to the everlasting birth of the Son from
               the Father, and 'passing over of the duality' to the procession of the Holy Spirit which is
               timeless and thereby without beginning, and by means of the words used as we have said he gave a
               philosophical<note type="footnote" n="1057" resp="#ebrooks">The word <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >φιλοσοφῆσαι</foreign> is here included.</note> explanation in mysterious and divine fashion
               of the lack of community in the Trinity towards bodies which exist in a duality. The passage
               contained in the homily entitled 'of Lights' which says, "But where there is purification there
               is shining, and shining is the completion of love, to those who desire things that are great, or
               that which <pb n="395"/> is great, or beyond what is great"<note type="footnote" n="1058"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Or. xxxix, 8.</note>, is plain and contains nothing difficult of comprehension.
               What he said is, "Where there is purification of the soul by means of virtues, there is the
               shining of knowledge, which raises and uplifts to the satisfaction of divine love". But the
               satisfaction of love is the end of things delightful and pleasing, which is God, who exists and
               is made known in things that are great, and in that which is. great, and beyond that which is
               great; in things that are great in the three hypostases which are equal in power and of which
               none is in anything inferior to the others in power and in equality in all things, except that
               they are distinct in the matter of non-generation and generation and procession, in the
               unconfused individualities which stamp each of the hypostases; in that which is great, <pb
                  n="396"/> because he is one and the same and because of the Unity of the Godhead; and beyond
               that which is great, because he is not limited by size and quantity. For, in. that we employ the
               poverty of names that exists among us, we name God great, when he is more than great. Therefore
               also the Psalmist said: "Great is the Lord and very admirable; and there is no end to his
               greatness"<note type="footnote" n="1059" resp="#ebrooks">Ps. CXLIV, 3.</note>. For all
               greatness is limited, but the Godhead cannot be limited, and is not limited by any boundary.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
