<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3131">To Caesaria the Hypatissa</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">229 [399]-246 [416]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="100">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE SAME FROM THE 3rd LETTER OF THE 6th BOOK OF THOSE AFTER
               EXILE, WHICH WAS ADDRESSED TO THE GLORIOUS CAESARIA. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0533">519-33</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> You say therefore that it has been discovered by certain persons concerning Balaam the
               soothsayer and seer and propitiator of falsely-named gods that it is testified by the divine
               words that he had such power in his mouth <pb n="400"/> that those whom he blessed were
               bles'sed, and those on the contrary whom he cursed were cursed. For this reason therefore the
               man who bore such a character was then lifted up to bless Israel also the holy people, the
               people which was named God's people; for you say that the same men who discovered this plainly
               produce these words. And at this I am not surprised; for it is the peculiarity of those who
               repeat the contents of divine Scripture cursorily and as it were from hearing, and not from
               learning and accurate knowledge, to arrive at false and erring notions. Where did the divine
               Scripture testify of the reprobate Balaam, as they said, that he had such a power? Moses who
               wrote these things, being inspired<note type="footnote" n="1060" resp="#ebrooks">Ms. om.</note>
               by the very excellent Spirit and being a minister of the truth, neither gave this testimony as
               in his own person, nor said of God that he gave any such testimony concerning Balaam, but
               recorded that Balak, King of the Moabites, being a demon-worshipper and a slave of foul fiends,
               thought of Balaam the soothsayer that he could curse and bless authoritatively and not in a
               worthless manner. And it is a simple thing to listen to the divine Scriptures manifestly
               proclaiming this: "And Balak son of Zippor, King of Moab, was at that time, and he sent <pb
                  n="401"/> ambassadors to Balaam son of Beor the interpreter of dreams, who was on the
               river-land of the sons of his people, to call him. saying. 'Lo! a people hath come out of Egypt,
               and lo! they have covered the face of the land, and this people hath encamped round me. And now
               come, curse me this people, because this people is stronger than we, in case we may be able to
               overthrow some of them, and cast them out of the land; because I know that they whom thou
               blessest are blessed, and they whom thcu cursest are cursed'"<note type="footnote" n="1061"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Num. xxii, 4-6.</note>. Since therefore Balak and the Moabites who were under
               subjection to him, and the Midianites their neighbours, who were barbarians, held this belief,
               God 'who wisheth that all men should live and come to the knowledge of the truth'<note
                  type="footnote" n="1062" resp="#ebrooks">1 Timothy ii, 4. </note> according to the apostle's
               saying, instructing our race, hard as it is to turn, by many various methods, first showed his
               power with which none can contend, and displayed the kings round about them, Sihon, King of the
               Amorites, and Og, King of Bashan, who were giants, and trusted to their strength, and were eager
               to engage in battle, and met Israel in warlike guise, slain with the sword and dead together
               with their followers; and <pb n="402"/> afterwards, when the same Balak, prince, of the
               Moabites, as we have said, perceived the feebleness of his own power, and feared lest he also
               should become the prey of the Israelite sword, and had recourse to the power of the
               falsely-named gods, and thought that by means of the soothsayer's curse he was escaping from his
               troubles, the wisdom that is higher than all understanding instructed the barbarian by the
               instrumentality of the very soothsayer himself in whom he trusted that there is no other god
               beside him, and that by the very demons and the very soothsayers who serve them witness is borne
               that he alone is true God. For it is his habit to convert those who are in error to the truth by
               the very paths of the error. And this we do not say out of our imagination, but because we learn
               it from Scripture itself. It is recorded in the first book of Kingdoms that the Philistines who
               dwelt in Ascalon and Gaza and the neighbouring cities took arms against Israel and won a great
               victory over them in combat, insomuch that together with the rest of the spoil they took the ark
               of God also and placed it in the sanctuaries and shrines of the idols, and every city to which
               they carried it was smitten with the disease of emerods for which there was no cure, and the
               land produced a multitude of mice, and they [deliberated]<note type="footnote" n="1063"
                  resp="#ebrooks">This is the sense required.</note> and took counsel <pb n="403"/> what they
               could do to escape from such distresses, and, having called upon the soothsayers, who were
               accustomed to instigate their actions by making use of the deceit of demons, they begged them to
               find a means of release from these calamities, and those men proposed to them the following
               plan; to bring cows that were first-born<note type="footnote" n="1064" resp="#ebrooks">1 Samuel
                  VI, 7. <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρωτοτοκούσας</foreign>.</note> and were unaccustomed to the
               yoke, and to yoke these to a new cart bearing the ark and golden figures of the emerods and of
               the mice, equal in number to the cities that had been smitten with a plague of this kind, and
               upon this to shut up the calves that had been born in one house, that, if their mothers went on
               drawing the cart to the land of Judah, where the ark was previously placed, they might know that
               the God of Israel had laid the plagues upon them as a punishment, but, if hey turned towards the
               cry of the calves and were affected in accordance with their own natural instincts, they might
               learn that it was not on account of Israel that the punishment came upon them, but they happened
               as men to suffer these things. And, when these things had been thus stated, those cows as if
               very forcibly driven by the command of God, went of their own <pb n="404"/> accord to the land
               of Judah and brought the ark with the propitiatory offerings, though it was not those words of
               the soothsayers that were able to do these things, but God himself acted according to their
               words, and by means of the soothsaying to which they were accustomed and which they loved led
               the Philistines who were in error to the knowledge of the truth. So too Nebuchadnezzar also had
               future things revealed to him beforehand by an ordinary vision seen in dreams, in order that by
               Daniel's wise interpretation concerning the things seen in the dream the Babylonians might know
               what the God of the Hebrews was; and Nebuchadnezzar must not on this account be placed among
               religious men, as neither must the soothsayers who advised the Philistines to adopt the
               above-mentioned plan; for even they themselves also could if they wished on the strength of such
               signs have recognised God and not remained in error. For neither did God bring such things about
               for any other purpose, condescending as he did at times to men who were not in the perfect
               state, except that every man might be saved, because he is indeed the Creator of all. The
               prophesyings and workings of miracles are not under all circumstances performed by men who are
               worthy, but perhaps by men who are unworthy also for their own profit, because they are <pb
                  n="405"/> barbarians, and cannot be brought to religion by teaching or by any other similar
               method. This same thing our Lord and God Jesus Christ also said in the gospel: "Many shall say
               in that day, 'Our Lord,] our Lord, did we not in [thy] name prophesy, and in [thy] name cast out
               demons, and in thy name do many mighty works?' and then will I profess unto them, ' I never knew
               you, depart ye from me, workers of iniquity'"<note type="footnote" n="1065" resp="#ebrooks"
                  >Matthew vii, 22, 23.</note>. And Caiphas, being president and ruler of the assembly of the Jews
               that contended with God, those who crucified our Lord, said prophetically that he should be
               crucified for the people; and this John the Evangelist who was indeed the Theologian described
               as follows: "But one of them, Caiaphas, who was the high-priest of that year, said to them, 'Ye
               know nothing, and do not consider that it is expedient for us that one man die for the people,
               and the whole people perish not'. But this he said not of himself, but, because he was the
               high-priest of that year, he prophesied that Jesus should die for the people, and not for the
               people only, but also that he might gather into one the sons of God who were scattered"<note
                  type="footnote" n="1066" resp="#ebrooks">John XI, 49-52.</note>. Accordingly therefore neither
               <pb n="406"/> Caiaphas nor Balaam are<note type="footnote" n="1067" resp="#ebrooks">Sic
                  Syr.</note> religious men, but actually blasphemers and contenders against God, and remained in
               the snares of impiety, although God, In order to show the truth, and in order to convert those
               who were in error, made use of their words.</p>
            <p><supplied reason="ellipsis" resp="#compiler">(<emph rend="ital">And after other things.</emph>)</supplied>
               The citations which we have made from the testimonies of the divine Scriptures are in themselves
               sufficient; but I will show by means of a few instances that the genuine doctors of the church
               also have taught us to think and say these things. The very wise John who became bishop of
               Constantinople in the 6th homily of the commentary on the Gospel of Matthew, when he was
               speaking about the Magi who by seeing the star were led to know our Lord and God Jesus, who was
               in swaddling-clothes and was being nurtured on milk from his mother's breast in the flesh,
               teaches as follows: "And wherefore did he attract them by such a sight? But how should he have
               done so? Should he have sent prophets? but the Magi would not have submitted to the prophets.
               But should he have emitted a voice from on high? but they would not have regarded this. But
               should he have sent an angel? but him also they would accordingly have <pb n="407"/> neglected.
               But on this account God, having set all these methods aside, calls them by means of things to
               which they are accustomed, condescending greatly, and showing them a great and peculiar star, in
               order by means of the size and the beauty of the appearance to make them astonished, and by the
               method of movement. Imitating these things, Paul spoke to the heathen from the starting-point of
               an altar, and cites testimonies from the poets, and he spoke with the Jews from the
               starting-point of circumcision, and with those who lived according to the law he took the
               beginning of teaching from sacrifices. For, since each man loves that to which he is accustomed,
               both God and also the men who were sent by him for the salvation of the world used facts in this
               way. Do not therefore think it an unworthy thing that he called them by means of a star; since,
               if it is so, you will find fault with all the practices of the Jews also, their sacrifices and
               their cleansings, and the beginnings of the months and the ark and the temple itself. For these
               things also received their origin from heathen denseness. But nevertheless God for the sake of
               the salvation of those who had gone astray consented to be worshipped by means of the very
               things by which the demons outside were worshipped, changing them himself a little, in order
               [that] he might <pb n="408"/> remove them gradually from the custom [and] bring them to the high
               philosophy; a thing which he also does to the Magi, in that he consented to call them by means
               of the appearance of the star, in order to make them thereafter higher. Since therefore he
               brought and led them, and set them by the manger, he did not again thereafter speak with them
               through a star, but through an angel, and so they gradually became better. The same thing he did
               also to the men of Ascalon and Gaza. For these five cities also, since after the coming of the
               ark they had been smitten with a regular plague, and found no escape from the plagues laid upon
               them, having called the soothsayers and held an assembly, wished to find a release from the
               plague which came from God. But the soothsayers said that they should yoke unbroken and
               firstborn<note type="footnote" n="1068" resp="#ebrooks">Jo. Chrys. <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >πρωτοτοκούσας</foreign>. </note> cows to the ark and let them go, no man leading them; 'for
               so it will be plain whether the plague is from God, or from some chance or disease. For, if'
               (they say) 'they either from inexperience break the yoke, or return to the calves when they low,
               it is a chance or an accident that has happened. But, if they walk straight, and are in no way
               affected by the lowing of their young, or by the ignorance of their error<note type="footnote"
                  n="1069" resp="#ebrooks">The translator seems to have read <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                     >πλάνης</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">πλανηθῶσι</foreign>.</note>
               <pb n="409"/> in the way, it is very plain that it is God's hand that has touched these cities'.
               Since therefore, after the soothsayers had said these things, those who dwelt in these cities
               obeyed, and did as they commanded, God also followed the counsel of the soothsayers, again
               condescending, and it did not seem to him to be a thing unworthy of him to carry into effect the
               thing stated beforehand by the soothsayers, and make them appear to be truthful men in what they
               spoke at that time. For indeed the success obtained was a great thing, that the adversaries
               themselves should bear witness to the power of God, and their own teachers themselves should
               pronounce a decision concerning him. And many other such things one may see that God performs by
               dispensation"<note type="footnote" n="1070" resp="#ebrooks">In Matthew Hom. vi, 3 (ed. Par. 2a,
                  VII, 105).</note>. And in the 24th homily of the same work, where he is expounding the passage
               which we ourselves mentioned above, which says, "Many shall say to me on that day, 'Our Lord,
               our Lord, did we not in thy name prophesy, and in thy name cast out demons, and in thy name do
               many mighty works?' And then he will profess unto them, 'I never knew you. Depart ye from me, ye
               who work iniquity'", he gave the same teaching in the following form: "Who therefore are these?"
               (he says). <pb n="410"/> "Many of those who believed received gifts, as was<note type="footnote"
                  n="1071" resp="#ebrooks">Sic Syr. and Jo. Chrys.</note> the man who was casting out demons and
               was not with him; as was<note type="footnote" n="1071" resp="#ebrooks"> Sic Syr. and Jo.
                  Chrys.</note> Judas, for even he also, being an evil man, had gifts. And in the Old Testament
               one will accordingly find that the grace often worked in men who were unworthy, in order to
               benefit others. For, since all had not readiness for all things, but some were pure in life, but
               had not an equal amount of faith, while others were in the converse position, he both entices
               the former by means of the latter in order that they may show great faith, and calls the latter
               by means of this incomprehensible grace to become virtuous. Wherefore also he used to gave the
               grace with great abundance, for '"We did many mighty works". But then will I profess unto them
               "I know you not". For now they think they are my friends, but then they will know that I did not
               give as to friends'. And why are you surprised if he gave his graces to men who had believed in
               him but had not a life consonant to the faith, when he is in fact found to work even in men who
               have fallen from both? For Balaam was an alien both to faith and to life; but nevertheless the
               grace was effected in him for <pb n="411"/> the sake of influencing others. And Pharaoh
               likewise; but nevertheless to him also as well he showed the future. And Nebuchadnezzar was a
               great transgressor of the law; and to him again he revealed things that should happen later
               after many generations. And to his son again who surpassed his father in transgression of the
               law he showed the future, in that he brought wonderful and great things to pass. Since therefore
               at that time also the proclamation was at its beginning, and it very was desirable that a
               display of its power should be made, many even among the unworthy also received gifts. But
               nevertheless those men gained nothing from these signs, but are even judged all the more.
               Wherefore also he said to them those terrible words, 'I never knew you'. For many he already
               hates even here, and before the judgment turns away from them"<note type="footnote" n="1072"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Op. Cit., xxxv, l, 2 (ed. Par. 2a, VII, 340).</note>. By means of all these
               things therefore he clearly establishes the fact that Balaam also and Nebuchadnezzar, and
               Belteshazzar the latter's son, and all such men, did not profit by the grace of God, in that
               they remained in the snares of demon-worship, but even endure the decrees of the sentences of
               tortures all the more.<pb n="412"/><supplied reason="ellipsis" resp="#compiler">(<emph rend="ital">And
                  after other things.</emph>)</supplied> But, as to the tunic of God our Saviour Jesus, on which those
               who performed the crucifixion cast lots, your mightiness' love of God should know that we should
               understand the statement exactly according to the letter. In Palestine it is the custom for men
               to make such tunics as are divided in the middle and not woven together throughout, but contain
               the sections of the texture separately; so that even now we may see many such tunics, made of
               wool and linen, in the city of Gaza; since afterwards, when it is about to be put on, and is
               skilfully and becomingly folded, that division is concealed by the tailors. But some<note
                  type="footnote" n="1073" resp="#ebrooks"> (V) 'all'.</note> of those who are of low station
               have it all woven together from beginning to end, and these they <pb n="413"/> describe
               according to custom as being woven from the top to the bottom, since there is no division in
               them. But this indicates also a mystery which shows<note type="footnote" n="1074"
                  resp="#ebrooks">A.v. (E) 'is further also shown by the mystery which appears in it'.</note>
               that the Only Word who was born below in flesh is above from God and the Father. Since every
               human soul has a body like some garment which springs up with it, as is said by Job the man of
               mighty endurance to God: "With skin and flesh hast thou clothed me, and with bones and sinews
               hast thou strengthened me"<note type="footnote" n="1075" resp="#ebrooks">Job, x, 11.</note>, so
               also our Saviour's body, if one conceives of it as a kind of tunic that sprang up at the same
               time, because it was united to the Word invariably by a natural union, was woven from the top,
               that is by the coming of the Holy Spirit, and not by human seed. That these things are so the
               genuine doctors of the holy church also show; for it is good that <pb n="414"/> we confirm every
               statement and opinion by the expressions used by these. John who became bishop of Constantinople
               in the 85th homily of the commentary on the Gospel of John wrote as follows: "But do you, I
               pray, observe the prophet's accuracy; for the prophet did not say only that they divided, but
               also that they did not divide. Some things they divided, but the tunic they did not divide, but
               also committed the matter to lot. But the expression 'woven from the top' is not added casually;
               but some say that by means of this expression one thing is indicated in place of another,
               because he who was crucified was not mere man, but had also the Godhead from above; while others
               say that the evangelist is depicting the actual pattern of the tunic, for, since in Palestine
               they join two pieces of material together and so weave garments, John signifies that the tunic
               was not<note type="footnote" n="1076" resp="#ebrooks">The negative, required by the sense, is
                  not in the Greek.</note> of this kind, in that he says that it was woven from the top. And this
               it seems to me that he says by way of signifying the meanness of the garments, and, as in all
               other things, so also in raiment he followed a simple form"<note type="footnote" n="1077"
                  resp="#ebrooks">In Jo. Hom. LXXXV, 1, 2 (ed. Par. 2a VIII, 576).</note>. And Athanasius the
               great in the homily on the Cross says these things: "Together with these things <pb n="415"/> he
               put on also an unsewn tunic that was woven from the top throughout, that from this also the Jews
               might be able to believe who and whence he is who put on these things; that the Word is not from
               the earth, but that he came from above, and he is not one divided, but is without division from
               the Father; because, when he became man, he had not a body that was sewn together from a man and
               a woman, but one that was woven from a virgin alone by the Spirit's workmanship"<note
                  type="footnote" n="1078" resp="#ebrooks">De Pass. et Cruc., 21 (P. G., XXVIII,
                  221).</note>.</p>
            <p><supplied reason="ellipsis" resp="#compiler">(<emph rend="ital">And after other things.</emph>)</supplied>
               But, as to the passage about the sweat and the drops of blood, know that in the divine and
               evangelical Scriptures that are at Alexandria it is not written. Wherefore also the holy Cyril
               in the 12th of the books written by him on behalf of the religion of the Christians against the
               impious demon-worshipper Julian plainly stated as follows: "But, since he said that the divine
               Luke inserted among his own words the statement that an angel stood and strengthened Jesus, and
               his sweat dripped like blood-drops or blood, let him learn from us that we have found nothing of
               this kind inserted in Luke's work, unless perhaps<note type="footnote" n="1079" resp="#ebrooks"
                  ><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἂρα</foreign>.</note> an interpolation has been made <pb n="416"/>
               from outside which is not genuine. The books therefore that are among us contain nothing
               whatever of this kind; and I therefore think it madness for us to say anything to him about
               these things; and it is a superfluous thing to oppose him on things that are not stated at all,
               and we shall be condemned to be laughed at and that very justly"<note type="footnote" n="1080"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Not elsewhere extant, and not among the fragments published by Neumann.</note>.
               In the books therefore that are at Antioch and in other countries it is written<note
                  type="footnote" n="1081" resp="#ebrooks">Luke xxii, 43,44. </note>, and some of the fathers
               mention it; among whom Gregory the Theologian made mention of this same passage in the 2nd
               homily on the Son<note type="footnote" n="1082">Or. Theol. iv, 16.</note>; and John bishop of
               Constantinople in the exposition composed by him about the passage, "My Father if possible let
               this cup pass from me"<note type="footnote" n="1083" resp="#ebrooks">In Matthew Hom. i.xxxm, 1
                  (ed. Par. 2a VII, 893).</note>. And I myself therefore in the 64th homily showed the religious
               meaning of the things thus brought about<note type="footnote" n="1084" resp="#ebrooks">P. O.,
                  VIII, 317 ff.</note>, according to the limited power that has been given to me from above.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
