<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3227">To Caesaria the Hypatissa</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">246 [416]-252 [422]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc><correspAction type="sent"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName></correspAction><correspAction type="received"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName></correspAction></correspDesc></profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="101">
            <head type="number">CI.</head>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE SAME FROM THE LETTER TO CAESARIA THE HYPATISSA.</head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0538">519-38</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> But the Lord, when after the Resurrection he breathed upon the disciples <pb n="417"/> and
               said, "Receive the Holy Spirit"<note type="footnote" n="1085" resp="#ebrooks">John xx.
                  22.</note>, (since you ask this question also besides), gave them a beginning only of the gifts
               of the Spirit, and, as one may say, one kind among the many gifts of the Spirit which Paul
               enumerated in writing to the Corinthians<note type="footnote" n="1086" resp="#ebrooks">I Cor.
                  xii, 7-10.</note>, I mean that of binding and loosing men's sins. This was signified by the
               addition, in that that Giver of the gifts of the Spirit said, "If ye forgive any men's sins they
               shall be forgiven to-them; and if ye bind any men's sins they shall be bound"<note
                  type="footnote" n="1087" resp="#ebrooks">John xx, 23.</note>. And by means of the breathing he
               taught them in very mysterious fashion that he is himself the Creator of Adam, whom he formed
               out of earth and into whose face he breathed the Spirit of life, and that he made man 'a living
               soul' as it is written<note type="footnote" n="1088" resp="#ebrooks">Gen. ii, 7.</note>, shining
               in the spiritual image and the beauty that flashes from it, and sharing in the divine likeness.
               And by breathing into the disciples he majestically shows that the Holy Spirit himself is of his
               essence<note type="footnote" n="1089" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >οὐσία</foreign>.</note> and not alien.</p>
            <p>And in addition to that you ask this other question, how then we are able to explain how it is
               that our Lord Christ does not speak falsely who says, "As Jonah was three days and three nights
               in the fish's belly, so shall the Son of man be three days and three nights in the heart of the
               <pb n="418"/> earth<note type="footnote" n="1090" resp="#ebrooks">Ms. om.</note>"<note
                  type="footnote" n="1091" resp="#ebrooks">Matth. XII, 40.</note>. Some say that we are to reckon
               the time from the very evening of the 5th day of the week when our Saviour supped with the
               disciples, and instituted the new Passover, causing the old to cease, since it was from that
               time that our Lord was virtually sacrificed of his own accord on our behalf, and went down into
               the lower parts of the earth, and they say that the one night and the six hours of the
               preparation should be reckoned as one day and night, and the darkness from the 6th hour to the
               9th and the light from the 9th hour till sunset as the 2nd day and night, so that
               consequentially the following night and the sabbath-day make up the whole of the 3rd day and
               night, and in this way it is to be believed that our Lord rose after three days and nights. But
               others<note type="footnote" n="1092" resp="#ebrooks">Dionysius of Alexandria; see Conybeare in
                  Journ. Theol. Stud., XV, 440.</note> have appeared to give another elucidation upon the
               question<note type="footnote" n="1093" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >θεωρία</foreign>.</note> before us, which is subtle and very accurate. They said that
               according to the custom and tradition contained in Scripture every day with the night preceding
               it are<note type="footnote" n="1094" resp="#ebrooks">Sic Syr.</note> combined into one entity.
               Thus in Exodus, when Moses was giving orders about the Passover and about the feast of
               unleavened bread, he said, "When the 14th day of the 1st month beginneth, ye <pb n="419"/> shall
               eat unleavened bread from the evening"<note type="footnote" n="1095" resp="#ebrooks">Ex. XII,
                  18.</note>, and he counted the beginning of the following day from the preceding evening: and
               the cessation of the sabbath he instituted the same way, so that they were to cease from work on
               the preceding night and the following day; and the Jews are known to observe this down to this
               day, and to honour not the night after the sabbath but the night before the sabbath by cessation
               and- abstention from work; and we ourselves on the Ist day of the week honour the preceding
               night as united with the honoured day, and not the night following. Accordingly therefore they
               say that every night-and-day is as one may say one entity, and, what therefore anyone does
               during one of these 24 hours, that act is said to have been performed on the whole of that day.
               As for instance, when a man is sent on a long journey and returns to his own country or city
               either on the 2nd or on the 3rd day of the week, this man entered the city during one hour or a
               small portion of an hour, but everyone says, "So-and-so arrived on the 2nd day of the week" or
               "on the 3rd", and they reckon the whole day which is one with the preceding night to his
               arrival. <pb n="420"/> And therefore, they say, we should on this principle regard the period of
               the three days' burial, and the descent of our God and Saviour who became incarnate into Sheol,
               as beginning from the time when he truly entered the heart of the earth; and that he did after
               he gave up his spirit, saying, "My Father, into thy hands I commit my spirit"<note
                  type="footnote" n="1096" resp="#ebrooks">Luke xxiii, 46.</note>, and then his spirit departed,
               and thus, though he was united in a perfect union, the soul and the body were separated from one
               another, and through the burial of the body he does away corruption in graves, and through the
               soul he is seen in the lower parts' of the earth, and he released those who were bound in
               graves. Then it was therefore that he entered the heart of the earth, when 'he went down', as
               Paul says, 'to the lower parts of the earth'<note type="footnote" n="1097" resp="#ebrooks">Eph.
                  iv, 9.</note>, that is to the lowest limits and to the gloomy crowns (?)<note type="footnote"
                     n="1098" resp="#ebrooks">This word is probably corrupt.</note> in the earth; From the departure
               of the spirit therefore the three day-and-nights are to be counted; and the departure took place
               at the 9th hour of the preparation, when three hours of the day remained. Since therefore the
               preparation is according to the custom handed down in Scripture united with the preceding night,
               we reckon that our Lord spent the whole of the day and the night of the preparation in the heart
               of the earth, and then after sunset the sabbath begins and its <pb n="421"/> night, the day
               which the Jews honour by a cessation; and the whole of this together with the following day
               which is joined to it our Lord spent in the lower parts of the earth. But, when the sabbath had
               gone by, and had been completed by the, setting of the sun, then began the night of the 1st day
               of the week; and the night again and the day following it are to be reckoned in order according
               to that same custom of Scripture, and our Lord will be found to have risen from the place of the
               dead on the 3rd day-and-night, that of the 1st day of the week; for in fact one who passed the
               beginning of a day-and-night in the heart of the earth is to be reckoned as having spent the
               whole of that day-and-night there. For this reason they say that Christ spent the preparation in
               the lower parts of the earth as regards the last portion of the day-and-night, and the 1st day
               of the week as regards the first portion, and the sabbath entirely through all the #twenty-four#
               hours, keeping the day of the Jews' feast in mourning, that thereby also he might fulfil the
               prophecy spoken through the prophet Amos, which threatens the Jews and says, "I will turn your
               feasts into mourning, and all your songs into wailing"<note type="footnote" n="1099"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Amos, viii, 10.</note>. But those men say also that the three hours' darkness
               which took place is reckoned to be a night, and this is forced; for this darkness is not a
               night, <pb n="422"/> but an affliction of day; and they say that they are prevented from holding
               anything of the kind by the prophecy of Zechariah also, who prophesies about that day as
               follows: "On that day there shall be no light, and cold and frost shall be one day, and that day
               shall be known to the Lord, neither day nor night, and towards evening there shall be
               light"<note type="footnote" n="1100" resp="#ebrooks">Zech. xiv, 6, 7.</note>. See! the prophet
               plainly says, "On that day there shall be no light", and, having first plainly named the
               darkness, he prevented such an affliction and the light which rose afterwards from being
               reckoned a night and a day by saying "neither day nor night"; and this he says plainly, in order
               that no one may reckon this a day and a night. As to the statement, "Cold and frost shall be one
               day", it is not unreasonable for us to understand it to mean that there was actually sensible
               cold and frost on that day; and supra-sensually that, because at a certain time fiery fervour
               had grown cold among the Jews, the grace of the Holy Spirit ceased to work among them<note
                  type="footnote" n="1101" resp="#ebrooks">Ms. om.</note>. This also besides we should know, that
               our Lord in the gospels sometimes said that he was destined to rise on the 3rd day, and
               sometimes that he would rise after three days, the expression signifying that even the beginning
               of the 3rd day is reckoned a whole day. <pb n="423"/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
