<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3233">To Thomas, Bishop of Germanicea</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">260 [430]-264 [434]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/"></persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="107">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">OF THE HOLY SEVERUS PATRIARCH OF ANTIOCH AS TO WHAT THINGS THE
               SOUL WILL ENCOUNTER. (To Thomas, bishop of Germanicea)<note type="footnote" n="1120"
                  resp="#ebrooks">In G M the heading is "Of the holy S. from the letter to Th., bishop of
                  Germanicea, who asked him about some passages from the epistle of Jude". For Thomas see Mansi,
                  VIII, 817; Mich., p. 267.</note>. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="38(?)">519-38(?)</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> For we have already said that those who became founders of these evil heresies find fault
               with the Old Testament<note type="footnote" n="1121" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign xml:lang="grc"
                  >διαθήκη</foreign>.</note>, and put forward the New, some adding to it, others mutilating it;
               men whom the apostle Jude accuses through the words stated as men who speak (?)<note
                  type="footnote" n="1122" resp="#ebrooks"> Conjectural correction of a corrupt text</note> great
               swollen words of railing, which he also called their shame which comes after<note
                  type="footnote" n="1123" resp="#ebrooks">Or. 'accuses'; see p. 57, 1.9.</note> it. But Michael
               the archangel who was then contending with the devil, when he was speaking about Moses' body,
               did not dare to bring a railing accusation, but said, "The Lord rebuke thee"<note
                  type="footnote" n="1124" resp="#ebrooks">Jude 9, 13, 16.</note>, which seems to me to convey
               the following meaning. The law which was given through Moses showed all the things that relate
               to the cleansing of the soul and its justification <pb n="431"/> by means of bodily types and
               indications. Such is the fact that it passes judgment upon the body of a leper as unclean, and
               similarly also upon a man with an issue; for God does not exact punishment for involuntary
               afflictions, but by means of these things annuls the stain of sin which is diverse and hard to
               wash away, by which the soul is in divers manners stained. After this pattern therefore he
               judges it pollution that the man should be dissipated on pleasures who begets fruits for the
               benefit of the rational and intelligent soul<note type="footnote" n="1125" resp="#ebrooks">The
                  following to 'day' (p. 433, 1. 2) is published in Greek in Cramer, Cat. in Epp. Cath., p.
                  161ff.</note>; and here therefore God further showed by a bodily type a certain mystery that
               happens to the soul. Since, when the soul is separated from the body after the release from this
               world, the angelic and good hosts and a company of evil demons meet it, in order that, according
               to the quality of the deeds which it has performed bad or good, either the one or the other may
               convey it to the proper regions to be kept till the last day, on which, we shall all rise,
               either to judgment<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἶς κρίσιν
                  πάντες παραστησόμεθα. κ</foreign>.</note> or to eternal life, or shall be brought to the
               unending flame of the fire, therefore, because God wished <pb n="432"/> to show this to the sons
               of Israel by some bodily type, he caused the burial of Moses to appear before their eyes at the
               time of the swathing<note type="footnote" n="1126" resp="#ebrooks">Mss. 'hiding.'; Gr.
                  πέριστολην.</note> of the body and at: the customary deposition in the earth, as if the evil
               demon were opposing and, Michael the good angel were, acting contrary to him, who met him<note
                  type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀντιπράττοντα κ. τούτῳ τὸν Μ.
                     ἀγαθὸν ἄγγελον ὄντα προσυπαντῆσαι</foreign>.</note> and drove him away, and did not
               authoritatively rebuke him, but yielded the judgment against that demon to the Lord of all, and
               said, "The Lord rebuke thee", that by means of these things those who are being instructed may
               learn that that the soul has a contest after the release from this world, and that we must by
               means of good deeds pre'pare ourselves in order that angelic help may come to us when the demons
               gnash their teeth enviously and bitterly at us. And, when this sight had appeared before the
               eyes, then there fell in that place a ray of light of a cloud<note type="footnote"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">νεφέλην ἢ φωτὸς ἔκλαμψιν γεγενῆσθα</foreign>.
               </note> that darkened and obstructed the sight of those who were standing on this side and that,
               that no man might know his grave. Therefore the Holy Scripture says in Deuteronomy also: "Moses
               the Lord's bondman ended his life there, in the land of Moab, by the word of the Lord; and they
               buried him there in <pb n="433"/> the land of Moab beside the house of Peor, and no man hath
               known the end or his grave to this day"<note type="footnote" n="1127">Deuteronomy xxxiv, 5, 6.</note>;
               which is also confirmed by that which the evangelist wrote<note type="footnote" n="1128"
                  resp="#ebrooks">This is the best emendation of a corrupt passage that I can make, but I do not
                  see the relevance of the citation. </note>, since Luke one of the evangelists said in the story
               of the rich man and Lazarus, "And it happened that the poor man also died, and was carried by
               the angels into Abraham's bosom"<note type="footnote" n="1129" resp="#ebrooks"> Luke, xvi,
                  22.</note>. These same details labout the burial of Moses men have stated to be contained in an
               apocrypha Book the more succinct title of which is 'The book of Generation or of Creation, which
               Moses himself wrote for us'<note type="footnote" n="1130" resp="#ebrooks">The story was told in
                  the Assumptio MosIsaiah (ed. Charles. p. 106), but the title seems rather to refer to the Book of
                  Jubilees or Parva Genesis, in the present text of which it is not found. The rest is in Cramer,
                  p. 162, headed: <foreign xml:lang="grc">Καὶ μετ᾽ ὀλίγα</foreign>.</note>. And to us this seems
               to be the interpretation of what he propounded, so that I thus understand it. But some have said
               that Jude calls the law itself the body of Moses; and, when he came down to show this to the
               sons of Israel, the devil opposed, and he worked in opposition retarding the gift of the law,
               and contending and saying, "The people does not deserve this to be done for them"; and therefore
               Michael went before him and drove away him who opposed, uttering the rebuke, "The Lord rebuke
               thee". And others <pb n="434"/> again: "He calls the people whom he was leading the body of
               Moses; and he meant<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks">Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">σῶμα τοῦ Μ.
                  ὃν ἐδημαγώγει λαὸν ἀπεκάλεσαν κ. εἶπον</foreign>.</note> that, when they were leaving the land
               of Egypt, the devil opposed and resisted, as if he were saying in contention with Moses, "His
               body (which is the people) does not deserve deliverance from Egypt to be given to it". And this
               devil when he was opposing Michael put in bonds, and he reproved him<note type="footnote"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Gr. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁ Μ. ἀπεῖρξε κ. ἀντιπραττόμενον
                     ἔπαυσε</foreign>.</note> saying, "The Lord rebuke thee".</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
