<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3241">To Caesaria the Hypatissa</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Original transcription and HTML encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person">Roger Pearse</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription correction and TEI encoding performed by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="a" type="supplied">Letters LXII to CXVII</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     A Collection of Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
                     , from Numerous Syriac Manuscripts
                  </title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/677</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1919-1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>2 fasc</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">II</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <!--  What should we use for the title?  -->
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="m">Tomus Decimus Quartus</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/680</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Firmin-Didot et cie</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/863">Paris</pubPlace>
                     <date>1920</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="fasc">I</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="page">284 [454]-290 [460]</biblScope><!-- FILL IN CORRECT PAGES -->
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/509">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>R.</forename>
                        <surname>Graffin</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/652">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>F.</forename>
                        <surname>Nau</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title xml:lang="la" level="s">Patrologia Orientalis</title>
                  <biblScope unit="tomus">14</biblScope>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <editor>Roger Pierce</editor>
               <ptr target="http://tertullian.org/fathers/severus_coll_2_letters.htm"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      <correspDesc>
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</persName>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2620">Caesaria</persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="117">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the Same Holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName>, From the Hypomestika to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2620">Caesaria</persName> the
               Hypatissa, From the 1st Book From the 20th Hypomnestikon<note type="footnote" n="1178"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Cf. ep. 55. The 1st book perh. means the Ist book of letters after episcopacy;
                  otherwise we must suppose an inordinate number of hypomnestika.</note>, Speaking About the
               Departed. </head>
            <dateline resp="#ebrooks">
               <date notBefore="0519" notAfter="0538">519-38</date>
            </dateline>
            <p> But they are conscious of services and prayers, and especially those that are made over the
               bloodless sacrifice on behalf of their life; and assuredly <pb n="455"/> some consolation
               results to them in proportion to the measure of each man's character. And they are conscious too
               of alms given to the poor on their behalf; for they also are a rational sacrifice as <persName>Paul</persName>
               teaches this and says, "To give alms and to impart forget not; for such sacrifices please
               God"<note type="footnote" n="1179" resp="#ebrooks">Hebrews xiii, 16.</note>. For that those who
               have fallen asleep in <persName>Christ</persName> are conscious of these things the ritual also which was handed down
               to the churches from of old by the apostles and from the beginning to the present day clearly
               witnesses; for the deacon makes proclamation to those who are standing while the bloodless
               sacrifice is being offered that they are to make supplication on behalf of those who have fallen
               asleep, and on behalf of those on whose behalf they are making commemorations and alms. But it
               is not lawful for us to say that any of the things enjoined in the holy churches is useless or
               vain.</p>
            <p>Of the same holy <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus</persName>, from the same 20th hypomnestikon.</p>
            <p>From the God-inspired Scripture we learn that in the resurrection both the just shall see the
               just and the sinners the sinners; but the just also <pb n="456"/> shall see the sinners who have
               conducted themselves in a manner opposite to their own being sent to the endless torments, and
               the sinners also shall gaze from afar at the righteous who have been injured by them enjoying
               pleasures. And this is a kind of punishment which they will bear in addition to their torments
               in the pains, that of being tormented by remorse, and then they will know from what good things
               they have fallen. These things the Lord taught us in the gospel as in an image and type
               delineated beforehand, by means of the parable of <persName>Lazarus</persName> and the rich man. <persName>Lazarus</persName>, having been
               justified by endurance in the distresses of poverty, was known by righteous <persName>Abraham</persName>, and was
               resting in his bosom; and the rich man also when judgment was being exacted from him for his
               sins, and his mercilessness towards <persName>Lazarus</persName>, while he was in the flame that is not quenched,
               from afar saw and knew <persName>Lazarus</persName>. This the Book of Wisdom also shows, in that it clearly depicts
               the wicked as knowing on the day of judgment the just who have been set at naught and evil
               entreated by them; and it speaks thus: "And they shall come to perception of their sins in fear;
               and their iniquity shall stand up against them and reprove them. Then shall the just man stand
               up with great boldness against the face of those who afflicted him and spurned his labour. They
               shall see <pb n="457"/> and be troubled with sore fear, and they shall be amazed at the
               greatness of his salvation. And repenting in their soul they shall say, and in affliction of
               spirit they shall groan and say, 'This was he who was then to us fools for a derision and a
               parable and a reproach. His life we counted folly, and his death contemptible. How is it that he
               hath been counted among the sons of God and his inheritance is with the saints? Did we then err
               from the way of truth, and did the light of justice not shine upon us?'"<note type="footnote"
                  n="1180">Sap., iv, 20; v. 6.</note> Lo! therefore they of whom we speak, who were friends to
               one another with the evil friendship that is of perdition, on the last day at the judgment shall
               recognise one another, and the just man, whom in this world they senselessly set at naught and
               derided, they shall see to have been counted among the sons of God and to be receiving
               inheritance with the saints; and so thereafter they shall be separated, the one party to the
               outer darkness as it is written<note type="footnote" n="1181" resp="#ebrooks">Matthew viii, 12;
                  xxii, 13; xxv, 30.</note>, or to the fire that is not quenched, or to the gnashing of teeth and
               to the weeping and to the worm that undyingly torments, and to judgments that are sent in such
               forms, and the other to the blessed abodes in the kingdom of heaven. For the words "Let the
               wicked man be taken away that he see not the glory of the Lord"<note type="footnote" n="1182"
                  resp="#ebrooks">Isaiah XXXVI, 10.</note> are spoken with this meaning, that he shall not <pb
                     n="458"/> share in the glory of the Lord that is given to his just ones. Though<note
                        type="footnote" n="1183">Marg. 'Very apt interpretation'.</note> they shall not come lo
               judgment nor stand before the judgment-seat<note type="footnote" resp="#ebrooks"><foreign
                  xml:lang="grc">βῆμα</foreign>.</note> of <persName>Christ</persName> according to what is stated by the psalmist:
               "Therefore the wicked shall not stand in judgment"<note type="footnote" n="1184" resp="#ebrooks">Psalm i, 5.</note>, yet still they will be aware what glory the just are enjoying, and of what
               they themselves have been deprived on account of their unbelief, in order that they may be
               tormented by this also. That it is the custom of Scripture to use the expression 'see' in place
               of 'share' or 'have experience' is made known by that which is stated by <persName>David</persName> also, "May the
               Lord bless thee out of <placeName>Zion</placeName>, and mayest thou look upon the good things of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>"<note
                  type="footnote" n="1185" resp="#ebrooks">Psalm cxxvii, 5.</note>. And <persName>Ezekiel</persName> the prophet shows
               that the grievous tyrants of the different peoples and the soldiers with them, who did evil with
               one another and armed themselves in sins, shall also be together in the eternal torments; for he
               said, "There is <placeName>Assyria</placeName>, and all his concourse"; and again, "There is <persName>Elam</persName> and all his host";
               and further on, "There were given <persName>Moshach</persName> and <persName>Thubel</persName>, and all their host"<note type="footnote"
                  n="1186">Ezekiel xxxii, 22, 24, 26.</note>. But that those who have lived uprightly will know those
               whom they love in the future life Isaiah <pb n="459"/> the prophet clearly cries, in that he
               terms them deer, inasmuch as by means of their struggles against passions they trampled upon
               serpents and scorpions, and upon all the power of the the adversary (for a deer is a
               serpent-slaying animal); for he said thus: "There the does met one another, and saw one
               another's face. They passed over in number and none of them perished. They sought not one
               another, because the Lord commanded them, and his spirit gathered them"<note type="footnote"
                  n="1187" resp="#ebrooks">Isaiah xxxi, 15, 16.</note>. And kinsmen shall know kinsmen, as the
               sacred Scripture teaches us, saying of <persName>Abraham</persName> and <persName>Isaac</persName> and <persName>Jacob</persName> who died, in one place, "he
               was added to his fathers", in another, "he was added to his kin", and again, "he was added to
               his people"<note type="footnote" n="1188" resp="#ebrooks">Genesis xxv, 8 (the best mss. have
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">λαόν</foreign>); xxxv, 29; XLIX, 33.</note>. And <persName>David</persName> the wise, who
               as a prophet was initiated in and saw the future hope beforehand, when he had buried his son,
               bathed and anointed himself, and changed his garments, and set out a table, saying, "Wherefore
               do I fast? Shall I be able to bring him back any more? I shall go to him, but he himself will
               not return to me"<note type="footnote" n="1189" resp="#ebrooks">2 Samuel XII, 23.</note>. He would
               not suddenly have been converted from that mournful sorrow to such great cheerfulness unless he
               had been assured that he should see the boy again living in the resurrection. The <pb n="460"/>
               doctors of the church, weaving words of consolation from these and similar thoughts and from
               scriptural indications, persuaded fathers and mothers who were mourning beyond measure that in
               the resurrection they would see and receive their children who had died, and in like manner
               kinsmen and friends.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
