<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of a Question and Answer</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
               target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_19">
               https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_19 </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- This work is mis-numbered in the body text of the print edition. The number here is based on the table of contents. -->
         <head>Chapter 19: Of the Question which <persName>a certain Brother</persName> brought to him, and its
            Answer</head>
         <p><persName>Rabbâ</persName> was on one occasion asked by a certain brother, who said, <quote>Why is it that, before
            the coming of that devil who vexeth us, we possess the understanding of the mind in a
            healthy state, and are able to make use of philosophy for the sake of self-denial, and
            humility, and the other virtues, but that when it cometh to us to make manifest in very
            deed the virtues of philosophy, that is to say, longsuffering in the hour of wrath, and
            the keeping of the temper in the season of anger, and a frame of mind from which
            vainglory is absent, and when there are praises [ascribed to us], and many other things
            which are akin thereto, the mind (or understanding) languisheth and becometh
            destroyed?</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>Rabbâ</persName> answered and said unto him, <quote>It is because we are not perfectly skilled in the
            performance [of these things], and because we are not so thoroughly acquainted with all
            the mind and vague thoughts of the devils that we are able, through the power of the
            sight of the soul, to recognize in quiet contemplation the advent of him who causeth us
            vexation, and who watcheth that he may be able to gather together the outpouring of
            suchlike thoughts. Therefore, every day and every hour it is the portion of the soul to
            watch, and we must pour out upon it, like oil, the fear of God, that is to say, the
            efficacious performance of work, and the lamp which will enable us to see the things
            which are falling upon us in the healing of the mind. Whosoever then will not be
            strenuous [will come] to anger, and wrath, and ill-temper, and to each of the passions
            which lead us on to wickedness. And the soul will see, and will depart to that
            incorporeal country, and it will make the mind to hold in contempt the things which are
            wrought by the devils, and will compel it to trample under foot serpents and scorpions,
            and all the power of the Enemy.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
