<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Pachomius and the Phantom</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_14"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_14
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 14: Of <persName>the Phantom</persName> which they saw by Night when they were going through the
            Monastery</head>
         <p>And it came to pass once when <persName>Rabbâ</persName>, and <persName>Theodore</persName> whom he loved, were walking through
            the monastery by night, that they saw suddenly a great phantom, which was full of the
            deepest deceit; now that which appeared was in the form of a woman, and its beauty was
            of so indescribable a character that no man was able to tell the beauty, or the form, or
            the appearance, which belonged to that phantom, and even <persName>Theodore</persName>, who looked at that
            phantom, was exceedingly perturbed, and his face changed colour. And when the blessed
            man saw that he was afraid, he said unto him, <quote>Be of good cheer in the Lord, O <persName>Theodore</persName>,
            and fear not,</quote> and the holy man, having said these things unto him, commanded him to
            pray with him, that the phantom which was striking wonder into them might be driven
            away. And as they were praying the phantom came nearer and nearer and took a solid form,
            and when it, and the company of devils which ran before it, drew nigh, for their prayer
            did not drive it back, it came forward and said unto them, <quote>Why do ye labour in vain? Ye
            are unable at this present to do anything whatsoever against me, for I have received
            power from God, Who sustaineth the universe, to tempt whomsoever I please; and I have
            abundance of time in which to do this, for this I have asked from God.</quote></p>
         <p>Then <persName>Pachomius</persName> asked her, saying, <quote>Whence comest thou? And whom dost thou wish to
            tempt?</quote> And the phantom answered and said, <quote>I am the daughter of the <persName>Calumniator</persName>, whose
            great power cannot be described, and unto me the whole company of the devils is subject.
            It was I who brought down the holy stars to the earth, and it was I who snatched <persName>Judas</persName>
            from the Apostolic power. I have received authority [or power] to make war against thee,
            O <persName>Pachomius</persName>, for I am not able to endure the reproach of the devils, and no man hath
            made me as weak as thou. Thou hast made me to be trampled under foot by youths, and by
            old men, and by <pb n="304"/>young men, and thou hast gathered together against me a congregation
            such as thou hast, and hast set for them [as] a wall which shall never fall the fear of
            God, so that my ministers are not able to approach with boldness and freedom unto anyone
            of you. Now all these things have happened unto me because of the Word of God Who was
            made man, for it is He Who hath given you power to trample upon all our might, and to
            hold us in derision.</quote></p>
         <p>And when the holy man <persName>Pachomius</persName> asked her, <quote>Hast thou come to tempt me alone according
            to what thou sayest?</quote> she said unto him, <quote>I have come to tempt thee, and all those who
            are like thee.</quote> <persName>Pachomius</persName> said unto her, <quote>So then thou wilt tempt <persName>Theodore</persName> also?</quote> And
            she said, <quote>I have received power over thee, and over <persName>Theodore</persName>, but I am never able to
            come nigh unto thee.</quote> And when <persName>Pachomius</persName> had said unto her, <quote>Why?</quote> she said unto them,
            <quote>If I were to make war with you [two], you would have an occasion for help and not for
            injury, and especially would it be so in thy case, O <persName>Pachomius</persName>, who with the eyes of thy
            body art worthy to be a spectator of the glory of God; but ye will not live for ever for
            those for whom at present ye make yourselves a wall through your prayers, and whom ye
            help; and the time will come after your death when I shall have dominion over those whom
            thou now protectest against me, for ye have made me to be trodden under foot by this
            multitude of monks.</quote></p>
         <p>Then <persName>Rabbâ</persName> said unto her, <quote>How knowest thou that those who shall come after us will not
            serve the Lord more truly than do we, and that they will not be able to confirm and
            strengthen those who come after us in the fear of God more than do we?</quote> And the phantom
            said unto him, <quote>I do know this.</quote> And <persName>Rabbâ</persName> said unto her, <quote>Thou liest by thy wicked
            head, because thou hast no knowledge whatsoever beforehand of the things which are going
            to take place, for unto God alone belongeth fore-knowledge; thou art then the chief of
            falsehood.</quote> And the phantom answered and said unto him, <quote>True, I have no knowledge
            whatsoever of anything by [the faculty] of fore-knowledge, even as thou sayest, for it
            belongeth to God alone to know what is going to happen beforehand, but I told thee that
            I had knowledge because [I judged] by analogy.</quote> And the blessed man said unto her, <quote>How
            canst thou judge by analogy?</quote> And she said unto him, <quote>By the things which have already
            taken place I am able to judge of what will take place in the future.</quote> Then <persName>Rabbâ</persName> said
            unto her, <quote>How?</quote> And she said unto him, <quote>I know that the beginning of every matter is in
            love and knowledge, and it receiveth <pb n="305"/>confirmation from the things which are provided,
            and especially through the divine care and the calling of heaven, and by the Will of God
            it becometh confirmed by wonderful things and signs, and it is confirmed also by various
            powers which are exercised therein; but when that beginning waxeth old and becometh
            grey, it falleth away from growth, and when growth hath fallen away [i.e., ceased], it
            perisheth of old age, or languisheth through sickness, or decayeth through neglect.</quote></p>
         <p>And afterwards <persName>Rabbâ</persName> asked her, saying, <quote>Why hast thou come, according as thou sayest,
            to tempt these great [saints] and not all the brethren? If it be as thou sayest, the
            destruction of souls resteth with thee to work, and thou surpassest in power all the
            devils, and thou must have all this power so that thou mightest be able to strive
            against men like these.</quote> And the phantom answered and said unto him, <quote>I have already
             told thee that when the strength of the Sustainer of creation, the <persName>Redeemer Christ</persName>,
            appeared upon the earth, we were brought so low that, like a sparrow, we were mocked and
            laughed at by men such as these who are clothed with the Spirit, and who seek to learn
            the Lord; but although we have become feeble through Him, we do not cease to work as
            much as we possibly can [against you], and we never cease from opposing you by every
            means in our power. And we sow the seed of our wickedness near the soul of him that
            striveth with us, and this we do especially when we see that he receiveth [it], and if
            we see that he really permitteth us to embrace him, then do we inflame him with fierce
            lusts, and we encompass him like mighty ones and cruel devils, whom it is exceedingly
            difficult to defeat. But if he is not willing to receive our seed, and will not, through
            his faith in God, and the watchfulness of his mind, accept with pleasure the things
            which are offered unto him by us, we dissolve away even as smoke is dissipated in the
            air. This is the reason why I am not permitted to wage war with all the monks, and I do
            not do so because all possess not perfection. For if it were permitted to me to wage war
            against them all, I should be enabled to lead astray many of those who lean upon
            thee.</quote></p>
         <p>And the blessed man said unto her, <quote>Fie upon your wickedness which never sleepeth! Ye
            will never cease to stir yourselves up against the race of the children of men until the
            divine and unpolluted grace of God descendeth from heaven and destroyeth you.</quote> Then,
            having said these things, <persName>Rabbâ</persName> commanded the phantom to depart unto the place whither
            it had been commanded to go, and never again to approach with her feet his monastery.
            <pb n="306"/>And when the morning was come, he cried out unto all the great brethren, and related
            unto them all the things which he had seen and heard from the destroying devils, and
            unto the other brethren who were living in the other great monasteries he sent letters,
            and informed them, in the fear of God, by means of these concerning the vision [which he
            had seen].</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
