<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Sylvanus the Actor</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_2"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_2
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 2: Of <persName>Sylvanus the Actor</persName></head>
         <p>Once there was a man among the brethren whose name was <persName>Sylvanus</persName>, who for a period of
            twenty years had worn the garb of a monk; now he was originally an actor, and at the
            beginning of his life as a monk he was exceedingly anxious about his soul, but after a
            short time had elapsed he began to be so negligent about his redemption, that he wanted
            to make merry and to enjoy himself, and besides <pb n="284"/>this he used to sing fearlessly among
            the brethren snatches or the lewd and ribald songs which he used to hear in the theatre.
            Then Abbâ <persName>Pachomius</persName>, the holy man, called this brother before the brethren, and
            commanded him to strip off the garb of a monk, and having received such apparel as was
            worn in the world, to go forth from among the brethren and from the monastery. And that
            brother fell down at the feet of <persName>Pachomius</persName> and entreated him, saying, <quote>O father, if thou
            wilt forgive me this once, and wilt not cast me forth, thou hast it from me that from
            this time forward I will repent of those things wherein I have hitherto shown
            negligence, in such a manner that thou shalt be able to see the change which hath taken
            place in my soul.</quote></p>
         <p>And the holy man answered and said unto him, <quote>Dost thou know how much I have borne from
            thee, and how many times I have admonished thee, and how many times I have beaten thee?
            I am a man who hath no wish to stretch out my hands in a matter of this kind, because
            when, of necessity, I was obliged to act thus in respect of thee, [my] soul suffered far
            more by the mention of association with passion than thou didst, although the stripes
            were laid upon thee. I beat thee for the sake of thy salvation in God, so that by that
            means I might be able to correct thee of thy folly; but since, even though I admonished
            thee, thou didst not change [thy course of life], and didst not follow after spiritual
            excellence, even though I entreated thee so to do, and since even when beaten thou wast
            not afraid, how is it possible for me to forgive thee any more?</quote></p>
         <p>But when <persName>Sylvanus</persName> multiplied his entreaties, and begged for his forgiveness long and
            earnestly, and promised that he would amend his life henceforward, <persName>Rabbâ</persName> demanded a
            surety from him that after he was forgiven he would no more continue his evil behaviour;
            and when the venerable man <persName>Petronius</persName> had made himself a surety for him concerning the
            things which <persName>Sylvanus</persName> had promised the blessed man forgave him. Then <persName>Sylvanus</persName>, having
            been held worthy of forgiveness, contended with all his soul, and to such good purpose,
            that he became the pattern of all excellence of the fear of God, both among all the
            younger and all the elder brethren. Now the virtue which surpassed all the other virtues
            which he possessed was that of absolute humility, and tears flowed from his eyes so
            unceasingly that even when he was eating with the brethren he was not able to restrain
            his weeping, and his tears were mingled with his food. And when the brethren told him
            that he should not behave thus before the face of strangers (i.e., visitors), or before
            any people, he took an oath, saying, <quote>I have sought <pb n="285"/>many times to restrain [my] tears
            for this reason, but I have never been able [to do so].</quote> Then the brethren said, <quote>Is it
            not possible for him that repenteth to seek to be alone? And would it not be better for
            him to act thus when he was praying with the brethren than when he was eating at the
            table with them? And is it not possible for the soul to weep continually with tears
            other than those which are visible?</quote> [Then turning to him, they said,] <quote>We wish to know
            what thou hast to say on the matter. For thou art so overwhelmed with [thy] tears that
            many of us who see thee in this state are ashamed to eat and take our fill.</quote></p>
         <p>Then <persName>Sylvanus</persName> said unto those who had asked him [those questions], <quote>Do ye not wish me to
            weep when I see holy men waiting upon me, men, the dust of whose feet I am unworthy [to
            sweep away]? Is it not proper that I should weep over myself? I weep then, O my
            brethren, because a man from the theatre is ministered unto by such holy men as these,
            and I am afraid lest I be smitten even as were <persName>Dathan</persName> and <persName>Abiram</persName>. And I weep especially
            because, being in ignorance, I cared so little at the beginning about the redemption (or
            salvation) of my soul, that I came in danger of being expelled by the brethren from the
            monastery, and I was obliged to give surety [for my better behaviour], and to take awful
            oaths that I would never again treat my life with contempt. For this reason I am not
            ashamed [to weep], and I have turned away from such things; for I know my sins and that
            if I was obliged to deliver up my soul I should find no happiness [in heaven].</quote></p>
         <p>And as this man strove nobly in this manner <persName>Rabbâ</persName> himself bore testimony before all the
            brethren, and spake thus: <quote>Behold, I bear testimony before God that, from the time when
            this monastery came into existence, among all the brethren who have lived with me
            therein, there hath been none who hath resembled completely the example [which I have
            conceived in my mind] with the exception of one.</quote> Now when the brethren heard these
            things some of them thought that the one man of whom he spake was <persName>Theodore</persName>, and others
            thought he was <persName>Petronius</persName>, and others thought he was <persName>Arsenius</persName>, and at length <persName>Theodore</persName>
            asked the holy man of which monk he had spoken when he said this thing; but <persName>Rabbâ</persName> did
            not wish to say. But because <persName>Theodore</persName> and the other great fathers continued to entreat
            him [to tell them], for they wished to learn who he was, <persName>Rabbâ</persName> answered and said, <quote>If I
            knew that vainglory would come to him of whom I am about to speak, and that he would be
            greatly praised, I would not shew [you] who he is; but, because I know that the more he
            is praised, the <pb n="286"/>more humble he will become, and the more he will think scorn of himself,
            and because [I wish] you to emulate his example, I will, before you all, fearlessly
            ascribe blessing to him. Thou, O <persName>Theodore</persName>, and all those, who like thee, strive in the
            fight, have bound the <persName>Calumniator</persName> with fetters like a kid of the goats, and have placed
            him under your feet, and daily ye trample upon him as ye trample upon dust; but if ye
            are the least unmindful of yourselves, the <persName>Calumniator</persName>, who hath been cast under your
            feet, will rise up again, and will set himself against you like an armed man. But this
            young man <persName>Sylvanus</persName>, who but a short time since was about to be expelled from the
            monastery, hath, by his strenuousness, so completely subjugated the <persName>Calumniator</persName>, and
            slain him, that he will never again be able to approach him, for he hath vanquished him
            utterly by his exceedingly great humility. Ye have humbled yourselves as if ye possessed
            works of righteousness, and the addition which ye would make to your spiritual
            excellence is reduced, for ye rely upon the things which have already been performed by
            you; but this young man, however much he striveth, never sheweth himself to the gaze [of
            his fellows], and he thinketh with all his mind and soul that he is a useless and
            contemptible being. And tears are always nigh unto him because he is always belittling
            himself, and because he saith that he is unworthy of the things which are visible. Ye,
            in your knowledge, and in your patient endurance, and in your strivings against the
            <persName>Calumniator</persName>, which cannot be measured, are better than he is, but he hath surpassed you
            in humility, because he, in this manner, cutteth off for the <persName>Calumniator</persName> nothing but
            humility, and the power of action which ariseth from the whole soul.</quote> Now therefore when
            <persName>Sylvanus</persName> had striven in this manner for eight years, he completed his fight, and laid
            down his life in such wise that his servant, a mighty man of God, testified concerning
            his departure, and said that an endless throng of holy angels, with great rejoicing and
            singing, received his soul as a choice sacrifice, and that they offered it up unto God
            like the marvellous incense which is found among the children of men.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
