<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of a Sinner who died</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_3"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_3
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 3: Of <persName>a certain Sinner who died</persName></head>
         <p>And it came to pass once that Abbâ <persName>Pachomius</persName> went to another monastery to visit the
            brethren who were there, and as he was on his journey he met the funeral of a certain
            brother of the monastery who was dead, and [the monks] were going to the funeral and
            were singing as they went; and there were also among them the parents of the man <pb n="287"/>who had
            died. Now the brethren saw from a distance the holy man coming towards them, and they
            set down the bier upon the ground so that he might come and pray over him. And when the
            blessed man had come, and had said a prayer, he commanded the brethren not to sing any
            more psalms and hymns over him; and he also commanded them to bring the garments of him
            that had died, and they brought them, and in the presence of them all he ordered the men
            to burn them; then, when they had been burned he commanded that the dead body should be
            taken and buried without any further singing. Then the brethren, and the parents, and
            kinsfolk of him that was dead threw themselves down at his feet and entreated him to
            permit them to sing over him, but he remained unmoved; and the parents of the dead man
            said unto Abbâ <persName>Pachomius</persName>, <quote>What hast thou done, O father? This is a new thing, and thou
            art sending away our son in an unlawful fashion. It befitteth not thy holiness to
            display such a want of compassion unto this dead man, and moreover, this savage cruelty
            is like to bring about sorrow. Even an enemy who seeth the dead body of his adversary
            knoweth how to shew pity many times over, although his disposition be unutterable and
            immovable. We have seen a new sight with you, O Christians, the like of which hath never
            been seen, even among the barbarians. Through this want of compassion [on thy part] thou
            hast made to cling to the family [of the dead man] a disgrace which shall never be
            blotted out. Would that we had never seen thee this day! For then our house, which hath
            ever possessed an untarnished name, would not have inherited disgrace. Would that our
            poor son had never come into thy savage hands! For then he would not have bequeathed
            unto us this everlasting sorrow. We beseech thee now, since thou hast caused even his
            clothes to be burned, to allow a Psalm to be said over him.</quote></p>
         <p>Then Abbâ <persName>Pachomius</persName> answered and said unto them, <quote>O my brethren, in very truth I have
            more compassion upon him that lieth here than ye have, and because, like a father, I am
            shewing exceedingly great care on his behalf, I have commanded these things to be done.
            Ye would take care of the body which is visible, but I strive for his soul [which is
            invisible]; for if ye sing Psalms over him he will receive the greater torments, and a
            reckoning will be demanded from him because of the Psalms which have been sung, for he
            departeth not with the power of the Psalms upon him. If then ye wish to make an addition
            to his everlasting sufferings, sing Psalms; but I tell you, of a truth, that if ye do
            indeed sing Psalms over him, he will certainly suffer more <pb n="288"/>pain because of them, and he
            will curse you. And because I know what will benefit his soul I take no care for his
            dead body whatsoever; for if I permit ye to sing Psalms, I shall be found to be in the
            sight of God as one who [striveth to] please the children of men, because for the sake
            of gratifying men I have treated with contempt that which will benefit the soul which is
            about to be punished in judgement. For because God is a fountain of grace He seeketh
            excuses upon which He can lay hold in order to pour out upon us the abundant streams of
            His grace; if then, we, who have been held to be worthy by God to become acquainted with
            the art of divine healing, do not apply the binding up which is suitable to the wound,
            we shall, like those who despise [God], hear that which is written, <quote>Those who despised
            [God] saw, and marvelled at the wonderful thing, and were destroyed.</quote> For this reason
            then, that is to say, that we may lighten his punishment, I entreat you to bury the dead
            man without any singing of Psalms; for the good God knoweth that in return for this
            slight which hath come upon him, we are giving him rest and are calling him to life. Had
            he listened unto me on the several occasions on which I admonished him, he would never
            have come to this pass.</quote></p>
         <p>And when the blessed man had said these things they carried him to the mountain without
            the singing of Psalms, and he was buried. And the holy man passed several days in that
            monastery in admonishing and teaching each one of the brethren the fear of God, and the
            way to strive rightly against the <persName>Calumniator</persName>, and against his arts, and wiles, and
            guile, and how in a short time, by the might of the Lord, we shall be able to bring to
            naught beforehand the things which are cared for by him.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
