<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Pachomius and the Wheat</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_11"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_111
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 11: Of how, not even in the time of Famine, was Abba Pachomius induced to
            take Wheat for nothing for the use of his Monastery</head>
         <p>When a famine took place in the days of Pachomius, and the brethren had no wheat, that
            is to say, when, so to speak, no wheat could be found in all Egypt, the holy old man
            sent to call one of the brethren that he might go round about in the cities and villages
            and seek for wheat to buy; and he gave him a sum of money for the purchase of the wheat,
            that is to say, one hundred dînârs. And having gone round about in very many places, the
            man who had been entrusted with this work came to a city which is called Armûtîn, and by
            the Providence of God he found there a certain governor of the state, who was an
            exceedingly reverent man and a fearer of God, and who had heard of the rule of the holy
            man Pachomius and of the brethren; now this governor was in charge of the wheat which
            belonged to the community, and the brother approached him, and entreated him to sell him
            wheat to the value of one hundred dînârs. Then the governor said unto him, <quote>Of a truth,
            O my brother, if I had wheat of my own, or even some [belonging to] my own children, I
            would take it and give it to you, for I have heard concerning your godly and spiritual
            rule of life; but hearken unto what I am going to say unto thee. The wheat which hath
            been placed under my charge belongeth to the community, and as it will not be required
            this year by the prefect, if thou wishest to take it I have the power over the wheat of
            the community, and I will keep it back until the time cometh for it to be laid up in the
            granary; and if thou knowest that thou wilt be able to return it by that time, take as
            much of it as thou wishest.</quote></p>
         <p>Then the brother said unto him, <quote>I do not wish thee to act thus for me, for I am unable
            to return so large a quantity as that which I wish to take; but if thou wilt sell me
            wheat to the value of one hundred dînârs, at the price which thou wishest [good and
            well], but if thou art not in any way able to keep back the wheat which belongeth to the
            community until the time [for storing it] in the granary, thou actest rightly [in
            refusing me].</quote> And the governor said unto him, <quote>Yea, I have power to keep back the
            wheat, and not only wheat to the value of one hundred dînârs but, if thou wishest,
            another like quantity. If thou wilt take the wheat thou wilt do me an act of grace, only
            pray for me.</quote> And when the brother said, <quote>We have only this amount of money,</quote> the
            governor hearkened, and said, <quote>Have no care about this matter, for whensoever ye are
            able to bring me the price of the wheat do so, at the rate of [thirteen] ardebs a dînâr,
            and in no other place in Egypt wilt thou obtain more than five ardebs a dînâr.</quote> And the
            brother journeyed by water to the monastery with great joy [bringing the wheat with
            him].</p>
         <p>And when Rabbâ heard that a boat full of wheat was about to arrive, and the manner in
            which it had been bought, he sent immediately to the boat and said, <quote>Ye shall not bring
            one grain of the wheat into the monastery, neither shall he who hath bought the wheat
            come into my presence until he hath returned it to its place; he who hath acted thus
            hath committed great wickedness. And not only this hath he done, but he hath also taken
            wheat to the value of one hundred darics more than [the hundred dînârs which I gave
            him], and I never ordered him to do this; but in carrying out his own desires he wished
            to have a superabundance, and having become inflamed by love of gain he hath brought us
            into subjection and laid us under condemnation. And moreover, he did not approach the
            generosity of the seller of the wheat satisfactorily, for he acted in a greedy manner,
            and he hath brought more wheat than he needed, and on his own responsibility he
            undertook to pay back that which we could never return. And not this only, for supposing
            that from some human cause an accident had happened, and the boat had sunk in the river,
            what could we have done [to make good the loss]? Should we not all have become slaves?
            Therefore let him sell all the wheat which he hath brought to the laity who are in this
            district at the rate at which he hath taken it from him that entrusted it to him, that
            is to say, at thirteen ardebs a dînâr, and after he hath sold them, let him take the
            gold and carry it to him that gave him credit. And with the one hundred dinars which are
            mine, let him buy wheat at the rate at which it is sold everywhere and bring it [to
            me].</quote> And the brother did even as Rabbâ said unto him, and he brought the wheat which he
            bought at a rate of five and a half ardebs a dînâr. And from that time Rabbâ did not
            allow that brother to go outside the monastery on business for the brethren, and having
            made him to remain inside he appointed other brethren to render service of the kind.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
