<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Pachomius and the Wages of the
               Brethren</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_12"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_12
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 12: Of how when the Work of the Brethren was sold Rabba was unwilling even
            that they should accept the full Price of the same</head>
         <p>And that same brother [who hath been mentioned above] took away from the shoemaker to
            sell a large number of shoes (or sandals) and other kinds of objects, and having
            received as their price a larger sum of money than the shoemaker had mentioned brought
            to him the oboli; and when the shoemaker had received the oboli, he reckoned up the
            price of the leather and of the labour of his hands, and the value of the work of the
            days wherein he had made the various kinds of [leather] objects, and found that it
            amounted to fifty oboli, whilst the money [which he had received] was three times that
            amount. Then straightway the shoemaker went to Rabbâ, and said unto him, <quote>Verily, O
            father, this brother will never prosper by such acts as these, for he still hath in him
            a worldly mind.</quote> And when Rabbâ said, <quote>What is this matter in which he hath behaved so
            badly?</quote> the shoemaker answered and said, <quote>I gave him sandals and other kinds of
            [leather] things to sell, and I said unto him, <quote>Their prices are so much,</quote> but he hath
            sold them for a great deal more, and he hath brought unto me a price which is three
            times as large as that which I mentioned to him.</quote> When Rabbâ had heard these things, he
            called the brother and said unto him, <quote>Why hast thou done thus?</quote> And the brother said
            unto him, <quote>Father, I told to the people who bought the sandals and the other things the
            price which this shoemaker told me to take, but they said to me, <quote>Brother, if these
            things had been stolen they would be worth a far higher price than what thou askest</quote>;
            and I, feeling ashamed, said to them, <quote>They have not been stolen, and I have been
            commanded to sell them at the price which I have named; but whatsoever ye wish to give
            [me] for them, that give</quote>; and they gave me what it pleased them to give me, and I never
            counted the oboli which were given unto me by them.</quote> When Rabbâ had heard [these things]
            he said, <quote>Thou hast sinned greatly in loving excess, but run quickly, and give back the
            excess in price to those who gave it to thee, and come and repent because of this
            offence, and sit in the monastery and perform the work of thy hands, for it is not good
            that thou, O my son, shouldst do again work of this kind</quote>; and the brother did even as
            the old man had said unto him. Then Rabbâ appointed the holy man Zakkai, a good man, who
            overcame all the praises of the children of men by the manifestation of good deeds, and
            he administered all the affairs of the monastery.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
