<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Further Remarks by Palladius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Further_Remarks_by_Palladius"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Further_Remarks_by_Palladius
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Further Remarks By The Writer Palladius</head>
         <p>Now therefore, though I must here add a few remarks about my beloved brother, who hath
            lived with me from my youth up until this day, I will make an end to my discourse in the
            haven of silence. It is indeed a very long time since I first knew this man, who is
            worthy of blessings; and I never knew him either to eat or to fast with desire; and, in
            my opinion, he overcame also the lust for possessions, and especially the passion for
            empty praise, and that which was his own was sufficient for him. He never arrayed
            himself in fine and costly apparel, but being made contemptible he received [acts of]
            grace, and in return for God’s true mercy he continued thus even unto death. And this
            man accepted the temptation of devils a thousand times when they rose up against him,
            and at length one day a certain devil pressed him, and said unto him, <quote>Agree thou with
            me for one day only, and commit sin only once, and any woman that thou shalt mention in
            this world I will bring unto thee.</quote></p>
         <p>And on another occasion that devil strove with him for fourteen nights, even as he
            himself told me, and he used to kick him with his feet in the night-season, and say unto
            him, <quote>Do not worship Christ, and I will never come near thee again.</quote> And he answered and
            said unto him, <quote>It is for this very reason that I worship Him, and I confess Him and
            glorify Him ten thousand times because thou art vexed thereby, and thou reelest away and
            dost tremble before Him.</quote> In his coming in and going out he walked through one hundred
            and six cities (or provinces) several times, and in the greater number of them he
            tarried for some time. By the grace and mercy of Christ he never knew the temptation of
            a woman, not even in a dream, except in [his] warfare [against fornication]. I know that
            he received food from an angel thrice: One day he was in a parched desert, and had not
            upon him a morsel of bread, and he found three cakes of bread in his cloak. Another
            time, when he lacked [food], an angel appeared unto him in a vision and said unto him,
            <quote>Go and take wheat and oil from such and such a man</quote>; and thereupon there came to him
            the man from whom the angel had commanded him to take [wheat and oil], and said unto
            him, <quote>Art thou such and such a man?</quote> and he said unto him, <quote>Yea, I am</quote>; and the man
            said, <quote>A certain One hath told thee to take thirty bushels of wheat from me, and twelve
            boxes of oil.</quote></p>
         <p>Now over a matter of this kind, for such was his nature, he would boast. And I know that
            on very many occasions he used to weep over people who were in straits and difficulties,
            and who were living in poverty, and he would give them whatsoever he possessed, with the
            exception of his body only, which he was unable to give. Now I have seen him very many
            times weeping over a man who had been caught in a snare, and had fallen into sin, but
            through his tears he made him to become penitent, and to repent of his sin. This brother
            swore unto me once, saying, <quote>I made supplication unto God that I would never make myself
            pleasing unto any man, especially the rich folk of the world, and the liars, lest they
            might give me whatsoever I had need of.</quote></p>
         <p>Now it is sufficient for me that I have been held worthy to set down completely in
            writing, and to make mention of the man who, by the grace of God, was able to make
            perfect all these things. Behold the summary [of the contents] of the book hath been
            written above.</p>
         <p>Here endeth the Second Part of the Histories of the Holy Fathers, which were compiled by
            the blessed Bishop Palladius, [and dedicated] to Lausus the Prefect. Glory be to the
            Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghost, for ever! Amen</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
