<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of a Vainglorious Monk</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_20"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_20
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- This work is mis-numbered in the body text of the print edition. The number here is based on the table of contents. -->
         <head>Chapter 20: Of how unclean and contemptible in the sight of <persName>Rabba</persName> was the man who who
            toiled with the Labour of his hands for the sake of Vainglory</head>
         <p>On one occasion when <persName>Rabbâ</persName> was sitting with a number of the other brethren in a certain
            place in the monastery, [he was told that] one of the monks in the monastery used to
            make two mats of plaited palm leaves daily and that day he placed them in front of his
            cell, opposite the place where <persName>Rabbâ</persName> was then sitting with the brethren. Now he did this
            because he was [unduly] exalted with the thought of vainglory, and he believed that he
            would be praised for such assiduity, because the rule [of the fathers] was that each
            monk should make one mat daily. And <persName>Rabbâ</persName> perceived that the monk did this for the
            purpose of making a display, and he understood the intention which was stirring in the
            man and moving him; and he sighed heavily and said unto the brethren who were sitting
            with him, <quote>See ye this man who toileth from morning to evening? He hath endowed <persName>Satan</persName>
            with all his labour, and hath left nothing whatsoever of his work for the comfort of his
            own soul. He hath toiled overmuch for the praise of the children of men, and he hath not
            worn out his body with all this work for the sake of God, and his soul is empty of work
            through the pleasure of him that doeth it, for he hath loved the praise of men more than
            the praise of God.</quote> Then he called that brother, and rebuked him, and charged him to
            stand up behind the brethren when they were praying, and to hold the two mats, and to
            say to them, <quote>O my brethren, I beseech you to pray for my degraded soul, in order that
            through your prayers God may shew abundant mercy to it, for I have held these mats in
            greater honour than His kingdom.</quote> And he also commanded that the man should stand up
            with the mats among the brethren when they were sitting at meat until they rose up from
            the table; and he commanded likewise that after this he should be confined to his cell
            for a period of five months, and should make two mats daily, and should eat bread and
            salt only, and that no man should visit him.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
