<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Funeral of a Holy Man</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_4"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_4
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 4: Of the Funeral of a certain Holy Man who died</head>
         <p>Now whilst Abbâ Pachomius was still there he heard that a certain brother from the
            monastery of Bêth Râyâ was sick, [and it was said to him], <quote>He wisheth to see thee and
            to be blessed by thee before he dieth.</quote> And when the man of God heard these things he
            rose up, and departed on the journey, but when he was about two miles from the
            monastery, the holy man heard a holy voice in the air, and he lifted up his eyes and saw
            the soul of the sick brother with the holy angels, singing hymns, and being borne aloft
            to a blessed and divine life; now the brethren who were accompanying him neither heard
            nor saw anything. And when the holy man had stood there and gazed for a long time
            towards the East, they said unto him, <quote>Why standest thou [here], O father? Let us hurry
            on so that we may reach him whilst he is still alive.</quote> And he said unto them, <quote>We shall
            not reach him there, for I have just seen him ascending to everlasting life; depart ye
            then, O my children, to your monastery.</quote> And when those brethren entreated him [to tell
            them] in what [form] he had seen the soul of the brother who had died, he said unto
            them, <quote>In a certain form</quote>; and when they had heard this they departed to their
            monastery. And they [enquired], and ascertained exactly from the brethren who were in
            the monastery, concerning the hour whereof Rabbâ had spoken to them, and then they
            recognized that the things which had been said unto them about the brother who had died
            were true.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
