<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Things which Pachomius did</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_6"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_6
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 6: Of the things which Abba Pachomius did when he arrived at his
            Monastery</head>
         <p>And when the brethren went forth to meet the holy man and to salute him, a certain young
            man also went out with them to salute Abbâ Pachomius, and he began to make a complaint
            to him, saying, <quote>Verily, O father, from the time when thou didst depart to visit the
            brethren until this present they have not cooked either vegetables or crushed peas</quote>; and
            the old man answered and said unto him readily and pleasantly, <quote>My son, grieve not, for
            from this time forward I will make them to cook these things for thee.</quote> And having gone
            round about through the monastery Abbâ Pachomius went to the place where the food was
            [kept], and he found him that did the cooking plaiting a mat of palm leaves, and he said
            unto him, <quote>How long is it since thou hast cooked vegetables for the brethren?</quote> and he
            answered, <quote>Two months.</quote> And Rabbâ said unto him, <quote>Hast thou acted thus in spite of the
            command and ordinances of the holy fathers which enjoin that vegetables shall be cooked
            for the brethren every Saturday and every Sunday?</quote> And the cook answered and said unto
            him, <quote>Truly, O father, I wanted to cook some vegetables on each of these days, but
            because I saw that when they were cooked they were not eaten (for all the brethren, so
            to speak, were restraining themselves, and were not eating cooked food), except by the
            young men who usually ate them, and when I saw that when they were not eaten they were
            thrown away, [I cooked] no more so that all the expense and all the trouble might be
            avoided. Now we pour into the cooked food of the brethren forty boxes of oil daily. And
            when I saw that the food was not eaten I did not cook it, for I did not consider it to
            be right that we should throw away and waste such costly things. And moreover, because I
            could not sit idle I began to plait a mat with the brethren, for I thought that one man
            would be sufficient in the kitchen to prepare the less important meals for brethren,
            that is to say, chopped garlic, and mountain herbs [mixed with] vinegar and olive oil,
            and herbs from the garden.</quote></p>
         <p>And when the holy man had heard these things he said unto the cook, <quote>How many mats have
            ye made? Ye who belong to the kitchen must have been continually at this work</quote>; and the
            cook said, <quote>Five hundred.</quote> And Abbâ Pachomius said unto him, <quote>Bring them here, for I
            wish to count them</quote>; and having brought the mats he ordered them to be thrown into the
            fire. Then, when they had all been consumed, Abbâ Pachomius said unto them, <quote>Why have ye
            forsaken the ordinance which hath been given unto you for the government of the brethren
            through [your] Satanic minds? I have destroyed pitilessly the labour of your hands, and
            have burned it in the fire, so that ye may learn what it is for a man to treat lightly
            the laws of the fathers, which have been given for the benefit of souls. How great is
            the help which ye have removed from the brethren through your not having cooked food for
            them! Have ye forgotten that a man hath power over a desire for food, and that he who
            restraineth himself from such and such a food, for God’s sake, shall obtain from God
            wages which are not small? while he who hath not received authority, and who denieth
            himself by force or necessity will seek for wages in return for this in vain? And do ye
            not know that, if cooked meat be placed upon the table, and the brethren eat it not
            because they restrain themselves therefrom for God’s sake, they shall receive abundant
            wages? But if cooked meats be not given unto them, because they have not seen them
            abstinence and self-denial can never be reckoned unto them. For the sake of eighty boxes
            of oil, for such is the excuse [which ye have made], ye have cut off all the preparation
            of all the brethren; I would rather that all the world should be wasted than that one
            small spiritual virtue should be cut off from [their] soul[s]. I therefore truly wish to
            have food in abundance cooked daily and set before the brethren, so that in practising
            abstinence every day, and in restraining themselves from partaking of what hath been
            given to them, they may make an addition daily to their spiritual excellence. For if a
            man should happen to fall sick, and did not desire to go to the hospital, if he should
            come to the common table in order to partake of the vegetables which are usually given
            to the brethren, and should not find any there, what would happen to me? Would not a
            brother be offended in not finding at the common table that of which he was in need? And
            do ye not know that young men especially [cannot] continue in spiritual excellence
            unless they enjoy some small gratification or a little consolation from their food?</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
