<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Pachomius and the Heretics</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_18"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_18
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- This work is mis-numbered in the body text of the print edition. The number here is based on the table of contents. -->
         <head>Chapter 18: Of how when on a certain occasion the <persName>Heretics</persName> came to him he did not
            yield to them, and of how he let them receive an experience of him by the Sign which
            they asked at his Hand</head>
         <p>And it came to pass on a certain occasion that certain heretical monks, who were in the
            habit of wearing garments made of hair, and who had heard concerning the blessed
            <persName>Pachomius</persName>, rose up and came to his monastery; and they said unto certain monks of <persName>Rabb창</persName>,
            <quote>Our father hath sent us to your <persName>Rabb창</persName> with a message, saying, <quote>If thou art in truth a
            man of God, and if thou art confident that God will hearken unto you, come hither, and
            let us walk together across the river on our feet, so that every man may know which of
            us hath more freedom of speech before God than the other.</quote> </quote> And when the brethren
            informed <persName>Rabb창</persName> concerning these things, he was exceedingly angry with them, and said
            unto them, <quote>Why did ye undertake to listen to those who have said these things? Know ye
            not that requests of this kind are things which are foreign to God, and are wholly alien
            to our rule? And besides this, they are not even things which are thought well of by men
            who live in the world. For what law of God teacheth us to do these things? And moreover,
            our Redeemer commandeth us to the contrary in the Holy Gospel, saying, <quote>Let not thy left
            hand know what thy right hand doeth</quote> (St. Matthew 6:3). For thou [thinkest] of something
            which is more wretched than the want of mind [i.e., foolishness] in imagining that I
            should give up mourning for my sins, [or cease to think] how I may flee from everlasting
            punishment, or that, even if I were a boy in my thoughts I could ever come to [make]
            such a demand as that.</quote></p>
         <p>And the brethren answered and said unto him, <quote>How is it then that this man, who is a
            heretic and alien to God, should be so bold as to call upon thee to do this [thing]?</quote>
            And <persName>Rabb창</persName> answered and said unto them, <quote>He is able to pass over the river as one who
            travelleth over dry land through the neglect of God, and the Calumniator helpeth him, so
            that his wicked heresy may not be brought to naught, and so that the faith of those who
            have gone astray may be more finally established by means of works of audacity which he
            performeth through him. Get ye out then, and say unto those who have brought such a
            message as this: <quote>Thus saith the man of God, <persName>Pachomius</persName>, I devote all my strivings, and
            all my anxious care, not that I may pass over the river by walking on the waters
            thereof, but in trying to flee from the judgement of God, and to escape, by the might of
            the Lord, <pb n="400"/>from such Satanic wiles as these.</quote> </quote> Then having said these things to the
            brethren he strictly forbade them to think greatly of their integrity, and to lust after
            the sight [of him walking across the river on the water], and to go with those who pry
            into such matters as these; [and he said] <quote>We must not voluntarily follow after such
            matters as these, and we must not put God to the test by such questions, for concerning
            the knowledge of events before they happen He hath commanded us by His Holy Scriptures,
            saying, <quote>Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God, saith the Lord</quote> </quote> (Deuteronomy
            6:16).</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
