<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Things heard by Pachomius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_5"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_5
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 5: Of the things which Abba Pachomius heard said in the Air by the Devils as
            he was journeying in the Desert to his Monastery</head>
         <p>Now when the holy old man was journeying to his monastery, and was by the side of the
            desert which is called <quote>Ammon,</quote> certain legions of devils rose up against him, and
            thronged him, both on his right hand and on his left, and others ran in front of him,
            saying, <quote>Behold the blessed man of God</quote>; and they acted in this wise because they were
            plotting to sow the seeds of vainglory in him. Now he knew the evil character of their
            cunning, and as they cried out these things he cried out to God, and made confession of
            his sins; then, having brought to naught the evil cunning of these wicked devils, he
            answered and said unto them, <quote>Ye are not able to persuade me to [indulge in] vainglory.
            O ye wicked ones, well do I know mine iniquities, and well do I know that it is right
            for me to weep concerning them continually, and concerning the punishment which is for
            ever. I have no need of fluent words and cunning error from you, for your work is the
            destruction of souls. I am not to be carried away therefore by your praisings, for I
            know well your cunning minds, O evil ones.</quote> And though the holy man Pachomius spake
            these words unto them, their audacious acts did not cease, for they clung round and
            about the blessed man until he drew nigh unto his monastery.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
