<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Revelation of Pachomiusa</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_7"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_7
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 7: Of the Revelation which Abba <persName>Pachomius</persName> received from God concerning
            <persName>certain Heretics who happened to visit him</persName></head>
         <p>And it came to pass that when the old man had said these things to the brethren, the
            doorkeeper came to him, and said, <quote>Certain travellers, who are men of importance, have
            come hither, and they wish to meet thee</quote>; and he said, <quote>Call them hither,</quote> and when they
            had entered into the monastery he saluted them with the brethren. And after they had
            seen all the brotherhood, and had gone round about among all the cells of the brethren
            they wanted to hold converse with him by themselves. Now when they had taken their seats
            in a secluded chamber, there came unto the old man a strong smell of uncleanness, but he
            knew not whence came such uncleanness, though he thought that it must arise from them
            because he was speaking with them face to face; <pb n="292"/>and he was not able to learn the cause
            of the same by the supplication which [he made] to God, for he perceived that their
            speech was fruitful [of thought], and that their minds were familiar with the
            Scriptures, but he was not acquainted with their intellectual uncleanness. Then, after
            he had spoken unto them many things out of the Divine Books, and the season of the ninth
            hour had drawn nigh meanwhile, they rose up that they might come to their own place, and
            <persName>Rabbâ</persName> entreated them to partake of some food there, but they did not accept [his
            petition, saying,] that they were in duty bound to arrive home before sunset; so they
            prayed, and they saluted us, and then they departed.</p>
         <p>And <persName>Rabbâ</persName>, in order to learn the cause of the uncleanness of those men, went into his
            cell, and prayed to God, and he knew straightway that it was the doctrine of wickedness
            which arose from their souls that sent forth such an unclean smell. Thereupon he went
            forth from his cell immediately and pursued those men, and having overtaken them, he
            said unto them, <quote>I beg of you to allow me to ask you one question</quote>; and they said unto
            him, <quote>Speak.</quote> And he said unto them, <quote>Do ye call that which is written in the works of
            <persName>Origen</persName> heresy?</quote> And when they had heard this question they denied and said that they did
            not. Then the holy man said unto them, <quote>Behold, I take you to witness before God, that
            every man who readeth and accepteth the work of <persName>Origen</persName>, shall certainly arrive in the
            fire of Sheol, and his inheritance shall be everlasting darkness. That which I know from
            God I have made you to be witnesses of, and I am therefore not to be condemned by God on
            this account, and ye yourselves know about it. Behold, I have made you to hear the
            truth. And if ye believe me, and if ye wish truly to gratify God, take all the writings
            of <persName>Origen</persName> and cast them into the fire; and never seek to read them again.</quote> And when Abbâ
            <persName>Pachomius</persName> had said these things he left them.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
