<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Revelation of Pachomius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_9"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_9
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 9: Another Revelation on this matter which [brought] Consolation</head>
         <p>And it came to pass that when he had said these things, Abbâ <persName>Pachomius</persName> heard a voice
            saying, <quote>Thou boastest thyself, O <persName>Pachomius</persName>. Thou art a man. Ask mercy for thyself,
            because everything standeth by compassion.</quote> Now when the blessed man heard these things,
            he straightway threw himself on his face upon the ground, and he asked God for mercy,
            saying, <quote>O Lord, Who dost sustain the universe, send Thy mercies to me, and take Thou
            them never away from me, for I know that without Thy mercy nothing can possibly exist.</quote>
            And having said these words straightway there stood by his side two angels of God, and
            there was with them a Young Man, Who had a face which is unspeakable, and an appearance
            which cannot be described, and on His head was a crown of thorns. Then the angels made
            <persName>Pachomius</persName> to stand up, and they said unto him, <quote>Because thou hast asked God to send thee
            His mercy, behold, this is His mercy, the Lord of glory, <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, the Only One, His
            Son, Whom He sent into the world, and Whom ye crucified; and ye set a crown of thorns
            upon His head.</quote> And <persName>Pachomius</persName> said unto the Young Man, <quote>I entreat Thee, O my Lord, and
            Thy holy nature, [to remember] that I did not crucify Thee.</quote> Then the Young Man relaxed
            His face a little in a smile, and said unto him, <quote>I know that thou didst not crucify Me,
            but thy fathers did; be of good courage, however, for the root of thy seed shall never
            come to an end, and thy seed shall be preserved upon the earth even unto the end of the
            world. And the seeds which shall burst into life in those times, through the abundance
            of darkness shall be found to be more excellent than those of this present time, and
            they shall be more completely subject to rule; for at this present, because thou art
            unto them as a light which is before the eyes, they lead lives of great excelence and
            according to rule, and they lean upon thy light. But those who shall come after them,
            and who shall live in a region of darkness, if with a good intent and from the mind
            voluntarily they run towards the truth, even though no man directeth them, they shall
            from out of the darkness draw nigh unto the truth; verily, I say unto thee, that they
            shall be free and shall be with those who now lead a blameless life of the highest
            character, and they shall be held to be worthy of forgiveness.</quote></p>
         <pb n="295"/>
         <p>Then having said these things straightway the Young Man went [up into] the heavens, and
            the heavens were opened, and the air shone so brightly that it is impossible for us to
            describe with human words the splendour of that light. And when <persName>Rabbâ</persName> had marvelled at
            the things which he had heard, straightway they beat [the board to summon] the brethren
            to the service of the night.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
