<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Gift of Tonguesa</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_15"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_15
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 15: Of the Gift of Tongues which <persName>Pachomius</persName> received</head>
         <p>And it came to pass that, when the blessed <persName>Pachomius</persName> was visiting the brethren in their
            cells, and was correcting the thoughts of each of them, he was obliged to visit <persName>a
            certain Roman</persName>, who was a nobleman of high rank, and who knew the Greek language very
            well. Now therefore, having come to this great man, so that he might exhort him with
            words which would be beneficial to him, and might learn the motions of his heart, the
            blessed man spake unto him in the Egyptian tongue, but the brother did not know what the
            blessed man said. And because the blessed man did not know how to speak Greek, <persName>Rabbâ</persName> was
            obliged to call some brother who would be able to interpret to each of them the things
            which were said by the other. Now when the brother came to interpret, the Greek did not
            wish to declare to <persName>Rabbâ</persName> through others the defects of his heart, and he spoke unto him
            thus, <quote>After God, I wish thee, and thee alone, to know the wickednesses of my heart, and
            I do not desire to declare them unto thee through others, for I do not wish that any man
            except thee should hear them.</quote> And when <persName>Rabbâ</persName> heard these words he commanded the brother
            who had come to interpret to depart, and because <persName>Rabbâ</persName> was unable to speak to the Greek
            brother the words which he wished to say to him about help and redemption, for he knew
            nothing whatsoever of the Greek language, he made a sign to him with his hand to remain
            until he came [back] to him. Then <persName>Rabbâ</persName> left him, and went to pray by himself, and he
            stretched out his hands towards heaven, and prayed to God, saying, <quote>O Lord, Thou Mighty
            One, Who sustainest the universe, if I am not able to benefit the children of men whom
            Thou dost send unto me from the ends of the earth, because I am not acquainted with
            their languages, what need is there for them to come? But if Thou wishest them to be
            saved here through me, give me, O Lord, Thou Star of all creation, the power to know
            their languages so that I may be able to set their souls in the straight way.</quote> And when
            he had prayed for more than three hours and had entreated God to grant him this
            knowledge, suddenly there <pb n="307"/>was sent from heaven into his right hand something which was
            like unto a letter written on paper, and when he had read it, he learned immediately how
            to speak all tongues, and he sent up praise to the Father, and to the Son, and to the
            Holy Ghost. And he came with great joy to that brother, and began to talk to him both
            Greek and Latin with such fluency that when the brother heard him, he saith that <persName>Rabbâ</persName>’s
            skill in speaking [Greek] surpassed that of all the learned men [of the day]. Then <persName>Rabbâ</persName>
            corrected him, as was right, and appointed to him the penance which was suitable to his
            defects, and he committed him to the Lord, and went forth from him.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
