<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Apostate Monk</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_13"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/The_Rule_of_Pachomius_at_Tabenna/Chapter_13
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 13: Of <persName>a certain ascetic Brother who was in the Monastery</persName>, and who desired a
            crown of Martyrdom unseasonably</head>
         <p>And there was also [there] among those who were very famous a certain brother who
            cultivated the ascetic life by himself, and when he heard of the divine rule of our holy
            Father <persName>Pachomius</persName> he entreated him to receive him in the monastery; and when <persName>Rabbâ</persName> had
            received him, and he had passed a little [time] with the brethren, he desired greatly to
            bear witness (i.e., to become a martyr), although the world was in a state of peace, and
            the Church was flourishing and was, by the grace of God, at peace, and the blessed
            <persName>Constantine</persName>, who had put on <persName>Christ</persName>, was at that time reigning. And this brother was
            continually entreating the blessed man <persName>Pachomius</persName>, and saying, <quote>Pray for me, O father,
            that I may become a martyr</quote>; but <persName>Rabbâ</persName> admonished him that he should not permit this
            thought to enter his mind again, and said unto him, <quote>Brother, endure the strife of the
            monks mightily and blamelessly, and make straight thy life in the way which will please
            <persName>Christ</persName>, and thou shalt have companionship with the martyrs in heaven.</quote></p>
         <p>As, however, the brother made his desire for this thing stronger each day, and he was
            wearying the holy man therewith, <persName>Rabbâ</persName>, wishing to drive away this kind of desire from
            him, said unto him, <quote>I will pray [for thee], but if thou seekest for this thing thou
            wilt be vanquished. And put armour on thy soul, lest, when the hour cometh wherein thou
            hast to bear witness, thou shalt deny <persName>Christ</persName>. Verily thou wilt certainly commit sin,
            because of thine own will thou drawest nigh unto temptation, although our Lord <persName>Jesus</persName>
            commanded us, saying, <quote>Pray that ye fall not into temptation</quote> </quote> (St. Mat<pb n="301"/>thew 26:41; St.
            Mark 14:38; St. Luke 22:40, 46). And having said these things unto him, he admonished
            him to take good heed unto himself, and not to meditate upon martyrdom.</p>
         <p>And it came to pass that two years later certain of the brethren were sent by <persName>Rabbâ</persName> to a
            village which was further to the south to collect wreaths [to make] mats for the
            monastery; now this village was nigh unto the barbarians who are called <quote><persName>Blemmyes</persName>.</quote> And
            whilst the brethren were there, and were on an island where there were large numbers of
            reeds, the blessed man <persName>Pachomius</persName> sent the brother who was wishing to suffer martyrdom to
            carry a little money to them for their expenses, and he commanded him to take good heed
            to himself. And he said unto him, <quote>The words which are written, <quote>Behold, now is the
            acceptable time (2 Corinthians 6:2) behold, now is the day of redemption,</quote> have a
            mystical signification [for thee], and ye shall not commit an offence against any man,
            so that there may be no blemish in our ministration</quote>; so the brother took an ass to
            carry the money and departed to the brethren.</p>
         <p>Now when he had arrived at the place which is opposite the desert, the barbarians came
            down [to the river] to draw water, and they came upon the brother, and made him to come
            down from off the ass, and they bound his hands, and took the ass and that which was
            thereon, and they led him up to a neighbouring mountain where there were other
            barbarians. Now when the barbarians saw that they came with an ass, they began to make a
            mock of him, and to say, <quote>O monk, come and worship our gods,</quote> and they slew some beasts,
            and poured out libations to their gods, and they brought the monk and urged the monk to
            pour out libations with them. And when he did not want to do this they rose up in wrath
            and came towards him with their drawn swords in their hands in a threatening manner, and
            said, <quote>If he be unwilling to sacrifice to our gods and to pour out libations to them, we
            will kill him.</quote> Then seeing the drawn swords and the savage disposition of the people,
            straightway the brother took wine and poured out a libation to their gods, and because
            he was afraid of dying the death of the body he slew his immortal soul by denying God,
            the Lord of all; now when he had done these things the <persName>Blemmyes</persName> sent him away.</p>
         <p>Then having descended from the mountain, when he had come to himself he knew his
            iniquity, that is to say, the wickedness which he had committed, and he rent his
            garments, and having beaten himself upon his face severely he came to the monastery; and
            the blessed man knew what had happened to him, and he went forth to meet him in sore
            affliction. <pb n="302"/>And when the brother saw that he was coming to him, he threw himself on his
            face upon the ground, and shedding tears cried out and said, <quote>I have sinned against God
            and against thee, O father, and I would neither listen to thy promise nor to thine
            admonition, and had I but hearkened unto thee, I should not have had to bear what I have
            suffered.</quote> And having said these words, <persName>Rabbâ</persName> said unto him, <quote>Rise up, O wretched man,
            thou hast snatched thyself away from the good things which were awaiting thee, for in
            very truth there was laid up for thee a crown which thou hast cast away from thee; thou
            wast ready to be reckoned with the holy martyrs, but thou hast cut thyself off from
            their blessed companionship. Our Lord <persName>Jesus</persName> <persName>Christ</persName> was near with His holy angels, and He
            wished to lay the crown upon thy head. Through thy momentary turning back thou hast
            refused (or denied) this, and in being afraid of that death which thou wast about to
            endure, a death which thou didst not seek, thou hast fallen away from God and destroyed
            thine everlasting life. Where are the words which [thou didst speak] before this
            [happened]? Where is thy desire for martyrdom?</quote> And the brother said, <quote>I have sinned in
            all these [respects], O father, and I am no longer able to lift up my face to heaven. I
            am lost, O father, I have no position wherefrom I may contemplate what I shall do, O
            father, I never expected that the matter would happen thus.</quote></p>
         <p>Then having said these words with tears, <persName>Rabbâ</persName> spake unto him, saying, <quote>Thou, O wretched
            man, hast made thyself altogether an alien to the Lord, but the Lord is good, and He
            never keepeth His anger for a testimony, for He is a lover of mercy, and He is able to
            sink our sins in the depths of the sea. As far as are the heavens from the earth so far
            hath He put away our iniquity and sins. For He desireth not the death of the sinner, but
            his repentance, and He wisheth not that a man who hath fallen should remain in his
            fallen condition, but that he should rise up; and He desireth not that he who hath
            turned back should keep afar off from Him, but that he should return quickly to Him.
            Therefore despair not, for there is still a hope of [thy] redemption. For it is said,
            <quote>If thou cuttest down a tree it shall renew itself</quote> (Job 14:7). If then thou wishest to
            obey me in everything which I shall say unto thee, thou shalt obtain forgiveness from
            God.</quote> And with tears the brother said, <quote>From this time forward I will obey thee in
            everything, O father.</quote> Then <persName>Rabbâ</persName> commanded him to seclude himself in a cell alone, and
            never to hold converse with any man until death, and to eat one meal daily, of bread and
            salt only, and to drink water only for the whole <pb n="303"/>period of his life, and to plait two
            palm-leaf mats daily, and to keep vigil as long as possible, and never to cease from
            crying. So that his brother departed, even as the blessed man had commanded him, and he
            carried out everything which he had told him to do. And he held converse with no man
            except <persName>Rabbâ</persName> and <persName>Theodore</persName>, and with a few of the other great sages; and he passed ten
            years in striving in this manner, and died in the grace of the Lord, and <persName>Rabbâ</persName> bore
            witness nobly concerning his tranquil state.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
