<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Eugenia</title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreading and initial markup of persons, places, and titles by </resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#anorth">Adelaide North</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title level="a">Eugenia</title>
                  <title level="m"> Select Narratives of Holy Women from the Syro-Antiochene or
                     Sinai Palimpsest as Written above teh Old Syriac Gospels by John the Stylite,
                     of Beth-Mari-Qanūn in A.D. 778. </title> Translated by Anges Smith Lewis
                  M.R.A.S. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>C. J. Clay and Sons</publisher>
                  <date>1900</date>
                  <citedRange unit="p" from="2" to="35">2-35</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <p>This transcription renumbers the original footnotes to run sequentially and includes
               marginal references for Biblical citations among the footnotes.</p>
            <p>This text is in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p n="1">The Acts and the Martyrdom of the Blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> <milestone unit="folio" n="21a"
         />and of her father <persName>Philip</persName> and of all who were martyred with them.</p>
         <p n="2">Whilst <persName>Commodus</persName> was reigning, ruler of the transitory world, in the great and
            famous city of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, in his own seventh consulate, he gave the command of a province to
            <persName>Philip</persName>, one of his magnates, and sent him to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> the great city, which is in the
            land of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and he thus gave him the command of all who were in the country, rich and
            poor, great and small, and of all the Roman troops who were there, that they should be
            obedient and <milestone unit="folio" n="21b"/> submissive to the laws and to the
            commandments which should be established and decreed to them by him. Now when <persName>Philip</persName>
            received the command of the province from the Emperor with his consort <persName>Claudia</persName> and his
            two sons, <persName>Avita</persName> and <persName>Sergius</persName>, and his daughter the virgin <persName>Eugenia</persName>, <pb n="2"/>they
            travelled from <placeName>Rome</placeName> to <persName>Alexandria</persName> and arrived quickly. But immediately when they had
            entered that country he sent decrees through every city and province, and thus it was
            written in them. By the commandments of the victorious Emperors. All the Egyptians shall
            be governed by the laws of the Romans, and they shall live by their customs
            continually.</p>
         <p n="3">Now <persName>Eugenia</persName> the daughter of this Eparch <persName>Philip</persName> was about sixteen years old, and
            she was proficient in much wisdom and in the learning of the Greeks and the Romans, and
            she was very skilful in speech; so that the philosophers and the wise men were amazed at
            her wisdom and her discourse and at the erudition of her mind.</p>
         <p n="4">Now upon a certain day her father asked her, saying to her, Art thou willing, my
            daughter, that I should betroth <milestone unit="folio" n="22a"/> thee to <persName>Aquilina</persName> the
            son of <persName>Hypatus</persName>? For behold! we know him that he is a wise and rich man and worthy of
            being thy betrothed.</p>
         <p n="5">But she answered and said to her father: It is expedient that I should espouse him
            who loveth integrity, and purity, and holiness; rather than this man concerning whom
            thou hast told me that he hath transient riches and possessions. For far better is he
            who hath promised glorious things to the soul which is pure from evil, than the natural
            man who is mortal and transitory. For there had fallen into her hands the book of the
            story of the discipleship of <persName>Thecla</persName> the holy virgin, and of <persName>Paul the Apostle</persName>; and by it
            the eyes of her understanding were enlightened in the fear of <persName>God</persName>. For when she read in
            it she wept passionately in secret, continually, and sighed bitterly; and she was the
            more grieved because she was the daughter of people who were heathens and were without
            the knowledge of <persName>God</persName>. Now truly when she <milestone unit="folio" n="22b"/> read in this
            story of the discipleship of <persName>Thecla</persName> the <pb n="3"/>virgin, she was desirous in her soul,
            longing every day that she might be of the religion of the Christians, and continue in
            the doctrine and in the reading of their sacred books. And on a certain day she asked of
            her parents that they would grant this favour to her and allow her to go from the city
            to a certain village to amuse herself, and they consented and allowed her to go, because
            they loved her greatly.</p>
         <p n="6">Now there went with her many eunuchs and servants for her honour. Now as the
            litter in which she was sitting with the pomp of noble women was going along, <persName>Eugenia</persName>
            was reading within it in the book of <persName>Thecla</persName>, and was meditating on a passage in it. And
            she said to the two eunuchs who were with her, whose names were these, <persName>Proteus</persName> and
            <persName>Hyacinthus</persName>: Do not disregard what the poets in the error of their hearts imagine and say
            concerning <persName>God</persName>, and what things also the philosophers in the error of their hearts
            falsify and deny about <persName>God</persName>, who is <persName>God</persName> in truth <milestone unit="folio" n="23a"/>and
            verity. For is such truth perchance found amongst those who are called gods as that
            which is made known in these sacred books of theology about the true <persName>God</persName> and about His
            mighty power? But little to a degree, and very miserable and childish is a soul which
            calls stones and bits of carved wood, blind and deaf and without feeling, gods, and
            calls them to its help.</p>
         <p n="7">Now as the <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName> said these things for the salvation of these her two
            eunuchs, the three of them began to consider together amongst themselves, discussing and
            investigating concerning the true <persName>God</persName> and concerning the worship of His Divinity. And
            they said to each other: There is nothing more important than this, that a man should
            fear the true <persName>God</persName>, and should be a worshipper and honourer of Him alone, in his faith
            and in his love and in his good works. Now when they had talked about these things and
            things like them with each other, as if in answer <pb n="4"/><milestone unit="folio"
               n="23b"/>they heard the Christians who were singing and saying: All the gods of the
            nations are demons; but the <persName>Lord</persName> made the heavens.</p>
         <p n="8">When the <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName>heard these things, she commanded that her litter should
            be instantly detained and should stand still. For the fear of the <persName>Christ</persName> entered into
            her heart when she heard this singing and she answered and said to the two eunuchs who
            were with her: We have quickly found evidence concerning the truth which the sacred
            books speak about concerning the true power of <persName>God</persName> who is to be worshipped, and about
            the perdition and vanity of the polluted worship of idols. But now we have learned the
            truth about both religions. What therefore shall we do that we may approach that
            glorious wisdom, and by means of a better life may be able to attain to these mysteries
            of the Divinity? Let us henceforth look to ourselves, my brethren. For how long shall we
            occupy ourselves with these useless things of error? Let us cast from ourselves all
            these vanities of this world, and instead of them let us meditate on the living words of
            <persName>God</persName>, and on <milestone unit="folio" n="24a"/> saving faith. Let our minds be
            established, that by these things we may be able to flee and escape from the snares of
            <persName>Satan</persName> and from the net of the adversary, and that we may hold and may be established in
            the faith of the <persName>Christ the Saviour</persName> of the souls of men.</p>
         <p n="9">And again the <persName>Blessed One</persName> answered and said to <persName>Proteus</persName> and to <persName>Hyacinthus</persName>: The
            fashion of this transient world has appointed me your mistress; but now the fear of <persName>God</persName>,
            which is implanted in our hearts by His love, makes me your sister, and henceforth, my
            brethren, I counsel you that we be one soul in the faith of <persName>God</persName>, in one love of <persName>God</persName>,
            despising and rejecting all the honours and desires and luxuries of this world, and
            progressing in love and in faith, and coming near to the glories of <pb n="5"/>the world
            that passeth not away for ever; having nothing opposed to us to hinder us by its hateful
            counsels that we should henceforth be removed from all this blessedness which meets us
            by the grace of <persName>God</persName> and by our good will.</p>
         <p n="10">And now as I speak to you and instruct you, so do. <milestone unit="folio"
               n="24b"/>Remove in the first place the hair from my head, and all this ornament that
            is upon me, and take away your own afterwards, and let us change our dress and direct
            the course of our journey this night to believing people, the servants of the living
            <persName>God</persName>. Let the two of you holding me on my right hand and on my left, gently with secrecy
            let me down from this litter without anyone perceiving it; and let the litter be going
            on empty, and let those who are with it be imagining that I am sitting inside it, and we
            three all alike in man's clothing will go joyfully to the people of <persName>God</persName>.</p>
         <p n="11">Now the counsel of the <persName>Blessed One</persName> pleased these eunuchs, and the next day they
            did joyfully as she had said to them. Now the <persName>Christ</persName> in whom they fully believed sent
            immediately in a very little while His grace to them. For as soon as she descended from
            her litter, and they <milestone unit="folio" n="25a"/> began to travel and to go on the
            road, the saint of <persName>God</persName>, the bishop <persName>Helenus</persName>, happened to be accompanying them with a
            great multitude who were with him, praising and singing and saying together: The paths
            of the righteous are straight, and the paths of the holy are ordered.</p>
         <p n="12">Then said the <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName> to <persName>Proteus</persName> and to <persName>Hyacinthus</persName>: Do ye understand the
            force of these words that they are singing now? Do ye know that upon us is accomplished
            the meaning of the words which we are hearing now from the Christians who are singing
            and praising their <persName>God</persName>; those which we also were speaking to each other yesterday
            concerning the truth of <persName>God</persName>, and concerning His mighty power? For we heard before <pb
               n="6"/>holy men singing and praising <persName>God</persName> and saying that all the gods of the nations
            are demons, and we removed ourselves far from the ruinous worship of idols: and now
               <milestone unit="folio" n="25b"/> again lo! we hear thousands of men singing together
            and saying: The paths of the righteous are straight and the ways of the just are equal.
            Now since we have heard these sacred words, let us go in with a good will and mingle
            with this crowd of singers, and let us be of them and be numbered in their ranks, that
            we may enter with them into the life that passeth not away, although we have been called
            late, as if at eventide, to the knowledge of the truth.</p>
         <p n="13">Now when they had entered and mingled with the crowd of Christians, they asked
            some of them, saying: Who is that old man who is sitting by himself in the midst of the
            people in a high place as if in honour? But some of the crowd answered and said unto
            them: That is the bishop <persName>Helenus</persName>, who has been educated from his birth in a monastery of
            Christian people, he who by his acceptable prayers was saved from the midst of a burning
            fire; and <milestone unit="folio" n="26a"/> what is to be told concerning the beauty and
            excellence of his former deeds! For lo! a short time ago a certain wizard who dwelt
            here, whose name was <persName>Iraus</persName>, approached the people of the Christians with the wicked
            artifice of his magic, and desired to turn away their minds from the sacred writings of
            theology, and from the certain hope which is signified in their living words. He waxed
            bold in his wickedness and approached the bishop <persName>Helenus</persName> and began to speak to him vain
            words and of the corruption of his error. But when the holy man saw the impudence of his
            wicked words, and knew that he could not reply to him about the truth in words, he said
            with a loud voice in the presence of all the people who were assembled there: Why need
            we argue in words with the son of perdition who now disturbs us? For behold! he is not
            willing to <pb n="7"/>submit to our own words nor to our teaching that he may turn to the
            truth. For by the seductiveness and incitement of his words he has caused many to fall
            from the faith of <milestone unit="folio" n="26b"/> <persName>God</persName> wherein they were standing. And
            behold! down to the present time he is eager in his wickedness that he may subvert and
            throw down those who are established and confirmed in their faith from the hope of their
            <persName>God</persName>. But henceforth in the first place it is incumbent on us to show by an experiment
            and by a deed that it is <persName>God</persName> who guides and helps all those who believe in Him and rely
            upon Him. He who by the hands of me, His humble and weak servant, is ready to show the
            glorious power of His sovereignty and the sublime redemption which He works for all His
            servants who love Him with their whole heart in truth and in verity.</p>
         <p n="14">And when the holy one, bishop <persName>Helenus</persName>, had said these things, he said again to
            all the people who were standing there and listening to them: Kindle a great fire in the
            midst of the city; and let us enter it together, I and this son of perdition who is
            leading you astray, and let us stand in the midst of the flame. And the one of us whom
            his <persName>God</persName> shall rescue from the fire and who does not burn, <milestone unit="folio"
               n="27a"/> his religion is true, and his <persName>God</persName> is the true <persName>God</persName> and is able to save from
            the fire all those who trust in Him. And when the bishop <persName>Helenus</persName> had said these things,
            this counsel pleased all the people; they said to him: Thou hast well said. Now when
            they had kindled a great fire, the holy bishop <persName>Helenus</persName> commanded that they both should
            go in together without fear, and that they should stand in the midst of the flame. But
            the wizard answered and said: Let it not be thus; but let us enter each of us alone. Now
            go thou in first, because thou hast counselled and incited the people that this should
            happen. And immediately, swiftly, the <persName>Blessed Helenus</persName>, with great <pb n="8"/>confidence
            in <persName>God</persName> his helper, spread out his hands towards heaven, and with sobs and with many
            tears called to <persName>God</persName> in his prayers, saying: Thou knowest, our <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ, Son
               of the Living God</persName>, the readiness of my soul; <milestone unit="folio" n="27b"/>Thou wert
            the fourth who didst appear to the three children of the house of Hanania in the midst
            of the furnace of fire. Thou knowest, my <persName>Lord</persName> and my <persName>God</persName>, that I had not one wish for
            human glory; but all my labour and longing and the eagerness of my soul is for the
            redemption of Thy people, over whom in Thy grace Thou hast appointed me a shepherd, whom
            the enemy and hater of good by means of his minister hath plotted to turn from the plain
            path of life. And because of this, for the redemption of Thy people I go joyfully into
            this fire, for there I shall find Thee before me. But sprinkle upon me swiftly the dew
            of Thy mercy, so that this fire may not at all touch me. And when he had said these
            things in his prayers, he signed himself with the sign of the cross and entered, and
            stood confidently exulting in the midst of the flame of the fire a long time, whilst in
            nothing was he hurt by that fire. Then when the people who were assembled there saw this
            great miracle which had <milestone unit="folio" n="28a"/> happened they laid hold of
            <persName>Iraus</persName> the wizard and without his consent threw him into the fire. But when he began to
            burn the blessed bishop <persName>Helenus</persName> ran and seized him by his hand so that he might rescue
            him. For although he was justly tortured in that fire, as his impudence deserved, yet
            the bishop <persName>Helenus</persName> seized and brought him out of it alive.</p>
         <p n="15">But when all the people had insulted that wizard and stoned him with stones, they
            left him and went away from there.</p>
         <p n="16">But him whom ye see, the grace of <persName>God</persName> has magnified him whilst continually
            without ceasing he praises and glorifies and exalts <persName>God</persName>, who by His hand hath wrought
            redemption for His people.</p>
         <pb n="9"/>
         <p n="17">Then the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> with those two eunuchs who were with her, <persName>Proteus</persName> and
            <persName>Hyacinthus</persName>, fell down before the holy bishop <persName>Helenus</persName> and did obeisance to him. And they
            implored and besought him to confirm them in the faith of the <persName>Christ</persName>; and they opened
            their mouths and persuaded him and besought him that by his hand they might approach to
            the knowledge of <persName>God</persName> completely, <milestone unit="folio" n="28b"/> The blessed one
            answered and said to them, My children, be ye continually in the church of <persName>God</persName>, and be
            ye zealous at all times in the holy service of your <persName>Lord</persName>, and thus the great day of the
            revelation of His coming shall find you watching and ready.</p>
         <p n="18">But the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> besought him and said unto him, I beseech of thee, my
            <persName>Lord</persName>, pray for me, and commend me to <persName>God</persName>, He whom thou servest gloriously from thy
            youth. For we three, my <persName>Lord</persName>, are by family Romans, and children of those who worship
            idols. But the mercy of thy <persName>Lord</persName> and His grace hath called us. When we heard His voice
            we did not delay to follow it, but immediately swiftly we left the vain worship of
            idols. And as we were seeking to journey after the sacred footsteps of thy holiness the
            grace of <persName>God</persName> brought us hither. And when the blessed ones had related these things to
            the holy <persName>Helenus</persName> he was silent and did not speak to them, for all the things that
               <milestone unit="folio" n="29a"/> had been related to him had been revealed to him by
            the revelation of the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>. And because it was evening they knelt and received a
            blessing from him, and thus they departed from his presence. But on the following day
            they came to the church and desired to appear to the blessed bishop. But a certain
            priest who dwelt with him chanced to be there; an illustrious and excellent man, whose
            name was <persName>Eutropius</persName>. And they persuaded him to go in and remind the bishop about them.
            And he went in to him with eagerness and said to him: Three young men, <pb n="10"
            />brethren, have come here of those who have forsaken the fear and the worship of idols,
            and they desire to become servants of the <persName>Christ</persName>, and to be numbered amongst His people,
            and to be amongst those who believe in Him and are admitted to His glorious mysteries.
            And they desire so great a gift by the hand of thy holiness and long to be worthy. Then
            said the blessed <persName>Helenus</persName>, I praise Thee, our <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>, that Thou hast
            caused us to attain to all this, and by Thy grace hast deemed us <milestone unit="folio"
               n="29b"/> to be worthy. I will see those of whom Thou hast already told me by the
            revelation of the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>. And he commanded and they entered his presence, and he
            rose immediately and prayed. And when he had finished his prayer, he took hold of the
            hand of <persName>Eugenia</persName> with those two who were with her, and said to them, How have ye received
            the knowledge of the truth, and committed yourselves to <persName>God</persName>, and [how] did ye ask to see
            me His humble servant? What have ye heard about me that ye have come to me? Reveal it to
            me, for I wish to know it from you, and I seek to see the good fruits of your
            promptitude, if it be that you wish to approach <persName>God</persName> with all your mind.</p>
         <p n="19">And the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> answered and said to him: We have considered amongst
            ourselves that it is not fitting that we should name the adorable name of <persName>God</persName> on stones
            and wooden things without feeling. And whilst we were discussing amongst ourselves which
            is the true religion in which the most high and adorable <persName>God</persName> delights, the grace of our
            <persName>Lord</persName> brought us hither. For we heard some of <milestone unit="folio" n="30a"/> you who
            were singing together and saying that all the gods of the nations are demons, but the
            <persName>Lord</persName> made the heavens. And when we heard this blessed voice, we dismissed immediately
            and swiftly the religion of idols from us. And we forsook their worship in haste. And we
            came hither eagerly, and we journeyed with all the people of the <pb n="11"/>believers
            in thy footsteps<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/>, Father, whilst we were believing
            in <persName>God</persName> who will help us, that we may assent to thy faith, and be established in thy
            truth, and we may show by deeds the truth of the words which have been spoken by us to
            thy holiness. But we three are all of us brothers. One of us is named <persName>Proteus</persName>, and
            another <persName>Hyacinthus</persName>, and I am called <persName>Eugenius</persName>. And in reply to these things which bishop
            <persName>Helenus</persName> heard from <persName></persName>, he answered and said to her, Thou art well called <persName>Eugenius</persName>;
            because joyfully and heroically thou doest everything, and thy soul is perfected; and
            thou approachest joyfully to the contest of <persName>Christ</persName>. But know that <persName>God</persName> has revealed and
            made known to us that thou art called <persName>Eugenia</persName>, and whence thou art <milestone
               unit="folio" n="30b"/> come and whose daughter thou art; and who these two are who
            have come hither with thee, our <persName>Lord</persName> hath shewn it clearly to me; and by the good will
            that was in thee towards <persName>God</persName> also those ones are found perfect, and assenters to thy
            faith. And he commanded them that they should be constantly three months in the churches
            and in the monasteries, that they might be helped by the sight and by the speech of
            many, and be established completely in the faith of <persName>God</persName>. And then afterwards he made
            them approach the baptism of atonement and made them partakers of the glorious mysteries
            of the Divinity. Now when he had done all these excellent things to them he led them and
            brought them into a monastery of men and committed them to the Abbot, and commanded him
            concerning them that he should have a care over them. But their deeds he revealed to no
            one as yet.</p>
         <p n="20">But at the first time of the discipleship of the blessed ones when <persName>Proteus</persName> and
            <persName>Hyacinthus</persName> had let down the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> from her litter, the litter went on empty,
               <milestone unit="folio" n="31a"/> whilst the young men who were going before it and
            behind <pb n="12"/>it knew nothing about what had happened; for they supposed that she
            was sitting in it and going. But the household of the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> when they thought
            that she had arrived from the village whither she had gone, went out to meet her with
            joy and to welcome her with exultation. But when they did not find her as they had
            expected, they lifted up their voice with weeping and with bitter wailing.</p>
         <p n="21">And they enquired of those who were with her what had become of <persName>Eugenia</persName>. They
            excused themselves, Until we arrived here we did not know what had happened, but we were
            trusting that she was sitting in the inside of this litter. And after these things there
            was a tumult and a great uproar in all the cities and in that country. And every one was
            in distress and in great grief because of her. And she was sought for in every place and
            was not found. <milestone unit="folio" n="31b"/>For her parents were mourning for their
            daughter; and her brothers for their sister; and her servants for their mistress. And
            every citizen was plunged into great sorrow, because they saw in what a grief her
            parents and her household were because of her. And they went round about in all the
            places and provinces seeking for <persName>Eugenia</persName>.</p>
         <p n="22">Now they inquired of the country people who were in that place and of the women
            who practised necromancy and they offered sacrifices to the idols on her behalf. And
            when they had sought for her in every place and she was not found, all the deluded
            people, the worshippers of idols, said this concerning her, The immortal gods have
            snatched her away, and she is exalted to heaven and she mingles with them. And when her
            father heard these things from the impostors he believed them, and his great grief and
            sore sorrow turned to much consolation. And they made her a statue of pure gold, and set
            it up in the city. But her <pb n="13"/>mother <persName>Claudia</persName>, and her brothers <persName>Avita</persName> and
            <persName>Sergius</persName> found no way whatever of being consoled in their grief.</p>
         <p n="23">Now the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> in the dress of a man with <persName>Proteus</persName> and <persName>Hyacinthus</persName>, in one
            perfect love, were in the <milestone unit="folio" n="32a"/>monastery which we have
            already named progressing in the fear of <persName>God</persName> every day, so that in a short time they
            were repeating by heart all the Holy Scriptures. But while the blessed ones were
            occupied with these chaste and holy deeds three years afterwards the Abbot of that
            monastery in which <persName>Eugenia</persName> with her two eunuchs was, fell on sleep, and his soul went to
            his <persName>Lord</persName> in peace.</p>
         <p n="24">And some time after the death of this Abbot it pleased all the brethren of this
            monastery to appoint <persName>Eugenia</persName> Abbot over them. But the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> declined this, for
            her conscience admonished her that she was a woman, and it was not fitting that she
            should be commander [and] governor to the men of <persName>God</persName>. And moreover she was afraid lest
            she might cause the minds of the brethren to stumble who were advising and persuading
            her to do this; for she saw clearly that the minds of all of them were consenting to
            that idea. And the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> answered and said to them, Many a time ye have heard
            such words <milestone unit="folio" n="32b"/> in your own synod, for ye say that our <persName>Lord
               Jesus the Christ</persName> will reveal and make known to us such things as be profitable according
            to His will. And now, if ye command it, let the holy Gospel be brought into [our] midst
            and let us stand and pray with fervour, and let us beseech the <persName>Lord</persName> that He will reveal
            and show to us such things as be profitable; and let us afterwards open and read, and
            whatsoever be the first passage that is found, let us assent to it, and let us hear it
            and do as it commands us.</p>
         <p n="25">Now when the holy Gospel came and was placed in the midst, they all stood and
            prayed. And afterwards the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> took it in her two hands and kissed it and
               <pb n="14"/>pressed it upon her eyes. And she worshipped the Lord and opened it. And
            when they saw what she had done there was great quiet amongst them. And when she had
            opened it, she found the place in which it is written that our <persName>Lord</persName> said to his
            disciples, Ye know that the chiefs of the nations are their lords, and their great men
            rule over them. It shall not be so among you, but whosoever among <milestone
               unit="folio" n="33a"/> you wishes to be the chief, let him be the servant and
            minister of every man. Now after this reading <persName>Eugenia</persName> said to them, Since ye have made
            known that this is your wish, it is incumbent upon us that we fulfil the commandments of
            the <persName>Christ</persName>. For it is required of a servant that he be obedient to his fellows in the
            fear of the <persName>Christ</persName> whilst he is cautious in his mind and in his estimation of himself;
            blameless and faultless let him draw near joyfully to <persName>God</persName>. When they had all assented to
            the words which the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> spoke to them, in order that she might not resist
            and vex them she accepted for herself only the title of Abbot. But they entreated her
            and besought her that she would accept all the rule of the monastery, as head and
            governor. She yielded to them also in this behaving amongst them with all humility and
            showing indeed the fruits of this humility. And the things which the last ought to do to
            the first in the service of the saints, she in her eagerness and in her humility used to
            do, all the <milestone unit="folio" n="33b"/> service pertaining to the fraternity; for
            she drew water from the well and cut wood and swept all the rooms of the convent, and
            fulfilled all the service of the brethren. And she made a little cell for herself by the
            side of the door of the monastery that she might be continually in it, that she might
            not be a burden on the brothers who were with her, and be better off in her dwelling
            than all those who were with her. For at the time of the service she would enter first
            and all the brethren would find her there. And there <pb n="15"/>was not in all that
            fraternity any one who excelled her in humility, and at all times she was assiduous with
            the brethren, warning and teaching them that they should not use any oaths at all, but
            that the truth should be spoken amongst them with quiet speech. For we learn from the
            commandments of <persName>God</persName> that we should conduct ourselves with all propriety and holiness and
            humility and patience. And let us have this eagerness continually, that <persName>God</persName> may in
            nothing be despised by us through the transgression of His commandments. For he hath
            denied his <persName>Lord</persName>, who teaches his companions that they should do things which <milestone
               unit="folio" n="34a"/> his Lord hath not commanded to be done. Now whilst they were
            learning these commandments every day from her, the brethren who were with her were the
            more confirmed in their faith and in their love and in good works. For neither by day
            nor by night did she cease from prayer and from the reading of the Scriptures. Now
            whilst she was living such a life, there was given to her by means of the grace of <persName>God</persName>
            the gift of healing, so that she cast out demons from men by means of the sign of the
            cross of our <persName>Lord</persName>, and health was given from <persName>God</persName> by her hands to those who were sick and
            afflicted. But because our word is not sufficient to describe the excellency of each one
            of her first works, such as they were, we leave them and we come briefly to relate her
            chaste and holy deeds.</p>
         <p n="26">Now the wife of a certain senator who was very rich in goods and in much wealth,
            whose name was <persName>Melania</persName>, had been sick of a fever and of an ague for a long time. She
            heard about the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName>, that our <persName>Lord</persName> wrought <milestone unit="folio" n="34b"/>
            healing by her hand to those who were afflicted; and she sent for her. And the blessed
            <persName>Eugenia</persName> did not decline to go at once with those who came for her. And when she entered
            her presence and saw her, she immediately signed <pb n="16"/>the sign of the cross on
            the breast and betwixt the eyes of <persName>Melania</persName> and prayed. And immediately her fever fled
            from her with her ague, and she was quickly made whole from her sickness.</p>
         <p n="27">And immediately the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> returned swiftly to her monastery. But after
            these things that had happened <persName>Melania</persName> was sending continually to the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName>
            and bringing her to her [self] not knowing that she was a woman. Now <persName>Eugenia</persName> went to her
            in the sincerity of her heart and in the uprightness of her soul. But <persName>Melania</persName> was not
            sending and fetching her with a sincere mind, nor yet as believing that by her prayers
            she had been healed of her sickness. But as she supposed that she was a man she spoke
            unseemly words to her, for she said, <quote>Why dost <milestone unit="folio" n="35a"/> thou
               trouble and vex thyself uselessly with fasting, and spoilest the appearance of thy
               youth? Does <persName>God</persName> perchance love sad people, and those whose faces are miserable; or is He
               pleased with those who make their bodies lean with hunger? Or is He glorified in those
               who flee from the marriage-bed? Nor does He magnify those who crucify themselves more
               than their companions. Does He command every man that he should accomplish the period of
               his life without joy and comfort? Let us then draw nigh and make use of the good things
               of this world which are given to us by <persName>God</persName>, that we may not be like ungrateful people
               and like people who are unworthy of His gifts that are beside us. Believe henceforth to
               thy advantage and thy profit in those things which are spoken to thee by me. For when
               thou shalt be with me in one love, thou shalt be heir of all that I possess. And good
               times of enjoyment and of gladness shall pass over thee. And thou shalt be lord of all
               my possessions. Also of myself who am speaking to thee, and am persuading <milestone
                  unit="folio" n="35b"/> thee. For I am adorned with beauty and with loveliness <pb
                     n="17"/>and with gladness, and I have endless riches. And I consider that this is not
               wickedness; and it is not sin before <persName>God</persName>, if thou wilt be my husband. And when thou
               shalt cast away from thee this mind in which thou hast been stedfast for many years thou
               shalt enjoy good things.</quote></p>
         <p n="28">But when <persName>Melania</persName> had said these things and more than these in her madness and her
            magical art, the <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName> rose up in much agitation, and withstood the words of
            perdition and of death with which <persName>Melania</persName> was clothed, and she wished to free the soul
            of the latter from corruption. And she tried to persuade her and said: The desires of
            this world are destroyers of the souls of men. And wherein a man thinks that he seizes
            for a little while the transitory desires of this world, he robs himself of the
            enjoyment which passes not away for all eternity. Therefore let us not seek bodily
            desires at all, because <persName>Satan</persName> our enemy endeavours by them to sink and destroy the souls
            of men. When these words were <milestone unit="folio" n="36a"/> spoken passionately by
            <persName>Eugenia</persName>, <persName>Melania</persName> shut her ear that she might not receive what was spoken to her. For her
            thoughts were bound with strong fetters of shameful desires. As it is written, to a
            guilty soul wisdom entereth not.</p>
         <p n="29">But <persName>Eugenia</persName> endeavoured and made a struggle that she might turn her if possible
            from the death of perdition towards salvation. And when she found no means of doing
            this, she departed from her, grieving about the destruction of her soul. But the mad
            <persName>Melania</persName> made herself sick and sent intercessors and persuaders to the <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName>,
            so that she might come and see her and pray over her and she might be healed. And she
            went into her presence with confidence, and sat down beside her in an inner apartment.
            And she took hold of <persName>Eugenia</persName> without shame and wished to embrace her secretly. And she
               <pb n="18"/><milestone unit="folio" n="36b"/>spoke to her unchaste and infamous words
            in her wicked-</p>
         <p n="30">Then the <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName> perceiving the treachery of <persName>Satan</persName> and the cunning of the
            mad woman his servant, stretched out her right hand and signed herself with the sign of
            the cross, and with weeping and with sobs said in a loud voice, Justly wert thou called
            <persName>Melania</persName>, for a heavy blackness and a putrid filth wells up within thee. Righteously art
            thou called <persName>Melania</persName>. For thou art the daughter of nameless sin and a guide to perdition
            to those who shall perish through thee, a daughter of ever-lasting <persName>Gehenna</persName>; a troubled
            spring of putridity, a fountain running with shame and overflowing, the enemy of <persName>God</persName> and
            the abode of the <persName>Evil one</persName>. For there is not even one good thing in thy heart, because
            thou art the dwelling-place of <persName>Satan</persName>. And thou art not worthy to have part or company
            with the servants of <persName>God</persName>.</p>
         <p n="31">Now when <persName>Melania</persName> had heard this contumely, she <milestone unit="folio" n="37a"
            />flamed into a great rage not enduring the shame that was hers. For she reflected that
            perhaps this rumour would come to the hearing of men, and she would become a reproach
            and a derision in the eyes of all her acquaintances. And she went at once to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>,
            and publicly in the sight of all the people she approached the governor of the city, and
            made an accusation before him against the <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName> and said: I denounce a certain
            young madman who has been saying of himself that he is a Christian. I sent for him and
            fetched him, that he might cure me; because I had been told about him that he could cure
            those who were pained and afflicted, and heal them of their sicknesses. And when I had
            commanded that he should enter my presence he immediately began to speak shameful and
            vile words and would have led me into disgrace. And why is it necessary for me to say
               <pb n="19"/>more? For at last he wished in his madness to assault me like a slave,
            and if a certain girl had not happened to be with me in my chamber, by whose help I
            escaped from <milestone unit="folio" n="37b"/> his hands and he prevailed not against
            me, he would otherwise, as his lasciviousness inclined, have wrought his pleasure on
            me.</p>
         <p n="32">Now when the governor had heard this accusation, he was greatly troubled. And he
            sent a troop of soldiers and commanded that she and all who were with her should be
            bound in iron fetters, and they should come speedily and their cause should be heard
            before all the people; and afterwards they should be cast to the wild beasts. But when
            the day arrived on which it was decreed concerning them, that the examination of the
            <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName> and of all those who were with her should take place, having put iron
            fetters on all their limbs and having bound them tight, they brought them in and made
            them stand up in the court in the sight of all the people. And when the crowd of people
            who had come together on their account saw them, not knowing the truth of what had
            happened, they lifted up their voice together and cried out against them, but those who
            were on the side of the mad <persName>Melania</persName> were shouting the more, and some of them were
               <milestone unit="folio" n="38a"/> crying that they should be cast into the fire, and
            be put to death in it, and their lives should perish, others were crying out that they
            should be food for the wild beasts. And others said that they should be punished with
            severe and bitter punishments, as was befitting their impudence. For with one consent
            the mind of all the people was against them, as against people who had done something
            worthy of death. Then the governor commanded that the clamour of the people should
            cease; and when they were quiet from what they were excited about, they brought in the
            <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName> and set her in the court <pb n="20"/>before the governor openly in the
            sight of all the people. And he began to question her, saying: What confidence induced
            thee to approach the patrician lady <persName>Melania</persName> for the purpose of offering her this wicked
            outrage? Thou didst enter in the deceitful dress of the Christians, and as one skilful
            in the craft of healing, that thou mightest bring a <milestone unit="folio" n="38b"/>
            woman of the aristocracy to the shame of wantonness.</p>
         <p n="33">Did the Christ perhaps teach you to do things like these? And is this the
            profession of your religion, that ye should do deeds of corruption and uncleanness?</p>
         <p n="34">But the <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName> returned an answer with much courage to the governor
            saying: I was praying that I might overcome all the temptations which should come on me
            into my mind and conquer them. And that I might reserve this accusation of calumny and
            oppression for the judgment that is to be. But in order that the purity of truth may not
            be abashed by those who out of an evil mind unjustly attack it; for purity which is
            guided by modesty cannot at all be hidden, for it will bring not merely the praise of
            men to those who love it, but it will be impelled to exist for the honour of <persName>God</persName> who
            gave it. For chastity and holiness and modesty are preserved completely by wise men, and
            the soul of the Christian perfects all her works faithfully in the love of <persName>God</persName>. I
               <milestone unit="folio" n="39a"/> declare this my mind publicly in the midst of and
            in the sight of all men. For by nature I am a woman. And I was not able to fulfil the
            desire of my soul regarding the fear of <persName>God</persName>, unless I changed myself into this chaste
            and honourable and excellent guise. And being a woman by nature, in order that I might
            gain everlasting life, I became a man for a short time, being emulous and imitating my
            teacher <persName>Thecla</persName>: she who despised and rejected the desires of this world, and became
            worthy of the good things of heaven by means of her chastity and her life. Therefore <pb
               n="21"/>I praised, Oh governor, every man who longs for the good things that are with
            <persName>God</persName>, and him who because of the love of the <persName>Christ</persName> hungers for so great excellence, and
            for the weakness which imitates the strength of full grown men. And because of this I
            also by the impulse of the love of <persName>God</persName> and by the fear of His sovereignty took the dress
            of an adult man in private and in public, keeping my virginity spotless to the <persName>Christ</persName> my
            Lord. <milestone unit="folio" n="39b"/></p>
         <p n="35">And when she had said these things, she rent the garment which she wore from the
            top as far as her girdle, and that which was hidden from the sight of men was instantly
            revealed, and the chaste breasts which were upon the bosom of a pure virgin were seen.
            And when she had done this, and convinced every one what she was, she at once swiftly
            covered and wrapped herself up with the rags which she had torn. And she continued and
            said to the governor: Thou art my own bodily father, and ye are my brothers <persName>Avita</persName> and
            <persName>Sergius</persName>. For I am thy daughter <persName>Eugenia</persName>, she who because of the love of <persName>Christ</persName> rejected
            this world and its desires with my two eunuchs <persName>Proteus</persName> and <persName>Hyacinthus</persName> who came with me
            to the covenant of the <persName>Christ</persName>, my Lord. And my <persName>Saviour Jesus the Christ</persName> has abundantly
            presented Himself to thee, that when I shall be to thee a teacher, the desire of the
            victory of the <milestone unit="folio" n="40a"/> <persName>Christ</persName>, him in whom I believe and hope
            that he will keep me in purity until the end, may in the presence of every one come upon
            thee.</p>
         <p n="36">Then the father recognized his daughter, and the brothers their sister. And they
            ran before all the people and embraced her, and kissed her weeping. This was also made
            known to her mother <persName>Claudia</persName>. And she ran in haste with her maid-servants to the theatre,
            and she also entered and wept before all the people, and embraced and kissed her weeping
            bitterly. And they brought costly <pb n="22"/>robes and clothed her against her will.
            And in order that she might be seen by all men they lifted her and placed her on a high
            place. And all the people when they saw her shouted with a loud voice saying, One is our
            <persName>Lord, Jesus the Christ</persName>, the true God of the Christians.</p>
         <p n="37">Now the Bishops, and the priests, and the deacons, and all the people of the
            Christians were sitting outside the theatre watching that when the saints should be put
            to <milestone unit="folio" n="40b"/>death they might take their corpses, and bury
            them.</p>
         <p n="38">They also went into the theatre praising and blessing <persName>God</persName> and saying, <!-- There is are start quotation marks here but no end quotations in this or the following paragraphs. Where should the end quotation marks go?-->"Thy right
            hand, O <persName>Lord</persName>! hath done mighty things; Thy right hand, O <persName>Lord</persName>! hath broken thine
            enemies. Now that the <persName>Blessed one</persName> hath been exalted above all men it has happened by the
            providence of <persName>God</persName> that by her modesty and by her dignity all who behold her might be
            helped. And that the glory of such modesty should not be concealed, all men seeing it,
            fire fell from heaven and burnt up <persName>Melania</persName> and all her house, and all that belonged to
            her. And there was great joy among all the people, and the church that had been closed
            eight years before was opened. And every one believed in the <persName>Christ</persName>, and became a
            Christian. And the Eparch was baptized, and his sons <persName>Avitus</persName> and <persName>Sergius</persName>. And <persName>Claudia</persName>,
            the mother of the <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName>, was baptized also, with all her hand-maidens; and
            people of the heathen without number were turned to <persName>God</persName>.</p>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="41a"/>
         <p n="39">And the Christians recovered their privileges and were singing praises as of old
            with their former customs, and all <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> was like one church, and the presbyters
            only were governing and serving the church. For he who previously had been called of <persName>God</persName>
            as by the law and had been bishop, had died in the <persName>Lord</persName>. Then all the churches came
            together to <persName>Philip the Governor</persName> that he might be bishop over them. And when he became
            (bishop) <pb n="23"/>by the grace of <persName>God</persName> which had called him, the holy Church held him
            in great honour. But though he was deemed worthy of this excellent degree of the
            Episcopacy, he also governed the affairs of the city, because that until now he held the
            command of the province. For he who should remove him from the command of the province
            had not yet arrived from the Emperors.</p>
         <p n="40">And at length all the inhabitants of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> were <milestone unit="folio" n="41b"/>
            converted by this means to the truth of the <persName>Christ</persName> from the religion of idols; and the
            churches in all the cities and villages which eight years before had been shut by the
            heathen the persecutors of the truth, were opened; and every day Christianity flourished
            and increased.</p>
         <p n="41">And whilst all these reformations were taking place by the grace of the <persName>Christ</persName>,
            in all the churches of that country, <persName>Satan</persName>, the persecutor of good things and teacher of
            hateful things, and secret conspirer of evil things, awakened some heathens amongst the
            chief men of the city, and incited them to make it known to the Emperors, the Rulers of
            that time, and these erring heathen did everything with envy against the church of <persName>God</persName>
            and against the holy bishop <persName>Philip</persName>. And there was sent against the blessed bishop <persName>Philip</persName>
            a man who should depose him from the command of the province, whose name was <persName>Perinus</persName>,
            for the Emperors had given him power, that if what they had heard against <persName>Philip</persName> from
            the chief men of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, were true, when he should reach him he should immediately
            slay him <milestone unit="folio" n="42a"/> with the sword. Then <persName>Perinus</persName> arrived and
            entered the city with much pomp and pride. But he was not able to effect at once what
            had been commanded by the Emperors against <persName>Philip</persName>, because all the people of the city
            loved him greatly, and held him in great honour as a good shepherd and a diligent
            governor. Now when <persName>Perinus</persName> saw that he was not able to kill him publicly, <pb n="24"/>he
            sent with guile against him wicked and rascally men who were dressed in the honourable
            fashion of the Christians. And when they had entered his presence in the church, they
            found the Blessed one standing in fervent prayer before <persName>God</persName>. And when they approached
            him, that they might receive a blessing, they immediately struck him and killed him, as
            <persName>Zacharia</persName> was slain between the temple and the altar. He was in the office of a bishop
            one year and three months. And as he died in the confession and witnessing for the
            <persName>Christ</persName>, he went to his <persName>Lord</persName> in peace.</p>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="42b"/>
         <p n="42">But the <persName>Blessed Eugenia</persName> took up the body of her martyr-father, and wrapped it up
            carefully, and placed it by the side of the hostel which had been made by her mother
            <persName>Claudia</persName> for the comfort of strangers and afflicted people, close to a place which was
            called <placeName>Natira</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> And by the solicitude of her
            brothers <persName>Avitus</persName> and <persName>Sergius</persName>, a regal martyr-shrine was built upon it to the glory of the
            <persName>Christ</persName>, and for the help and edification of the souls of men. And when all these things
            were effectually finished, the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> with her mother <persName>Claudia</persName> and her brothers
            <persName>Avitus</persName> and <persName>Sergius</persName> went up from <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> to <placeName>Rome</placeName>, the grace of <persName>God</persName> accompanying them,
            through which they found favour before all the senate. And they were greatly welcomed by
            all men, so that one of them became proconsul in <placeName>Carthage</placeName> a city of <placeName>Africa</placeName>, and the
            other was appointed with honour over the country of <placeName>Africa</placeName>.</p>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="43a"/>
         <p n="43">But <persName>Claudia</persName> and <persName>Eugenia</persName> her daughter by the commandment of <persName>God</persName> were occupied
            every day with good works and chaste deeds which are pleasing to <persName>God</persName>. And they were
            turning many souls from the fear of idols and were bringing them near to <persName>God</persName>. And they
            were praised <pb n="25"/>by all the noble women of senatorial rank and by all the
            virgins amongst the chiefs, and they were all zealous to imitate their life in the fear
            of the <persName>Christ</persName>.</p>
         <p n="44">But a certain virgin named <persName>Basilia</persName>, near of kin to the <persName>Emperor Gallienus</persName>, who was
            very prudent and wise, came secretly to the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName>, and heard from her the word
            of truth. And immediately she was rooted in love in the depth of her understanding, and
            she believed fully in the <persName>Christ</persName>, so that no man was able from that time to uproot from
            within her heart the plant of faith in <persName>God</persName>. But because <persName>Basilia</persName> could not continually be
            seeing <persName>Eugenia</persName>, <persName>Eugenia</persName> gave <persName>Proteus</persName> and <persName>Hyacinthus</persName> her <milestone unit="folio" n="43b"
            /> two eunuchs as a present to <persName>Basilia</persName> the virgin: and from that time, by day and by
            night, she was constant in the praise of <persName>God</persName> and in prayers and in reading of the sacred
            books.</p>
         <p n="45">Then the bishop of the city, whose name was <persName>Soter</persName>, a pure and holy man, who was
            very eminent in the fear of <persName>God</persName> and in the training of the teaching of the sacred books
            of theology, came to <persName>Basilia</persName>, and baptized her in the holy font, for the pardon of
            trespasses and for the remission of sins, and from the sacred books of theology he
            confirmed the minds of all who were with her in the faith of the <persName>Christ</persName>, so that they
            all together were prepared to go forward and to become willing martyrs. All the time
            that <persName>Bishop Soter</persName> presided over the church, the Christians were in tranquility and
            peace, for not one vexation was aroused against them by the enemies. But <persName>Bishop Cyprian</persName> in the city of <placeName>Carthage</placeName> endured many sufferings and afflictions because of the faith of
            <persName>God</persName>. For <milestone unit="folio" n="44a"/> <persName>Maximus</persName> the Pro-consul by command of the
            Emperors who ordered him by means of letters, slew the holy <persName>Bishop Cyprian</persName>. Then <persName>Bishop
               Soter</persName> when he heard these things hid himself, and lived alone, but he taught many of the
            Roman citizens, honourable men, secretly. Now on a <pb n="26"/>certain day <persName>Basilia</persName> came
            to the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName>, and when she saw her she received her with great joy. And
            <persName>Eugenia</persName> answered and said to her, This day our <persName>Lord</persName> has made known to me clearly that
            from thy face which is like a rose much blood will be shed. Now this means that thou
            shalt have contended and conquered in the confession of the <persName>Christ</persName>, thou shalt receive
            from Him the crown of victory of thy martyrdom with joy.</p>
         <p n="46">Now when the blessed <persName>Basilia</persName> had heard these things from the holy <persName>Eugenia</persName>, she
            lifted up her hands to heaven and praised <persName>God</persName> with great joy. Now when they had
               <milestone unit="folio" n="44b"/> prayed and finished their prayer, they sat down,
            and <persName>Basilia</persName> said to <persName>Eugenia</persName>, <quote>To both of us as I see, our <persName>Lord</persName> and <persName>our Redeemer Jesus
               the Christ</persName> has revealed and shown us the glory of our crowns. For as thou hast seen
               regarding me, so also to me the <persName>Christ</persName> has already made known the time of thy departure.
               For I saw that thou didst receive two crowns from heaven, one because of the struggle
               for thy virginity which thou hast made, and hast kept it spotless to the <persName>Christ</persName>; and
               the other one because thou shalt struggle in the conflict, and shalt conquer the enemy,
               and thy blood will be shed because of the <persName>Christ</persName>. These things thou art about to
               receive.</quote></p>
         <p n="47">Now when the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> had heard these things, she rejoiced and exulted
            greatly, and called all the virgins who had been drawn to the fear of <persName>God</persName> by her means
            and who longed to preserve their virginity pure to the <persName>Christ</persName>, and persuaded them that
            they should pray with her, and commit her in their prayer to <persName>God</persName>. And after they had
            finished their prayer, she began to talk with them, saying to them: Now the time of
            vintage has arrived in which the <milestone unit="folio" n="45a"/> first-fruits are to
            be gathered, about which our <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName> hath made known to me by means of the
            mysteries <pb n="27"/>which He hath revealed to us beforehand. And now, my beloved ones
            and my disciples, send ye me in the first place before you to our <persName>Lord</persName>. And be ye also
            watching and making ready that ye may go out to meet the <persName>Christ</persName>, your betrothed, whilst
            your lamps are shining. For the beauty of virginity appears first of all before <persName>God</persName>, for
            it is the likeness of the angels which are in heaven. And it is near to <persName>God the
               Almighty</persName>, and it is akin to the life that is about to be revealed, and the mother of
            modesty and the teacher of purity. And a mistress<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/>
            without care, and the height of happiness, and zealous for chastity, and the illustrious
            crown of faith, the hope and succour and honour of those who love it; the glory of the
            soul, and eternal rest, the cause of good things and the guide to the kingdom of heaven.
            Let there be for you no other labour and urgency like this, that you may keep your
            virginity purely and holily to the <persName>Christ the Son of <persName>God</persName></persName> your betrothed. For there are
            in this world incitements and wicked desires, which remain for a short time with their
               <milestone unit="folio" n="45b"/> lovers, and afterwards beget weeping and sobbings
            in the <placeName>Gehenna</placeName> of fire. These in their beginnings appear exhilarating to men, but in the
            end they torture those who do them with bitter punishments and sore torments which are
            endless. For they do their deeds without care in this transitory world that they may be
            condemned completely in everlasting endless torture. And now, my daughters, honoured
            virgins, who bravely and believingly keep your virginity along with me, remain in the
            love of each other and in the love of <persName>God</persName> in which ye dwell and in which ye are
            abundantly confirmed. For it is time now that ye mourn and cry to <persName>God</persName> because of the
            former time which has passed away, when error had fast hold of you, that ye may be
            filled with everlasting joy, before <pb n="28"/>the face of <persName>God Almighty</persName>. But I have
            committed you to the <persName>Holy Spirit of <persName>God</persName></persName>, whilst I believe and it is certain to me that
            He will receive you in His kingdom <milestone unit="folio" n="46a"/> spotless and
            blameless. Therefore do not seek for my bodily appearance but let each of the beautiful
            examples that I have shown you in my day be continually before your face. And remember
            my teaching, humble though I be, and love it every day.</p>
         <p n="48">When she had taught these things and things like them and had committed them (to
            <persName>God</persName>) she kissed them all with a holy kiss weeping. After she had saluted them, she said:
            Be ye sound and true in our <persName>Lord</persName>, my daughters and my sisters, for <persName>Basilia</persName> and <persName>Eugenia</persName>
            your sisters are departing from this world to our <persName>Lord</persName>. But at that time, one of the
            maidens of <persName>Basilia</persName> went to <placeName>Pompeius</placeName> her betrothed and said to him, Dost thou know that
            thy betrothed, the <persName>Lady Basilia</persName>, has been persuaded by <persName>Eugenia</persName> to decline to be thy
            wife? And when <persName>Pompeius</persName> heard these things from that girl, he was greatly troubled and
            angry at <persName>Eugenia</persName>, and was sore distressed because of <persName>Basilia</persName> his betrothed. And he went
            to her and wished to enter the chamber where <persName>Basilia</persName> and <persName>Proteus</persName> and <persName>Hyacinthus</persName> were
            performing their customary prayers and <milestone unit="folio" n="46b"/> praises. He
            found the doors closed and he knocked at the door and wished to enter their presence.
            But the blessed <persName>Basilia</persName> sent to him (saying), If thou art come in order to see me, know
            that I have fully renounced thee. And I cannot do otherwise, because of my faith in <persName>our
               Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>. And when he had heard these things, he departed thence in great
            rage and vexation. And he sent to call the wives of the senators and some of the noble
            women of the city, and he persuaded them and sent them to her, that they should enter in
            and speak with her words of persuasion and advise her to become his wife. <pb n="29"
            />And when these noble women came to speak to her words of persuasion and
            reconciliation, so that she might become wife to her betrothed, the blessed <persName>Basilia</persName>
            replied [in] these words to the noble women, saying to them: There is a great difference
            between the ignorant and the wise people, for the ignorant do not care to receive good
            things, nor do they wish to decline the evil things, but wise men enquire about good
            things, and progress towards excellent things, and suddenly they completely renounce
            [them]. For if this appear to you to be good, that I should <milestone unit="folio"
               n="47a"/> take for my betrothed a certain mortal and transient man, how much better
            will it appear to you, that I should take to myself the Bridegroom who dieth not, and
            remaineth for ever. I rejoice and exult that in my soul I have decided this, that I
            should be betrothed alone to the Bridegroom who dieth not; to Him who is our <persName>Lord Jesus
               the Christ</persName>; and I have committed my soul with my body to Him: and thus I am eager to
            keep them spotless to Him. For I see that everything in this world is transient and
            perishing, and its joy lasts but a short time. Why then have we not hope to get
            possessions over which death has no power, and which last for ever? For with which of
            mankind remain the blessings of this world and comfort him? those which flourish a
            little while, and quickly hastily wither. For this reason ye who have wisdom <milestone
               unit="folio" n="47b"/> and understanding see with the good eye of your minds and
            consider what hath been spoken to you by me. Be not ye now walking in the broad path of
            the good things of this world, neither have ye any reliance on what is seen, to which
            the weakness and inexperience of men devotes itself. But [be ye] those who forsake human
            things and place their hope in <persName>God Almighty</persName>, He who sent His only One, our <persName>Lord Jesus
               the Christ</persName>, to us, that He might show us the way of truth in which we should <pb n="30"
            />walk confidently, and that through Him we might know the true faith and the perfect
            love which we have, in whom we are eager for this true faith, and we have great
            solicitude on this account that we may keep it spotless and blameless, by the strength
            and the help which is given to us by the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>. Let no man therefore advise us
            that I should be neglectful of Him whom I confess, who is our <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>, Son
            of the <milestone unit="folio" n="48a"/> living <persName>God</persName>, He who was born of <persName>Mary</persName> the holy
            Virgin whilst she remained in her uncontaminated virginity. For our <persName>Lord</persName> was born from
            her by His own will, as a man; and was worshipped as a king by the shepherds and by the
            Magi. He was submissive as a disciple whilst He was a learned man and a teacher. He was
            tempted as a mortal, and He conquered death as an immortal. He was sold as a slave, and
            He came in glory as Lord and God. He was thought to be a prophet, whilst <persName>His Spirit</persName>
            spake by the prophets. And He was anointed as <persName>the Messiah</persName>, whilst He anointed kings and
            priests and prophets. He suffered and died as a man, and was raised and arose like <persName>God</persName>.
            But lest men should go on in the footsteps of the Jews, the crucifiers, whilst all His
            disciples were together gazing at Him, He was taken up from them to heaven and sitteth
            at the right hand of <persName>His Father</persName>. They are those who by their martyrdom have sealed the
            truth of this; for after His ascension to <persName>His Father</persName>, He gave light and eyesight to the
            blind, He offered health to the pained and <milestone unit="folio" n="48b"/> the sick.
            They scared away demons from men by their commandment and by their seals; they cleansed
            the lepers; they raised the dead; that by means of all these things which were done by
            their hands we may know how much love and care <persName>God</persName> has for us. And He wishes for us that
            we should be heirs of the kingdom of heaven.</p>
         <p n="49">And when the blessed <persName>Basilia</persName> had spoken all these <pb n="31"/>glorious things to
            the noble women who were listening to her, then suddenly by the love of the <persName>Christ</persName> their
            minds waxed fervent in spirit and they did not wish henceforth to go to their homes; nor
            were they minded to return an answer from themselves to <persName>Pompeius</persName>. But when <persName>Pompeius</persName> had
            taken the evidence of all these women of senatorial rank he went before the Emperors,
            and cast himself on his face before them, saying, Help us, O ye Emperors victorious and
            merciful to us your own people of <placeName>Rome</placeName>, be prompt and put away from this city the new
            gods which <persName>Eugenia</persName> has brought from <placeName>Egypt</placeName>. For there are found gods who prohibit men
            from begetting children, and if men are hindered from begetting children <milestone
               unit="folio" n="49a"/> how will there be a renewal to <placeName>Rome</placeName>? And how will the army of
            the Romans be increased and grow? by means of which conflicts are carried on, and by
            which the victorious right hand of your Divinity subdues in battle the hosts of the
            foreign enemies which oppose it. If therefore conjugal intercourse [be lawful] to us,
            let thy majesty command "take thy betrothed bride," and from to-day and henceforth we
            shall be at peace, and the Christians may do as they please.</p>
         <p n="50">And when <persName>Pompeius</persName> had said these things and more in his accusation, the <persName>Emperor
            Gallienus</persName> commanded [him] to take his betrothed <persName>Basilia</persName>, and that if she did not wish to
            be his wife, she should be slain with the sword. Then a decree went forth from the
            Emperor concerning <persName>Eugenia</persName>, that she should sacrifice to the gods, but that if she
            should contumaciously resist, and should not wish to sacrifice, she should be tormented
            with bitter punishments and with severe tortures, as her temerity deserved, and at the
            last she also should be condemned to death with the sword. Again a command went forth
            from the Emperor that if any man of the Christians should <milestone unit="folio"
               n="49b"/><pb n="32"/>introduce another religion and should not wish to sacrifice to
            the gods, he should be deprived of dear life by means of various tortures. But the
            blessed <persName>Basilia</persName> refused every day to become the wife of <persName>Pompeius</persName> her betrothed. For many
            days she was tormented by persuasive words of many people. On one day she was harassed
            by women of senatorial rank and on another day by women who were neighbours and
            relatives, who advised her to obey the command of the Emperor, and to become the wife of
            her betrothed.</p>
         <p n="51">And why is it necessary for us to say more? For by the wisdom and providence and
            grace of <persName>God</persName> which accompanied and assisted her, she overcame all these persuasions and
            blandishments. Because she was of the imperial family, and she could not be interrogated
            and judged publicly, the Emperor commanded that she should be beheaded with the sword in
            the interior of her house, and according to the commandment of the iniquitous Emperor
            her head was taken off with the sword.</p>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="50a"/>
         <p n="52">But when the blessed <persName>Basilia</persName> had died in the confession of our <persName>Lord Jesus the
            Christ</persName>, a commandment went forth again concerning <persName>Proteus</persName> and <persName>Hyacinthus</persName>, that they also
            should sacrifice to the gods; but if they should resist the commandment and should not
            wish to sacrifice, they also should die by the sword. But when the blessed ones did not
            consent at all to sacrifice according to the commandment of the tyrant, severe tortures
            and bitter torments were applied to their bodies, [and] at last they were beheaded with
            the sword. And when these blessed ones had died blissfully in the confession of our <persName>Lord
               Jesus the Christ</persName>, the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> also was apprehended and brought before <persName>Anicetus</persName>,
            Eparch of the city. And he commanded that she should go immediately and sacrifice to the
            goddess <persName>Artemis</persName>.</p>
         <pb n="33"/>
         <p n="53">But when the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> came to that place and went into the temple she
            turned to the east and lifted up her hands to heaven and prayed for a long time. Now
            when she had finished her prayer, the image of <persName>Artemis</persName> fell and was broken, and it was
            ground so fine that even its powder could not be perceived. But those who did not
            <milestone unit="folio" n="50b"/> understand the power of <persName>God</persName>, thought it the craft
            of magic; and he commanded that they should tie a great stone on the neck of the blessed
            <persName>Eugenia</persName> and that she should be thrown into the river <placeName>Tiber</placeName>. But when they carried her
            and threw her in, immediately her bonds were broken, and the stone which they had hung
            round her neck fell; but the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> was walking and going on the top of the
            water. Now when all the Christians saw this great sign that took place, they were filled
            with joy and exultation, and they praised <persName>God</persName> with a loud voice, saying, Great is the
            <persName>God</persName> of truth, who hath helped <persName>Eugenia</persName> His handmaiden, and hath not left her to perish,
            as He was with <persName>Peter</persName> in the sea, and did not leave him to sink. But when she went and
            came on the water, and reached the banks of the river, and emerged and stood on the firm
            land, the servants of the tyrant seized her immediately and conveyed her to prison. But
            the Eparch commanded that the bath which is called <milestone unit="folio" n="51a"/> of
            <persName>Severianus</persName> should be heated strongly until its colour became like the colour of iron
            which is heated in the fire; and that she should be cast in there and perish and be
            consumed by the blast of the flame. And when the command of the tyrant was fulfilled,
            they brought the blessed one and threw her into that bath. But immediately when she
            entered into it, the flame of the fire was quenched before her, so that henceforth it
            could not be kindled through the great cold that was in it by the commandment of
            <persName>God</persName>.</p>
         <p n="54">But when the handmaid of the <persName>Christ</persName> had conquered also this device of the erring
            ones, he commanded that she <pb n="34"/>should go to the prison; and there be cast into
            the dark cell, and that no bread and no water should be given to her. But when she
            entered into the house, that house was immediately filled with great light. And the
            blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> was in that prison twenty days, whilst that light shone there every day.
            And an angel of the <persName>Lord</persName> appeared to her, strengthening her and saying, Hail to thee, O
            <milestone unit="folio" n="51b"/> handmaid of <persName>God</persName>, <persName>Eugenia</persName>, for our <persName>Lord Jesus the
               Christ</persName>, He whom thou hast loved with all thy heart, and hast served with all thy soul,
            hath sent me<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> to thee, and saith, Be courageous and
            be strong, <persName>Eugenia</persName>, for to-day thou shalt ascend to heaven, gaining the victory over the
            enemy.</p>
         <p n="55">But on that day, which was the birth-day of the <persName>Christ</persName>, the Eparch commanded that
            one of the executioners should go, and there in the prison slay her with the sword. And
            when the blessed one had died<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> by means of the sword
            in the prison according to the command of the Eparch, the Christians heard (of it) and
            they came and took up the body of the holy <persName>Eugenia</persName>, and they carried it in triumph as
            something they had found, and laid it in a beautiful place which was not far from the
            city, on the road which is called the <placeName>Latina</placeName>.</p>
         <p n="56">Now her mother <persName>Claudia</persName> was sitting at the grave and weeping. And the blessed
            <persName>Eugenia</persName> appeared to her and said to her, Rejoice and exult, my mother, for our <persName>Lord
               Jesus the Christ</persName> has exalted me to the rest and joy of the saints; <milestone
                  unit="folio" n="52a"/>and has placed my father <persName>Philip</persName> in the host of just and
            righteous fathers. And as for thee, on the coming first day of the week<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> He will receive thee in peace. And command my
            brothers, <persName>Avita</persName> and <persName>Sergius</persName>, to keep the seal of the <persName>Christ</persName> which they have received,
            that by means of it they may be worthy to become partakers and heirs of the kingdom of
            heaven, with all the martyrs and confessors. But <pb n="35"/><persName>Claudia</persName> went up to her
            house, and informed her sons according as the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName> had informed [her]. And on
            the first day of the week as they were consummating the glorious mysteries of the
            divinity, while she was standing in the church and praying, she committed her spirit to
            the <persName>Lord</persName> of all spirits, who is our <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>; and her sons took her up, and
            laid her beside their sister, whilst they also excelled in good works and were pleasing
            to <persName>God</persName>, so that they converted many of the heathen from the impure sacrifices of idols;
            and taught them to believe in <persName>our Saviour and Redeemer</persName>, in<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n7"/> our <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>. And they received with joyful delight those
            who went <milestone unit="folio" n="52b"/> down to the baptismal font of holiness and
            were cleansed from their crimes and their sins, and gave them rest in their houses. But
            they did not cease to save every day the souls of men from the captivity of the dragon,
            the accursed calumniator, and they brought them near to the <persName>Christ</persName> their Lord. But they
            also were counted worthy to imitate the excellent deeds of their father, and of their
            sister; and to inherit the portion and the bliss of the saints together with them. For
            they pleased the <persName>Christ</persName> in their life; and they entered and mingled with the glorious
            hosts of the just and the righteous. May we also be worthy to be heirs with them of the
            kingdom of heaven, by the grace and tender mercy of our <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>! with whom
            also to <persName>the Father</persName> be glory and honour and praise and exaltation with the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>
            now and in all time for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
         <p n="57">Here endeth the testimony of the blessed <persName>Eugenia</persName>, and of all the holy martyrs who
            were martyred with her: Glory to the <persName>Hidden One</persName> who was made manifest in our body; and
            we have seen Him who is invisible, visible in our body.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n8"/></p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">1 Literally <hi rend="doubleQuote">in the footsteps of thy Paternity.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n2">1 Perhaps <hi rend="doubleQuote">Nitria.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n3">1 Or <hi rend="doubleQuote">Martha.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n4">1 Cod. <hi rend="doubleQuote">us.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n5">2 Literally <hi rend="doubleQuote">was crowned.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n6">3 Or <hi rend="doubleQuote">Sunday.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n7">1 Literally <hi rend="doubleQuote">on.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n8">2 Or <hi rend="doubleQuote">in our visible body.</hi></note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
