<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Euphrosyne</title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreading and initial markup of persons, places, and titles by </resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#anorth">Adelaide North</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title level="a">Euphrosyne</title>
                  <title level="m"> Select Narratives of Holy Women from the Syro-Antiochene or
                     Sinai Palimpsest as Written above teh Old Syriac Gospels by John the Stylite,
                     of Beth-Mari-Qanūn in A.D. 778. </title> Translated by Anges Smith Lewis
                  M.R.A.S. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>C. J. Clay and Sons</publisher>
                  <date>1900</date>
                  <citedRange unit="p" from="46" to="59">46-59</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <p>This transcription renumbers the original footnotes to run sequentially and includes
               marginal references for Biblical citations among the footnotes.</p>
            <p>This text is in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="46"/>
         <p n="1">Again, the story of <persName>Euphrosyne</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.</p>
         <p n="2">Now there was once upon a time in the great city of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> a certain
            honourable man whose name was <persName>Paphnutius</persName>, and he was assiduous in fulfilling the
            commandments of <persName>God</persName>. And he took a wife who was modest and worthy of his choice, and she
            was of a well-known and honourable family, and she was barren and she did not bear [a
            child]; and her husband was in much concern and in sore vexation, because he had no son
            to whom he might leave his wealth, after his departure from the world, to dispose of his
            wealth properly to the needy. But when his wife saw her husband was vexed, she rested
            neither by night nor by day, being continually in the churches imploring with fasting
            and with prayer that <persName>God</persName> would grant her a child. She gave great wealth to the poor and
            to the sick, and distributed <milestone unit="folio" n="77a"/> it to holy dwellings and
            to monasteries. And in that city her husband also, when he passed by the churches and
            the monasteries, groaned and desired that he might meet with a monastery and might find
            a man who was worthy before <persName>God</persName> who was likely by means of his prayer to persuade <persName>God</persName> to
            grant him the desire of his heart. And at last he went to a certain monastery in which
            there was a famous Abbot. A certain great God-fearing monk was in it. And when he
            entered that monastery he gave him a benediction and he sat in an expansive and
            protracted conversation with the Abbot and with the brethren who were sitting with him.
            Then after a little while he revealed his secret to the Abbot, and he was <pb n="47"
            />inclined to his request that they should persuade <persName>God</persName> on his behalf, to grant them
            fruit of their loins. And <persName>God</persName> took pity on the request of the two and granted them one
            daughter.</p>
         <p n="3">Now when <persName>Paphnutius</persName> saw the good government and modest life of the Abbot, he did
            not go away from that convent. On this account also he brought his wife many times there
            to be blessed by the Abbot and by the brethren who were with him. When the girl was
            weaned and was about six years old they baptized her and called her name <persName>Euphrosyne</persName>. But
            her parents rejoiced greatly that she was beloved by <persName>God</persName> and was beautiful of
            countenance and was very lovely in her aspect.</p>
         <p n="4">Now when she was thirteen years old her mother departed from the world, and her
            father continued to educate and teach her in the Scriptures and the wisdom of <persName>God</persName>.
               <milestone unit="folio" n="77b"/> But the girl was worthy to be on the right side by
            nature and as the fruit of prayer. And she loved instruction to such a degree that her
            father admired her because of it. And her name was spread abroad in all the city because
            of her wisdom and love of learning. But yet more because of the great development of her
            stature, and the splendid beauty of her countenance. And many great and powerful men
            were attracted to love her, to betroth her as a bride for their sons, and many came to
            her father in order to get an advantage over each other in betrothing her to their sons.
            But he said to them, Let the will of <persName>God</persName> be done. Now one of the great men who was more
            excellent than them all in power, and in might, called her father and spoke with him
            about the matter; and [her father] was persuaded and betrothed her to his son, and he
            gave her a betrothal present. But a short time afterwards, when she was about eighteen
            years of age, her father led her and conducted her to that monastery, <pb n="48"/>and
            carried with her all good things to do honour to the Abbot and to the brethren who were
            with him. And whilst he was talking with them he said to the Abbot: Behold, I have
            brought to you the fruit of your prayers about which you prayed. If <persName>God</persName> wills, I wish to
            give her to a husband. And the Abbot commanded that they should lodge him in the hospice
            for strangers of the <milestone unit="folio" n="78a"/> convent, whilst he talked with
            the girl and blessed her and prayed for her. And he talked of many things with her about
            purity and virginity and the fear of <persName>God</persName>. And she progressed very greatly in her
            learning. When she had been in the convent three days she listened to the singing of
            their daily service, and she saw the beautiful assiduity of their conduct and she
            wondered at their virtues, saying, Blessed are these elect ones because that although
            they are in the world they have the likeness of angels; and after their departure from
            this world they are worthy of eternal life. And she began to repent in her heart,
            because of the fear of <persName>God</persName>.</p>
         <p n="5">But after three days <persName>Paphnutius</persName> said to the Abbot: Command, O spiritual father,
            concerning thy handmaiden that she may come to thee, and grant her the prayer of thy
            mouth. For it is our desire to go to the city. But when she came into the Abbot's
            presence, <persName>Euphrosyne</persName> threw herself down before his feet, saying to him, I beseech thee,
            father, pray for me that <persName>God</persName> may redeem my soul. And the Abbot raised his hands and
            said: <persName>God</persName> who knowest everything when it has not yet been, do Thou lead this Thy
            handmaid to grace, that she may please Thee and may be worthy to find a portion and an
            inheritance with those who please Thee. And they took leave of the Abbot and went away
            to their city. But her father, when he saw a hermit in the city, received <milestone
               unit="folio" n="78b"/> him and brought him into his house, and persuaded him <pb
               n="49"/>to pray for him and his daughter. But a certain day came when there was to be
            the commemoration of the monastery. And the Abbot sent a certain brother to bring
            <persName>Paphnutius</persName> to the commemoration and the vigil of the monastery. And when this brother
            went to his house and asked about him the young men said that he had gone out. But when
            <persName>Euphrosyne</persName> learnt about the arrival of that recluse she called him and recognized him,
            saying to him, <quote>About how many brethren are there in that monastery?</quote> And he said to
            her, <quote>Three hundred and fifty-two.</quote> And she said to him, <quote>Whosoever therefore wishes to
               go and dwell there, do they receive him, O father? And do you all therefore sing in one
               church? And do you keep one fast?</quote> The recluse said to her, <quote>The music is sung by all of
                  us in a congregation, but each [keeps] the fast as he wishes and can endure.</quote></p>
         <p n="6">Then when she had inquired about all the affairs of the monastery she said to the
            recluse, <quote>I could have wished that I were able to go out from this vain world, but I
               fear that my father wishes to give me to husbands because of the vain wealth of this
               world.</quote> The recluse said to her, <quote>Nay, my daughter, let not a man dishonour thy body,
                  and do not surrender such beauty to shameful passion, but be thou altogether in thy
                  purity a bride to the <persName>Christ</persName>, who is able to give thee instead of these transitory
                  <milestone unit="folio" n="79a"/>. things the kingdom of heaven. Therefore shave thy
                  head in secret and go to the monastery and thou shalt be saved.</quote> Now when she had heard
            these words she said to the hermit, <quote>And who will shave me? for I do not wish to be
               shaved by laymen, for they do not keep secrets.</quote> The hermit said to her, <quote>Behold I am
                  about to take thy father to the monastery, and he will be there three or four days. Thou
                  therefore send and call one of the recluses and thus as thou desirest he will arrange
                  for thy comfort.</quote> But <pb n="50"/>whilst Euphrosyne and the hermit were talking her
            father also arrived. And when Paphnutius saw the hermit, he recognized him and asked
            him, "What is the reason of the work of God's love in thee towards us?" The recluse said
            to him, "It is the vigil and commemoration of the monastery, and our father the Abbot
            sent us that thou shouldest come and enjoy his prayers with us." And when Paphnutius,
            the father of Euphrosyne, had heard it he rejoiced greatly. And he carried with him what
            was necessary for many days, and put it into a ship whilst he went to the monastery. And
            when Paphnutius arrived at that monastery he was blessed by the Abbot. And while
            Paphnutius was in the monastery Euphrosyne sent one of her faithful servants to the
            church where the recluses were assembled, the one which was called of Theodosius, and
               <milestone unit="folio" n="79b"/>said to that young man, "Look for the first hermit
            who meets thee in the church, take him and bring him to this place." And when the young
            man had gone as he was bidden, as if it were by the doing of God a very old man met him
            who was from Scete. Now when the boy who was sent by Euphrosyne saw the old man, he took
            him and brought him to her. And when the girl saw him she said to him, "Pray for me,
            father." And when he had prayed for her he sat down. But she said to the old man,
            "Father, I have a father and he is a servant of God, and he has great riches, and he had
            a wife and from her he begat me; and he wishes because of his riches to marry me in this
            sinful world. And I do not at all wish to be contaminated by the pollution of this
            world, and on the other hand I fear to rebel against my own father: and what I shall do
            I know not. For all this night I have been awake on account of this; whilst I implored
            of God that He would make known to me what is profitable for my poor soul. And after the
            light had dawned it was shown to <pb n="51"/>me that I should send to the church, and
            should fetch the first hermit who met me. And behold, as if by the guidance of God, thou
            hast been sent to us, and now I would persuade thee, father, teach me what will help
            me."</p>
         <p n="7">But when the old man had heard these words from her he began to talk with her,
            saying, "And what dost thou wish my daughter? When our Lord saith that whosoever
               <milestone unit="folio" n="80a"/> hateth not his father and his mother and his
            brethren and his sisters, and even his own life, he cannot be my disciple. But what
            business have I to say more than this to thee? If therefore thou art able to endure the
            temptations of the adversaries, leave everything and flee; for to the wealth of thy
            parents many heirs will be found. Lo! there are churches, and there are asylums for the
            poor, and there are prisons, and there are hospices, and there are monasteries, and
            there are orphans, and there are widows, and there are lepers, and there are sick
            people, and there are prisoners; let thy father leave them to whatsoever place it may
            please him. But only do not thou lose thy soul."</p>
         <p n="8">Euphrosyne said to him: "I hope in God by your prayers, that I am eager to save my
            soul." The old man said to her, "My daughter, if thou wilt do this, do it quickly,
            without delay, lest thou be prevented and prohibited through negligence from this
            beautiful purpose of thy heart." The girl said to the old man, "I brought thee here, my
            lord, for this purpose, that thou mightest accomplish the desire of my soul." And
            forthwith the old man rose up, engaged in prayer, shaved her, dressed her in a robe and
            prayed for her, saying, "May God who hath redeemed all the saints keep thee from evil."
            And when the old man had said these things he departed from her. Then Euphrosyne
            considered and said, "If it be that I am to go to a convent of women <pb n="52"
               /><milestone unit="folio" n="80b"/> my father will never cease to seek till he has
            found me, and he will snatch me away by force from the convent on account of my
            betrothed. But I will put myself into a domicile of men, in a place where no one will
            suspect me." And she took off women's clothes and wrapped herself in the garb of a man.
            And when it was evening she went forth from her house, taking with her five hundred
            dinars.</p>
         <p n="9">And in the morning her father arrived and came to his city, and as if it were by
            the direction of God he went at once to the church. And Euphrosyne his daughter went to
            the very monastery which her father loved. And she talked with the porter and said to
            him, "Brother, if it please thee, go and say to the Abbot that a certain eunuch from the
            palace is at the door outside and desires to speak to thee." And when the porter had
            entered and related her business to the Abbot, he commanded him to enter. And when he
            had entered, he threw himself down and did penance. And after a prayer had been offered
            they sat down. The Abbot said to her: "Why has the love of God that is in thee made thee
            trouble thyself about us?" She replied to him, "Father, I am from the palace, and I had
            a love for the garb of a recluse: and I knew our city does not know very well that a
            monastic community dwells in it. And I heard about thy Holiness and about this
            monastery, and I am come to be with you if it please you to accept me. I have great
            wealth, and if we are seated on our seats in the quiet of this dwelling I will bring it
            to <milestone unit="folio" n="81a"/>the door." The Abbot said to him: "Thou hast done
            well in coming, my son: behold the monastery is before thee, if it seem good in thine
            eyes, abide with us." And again the Abbot said to him: "My son, what is thy name?"
            "Esmeraldus," he replied. The Abbot said, "Since thou art so young, and thou canst not
            dwell alone, it is expedient <pb n="53"/>for thee to have an older man with thee, that
            he may teach thee the rule of monasticism." "I will do as thou desirest," said the
            blessed one. And Esmeraldus brought out the five hundred dinars and gave them into the
            hands of the Abbot, saying, "Take these, father, and do as thou wilt with them, and if I
            know that I can live quietly here, I will bring also the remainder."</p>
         <p n="10">Then the Abbot called a certain brother whose name was Agapius, a sensible man,
            and delivered over Esmeraldus to him, saying, "Let this man be henceforth thy son and
            thy disciple." And he bent the knee and prayed, and Agapius took him away to his cell
            because his face was covered with beauty like an emerald. And when he came into the
            refectory Satan made many to stumble at his beauty, so that they complained against the
            Abbot, that he had received such a fair and beautiful face into the monastery, and when
            the Abbot learnt it he called for Esmeraldus and said to him, "The fair beauty of thy
            face has occasioned many falls to those who are not well established. I therefore desire
            thee to dwell in a separate cell at some distance from [the monastery] and thou may est
               <milestone unit="folio" n="81b"/> be quiet and sing hymns there and eat; and do not
            let thyself be seen by the brethren." And he ordered Agapius to prepare a separate cell
            so that Esmeraldus might dwell in it.</p>
         <p n="11">Then Agapius did all that he was commanded to do by the Abbot, and he conducted
            Esmeraldus and led him into a cell. And whilst he was occupying this cell he was very
            zealous and constant in fasting, vigil, and prayer, and in sleeping on the ground, and
            in the reading of the sacred Scriptures; and was praising God by night and by day, so
            that Agapius saw the assiduity of Esmeraldus and the great excess of his humility, and
            was amazed. He related to the brethren all about his great zeal, and by this they made
            progress and were instructed.</p>
         <pb n="54"/>
         <p n="12">But the father of Euphrosyne arrived at dinner-time and went into his house. And
            when he did not find his daughter he asked his servants, "Where is Euphrosyne, my
            daughter?" And they said to him, "We saw her last evening, but since the morning we have
            not seen her." Then her father thought that perhaps her betrothed had come and taken her
            away; and he sent to inquire about this matter. But when the father of her betrothed and
            his son heard this they were greatly disquieted, and they arose and came in haste to the
            house of Paphnutius, and found that he had flung himself on the earth and was in tears.
            And he said, "Perhaps some man has deceived her and taken her away and fled with her."
            He sent horsemen instantly through all Egypt and to the provinces, and he sent ships and
            skiffs on the sea in quest of her, and the nunneries and the churches and the caves and
            the deserts <milestone unit="folio" n="82a"/> were searched; and they inquired about her
            of their friends and neighbours, and they searched for her over all the city. But no
            searcher found her.</p>
         <p n="13">Now when they had sought for her in every place and had not found her, they
            wailed and wept for her as for one dead. The father-in-law wept for his daughter-in-law,
            the father wailed for his daughter, saying, "Woe is me, my fondly loved daughter! Woe is
            me for the light of my eyes! Woe is me for the consolation and solace of my soul! Who is
            he that hath robbed me of my treasure? Who is he that hath snatched away my nestling?
            Who is he that hath scattered my wealth? Who is he that hath carried away the beauty and
            ornament of my house? Who is he that hath entered and robbed me of my own hope? Which
            wolf has snatched away my sheep? What place hides the beauty that is like the sun? What
            abyss holds captive from me that royal seal? For she was to be the raiser up of my race.
            She was the staff of my old age. <pb n="55"/>She was my rest in labours. She was the
            repose of my troubles. She it was who lightened my miseries. 0 earth! cover not the
            blood of my darling till I learn who has turned my joy into sorrow."</p>
         <p n="14">Now when Paphnutius' friends and neighbours heard how he wept for his daughter,
            and wailed for her in such words, they also wailed and wept for her with a loud voice,
            until the whole city was stirred by the noise of their mourning and wept for the sudden
            loss of the young girl.</p>
         <p n="15">Now when Paphnutius had come to acquiesce in the inexorable nature of his sorrow,
            he went to the monastery, <milestone unit="folio" n="82b"/> and threw himself at the
            feet of the Abbot, saying to him, "I beg of thee, my father, do not neglect prayer to
            God until they find the effects of thy prayers. Thy handmaiden, my daughter, has been
            abducted." And when the Abbot heard this he was greatly troubled, and he commanded them
            to beat the wooden gongs, so that the brethren might be assembled. And when they had
            come together, he said to them, "Brethren, make [a confession of] sins, and appoint a
            sabbath, and fast every two days, and strive with God, and beg Him to reveal and
            disclose to us where is the daughter of Paphnutius." But when they had fasted all the
            sabbath, God did not reveal the matter to any one of them, because her own prayers
            overcame the prayers and vigils of all the brethren. For she had striven with God, and
            had persuaded Him not to disclose anything concerning her in her lifetime. For all the
            brethren were sorrowing because God had not revealed this matter to them. But the Abbot
            encouraged Paphnutius, saying, "Do not afflict thyself, nor grieve, but thank God, and
            whatever He wills He will make known to thee concerning her, for thou knowest that she
            has not devoted herself to any evil, but to good; and for this reason God <pb n="56"
            />does not wish to make known what concerns her to any of us. If she had been about any
            evil, God would not have been neglectful of thy labours, and of those of the holy men
            who are amongst us." And when Paphnutius heard this he was a little quieter in his
            affliction and went away to his <milestone unit="folio" n="83a"/> city praying that God
            would make him worthy of the good and beautiful home<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"
            />. Then after a little while he again went to that monastery and paid his respects to
            the brethren and returned to his city. On one of the days when he went to the monastery
            the Abbot said to him, "I want you to talk with a certain good brother from the palace
            of the Emperor Theodosius." Paphnutius replied, "Father, I am content," and the Abbot
            sent and called Agapius his chief [monk] and said to him, "Take my lord Paphnutius and
            lead him to brother Esmeraldus, so that he may profit by him. And he took him and
            conducted him thither." But when Euphrosyne saw her father she was all bathed in her
            tears. But her father imagined that penitence was the reason of her tears. He did not
            recognize her in the very least, for her beauty was withered up by her much fasting, and
            her vigils, and by her sleeping on the ground, for she had covered up her face in a rug,
            so that her father might not recognize her by some tokens. When they had engaged in
            prayer he sat down and she began to talk to him about mercy and righteousness and love
            and chastity, and about the freedom of souls, and while Esmeraldus was speaking the
            heart of Paphnutius was moved, and he was full of tears. And he was impelled by his love
            to embrace her. But he was ashamed <milestone unit="folio" n="83b"/> of it, and
            restrained himself. So while they were speaking to each other about things profitable to
            the soul, Paphnutius went away from Esmeraldus, and going to the Abbot, said to him,
            "Glory be to God, O father, for how much have <pb n="57"/>I profited by this man. God
            [only] knows how my soul has been captivated by his love, as if he had been Euphrosyne
            my daughter." And he took leave of the brethren and returned to his city.</p>
         <p n="16">Now when Esmeraldus had been in the monastery for thirty-eight years, he fell ill
            of the sore sickness which was the cause of [his] death. And during his sickness
            Paphnutius also arrived and came to that monastery. And after he had talked as usual
            with the Abbot, he said to him, "My lord, I wish to see Esmeraldus, whom my soul loves
            fondly." And the Abbot sent and called for Agapius and said to him, "Take my lord
            Paphnutius and conduct him to our brother Esmeraldus, for it seems to me that he will
            not again see him in life." And when Paphnutius went he fell on the rug on which
            Esmeraldus was lying and kissed his feet, saying, "Pray for me, brother, that God may
            give me consolation concerning my daughter, for my soul is not yet healed of its grief
            (about her)." Esmeraldus said to him, "Do not grieve, and do not weep, for whilst thou
            art here God will disclose and make known to thee [something] concerning thy daughter.
            But I advise thee to stay here for <milestone unit="folio" n="84a"/> three days, and not
            to go far away from me." He said to him, "Thou hast commanded and I will certainly do
            it. I will not go away, I will not leave thee for these three days."</p>
         <p n="17">Now when the third day arrived, and he knew therefore that he was departing to
            his Lord, she said to Paphnutius, "My father, since God has guided me according to His
            will, and has fulfilled the desire of my soul, I wish that from to-day thou mayest be
            quit of grief in the matter of Euphrosyne thy daughter. For I am that poor and miserable
            one, and behold! thou hast seen me, and thou art at rest, and thy wish is fulfilled. But
            for the sake of our Lord let no one know this. Moreover, do not allow any one else to
            shroud my body, but thou only, do thou <pb n="58"/>shroud me. And because I confessed to
            the Abbot, my father, when I came here and took upon myself this gentle yoke, that I
            possess great wealth, and that being permitted to sojourn here, I should leave it to
            those in this monastery, leave it to them, father. And thou also, my father Paphnutius,
            knowest this place where we live in the fear of God, and I beg of thee, my father, pray
            for me, a miserable creature."</p>
         <p n="18">And when the blessed, holy Euphrosyne had said this she yielded up her spirit to
            God. Now when her father Paphnutius had heard it, he wondered and fainted, and fell to
            the ground, and was as one dead. And Agapius, the master of Esmeraldus, entered and saw
            that he was already dead, and he sprinkled water on his face, saying to him, <milestone
               unit="folio" n="84b"/>"What is the matter with thee, my lord Paphnutius ?" But he
            said to him, "Leave me to die here, for I have seen glorious things to-day." And when
            Agapius had raised him up, he threw himself again on his face, and kissed her, and
            drenched her with his tears, crying out and saying, 11 Woe is me, my beloved daughter!
            Woe is me for the light of my eyes! Wherefore didst thou not disclose this to me
            aforetime, that I also might die willingly with thee? What a great wonder that thou hast
            despised in such a way the wickedness of the enemy! how thou hast escaped from the power
            of the princes of the darkness of this world, my daughter, and hast entered into
            everlasting life! "</p>
         <p n="19">Now when Agapius heard these things, a great astonishment fell upon him; and he
            ran weeping to the Abbot, and related all the occurrence to him. Now when the Abbot had
            heard these things he came in haste and fell upon the corpse of the holy Euphrosyne
            weeping, and crying out and saying: "Bride of the Christ! and holy daughter, do not
            disappoint the members of thy community, nor this holy monastery, but pray and beg from
            God that He may <pb n="59"/>give us understanding that we may direct it courageously and
            reach the haven of salvation, and enjoy with thee the good things of eternity." And he
            commanded them to beat the wooden gongs, and to assemble all the communities, and
            accompany her with great honour. Then when all the communities were congregated to learn
            about the story of the saint, a great amazement fell upon them all, and they sang
            praises to God who had done signs and wonders. Then <milestone unit="folio" n="85a"/>
            one of the brethren who had only one eye, the other one being closed, stepped in to
            embrace the body of the saint. And when he put his face to her face, his eye, which was
            closed, was opened and he saw with it. And when all the brethren saw it they sang
            praises to God, who is to be admired in His saints and who doeth signs and wonders by
            their hands, and who hath given the seal of remission and of redemption to those who are
            willing to take refuge in the love of our Lord Jesus the Christ And they carried the
            body of the saint in procession with psalms and hymns as it was fitting. And they put
            her on the bier of the fathers in a place of honour. Then her father Paphnutius gave all
            his wealth and his possessions to the churches and to the monasteries, to the poor, the
            orphans, and the widows. But he gave the greater part of his riches to the monastery in
            which his daughter Euphrosyne lay. And, moreover, he shut himself up in his daughters
            cell. And he had great consolation in the rug upon which his daughter had lain on the
            ground during her life. And her father lived for ten years in that monastery and
            departed to his Lord. And he left the things of earth, and was buried by the side<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> of Saint Euphrosyne his daughter; to the glory of
            the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost, to whom be dignity, praise and honour
            for ever and ever. Amen. </p>
         <p n="20">Here endeth the story of Esmeraldus of Alexandria.</p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">1 Or " conduct."</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">1 Literally "over the body."</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
