<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Drusis</title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreading and initial markup of persons, places, and titles by </resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#anorth">Adelaide North</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title level="a">Drusis</title>
                  <title level="m"> Select Narratives of Holy Women from the Syro-Antiochene or
                     Sinai Palimpsest as Written above teh Old Syriac Gospels by John the Stylite,
                     of Beth-Mari-Qanūn in A.D. 778. </title> Translated by Anges Smith Lewis
                  M.R.A.S. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>C. J. Clay and Sons</publisher>
                  <date>1900</date>
                  <citedRange unit="p" from="70" to="76">70-76</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <p>This transcription renumbers the original footnotes to run sequentially and includes
               marginal references for Biblical citations among the footnotes.</p>
            <p>This text is in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="70"/>
         <p n="1">Again, the martyrdom of Saint Drusis, and of those who were martyred with her in
            Antioch, in the reign of Trajan, the bad and wicked man. He had a daughter, a child of
            his [own] body, but not of his [own] faith. This Trajan had a burning desire and
            solicitude to build a public bath in the city of Antioch in Syria, and all the more
            because of his partners in wickedness, inasmuch as both by name and by nature he was a
            tyrant.</p>
         <p n="2">He had also a sinful ardour and a great eagerness in seeking to destroy and
            suppress the holy people of the Christians. Therefore he was considering and imagining
            evil things every day against the worshippers of the Christ. And when he had put three
            people to death every day, he went to see the work of the building of his public bath;
            for he would not go previously to look at it until he had put many Christians to death:
            the corpses of the saints lying unburied in various places.</p>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="92a"/>
         <p n="3">Now there were five virgin-nuns, three of them being virgins and sisters and also
            their mother. And they had a spiritual sister who was named Sufu. These lived in a
            convent, and they went out by night and stole the bodies of the saints who had been
            slain by the wicked Trajan. And they wrapped them up and hid them in the garden of their
            convent, anointing their limbs with sweet ointment. But this matter was made known to
            the wicked Trajan; that women were coming by night and stealing the corpses of these
            unclean Christians. And if they were permitted to act thus, every one would be driven
            from <pb n="71"/>the house of the gods, through the function of services to their
            corpses. And when the lamb of the Christ, Drusis, heard what had been said by her father
            about these people, she was moved to penitence in her spirit, and she stole a costly and
            valuable garment belonging to her father, and she ran away whilst the men of her
            body-guard were sunk in sleep; and when she went out, she saw these sisternuns carrying
            the corpses of these holy martyrs, and she went with them into their convent, she also
            carrying a corpse on her pure back; rejoicing and exulting because of the good [fortune]
            that Sufu had received her amongst them.</p>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="92b"/>
         <p n="4">But Adrianus was the adviser of the Emperor Trajan, and was also the betrothed
            bridegroom of the maiden Drusina; and he advised Trajan, saying, "My Lord the Emperor,
            command the soldiers to guard the city by night, that we may know who these are who
            steal the bones of the Christians who have met with a violent death." And this counsel
            was pleasing in the eyes of Trajan, and he himself gave orders to the soldiers, saying,
            "Watch and arrest for me those who steal the pestilent and unclean bones of these
            Christians, so that I may know because of what hope and expectation they do this."</p>
         <p n="5">Now whilst the soldiers were doing what they had been commanded by the Emperor [to
            do,] they found these five nuns with Drusina, who were accompanying and wrapping up the
            bodies of the saints, and they imprisoned these five carefully and put irons on their
            feet. Then they came to Drusis, and when they saw her, they said to each other, "Let us
            not put irons on this one, lest he take pity, like a father, on his daughter, and lay
            evil things upon us. But, nevertheless, let us be careful with her, and keep her till
            the morning."</p>
         <p n="6">And when the morning came, they made it known to <pb n="72"/>Trajan, saying, "My
            Lord the Emperor, the gods have fulfilled thy desire; but one thing prevents and
            restrains us from speaking in thy presence." Then he said to them, "Fear not." Then the
            soldiers of the wicked (Emperor) replied to him, saying: "We found five nuns whose faces
               <milestone unit="folio" n="93a"/>were shining like the stars of heaven, and we
            imprisoned these nuns and put them in irons. But when we were going to lay hands on the
            sixth, we saw her face shining and beaming more than the sun; and on her therefore we
            did not dare to put irons; lest haply thy divinity should be angry with us. For she is
            our mistress, the daughter of the Emperor." Now when Trajan and his son-in-law Adrianus
            heard this they were very angry and they said to the soldiers, "O what a cruel death ye
            shall die! My lady Drusis is in her bed-chamber, and how say ye that she is imprisoned
            outside?" And the Emperor summoned the body-guards of his daughter, and inquired from
            them where Drusis was. But they said to him, "O Lord the Emperor, our life and our death
            are in thy hands. Whilst we were sleeping, we did not know what became of her." Then
            Trajan was persuaded, and believed what the lictors had said to him. And Adrianus
            counselled along with the priests, the teachers of evil, saying, "How hast thou
            commanded that these five women should die?" Some of them were saying that they should
            be thrown into the river Orontes, and be drowned; and others were saying, "Nay, but
            shame them and put them in the pillory<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/>." <milestone
               unit="folio" n="93b"/>Adrianus said: "My Lord the Emperor, behold! there is the
            public hall, and nothing is wanting but that we should set up its own foundry. Command
            therefore, my Lord the Emperor, that there be a great furnace, and let copper things be
            fused in it, so that when they are consumed in it, not a single bone of them may be
            visible." <pb n="73"/>And this counsel pleased every one, and he sent and summoned the
            smelters of statues, and said to them: "Prepare a furnace for yourselves, lofty in
            height, and throw these wicked women into it. And whilst ye are heating them, pour
            copper upon them, so that their floor and the copper may become one; and then arrange it
            and make from them the bottom of brass. I desire then that at the feast of the
            consecration of the public bath, in the high place which is called Apollonia I may do
            what will appease the gods." And he commanded that Drusina should be kept with great
            care, saying, "Perhaps she will repent of what she has formerly done. And what the gods
            have bestowed upon her I will repay to them instead of her. For the faith of the
            Christians is the strongest of all witchcrafts; and it is very difficult for those who
            are falling into it to change to another religion."</p>
         <p n="7">Then Adrianus was inciting him, saying, "As thy majesty has commanded, I will
            arrange these [women] in order in the furnaces of Apollonia, near [this]. Command
            therefore, my Lord the Emperor, that it be proclaimed this day." Then <milestone
               unit="folio" n="94a"/> he decreed a law and commandment in all the town after this
            manner: "Men of Antioch, all ye who believe in the gods, prepare yourselves and go up
            with us in the beginning of the month of Tammuz. For I desire and am ready to celebrate
            the consecration of the public bath of Trajan along with that of Zeus, that is, [in] the
            temples of Zeus and of Apollo. All therefore who hated the Christ, and were worshippers
            of idols, go ye up with songs and choruses, and in dazzling white dresses with me to the
            consecration of the public bath." And every one therefore who went in to wash himself,
            when he opened the first door of the building, fell down instantly and gave up the
            ghost, so that no man was able to enter by that first door. Then they made known this
            matter to the wicked Trajan. And the priests of <pb n="74"/>vanities and servants of
            worthless idols said in his presence, "O Emperor, these bones which have been melted in
            that copper have removed the mercies of the gods. But command that there be second
            furnaces and thus shalt thou purify the public bath."</p>
         <p n="8">And when these things had been so done, Adrianus counselled that the first copper
            of the furnace should be set up in the middle of this, and that they should place them
            (the women) in the public bath for the scorn and contempt of every one. Then there
            appeared to the wicked Trajan <milestone unit="folio" n="94b"/> in a dream five pure
            lambs feeding in a park, and the shepherd who tended them answered and said to the bad
            and wicked Trajan, "Those whom thou hast expected to expose to scorn, the good and
            gentle Shepherd has snatched them from thee, and has put them in that place to which
            Drusina also is ready to enter without stain." And when the wicked man awoke he was very
            angry, because that after their death those handmaids of God would be bringing shame to
            his conscience and to his counsels. Then he commanded that there should be two furnaces,
            and that they should be heated every day.</p>
         <p n="9">And when first he arose from his sleep he issued a decree after this fashion: "Ye
            men of Galilee, ye who worship the Crucified One, save yourselves from tortures, and me
            also from troubles; and let each of you throw himself into these furnaces. For every
            time that I do something to diminish you, your God makes you to increase greatly."</p>
         <p n="10">Now when this decree was ordained, the lamb of God, Drusina, listened, and every
            one of the Christians came, and, with the loving fervour of faith, threw himself into
            the furnace, whilst the Lord wrought miracles and wonders by their means. But the simple
            lamb Drusina threw her glance <pb n="75"/>up towards heaven, and said: "O Lord God, if
            Thou hast willed the salvation of Thy handmaiden, chase away from me the vain fear of
            Trajan's threats. Receive me <milestone unit="folio" n="95a"/> also in Thine espousals,
            and deliver me from wedlock with the wicked Adrianus. And plunge my custodians in sleep,
            and deliver me from them." And she took off the imperial robe and ran away with the
            intention of throwing herself into one of the furnaces with those who believed in the
            Christ. And when she came and stood beside the first furnace in the vicinity of the
            public bath of her father Trajan, she came to herself and said, "Behold! Drusina is
            going to God's presence, and she has no wedding garment. How shall I who have received
            no purification go to that Holy One? How shall I go, being unbaptized? I will go towards
            the second furnace. Perhaps one of God's servants will be found and he will baptize me
            and I shall go adorned as a bride." And when she came near to the second furnace, she
            saw all those who had thrown themselves [into it] for the sake of the Christ, and it
            grieved her much. And she saw a well of water to the north of the second furnace; and
            she lifted up her eyes<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> to heaven and said: "King of
            all kings, behold for Thy sake I have left my imperial palace, so that Thou mayest place
            me amongst the doorkeepers of Thy kingdom. Thou art pure and holy <ellipsis>
               <metamark>......</metamark>
            </ellipsis> look on me and baptize me by the Holy Spirit. Come therefore, Thou beloved
            Son, with the blessed and immortal Father, in thy Holy life-giving <milestone
               unit="folio" n="95b"/>Spirit, and baptize me in this place, and let all the holy
            angels say Amen."</p>
         <p n="11">And when she had said, Amen, she took sweet salve and promptly anointed her whole
            body, and threw herself into the well. And thus was the holy Drusina crowned. <pb n="76"
            />But she lived for seven days after her immersion in the font, when she had partaken of
            the body and blood of our Lord Jesus the Christ from the hands of the holy angels. And
            on the eighth day she died<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> by being burnt in the
            furnace with those believers, and surrendered her spirit, to the glory of God the
            Father, and our Lord Jesus the Christ, to whom be praise and honour for ever.</p>
         <p n="12">Here endeth the story of Drusina, and of those who were martyred with her.</p>
         <noteGroup>
            <note xml:id="n1">1 Literally "place of retribution."</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">1 Literally 'glance.'</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">1 Literally "was crowned."</note>
         </noteGroup>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
