<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Mary</title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreading and initial markup of persons, places, and titles by </resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#anorth">Adelaide North</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title level="a">Mary</title>
                  <title level="m"> Select Narratives of Holy Women from the Syro-Antiochene or
                     Sinai Palimpsest as Written above the Old Syriac Gospels by John the Stylite,
                     of Beth-Mari-Qanūn in A.D. 778. </title> Translated by Anges Smith Lewis
                  M.R.A.S. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>C. J. Clay and Sons</publisher>
                  <date>1900</date>
                  <citedRange unit="p" from="85" to="93">85-93</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <p>This transcription renumbers the original footnotes to run sequentially and includes
               marginal references for Biblical citations among the footnotes.</p>
            <p>This text is in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="85"/>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="100b"/>
         <ab n="1">Again, the martyrdom of the blessed <persName>Mary</persName>.</ab>
         <ab n="2"><persName>Hadrian</persName> and <persName>Antoninus</persName>, the wicked Emperors, had sent an Imperial decree, that
            everyone who worshipped the <persName>Christ</persName> should turn to their own religion and law, whilst
            they [who] should eat of the impure sacrifices should live and not die; and that those
            who should be contentious and should resist the decree were to be delivered over to
            judgment.</ab>
         <ab n="3">Now at that time the blessed <persName>Mary</persName>, the bride of the <persName>Christ</persName>, had grown up in the
            Christian confession; for she was the bond-servant of <persName>Tertullius</persName>, a chief man of the
            city. But she was altogether a free woman of the <persName>Christ</persName>, and as it is written, <quote>He who
               is called being a slave in the <persName>Christ</persName>, is the <persName>Lord</persName>'s freeman.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="4">Now the birthday of the son of <persName>Tertullius</persName> arrived. And on that day he offered
            sacrifices and libations to the demons. And the noble <persName>Mary</persName> was slandered in the presence
            of her mistress by one of her companions. And she called her and said to her, <quote>Tell me,
               why didst thou fast, and didst not keep<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> the feast
               with us? Was it a vexation to thee?</quote></ab>
         <ab n="5"><persName>Mary</persName> said, <quote>Because I have lately been fasting. Or didst thou not know that I am a
               Christian, like my fathers?</quote></ab>
         <ab n="6">And her mistress constrained her by force to eat. But she cried to the heavenly
            Bridegroom, to <persName>Jesus the Christ</persName>. And she answered and said, <quote>Ye have power over this my
               body, but not over my soul. Let my speech be heard (though spoken) with boldness. Dost
               thou not understand <milestone unit="folio" n="101a"/>that the festival of thy son was
               celebrated with the music of <pb n="86"/>flutes and with cymbals and with impure rites
               and with drums and with lyres? But the festival of the Christians is celebrated with
               fasting and with praying and with purity and with spiritual songs.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="7">But as her mistress could not endure her boldness, she said, <quote>I will treat thee so
               that thou shalt die of scourging.</quote> <persName>Mary</persName> answered, saying, <quote>Do what thou wilt, because of
                  the help of the <persName>Lord</persName> that is with me.</quote> And when her husband <persName>Tertullius</persName> came from the
            Forum she told him about the blessed <persName>Mary</persName>. And immediately without examination he
            commanded them to scourge her with whips. And he commanded them further to shut her up
            alone in a closet, and to give her food by measure. But the blessed one praised <persName>God</persName>,
            praying continually, that she might remain constant in bearing testimony for the
            <persName>Christ</persName>.</ab>
         <ab n="8">And when three days<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> had passed it was told to
            the governor of the city that <persName>Tertullius</persName> had a certain Christian maid-servant in his
            house, and he was entreated that they might be in their city without any danger till the
            matter should be inquired into. And on the following day the governor sat on the
            judgment-seat, and commanded that they should fetch <persName>Tertullius</persName>. And all the Praetorium
            was assembled and all the people of the city. And the law of the Emperors was read in
            their presence, in which it was <milestone unit="folio" n="101b"/> thus written: <quote>The
               great and mighty Emperors, the terrible and merciful <persName>Diocletian</persName> and <persName>Antoninus</persName>, the
               saviours and architects and supporters of the whole inhabited world, to all those who
               are under the sway<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> of our Empire, and observe the
               right of our majesty and are diligent in the worship of the gods, much greeting.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="9"><quote>Forasmuch as a report has come to our ears, that suddenly the teachings of
               various men have sprung up, <pb n="87"/>which are contrary to the commandments of the
               gods and that seek to abolish the festivals of sacrifice, and the former laws of our
               ancestors and their great festivals are derided, therefore with the advice of the two
               Emperors, we command simultaneously, because we desire that all men should worship with
               reverence<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> and fear, and should propitiate the
               gods by sacrifice, and should not be like wandering beasts. And whosoever shall hide a
               Christian man or Christian woman, young men or maidens, old men or children, he shall
               die by the edge of the sword; and his wealth shall be given to the treasury. And
               whosoever shall trace out these people, he shall receive all that they possess, and four
               hundred dinars shall be given to him over and above by the Emperors. And if a man be
               found who has transgressed these things which we command, he shall be held guilty by the
               law.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="10">And after the decree of the Emperors had been read, the governor answered and
            said to <persName>Tertullius</persName>, <quote>Make a reply concerning this matter, for this is not a simple
               calamity for thee.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="11">The advocate, who stood up, said, <quote>Hear us, O wise judge. The girl in whose
               account this innocent man is accused, was given with the dowry of his wife.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="12">The governor said, <quote>Is his wife of a free family?</quote><milestone unit="folio"
               n="102a"/> - The advocate replied, <quote>Yes, my lord, she is the daughter of a certain
                  <persName>Aquilinus</persName>.</quote> The governor said, <quote>Was this girl born in the house or was she bought with
                     money?</quote> <persName>Tertullius</persName> said, <quote>She was born in the house, but her parents were bought by
                        sale.</quote> Then the governor asked, <quote>Is the steward alive or dead?</quote> <persName>Tertullius</persName> said, <quote>Yes,
                           my lord, he is dead.</quote> Then he asked him, <quote>Are the parents of the girl alive?</quote> <persName>Tertullius</persName>
            said, <quote>They are not alive.</quote> The governor said, <quote>Were they of the religion of the
               Christians, or did they fear the gods?</quote> The master of the <pb n="88"/>girl answered,
            <quote>They also worshipped the <persName>Christ</persName> who was crucified.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="13">The advocate said, <quote>O most wise of judges, they have scourged her with many
               stripes, that she might come to this worship; and if not, thou canst not turn her by
               force from her faith.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="14">And when the governor had asked all these things he said, <quote>Because the whole of
               the Pretorium bears witness to <persName>Tertullius</persName>, and they do honour to his family with their
               praises, because he is of the senate, and they proclaim what is straightforward and good
               about him, and that he is a worshipper of the gods, and obedient to the Emperors; and I
               also am convinced by the ancient writings, and the innocency of the man has been truly
               shown to me, he is therefore freed from our judgment until the Emperors can hear him:
               but let the insolent girl stand before the <milestone unit="folio" n="102b"/>
               judgment-seat.</quote> And the lictors brought the bride of the <persName>Christ</persName> and placed her before
            the judge in the court of judgment. Then the wicked and bloodthirsty people shouted
            against her (saying) that she ought to be burnt alive. But the thoughts of the believing
            woman were all with <persName>God</persName>, and she looked up to the height of heaven, and called with
            boldness on our <persName>Lord</persName>, saying:</ab>
         <ab n="15"><quote>O <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ, Son of the Living God, true Son of the Father</persName>, whose
               birth no man can oppose; neither emperors, nor judges, nor yet principalities, nor
               powers, nor yet lords, nor yet cherubim, nor yet seraphim; because, O <persName>Lord</persName>, they all
               have been created by Thy hands; and without Thy mandate nothing could have existed; and
               only Thy Father knoweth thee. Therefore He sent Thee from the highest heavens to the
               sinners who were awaiting Thee. Thou, O <persName>Lord the Christ</persName>, art the glorious <!-- should this have a persName or is it more of a description than title -->High-Priest,
               the Redeemer and Saviour of our souls. O <persName>Lord</persName>, help Thy handmaiden, for she has no
               helper but Thee; that Thy holy name may be <pb n="89"/>glorified, whilst Thou doest
               these things quickly. Accept the prayer of thy handmaid.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="16">The governor was amazed and astonished for about an hour: and he commanded that
            they should bring her before the judgment-seat; and he asked her, saying, <quote>What is thy
               name?</quote> And she returned an answer, saying, <quote>Why dost thou seek after my name? I am a
                  Christian.</quote> The governor said, <quote>Is he who stands [there] thy master?</quote> The noble woman
            said, <quote>He is the master of my body only, but over my soul <persName>God</persName> rules.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="17">The governor said, <quote>Why dost thou not worship the <milestone unit="folio"
                  n="103a"/>gods as thy master worships (them)?</quote> <persName>Mary</persName> said, <quote>I am a Christian, and I do
                     not worship the dumb idols, but I worship the living and true <persName>God</persName>, who is eternal.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="18">The judge said, <quote>From whom didst thou receive (the idea) of being a Christian?</quote>
            <persName>Mary</persName> said, <quote>I received it from my parents.</quote> The judge said, <quote>And were thy parents
               Christians?</quote> <persName>Mary</persName> said, <quote>They also received it from their parents.</quote> The judge said, <quote>I
                  suppose that before they received it ye were chiefs in this religion. But even if it be
                  so, approach and sacrifice, so that thy master may be quit of the accusation of the
                  law.</quote> The noble woman said, <quote>How has this entered into the desire of my mind? He also
                     ofttimes constrained me to eat of what was sacrificed, and has tortured me with many
                     scourgings, but the love of the <persName>Christ</persName> my master is stronger in grace, more than the
                     torments of the wicked (man). And because my parents laid hold of the divine teaching
                     which was preached by <persName>Paul the Apostle</persName>, for he said, <quote>Who shall separate us from the
                        love of the <persName>Christ</persName>? shall tribulation, or anguish, or persecution, or nakedness, or the
                        sword?</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> And because they laid hold of these
                     things, they confessed the <persName>Christ</persName>, and believed that neither death, nor life, nor
                     angels, nor principalities, nor <pb n="90"/><milestone unit="folio" n="103b"/>things
                     present, nor any other creature can separate us from the love of <persName>God</persName>, which is in <persName>Jesus</persName>
                     <persName>Christ our Lord</persName>. As I also say the truth, and I lie not, my conscience, which is <persName>Christ</persName>,
                     bearing me witness, that I depart from this world a Christian.</quote> <persName>Mary</persName> said, <quote>Will thy
                        torturers continue to the end, as they have but a short time? Therefore do what thou
                        wilt, for I have the <persName>Christ, the Saviour</persName> of my soul.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="19">And when the judge had heard this he commanded that they should strip her and
            prepare her for the tortures. And when many people saw her, they wept bitterly and shed
            tears with sobs, and they cried out against the governor, saying that he should show her
            a little patience. But the governor was not willing to be persuaded, but decreed that
            they should torture the blessed one. And again the bystanders cried out against the
            governor, <quote>Thou judgest wickedly; thou art going beyond the law.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="20">And when the governor heard the voice he was astonished. It appeared to him that
            it was not only men who were crying, but also the buildings were wailing. And he
            commanded the lictors who were standing there not to keep her. And he said to the people
            who were present, <quote>Wherefore are ye making a tumult, and resisting the commands of the
               Emperors? Is it not right for us to hearken unto the commands of the Emperors?</quote></ab>
         <ab n="21">They all answered as with one mouth, saying, <quote>The judges of the province, the
               victorious Emperors, command <milestone unit="folio" n="104a"/> with gentleness and
               persuasiveness that men should be led forward to sacrifice. But if they do not obey,
               they are to die by the sword. Now if she does not obey, command concerning her that she
               die by the sword. And we request this, that three days be given to her, so that perhaps
               she may be persuaded, and fulfil the law of the Emperors.</quote> The judge said, <quote>Do ye
                  persuade her, for, lo! ye have <pb n="91"/>seen that she was not in the least persuaded
                  by me.</quote> The interpreter said, <quote>What dost thou say, <persName>Mary</persName>, if three days be given to thee,
                     wilt thou sacrifice?</quote></ab>
         <ab n="22"><persName>Mary</persName> answered, <quote>My helper from of old was the <persName>Lord</persName>.</quote> The judge said, <quote>I give thee
               a respite of three days, and I swear by all the gods that if thou art so stubborn again
               thou shalt die by a variety of tortures.</quote> The noble woman said, <quote>Only one thing do I ask
                  of thee, that my master shall be held blameless, and shall be liberated, as innocent,
                  from the judgment.</quote> The governor said, <quote>He shall be liberated blameless; and thou, if
                     thou wilt be persuaded, shalt receive gifts, and shalt find freedom, which is a great
                     thing among men.</quote> <persName>Mary</persName> said, <quote>As the <persName>Christ</persName> liveth, He who hath given me all freedom,
                        and in whom I trust.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="23">Then he commanded that she should be kept carefully without dishonour. And the
            blessed one descended from [before] the tribunal and signed herself with purity. And she
            ran actively and lifted up her eyes to heaven and prayed, saying, <quote>I will lift up mine
               eyes unto the mountains, from whence my helper shall come. My help cometh from before
               the <persName>Lord</persName>, who made heaven and earth.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> And suddenly
            she saw wonderful <milestone unit="folio" n="104b"/>things; the heavens which were
            opened and troops of the angels and the archangels standing, and the prophets, and the
            apostles, and the martyrs, and the confessors, and amongst them she saw <persName>Thekla</persName> her
            sister. And then she saw the cherubim and the seraphim and the <persName>Son of God</persName> <!-- Should God have a persName within "Son of God" --> on the right
            hand of <persName>His Father</persName>. And thus the noble woman rejoiced, as one who has just entered
            through the gate of <placeName>Paradise</placeName>. But as for her persecutors their limbs became weak, and
            they fell, because of the help of the <persName>Lord</persName>, which accompanied His handmaiden. But many
            others were pursuing her. And when they surrounded her on every side she cried with a
            loud voice, saying, <quote><persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>, Thou art He who came down to <pb n="92"/>the
               fiery furnace in <placeName>Babylon</placeName> and rescued the three young men from the fire. And Thou art He
               who didst shut the mouth of the lions and rescued <persName>Daniel</persName> Thy servant, and didst lift him
               out of the lions' den unharmed. Also Thou didst deliver <persName>Jonah</persName> from the sea and from the
               belly of the fish, and Thou didst bring him up in three days. Thou, <persName>Lord Jesus</persName>, didst
               give light to the blind, and didst give hearing to the deaf. Thou wast the Healer of all
               sufferers, and the expectation of all the righteous. Thou art He, <persName>Lord</persName>, who didst hear
               the voice of the blood of <persName>Abel</persName>, and didst avenge him of <persName>Cain</persName> his brother. Thou art He,
               <persName>Lord</persName>, who wast present with <persName>Joseph</persName>, and didst deliver him from being slain by his
               brothers. Thou art He, <persName>Lord</persName>, who didst come, and art about to come to judge the quick
               and the dead. Redeemer of Thy handmaid! <persName>Jesus the Christ</persName>! hearken to my voice, and
               receive my soul; for dogs have compassed me about. Deliver not Thine handmaid into the
               hands of those who hate Thee. Thou, <persName>Lord</persName>, art the Mediator between <persName>God</persName> and man. Hear,
               <persName>Lord</persName>, the voice of Thy handmaiden, and redeem me according to the plenteousness of Thy
               mercy.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="24">And when she had finished her prayer, the rock before her was cleft, and it
            opened its bosom for [her] deliverance <milestone unit="folio" n="105a"/> like a
            foster-mother for her son; and it treasured up the bride of the <persName>Christ</persName> in its bosom. And
            the great crowd who were there went round about like blind people seeking for her. And
            when they came to that rock they found on the top of it something like three
            finger-breadths of the corner of her veil, and the fringes which were visible. And they
            returned and informed the governor of what had happened.</ab>
         <ab n="25">And the governor, in a great rage, commanded a certain man whose name was
            <persName>Placimus</persName>, the ruler of the city, to go to that place with a great many people, and to
            quarry the rock, and to dig deep in the earth, until they <pb n="93"/>should find the
            blessed one. And when <persName>Placimus</persName> had received this commandment, he ordered the herald to
            cry aloud in the city and to say, <quote>All ye citizens! assemble yourselves, and gather at
               the appointed time, and come; and let us take vengeance for our goddess.</quote> And when they
            were all assembled in the temple of the idols, he commanded them to take iron tools that
            they might dig the place with them. And when they were all assembled, and were ready to
            go and work, suddenly there was lightning from the east, and fearful thunder, and a
            great earthquake, and there appeared two terrible horsemen descending as it were from
            heaven to earth; and their lances were like burning lamps, and at the same moment many
            fell down through fright and died. And those who remained were chased by them as far as
            the door of the idol-temple. But when <persName>Placimus</persName> arrived at the door he also suddenly fell
            and died. And fire came down from heaven and burnt up the <milestone unit="folio"
               n="105b"/> house and the idols, and many of the wicked people were burnt. And those
            who died were, with those who were burnt, two thousand seven hundred in number. And
            those who were left fled to the city, and they cried, saying, <quote>Great is <persName>Mary</persName>'s God and
               great is the <persName>God</persName> of the Christians, and He is God in truth.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="26">And they ran in a crowd and went into the church, seeking mercy from <persName>God</persName>, for the
            wicked things which they had done. And three thousand souls from amongst them believed
            on that day. And in the days of the martyrdom of the blessed <persName>Mary</persName> the persecution of the
            Christians ceased.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/></ab>
         <ab n="27">Here endeth the martyrdom of the blessed and noble <persName>Mary</persName>, and she conquered in the
            conflict with the wicked judge.</ab>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">1 Literally <hi rend="doubleQuote">make.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">1 Sinai Palimpsest <hi rend="doubleQuote">months.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">2 Literally <hi rend="doubleQuote">hand,</hi> literally <hi rend="doubleQuote">mercifulness.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">1 Literally, <hi rend="doubleQuote">mercifulness.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">Rom. viii. 35</note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">Ps. cxxi. 1</note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">1 The Sinai Palimpsest adds: <quote>May the Lord grant to us to find mercy
                  in the judgment, in the place where there shall be a recompence to the righteous,
                  (and) shame to the sinners, by the grace and mercy of our Lord Jesus the Christ. With
                  Him also to His Father be glory and honour with the Holy Ghost for ever.</quote></note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
