<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Irene</title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreading and initial markup of persons, places, and titles by </resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#anorth">Adelaide North</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title level="a">Irene</title>
                  <title level="m"> Select Narratives of Holy Women from the Syro-Antiochene or
                     Sinai Palimpsest as Written above teh Old Syriac Gospels by John the Stylite,
                     of Beth-Mari-Qanūn in A.D. 778. </title> Translated by Anges Smith Lewis
                  M.R.A.S. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>C. J. Clay and Sons</publisher>
                  <date>1900</date>
                  <citedRange unit="p" from="94" to="148">94-148</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <p>This transcription renumbers the original footnotes to run sequentially and includes
               marginal references for Biblical citations among the footnotes.</p>
            <p>This text is in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="94"/>
         <p n="1">Again, the story of Saint Irene.</p>
         <p n="2">In the six hundredth and twenty-first year of the reign of Licinius, king of the
            city of Magedo, an only daughter was born to him, and he called her name Penelope. And
            when she was six years old her father and mother consulted as to how they should shut
            her up, and in what place there <milestone unit="folio" n="106a"/> should be a retreat
            where she might learn [her] letters, until she should come to full stature and arrive at
            a marriageable age, so that the wedding-feast might take place when she should emerge
            from the retreat. And they proposed to build a castle outside of the city and to
            surround it with a strong wall; and that Apellianus, her secretary, should mount with
            ropes by means of the contrivances of an engine of the artificers to her own high window
            in the castle; and whilst he sat outside there were curtains hung between him and the
            maiden, [and] he was to teach her letters. Licinius the king agreed on these things with
            his wife. And they began at once to the work, and he commanded and the artificers came,
            and he set the men to work immediately. And he appointed three hundred overseers who
            made the slaves and the builders work. And five thousand skilful carpenters to prepare
            wooden instruments, and two thousand stone-cutters, men who were to cut stones from the
            mountain, and three thousand carts which were to carry the stones. For the king was
            eager and hurried the workmen to finish the castle in nine months.</p>
         <p n="3">But when they had begun the work, the building progressed chiefly through the
            insistence of the king <pb n="95"/>who was beside them. And when the castle was
            completed, with its ornamentation, and its beauty, and everything suitable to it, the
            king desired to have a dedication festival for it; and he sent and invited five
            neighbour kings, and they came at the appointed time with their armies, and with a great
            endless crowd accompanying them.</p>
         <p n="4">And when the king saw the great crowd, he commanded <milestone unit="folio"
               n="106b"/> that five thousand oxen should be slaughtered, and ten thousand sheep; and
            these kings and their armies enjoyed themselves for thirty days; and at the end of three
            days every man departed to his home. And the kings and their armies went one by one to
            his city.</p>
         <p n="5">But afterwards the king called for his daughter and said to her, affectionately,
            "My daughter, I have built a castle for thee, adorned with all beautiful things; elegant
            in its loveliness, very wonderful in its aspect, glorious in its appearance, firm in its
            foundations, and strong in its walls, and superb in its apartments, loftier than all
            work, an astonishment to its beholders; wonderful in its construction, impregnable and
            invincible to men, that cannot be overthrown by giants. Now therefore, my beloved
            daughter, I wish to shut thee up there in that castle for a fixed term of years, until
            thou shalt come to full stature, and arrive at thy wedding-day. Do not murmur then, my
            daughter, and let there be no anxiety in thy heart, and let not fear dwell in thy mind.
            For, lo! I have commanded that ninety-eight gods shall mount thither with thee and take
            care of thee. For I will set up seven gods in each chamber of the castle, that the evil
            one and his power may not rule there, nor trouble thy childhood. Be not therefore
            anxious, for, lo! I have made everything that is beautiful for thy comfort: my beloved
            daughter."</p>
         <p n="6">But when the king's daughter heard these things from <milestone unit="folio"
               n="107a"/>her father, she lifted up her voice with weeping, and said <pb n="96"/>to
            her father with bitter tears, "Thou art shutting me up alive, my father, within the
            gates of Hades, whence I shall never go out; and I shall never again hear the sweet
            voice of my mother nor of other women. I shall not see the sun, nor the moon, nor shall
            I contemplate the brilliancy of heaven, nor the stars. My eye shall not delight in the
            birds of the air, I shall not distinguish between day and night in my prison-house
            whilst I am in it. I shall raise my [voice] to heaven. Never again shall I walk on the
            earth, I shall not even need a shoe, except for ornament. Forasmuch as I cannot take a
            walk, what can it profit me? Affliction and anxiety come upon me from all sides. My
            father! I shall never again see children like myself, of my own age. Henceforth I
            renounce all created things. Forasmuch as I shall suffer in Hades and in the grave,
            whence I shall never go out, truly my beloved parents will weep for me with sobs and
            even with lamentations."</p>
         <p n="7">And when she had said these things there was great weeping and much mourning in
            the house of the king. And also the faces of all his servants wore a look of
            sadness.</p>
         <p n="8">But when the queen, the mother of the girl, saw her daughter, and heard these
            words from her, she rose in haste and went hurriedly to the girl, and threw her arms
            round her neck, and embraced her weeping. And she said to the <milestone unit="folio"
               n="107b"/> king with anxious tears, and with bitterness of heart, "I shall not leave
            my daughter. I will go to the grave with her and be imprisoned in Hades. I will die with
            her, and I will live with her/'</p>
         <p n="9">And it came to pass, on a certain day in the palace of her father, that at the
            turn of the day the king dismissed all those who were coming in and going out from his
            presence; and he led his daughter and went to the castle which he had built; he and his
            daughter and a great crowd <pb n="97"/>of the magnates of the city with him. And he took
            his daughter up to that castle and her thirteen handmaidens with her for her honour and
            for service. And he took up a throne and her chairs, and a dining-table and a
            candlestick; and all the vessels for her service with her; and her ornaments, and her
            trinkets, and her crowns, all of gold, and emeralds, and pearls; eleven changes of
            raiment of all colours; of linen, and silk, and purple. And afterwards the king and the
            queen kissed the girl and went out. And they left her in peace, they and the magnates of
            the city, whilst the slaves and the handmaidens were weeping like people who are
            mourning and grieving for a dead person at the grave.</p>
         <p n="10">Then the king commanded and they shut the outer doors of the castle and he sealed
            them with his signet ring, and he commanded that they were not to be opened until the
            time arrived for his daughter to be betrothed to a husband. But the king had made the
            castle as a pavilion because he feared lest the sun should look upon the girl's beauty
            and blacken her colour with its heat. And <milestone unit="folio" n="108a"/> when he had
            shut the doors and sealed them he entered the city, and set guards over the castle
            outside its walls, one thousand five hundred men, that they might keep watch continually
            by day and by night.</p>
         <p n="11">But during all the days of her imprisonment Apellianus her secretary came to
            teach her letters. • And the guards drew him up with the ropes of the machine to the
            highest window of the castle. And he sat outside and taught her letters, never seeing
            her face.</p>
         <p n="12">But the girl, the daughter of the king, meditated in the castle when she was six
            years old, and she was there six years and three months, and at the end of this period
            the king's daughter saw as in a dream that the window on the east side of the castle was
            opened, and she saw that a <pb n="98"/>dove entered from it carrying an olive-leaf in
            its mouth, and it set it on the table in front of her bed and went out. And afterwards
            she saw again an eagle entering by the same window and carrying in its mouth a wreath
            adorned with all flowers, and it also set it on that table and went out. And she again
            saw a raven carrying a wriggling serpent, and it set it upon the table and went out. And
            she saw these things and called out for her [confidante] and they took refuge with each
            other out of fright.</p>
         <p n="13">But on the morning of the day her secretary came as usual to teach her letters.
            And she related to him all the <milestone unit="folio" n="108b"/> signs and wonders
            which she had seen. Her teacher said to her, "Do the objects which the birds of heaven
            laid upon the table remain there until now? "But she said to him, "No, we saw them only
            in the vision; and they were taken away immediately from before my eyes." And the
            teacher was filled with the inspiration<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> of the
            Spirit, and he said to her: "Hearken, O daughter of the king! The dove which thou hast
            seen is the doctrine of the teaching of the Wisdom of God; and the olive-leaf is the
            grace of the Christ, and it announces the opening of the baptismal font. And the eagle
            is a great and powerful king, and the wreath which it carried in its mouth, adorned with
            all flowers, is the vocation which hath called thee to the espousals of the Heavenly
            Bridegroom, and the perfection which is completed by faith. And the raven is Satan the
            weak and crafty one, [who is] also the tempter<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> of
            the righteous; and the serpent which he carried in his mouth is affliction and anxiety,
            misery and tumult, and persecutions. Therefore hearken, oh queen and daughter of the
            king! to what I tell thee. Thou art called to the city of the great and Heavenly King;
            and thou shalt be hidden under the shadow of His wings. Thou shalt surely see much
               afflic<pb n="99"/>tion upon earth. And thy father and thy mother shall deliver thee
            up to thine enemies; and thy father himself shall be a and persecutor to thee; and shall
            meditate evil, and not good, against thee. But why do I talk much with thee? for, lo! a
            man of God shall be sent to thee, an <milestone unit="folio" n="109a"/> angel of peace
            from the presence of the mighty King of Heaven, and he will teach thee all that is
            necessary to thee." And when her secretary had said these things to her, he descended
            from her presence at the time when he was accustomed to do so.</p>
         <p n="14">Now at the dawn of day the king said to the queen, "The day has arrived for the
            wedding-feast of our daughter. Let us go and see her face; for the day of the marriage
            is come."</p>
         <p n="15">And the king and queen arose and went both of them to the castle; and the king
            called his daughter. And she stooped down; and he saw that her face was shining and
            lovely like the radiance of the sun. Then he was filled with a great joy and said to his
            daughter, "My daughter, the day of thy wedding has arrived. Tell me therefore, my
            daughter, that I may tell<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> the time and the place to
            those who are entering and who are going out; and that I may appoint and make known the
            date of thy wedding-feast; and that one of the sons of a king who shall please thee, and
            shall enliven thy soul, let him be thy betrothed."</p>
         <p n="16">His daughter said to him, "My father, have patience with me for a single
               week,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> and I will take counsel with my thoughts;
            and then after the lapse of a week<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> I will tell
            thee.</p>
         <p n="17">And when the king had heard the speech of his daughter, he was persuaded by her,
            and said, "As thou wilt, my daughter, be it unto thee."</p>
         <p n="18">Then he left her and went into the town rejoicing and with exulting mind. Now
            after her father had left her and <pb n="100"/>had gone into the city, she drew nigh and
            spoke to the gods — the idols — those which had been set up there beside her. And she
            curtsied before them, and said to them, "If ye be gods, hearken to my voice, [regarding]
            what I say to you. Give me back an answer and teach me the true <milestone unit="folio"
               n="109b"/> thing that will help. My father will constrain me to be given to an
            husband. But I have accustomed myself to the solitude of widowhood, and to the humility
            of sterility, and to the desolateness of orphanhood. Verily the wedding-feast of the
            world leadeth away from the truth and it is an obstacle in the presence of the
            Lord."</p>
         <p n="19">She said again to the idols, "If ye be gods, tell me beforehand. Shall I be given
            to a husband, or no? ' And she saw that there was no voice, nor any one that listened,
            nor any who gave her an answer. And she turned herself to the eastern window and she
            looked at the sky, and she prayed and said, "Lord of the heaven and of the earth, and of
            the seas, and of all that creepeth in them, if Thou art God the Almighty, Jesus the
            Christ, the Son of the Living God, He whom the Galileans have preached, if it is proper
            for me to make a transitory wedding-feast for myself, and to be given to a mortal man,
            and a bridegroom who will perish; show me plainly Thy divinity." And when she had said
            this she sang praises to God.</p>
         <p n="20">On that night she lifted up her eyes, and saw the angel of the God standing
            beside her, clothed in white. And when she saw him, she was sore afraid, anb! her mind
            was perturbed. And when the angel saw that she was afraid,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n6"/> he said to her, "Peace be unto thee, fear not, for behold! thou hast
            found mercy and grace before God. And I have been sent to thee to show thee and to teach
            thee the things to come. And henceforth thy name shall no more be called Penelope, but
            Irene, which, being <milestone unit="folio" n="110a"/>interpreted, is Peace. And thou
            shalt be a strong tower <pb n="101"/>against all the tricks of the crafty one; and many
            men shall find a refuge with thee, and shall repent and believe in God for thy sake; a
            thousand three hundred and thirty thousand people, men, women and children. And
            everything that Apellianus thy teacher has said to thee he said well, about those birds
            which thou hast seen, and what they carried and laid upon thy table. He spoke justly,
            for the Holy Spirit spake by him and prophesied, and that man is not far from the
            kingdom of God. For a man of God shall come to thee from Paul the Apostle, a skilful
            doctor of the church of God. And he shall have a letter on (his person) and he will read
            it in thy presence, and will teach thee the faith and the religion of God; and he will
            baptize thee in the name of the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Ghost. Surely an angel
            of God will accompany him, and will break down the castle, and he will enter thy
            presence and baptize thee in the name of the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Ghost.
            And after thy baptism power and strength will be given to thee, with fortitude and the
            wisdom of God. And thou shalt have purity from guilt, with the remission of sins."</p>
         <p n="21">And the angel went up from her to heaven. And afterwards the blessed lamb of the
            Christ remained rejoicing and exulting in her mind and praising God for all that she had
            heard from the angel. And she was looking for the arrival of Timothy that she might be
            baptized by him, and might receive the sign of the Christ. And on the following day
            there came to her the holy priest Timothy, accompanied by an angel of God, and said to
            her, "What is thy care, my daughter, [because of which] <milestone unit="folio" n="110b"
            /> I am come to thee to-day?"</p>
         <p n="22">And she said, "It is well that thou art come, my father and lord, for it is the
            time that my sins should be remitted, and my transgressions and faults should be <pb
               n="102"/>blotted out by thy coming, in peace, and that I should obtain salvation in
            God." And when the holy priest Timothy had heard these words he gave thanks, and blessed
            the oil and the water; and he baptized her in the name of the Father, and the Son, and
            the Holy Ghost; her, and the thirteen handmaidens who were with her, whom her father had
            given to her for her service. And after she and her handmaidens had been baptized that
            holy priest taught them the faith and the fear of God. And the angel who was with him
            was taken away.</p>
         <p n="23">And the blessed lamb of the Christ blessed and praised God without ceasing. And
            she turned to those senseless idols of the gods and said to them, "I entreated and
            besought you to tell me the truth, and ye did not tell me. Now therefore, if ye are
            gods, stand up for yourselves. For the gods who did not make the heaven and the earth
            shall perish from beneath the heaven."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> And she
            obtained power and strength and heroism. And she lifted these idols with power, and
            flung them from the eastern window, <milestone unit="folio" n="111a"/> to the ground
            below, saying to them, "Stand up yourselves, if you can, and help yourselves by your own
            power, for ye were not able to do anything to help me."</p>
         <p n="24">But they were greatly smashed by [their] fall from the great height, and they
            were ground to pieces like salt, and became as dust.</p>
         <p n="25">But when the appointed period of seven days had come to an end the king Licinius
            went to the castle to see his daughter. And he called her and said to her, "My daughter,
            behold the appointed period of seven days is finished, as thou didst say, according to
            thy wish, and what dost thou say?"</p>
         <p n="26">Then all the great men who were with him said to him, "O king, mayst thou live
            for ever! Let thy majesty command and bring down the maiden from the castle, and <pb
               n="103"/>bring her into the city, and there will we delight ourselves with her
            beauty; and she shall be in the palace of the</p>
         <p n="27">Then when she had heard [it], she said, "After I have entered the palace of the
            Heavenly King and have dwelt in it; and have delighted in the seal and in the espousals
            of Jesus the Christ, the Son of the Living God, shall I leave Him and enter a palace of
            human weeping and full of sin? " "Be it far from thee," said the nobles to her. "From
            what thou speakest perhaps thou art a Christian?" She said to them, "Now you certainly
            know that I am the handmaid of the Christ and the bride of Jesus. For behold all the
            week that I was baptized these were the days of my wedding-feast and of the joy of my
            nuptials. Oh! do ye not see the destruction of your gods, and if they did not help
            themselves when they were hurled down from above, how can they help you? Truly ye
            cherish a vain and empty <milestone unit="folio" n="111b"/> hope in them. For all the
            gold and silver that ye possess, which ought to be given to the orphans, and to the
            widows, and to the needy, and to the oppressed in spirit, ye have called for the
            goldsmiths, and have given it to them; and by their skill they have made you artificial
            gods; and ye have worshipped them, and have given to unsavoury demons and to dead idols
            the adoration which was due to God. They have eyes, but they see not; they have ears,
            but they hear not; and there is no breath in their mouth. They that make them shall be
            like unto them, and every one that trusteth in them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"
            /> Therefore ye are the oppressors of the orphans and of the widows, and spoilers of the
            poor and of the unfortunate; and the enemies of righteousness; and aliens from God;
            fornicators and adulterers; deceivers and deniers of God. Repent and turn to the living
            God. Know ye the merciful God who is able to kill and to make alive; to bring [down] to
            Sheol and to bring up <pb n="104"/>[again]. Turn ye to God, while there is room, before
            the day of doom cometh, and ye fall into the judgment of righteousness. Hearken to me,
            my own father, for my word is to thee! know what I say to thee. When thou didst begin to
            build this castle, thou didst build it with many people— there was no end to them — and
            by thy presence which was with them at every moment. Thou didst finish it in nine
            months, with its ornaments and with all its decorations; and thou wert praised amongst
            men and lauded for thy work. But our adored God made the heaven and the earth and the
            seas, and all that moveth in them in six <milestone unit="folio" n="112a"/> days; He
            made the sun and the moon and the stars, and to all of them He gave names. He created
            the mountains and the hills and the valleys and the plains. He created every tree whose
               seed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/> is in itself on the earth. And on the
            completion of these things He formed man in His own image and in His likeness; and
            clothed him with brightness and made him lord and ruler over all the brutes and the
            beasts, and the creeping things and the flying things, and subjected all these creatures
            to Him; and He created them<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/> all by His word; and
            that was our Lord Jesus the Christ; He whom the Jews have crucified; He who has been
            persecuted by the unjust people, and He was taken, and was scourged, and was crowned
            with a crown of thorns, and was crucified, and He tasted the vinegar and the gall on the
            cross; which sweetened our bitterness; He died and was buried; and in three days He rose
            by the Divine power which dwelt in Him. And He was exalted and taken up to Heaven to His
            Father. And He sat down on the right hand of Him who sent Him. And the cherubim bear His
            throne, and the seraphim stand before Him, and He is worshipped by the hosts of Heaven.
            He it was <pb n="105"/>who in six days created and made everything by His word. This
            light hath dawned on the earth, and those who are sitting in darkness and in the shadow
            of death have seen His light. And the truth ran upon the earth; the sick were healed;
            the afflicted were comforted; even the diseased were cured; the lepers were cleansed;
            the demons were cast out; the palsied were made whole; the [eyes of the] blind were
            opened; and the dead were raised up; and souls were saved and the lost were found;
               <milestone unit="folio" n="112b"/> and the erring turned back; and the sinners
            repented; and the righteous rejoiced; and debts were prolonged; transgressions were
            forgiven; the baptismal font was opened and many were baptized; the impure were made
            holy, and the earth rejoiced; Heaven exulted; the hosts of heaven sang, and shouted,
            saying, ' Glory be to God in the highest, and good will to all men; by the will of the
            Living God.'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> Thou therefore, my father, hast been
            praised and glorified 14 by men for a small and transitory work; and thou hast not
            thyself searched and wondered and confessed and glorified Him who in six days made all
            these things and created the creatures; nor our Lord Jesus the Christ, He who extended
            His grace upon the earth; and filled creation with His peace. And to the Living Spirit,
            who is the Holy Paraclete, who calleth all men to the kingdom of heaven/ 5</p>
         <p n="28">And when the blessed Irene had said these things to her father, Licinius returned
            her an answer, saying, "I have had great patience with thy speech, my daughter, on
            account of thy sweet grace, because for years I have heard thy voice; and sweet to me is
            the sound of thy sentences. Therefore let us go into the city. And thou hast told me
            what thou desirest. ,,</p>
         <p n="29">Then the king and his nobles led the blessed Irene and went into the city. But
            the queen her mother followed <pb n="106"/><milestone unit="folio" n="113a"/>after her
            daughter bent in person, and she lifted the dust from beneath the feet of her daughter.
            And she applied it to her eyes and on her body, saying, "May this dust from beneath the
            holy feet of my beloved daughter be to me rest and healing, and for the redemption of my
            life and for the remission of sins, and for the new eternal life." And all the people
            who saw her, did likewise. And the king turned round, and saw [it], and commanded that
            no man should hinder them.</p>
         <p n="30">And when the blessed one had entered the city the magnates and the patricians and
            the patrician ladies came out to meet her, and they did obeisance to her, because they
            saw that she was lovely. But the plebeians and the poor people could not see her because
            of the great crush; for they were longing greatly to see her; and were running to the
            high places and standing, and studying her beauty from thence. And everyone who saw her
            was filled with great joy, as if they had already beheld the face of an angel. And when
            she came to enter by the door of her father's palace, a certain vicious demon met her,
            and said to her, "What is there between me and thee, thou handmaid of Jesus? Get thee
            out of this city, for no Christian <milestone unit="folio" n="113b"/> can dwell in it."
            But the blessed Irene said to that demon, "Who art thou? and what is thy name? "The
            demon said, "Nargium is our name. And I guard this city, and many people are mine. I am
            the first charioteer of the gods; and I rejoice in quarrels, and exult in slaughter. And
            I excite disputes, and I rejoice in the shedding of blood. I supply the wizards, and
            enchain many by means of them. I am the father and the originator of all evils. I am the
            rock of adamant on which all the souls of the wicked shall be dashed. Now I have made
            known to thee my power and my courage. Therefore get thee away from the city, lest thou
            be angry, and I go to thy father, and ruin thee also."</p>
         <pb n="107"/>
         <p n="31">Irene answered, "I say to thee, vile demon, and rabid imp, In the name of our
            Lord Jesus the Christ, it is not lawful for thee to be in this city, nor to ruin nor to
            hurt any one of its inhabitants. Therefore begone! lest I destroy thee in the name of
            Jesus."</p>
         <p n="32">But he, when he heard the glorious name of Jesus, fled in fear and trembling, and
            went out of the city astonished. And as he was going out, he approached the king and
            whispered in his ear, saying to him, "If thou art mine, Licinius, be strong and of good
            courage; for thy daughter is mixed up with the error of the Christians." And when he had
            said this, he went out of the city shaking and howling. And at the dawn of day the king
            called to the <milestone unit="folio" n="114a"/> queen and said to her, "What shall we
            do, for our daughter is mixed up with the error of the Christians? "</p>
         <p n="33">The queen said, "Why dost thou think that our daughter is certainly in error? Be
            it far from her! let it not be! for our daughter has not erred and does not err."</p>
         <p n="34">The king said, "She confesses the Christ and denies the gods, does she not surely
            err?"</p>
         <p n="35">The queen said, "But the gods who did not make the heaven and the earth, how are
            they gods? I also say let them perish from beneath the sky. I disown them and those who
            worship them. Peace be to our daughter, and glory be to the Christ, who hath called her
            to immortal life."</p>
         <p n="36">Then the king was terribly angry, and he commanded that they should put the queen
            out of the palace; and that she should remain out of it. But one of the maidens ran and
            told Irene, "Thy father hath chased thy mother away because of thee." But when she heard
            it she said to the handmaiden, "Fear not, for beside me my father has the strength of an
            ant."</p>
         <pb n="108"/>
         <p n="37">And the blessed one rose in haste, and went to the palace of her father, that she
            might enter his presence with all speed. But many of the magnates and of the king's
            servants prevented her and tried to persuade her not to do so,<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n12"/> for they said to her, "Do not shew thyself to-day to thy father;
            because he is growling<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> like a lion to destroy
            thee." But when the blessed one heard it she laughed again and said: "As my Lord and my
            God Jesus liveth <milestone unit="folio" n="114b"/> to-day and at this moment I will see
            him! "</p>
         <p n="38">Now when they heard a knock at the kings door, they went in and made it known to
            the king, saying, "Thy daughter is standing without and desires to enter thy presence
            and see thee." When the king had heard it, he commanded her to enter. And the holy Irene
            entered and stood before her father. And when he saw her, he bent his head<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/> down, and gazed on the ground in the anger of his
            mind. For he could not bear to look at her in the wrath of his heart. When Irene saw it,
            she said, "Why art thou of sad countenance to-day, my father, and not as usual. Thou
            hast one only daughter; and lo! she is standing before thee. Whereabouts in the palace
            is the queen, my mother and mistress dwelling? Is she well?"</p>
         <p n="39">But he did not answer her a word. Irene said, "Whence hath this anxiety [come] to
            thee, my father? And I do not know my own parent by reason of his sad countenance." And
            the king said, "Would that I had not begotten thee, my daughter! then I would not have
            fallen into this anxiety on thy account. I made a famous castle for thy sake; and I
            adorned it with all beautiful things; and I surrounded it with a strong wall; and I
            placed guards over it and I set up ninety-eight gods in it for thy glory and that they
            might protect thee. And I gave a table and a <pb n="109"/>candelabrum and a throne and
            all the vessels for thy service of wrought gold, and crowns of emeralds and gold, also
            pearls. I made thy dresses of all colours, of fine linen and of silk, and of spun gold,
            and all of them were beautiful. And hast thou repaid me for them, my daughter?" Irene
            said, "But what evil have I done to thee, my father? "The king said, "Is it a little
            thing to me, this anxiety and <milestone unit="folio" n="115a"/> wrong which thou hast
            caused to me and hast repaid me</p>
         <p n="40">[with]? Thou hast confessed the Christ, and hast believed in Jesus, and hast
            denied the gods.''</p>
         <p n="41">Irene said, "That is not a wrong to thee, my father, that I have believed in the
            Christ. Nor again is it an anxiety to thee that I confess Jesus. I am hurting thee in
            nothing. For I rely on the Lord Jesus that thou also wilt soon confess and believe in
            the Christ. And I know not why thou art anxious."</p>
         <p n="42">The king said: "My beloved daughter Penelope, is it thy wish that I should not be
            anxious?" "Yes," said Irene. "Sacrifice to the gods," said the king.</p>
         <p n="43">Irene said, "My father, do not twist thy tongue, nor call me Penelope; do not
            change my name, for it is not Penelope." </p>
         <p n="44">"And what is thy name?" said the king to her.</p>
         <p n="45">Then she said: "Irene is my name, for by that name my betrothed and my God called
            me when I was in that castle which thou didst build for me."</p>
         <p n="46">But when the king heard it he was extremely angry, and said, "I renounce this
            child, artful for evil and not for good, and would that thou hadst never been !" Then
            the king commanded his magnates to take her away to the circus; and to bind her with
            ropes and throw her down and cause chariots with horses to run over her; that she might
            die by the trampling of horses and the wheels. And the servants of sin led her at once
            and bore her to the <pb n="110"/>circus. And with weeping and bitter tears they brought
            her near the place in which there was to be an end to her <milestone unit="folio"
               n="115b"/> life. And after these things the king arose and went out of the palace to
            go to the circus and see the death of his daughter. And one of the noble horses who were
            there who had been made chief of the stable, cut the ropes of his halter and destroyed
            the stall in which he was standing and ran straight on the king and bit him and he fell
            down and died. And it seized his right arm and carried it away from his shoulder, and he
            fell and died. And it returned and stood in its stall where it had been standing. And
            suddenly there was much mourning and weeping in the king's house. But as for that horse
            to it was given the speech of man, for the glory of God. And it spoke and said thus:
            "Blessed art thou, Irene, handmaid of God, and blessed art thou among women. Thou hast
            been delivered into the hands of the wicked upon the earth, and in heaven thine
            espousals and their adornment are prepared. Thou hast wept upon earth, and in paradise
            thou shalt be embraced by the sweetness of heaven. Here thou art afflicted, but thou
            shalt be made splendid beyond the splendour of light Thou art hated by many upon earth,
            but thou shalt stand and be glorified beside Jesus thy betrothed. Blessed be thou and
            blessed be thy soul."</p>
         <p n="47">Now when the horse had said these things, they led the horses and brought them
            down to the circus. But that horse remained apart from them; because by reason of its
            strength they were unable to bring it down with its companions; and because they were
            afraid that it might kill them, like the king. Now it had happened to the blessed Irene
            that they had bound her with ropes according to the commandment of the king, and all the
            horses came and knelt down and did obeisance before her. And all <milestone unit="folio"
               n="116a"/> the people were amazed at this wonder. And suddenly <pb n="111"/>her
            fetters were loosed from her; and they saw it and glorified God. And in that hour the
            servants of the king came and said to her, "A horse has bitten thy father and he is
            dead; and behold! he is thrown on the ground, and his arm is taken off."</p>
         <p n="48">And she said: "Fear not, he is not really dead, but is sleeping and this that has
            happened was for the glory of God. Ye also shall see [it,] and believe in God."</p>
         <p n="49">And when the great crowd heard that the king was dead, grief and sorrow
            overspread their mind; and they came and fell down before the feet of the blessed one,
            and did obeisance to her; and they persuaded her saying, "Lady, take pity on thy father
            who is dead; and it is grievous to thee, for his hand, too, has been taken away, and
            thrown aside."</p>
         <p n="50">And the blessed Irene came and stood over the corpse of her father. And all the
            people wondered; for they left off their mourning for the dead king, and were amazed at
            the speech of the horse and at the loosening of its bonds.</p>
         <p n="51">The holy Irene said: "Bring the hand that was cut off close to the place from
            which it was cut. And make it touch the place." And they did accordingly. Then Irene
            turned to the East, and lifted up her eyes<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15"/> and her
            hands to heaven. And she prayed, with weeping and sobs, to God, saying, "God the Father
            in heaven, who hast established the foundations of the earth; Thou Rock that never
            movest, and fortress that never dost capitulate, Sun of Righteousness and path of life,
            and Way of salvation, who sittest on the right hand of Him who sent thee, O Lord, my God
            and my betrothed, Jesus the Christ, Son of the Living God, Thou who callest sinners to
            repentance, that they may turn to <milestone unit="folio" n="116b"/> the knowledge of
            the truth and not perish, Merciful and Pitiful One, hearken to my voice, and look on the
               humble<pb n="112"/>estate of Thy handmaiden. May Thy strong power come from heaven on
            this dead man and raise him up, that this crowd may see these things and believe and
            glorify Thy holy name; and know that Thou art the Lord of the heaven and of the earth,
            and the Redeemer of all men who believe in Thee."</p>
         <p n="52">And when she had finished her prayer, the soul of that dead man entered into him,
            and he lived, and arose, and sat up. And his daughter turned and saw him; and she went
            up to him and took him with her hands and set him up, saying to him: "Rise, my father,
            by the power of Jesus." And he arose and walked to and fro, his hand that was cut off
            being quite whole, and not a blemish being on his body.</p>
         <p n="53">And when all the people saw it, they cried saying, "Great is the God of Irene and
            there is none but Him." And they believed, and turned to God: and three thousand people
            were baptized on that day.</p>
         <p n="54">Then Licinius the king took his daughter by the hand, blessing God and saying,
            "Great is the triumph of thy victory, my daughter! and great thy promise in heaven. Thou
            art called the possession of Jesus, and the inheritance of the Christ; O most fortunate
            of children! O consolation and faith of parents! Children like thee, my daughter, are
            able to save their fathers from a painful death! Behold! I also am henceforth a
            Christian, and a servant of Jesus. And henceforth I renounce this kingdom of the world
            that <milestone unit="folio" n="117a"/> passeth away, and I look for the kingdom of
            heaven that passeth not away; and I leave this kingdom to him who wishes to inherit it.
            And I will take thy mother, my daughter, and I will go to the castle that I have built
            for thee; and I also will see Jesus as thou hast seen Him; and I will know Him like
            thee; and I will be His own and will seek refuge in Him. For I am unable to be king <pb
               n="113"/>inasmuch as I have confessed Jesus and have been called a Christian; lest
            the neighbouring kings come upon me and destroy me from life. For I know and I believe
            that inasmuch as I have believed in Jesus, they will not be able to hurt me."</p>
         <p n="55">Then the king took the queen, and they went away to the castle, and were there
            confessing the Christ.</p>
         <p n="56">Then the blessed one remained in the city doing miracles, and signs of cures. And
            she taught the word of truth and instructed many; and baptized them in the name of the
            Father, and the Son, and the Holy Spirit.</p>
         <p n="57">After these things Zedekia the king heard what had become of king Licinius, and
            of the deeds which his daughter had done: and he was astonished. And he took a great and
            countless army, and went to Magdu, the city of king Licinius: and when he entered it and
            alighted in it, he called the magnates of the city, and asked them, "Where is your king?
            "And they returned him an answer and said, "He is dwelling in the castle which he had
            built for his daughter, he and his wife." The king said, "And his daughter, is she with
            him?" The <milestone unit="folio" n="117b"/> magnates said, "No, my lord." The king
            said, "And where doth she dwell? Is she in the city?" They said, "She dwells with
            Apellianus her teacher."</p>
         <p n="58">And then the king sent to seek Apellianus the teacher. And he came, and stood in
            his presence. "Tell me," said the king, "thou old man, is the maiden, the daughter of
            king Licinius, with thee? " "Yes, my lord the king," said Apellianus. "What is her
            mind?" said the king, "and what are her meditations? dost thou not know? " "Her thoughts
            and her meditations," said Apellianus, "are mine and those of all who fear God. For from
            evening till evening she partakes of an ounce of bread, and drinks a sixth part of a
            hemina of water. She knows not a table, <pb n="114"/>nor is she acquainted with a bed,
            and neither by night nor by day does she cease from the praise of God, and her eye is
            never done with tears."</p>
         <p n="59">And when the king heard it, he was greatly astonished. And at the dawn of day he
            sent Euphorba with ten chief men to king Licinius, to that castle, and they said to him,
            "O king, live for ever! Come to our city and receive us, as is thy good custom. What is
            this that thou hast done? Art thou making a trial of us? Come to thine own palace."</p>
         <p n="60">But when the magnates had said these things to Licinius the king, he said to
            them, "Go ye and say to the king who sent you, * O noble king, live for ever! My kingdom
            is given unto thee/ "</p>
         <p n="61">Now when king Zedekia heard these things, he went into the palace of king
            Licinius; and he took his kingdom <milestone unit="folio" n="118a"/> and inherited
            everything that he possessed.</p>
         <p n="62">And on the following day king Zedekia sent his secretary and his great men for
            the maiden Irene, because of the honour [due to] her father. And the Hyparch and the
            magnates who were with him went to the house of Apellianus, to Irene; and they said to
            her, "O daughter of a king! behold the king seeks thee."</p>
         <p n="63">And she arose with great joy, and went, and entered the king's presence, and
            stood before him. And when the king saw her, he said, "Peace be to thee!" But she did
            not answer him a word. And after a little while she said to him, "Why didst thou call
            for me? "The king said, "Let us sit and talk about the peace of the city." Irene said,
            "I will not sit with iniquitous people, nor will I enter into the assembly of the
            sinners; nor will I sit upon the seat of the scorners."<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n16"/> "Am I then a sinner and an iniquitous man ?" said the king. Irene
            said, "Truly every one who is a pagan is wicked and iniquitous." Irene said, "I will not
            sit with iniquitous people, nor will I enter into the assembly of the sinners; nor will
            I sit upon the seat of the scorners. " "Am I then a sinner and an iniquitous man ?" said
            the king. Irene said, "Truly every one who is a pagan is wicked and iniquitous."</p>
         <pb n="115"/>
         <p n="64">But when the king heard [it] he was exceedingly wroth, and was filled with
            threatenings: and he said, "Irene, sacrifice to the gods ! "Irene said, "In vain art
            thou disturbed, O king! Satan, thy father, excites thee and inflames thee against me.
            But I do not fear thy threats; because I have believed in Jesus. And He saves me from
            all thy wiles, and all thy hateful counsels concerning me are useless.'' And the king
            commanded them to dig a pit thirty cubits wide and thirty cubits deep, and to throw wild
            beasts into it, and snakes, and scorpions, and asps, and serpents, and vipers, and all
            the stinging things of Satan. And the servants of wickedness did accordingly.</p>
         <p n="65">And the king commanded them to bring the blessed <milestone unit="folio" n="118b"
            /> Irene, and to carry her and throw her into that pit. And the servants of sin led her
            and carried her thither. And they said to her, weeping, "Why dost thou not sacrifice, O
            daughter of the king, and live? but thou hast made this choice for thyself to die a
            grievous death." But she said, "Be silent, for ye know not what ye are saying."</p>
         <p n="66">And that blessed one looked down into the pit and saw all the reptiles that were
            in it, and she said, "How shall I go down? "And they said, "The king has commanded that
            thou shalt be thrown head downwards into it."</p>
         <p n="67">Then Irene lifted up her hands and raised her eyes<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n17"/> upwards, weeping; and she prayed to Jesus, saying, "O Lord the
            Christ, behold, for Thy sake I bear these things. And I go down into this pit [leaning]
            on the power of Thy divinity. Show Thy favour to me, O Lord, and let the iniquitous
            people and their father, Satan, be ashamed."</p>
         <p n="68">And she made the sign of Jesus between her eyes, and on her breasts, and threw
            herself head downwards into the midst of the pit. And when she reached the bottom, all
            these reptiles ran away from before her, and stuck to the <pb n="116"/>walls of the pit;
            and had stuck [to them] and died. And the blessed Irene opened her mouth and prayed,
            saying, "I confess to thee, O Lord, whose are the heaven and the earth, that Thou art
            from everlasting to everlasting. Thou hast created all men, O Lord, upon the earth. Thou
            didst send our Lord Jesus the Christ, Thy Son, and Thy Beloved, for the redemption of
            the world; and He came and was <milestone unit="folio" n="119a"/>born of Mary the
            Virgin; and He conquered all the power he enmity of Satan; and frustrated all his wiles;
            and He gave strength and power to those men who worship Him and believe in Him, that
            they should tread on the wild beasts, and the scorpions, and the serpents, and the
            vipers, and on all the stinging things of the enmity of Satan. And Thou hast to-day
            shown Thy grace towards the weakness of Thy handmaiden. And Thou hast slain all these
            evil reptiles by Thy strong power and Thy swift commandment. And Thou hast saved me by
            the help of Thy favour. I confess to Thee and I give Thee glory that Thou hast not
            overlooked my low estate. And Thy grace has come to my help. And Thou hast kept me as
            the apple of the eye."</p>
         <p n="69">And she was in the pit for fourteen days, and she took no nourishment. But she
            was fed by the Holy Spirit. And it was told to the king that all these evil reptiles had
            died; and had stuck to the walls in dying. And the king and his magnates were greatly
            astonished when they heard it. And on the following day the king called her and said to
            her, "Irene, sacrifice to the gods! Behold, thou hast killed all the reptiles, and thou
            art alive."</p>
         <p n="70">Irene said, "O many headed Satan! is this thy question with me? But I ask thee, O
            son of deceit, tell me." She said, u Has the weak power of thy gods done any
            enchantments like these? or is there any power like this that they have killed evil
            reptiles? except the power of Jesus?"</p>
         <pb n="117"/>
         <p n="71">But when the king heard this, he was filled with <milestone unit="folio" n="119b"
            />rage and said, "Bring me hither two carpenters and two saws." And they brought [them]
            to him as he had said. And he commanded them to squeeze the lamb of the Christ in the
            press of the carpenters, and to saw her in twain. And the servants of sin did according
            to the commandment of the king; and they squeezed her in the press. And they placed a
            saw above her head; and the carpenters lifted them up to saw her; and the saw became
            blunted, and did not hurt the body of the maiden. When the judge saw that the saw did
            not touch her body, he commanded that there should be a tall engine, and that they
            should tie her there to stakes, and saw her in twain. And the engine came; and they tied
            the blessed one to it, and they placed the saw above her head. And they let go the saw,
            and in that hour the saw was cleft in twain; and the carpenters fell from the engine;
            and they also were cleft and died. And the king saw that the two carpenters were dead,
            and that the saw was cleft. And he turned towards all the people and said, "They have
            made the engine idiotically, and they have let the saw go suddenly, and it was cleft,
            and the engine is fallen, and they are dead. It has befallen them well; for it was not
            right for them to meddle with a matter that was too difficult for them, and that they
            knew nothing about, I am free from their mistake and from their blood." And he commanded
            that there should be a saw double the size of the one which was cleft. And they squeezed
            the blessed one again into the carpenter's press; and began again to saw her. And that
            saw was melted like wax.</p>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="120a"/>
         <p n="72">And the believing woman laughed at their tortures and [their] sawing; and her
            body was not hurt, and her colour was not changed: and she gave glory to God.</p>
         <p n="73">And when the king saw that it profited nothing, he commanded them to bring a
            great saw, and to bring a huge <pb n="118"/>stone of five hundred pounds [weight] and
            they put it on her breast; and that they should saw her feet off from her knees. And the
            servants of sin did accordingly; and they sawed off the feet of the blessed one.</p>
         <p n="74">But she was singing praises to God with joy and with a loud voice. And she did
            not feel the pain. And when the king saw that the feet of the blessed one were cut off,
            he laughed, and said, "Irene, where is thy God? let Him come now and deliver thee from
            my hands, if He can." Irene said, "By the life of Jesus who has redeemed me and is
            redeeming me, for there is no grace for thee."</p>
         <p n="75">And the king was enraged and blasphemed God; for the bystanders were afraid to
            weep openly in his presence but they wept in secret and murmured, saying, "Bitter are
            the punishments of the king and iniquitous are his commandments." For they took pity on
            the beauty of the maiden and on her youth.</p>
         <p n="76">And suddenly the air was aflame, and there were fearful thunderings and fierce
            lightnings; and terrible noises and mighty voices, like none that had ever been before.
            And darkness overspread the earth, and the earth trembled; and a voice of the trumpeting
            of angels came from the sky.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18"/> And when the king saw
            it, he feared greatly, and said, "Let us flee to the city! let every man flee to
               <milestone unit="folio" n="120b"/>his house!" And the king fled and those who were
            with him to get into the city. And the blessed one remained with her feet cut off, and
            that stone lying on her breasts. The king said, "Lift it away. Now we will see if the
            Christ will come to deliver her." And when they had lifted it, and all the people had
            fled, one of the harlots remained beside her whose name was Curica. She said to the
            blessed one, "I will not leave thee, thou handmaid of the Christ! with thee I will die,
            and with thee I will live in life eternal."</p>
         <pb n="119"/>
         <p n="77">But as for the king and the great men who were with him who had fled, that they
            might go into the city, they imagined that he had gone before them; justice was behind
            them bringing (him) to them. And they had come unwillingly, and stood beside the blessed
            one, and then they knew that God had come near on her behalf. And when the king saw that
            harlot beside her, he commanded, and they beheaded her with the sword. And when she was
            dying the handmaid of the Christ said, "Pray for me, that I may not be separated from
            thee." And Irene sealed her in the name of the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
            And she stretched out her neck and received joyfully the crown of martyrdom by the
            sword. And suddenly God cast fear upon the king and upon his great men, and they arose
            affrighted and were silent in astonishment; and were unable to walk hither or thither.
            Then two angels came down from heaven by the com- <milestone unit="folio" n="121a"/>
            mandment of God, beside the virgin of the Christ, and they loosed her from her bonds,
            and rolled away the stone from her breasts; and took up her feet which had been cut off,
            and brought them close to the places from which they had been severed. And the blessed
            one was healed and arose sound in body. And they went up to heaven.</p>
         <p n="78">And the handmaiden of the Christ sang praises to God without ceasing. And she ran
            and reached the city before the king. But a current of air followed the king and his
            magnates, it was very cold by reason of the hail which had come; and it slew three
            thousand men of these pagans, but it did not hurt the king; because he was kept for the
            wrath to come.</p>
         <p n="79">And the people who were left cried out, saying, "Truly great is the God of Irene,
            and there is none but He." And they called on the Lord, saying, "Have mercy upon us, O
            God! according to Thy grace, and blot out our sins in <pb n="120"/>Thy compassion.
            Forgive us our iniquity in Thy pity, because our hope is in Thee; and in Thee we take
            refuge." And on that day eight thousand souls believed.</p>
         <p n="80">And the king called the damsel, and said to her, "Lo! thou hast killed three
            thousand people with thine enchantments, and thou hast snatched away eight thousand from
            the gods. When they saw that thy feet were healed they believed in thy God. Now approach
            and sacrifice, lest thy life vanish miserably from the world."</p>
         <p n="81">Irene said, "O furnace of falsehood<ellipsis>
               <metamark>......</metamark>
            </ellipsis>of error, son of Satan! art thou not ashamed and dost thou not fear God? Thou
            hast not laid to heart the coldness of the air which <milestone unit="folio" n="121b"/>
            occurred. And did not trembling dwell in thy heart at the death of thy wicked comrades?
            and didst thou not fear Him who saved thee from a death like theirs?<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n19"/> For thou didst not escape from that death because
            of thy righteousness, but that the crown of my martyrdom might be plaited and adorned by
            thy hands."</p>
         <p n="82">And when the king had heard (this) he was filled with a great rage, and he called
            the Eparch, and said to him, "Wilt thou not say by what kind of death I shall slay that
            [woman] of hateful name? "The Eparch said, "Let them carry her to where there is a mill;
            and let them bind her against the spoke of the wheel; and let them fix iron hooks on the
            ends of the spokes, and let the water on to the wheel. And when the force of the water
            shall strike on the wheel and it shall revolve, the hooks will take away from her sides,
            and thus the disappearance of her life from the world will be very grievous." And the
            servants of sin did thus, and they fixed wood against the wheel, and bound the virgin of
            the Christ to it. And they let out the water at the wheel, and at once the water became
            hard as stone, and did not move. And the wheel did nob tremble, and <pb n="121"/>the
            body of the blessed one was unhurt. But the king and the magnates who were standing
            round him were amazed. And the blessed Irene laughed and said to them, mocking, "O
            mistaken people! Ye have made instruments of torture after your own pleasure by your
            commandment, and they do not obey you. And in vain do ye weary yourselves<ellipsis>
               <metamark>......</metamark>
            </ellipsis>therefore do what is incumbent on you<ellipsis>
               <metamark>......</metamark>
            </ellipsis>that<ellipsis>
               <metamark>......</metamark>
            </ellipsis>of fortitude, and my heroism may be made known to you and to many." But the
            king and his magnates said to her, "Irene, why dost thou not sacrifice to the gods?" And
               <milestone unit="folio" n="122a"/> she said, "Because of the hour of the trumpet
            which will bring you to life."</p>
         <p n="83">Then she said, "When I have truly seen dogs p s. xxii. 16 encompassing me, and
            the assembly of the wicked have enclosed me,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20"/> as
            David has said, 'The wicked walk on every side,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21"/>
            like the vile exaltation of the sons of Edom, and their words are softer than oil, yet
            are they javelins; their tongue is as a sharp sword;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22"
            /> and their poison is like that of cruel vipers. They have compassed me like hornets,
            they are quenched as the fire of stubble.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23"/> Their
            sword shall enter into their heart, and their bows shall be broken.'<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n24"/> O hypocrites! hearken and understand, 15 that the
            prophecy has said these things against you."</p>
         <p n="84">The king said, "Irene, come, go up the ascent of the mill-wheel, till my mind
            takes counsel and my intelligence devises<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25"/> tortures
            that are more bitter than these for thee." And when she had gone up, he commanded that
            she should be bound in the prison-house. And the servants of sin carried her and shut
            her up in the prison-house. And suddenly God cast contentions into the minds of all the
            citizens, and excited them against the king. And they raised a persecution against him,
            and the patricians and the plebeians of the whole city were assembled, and they <pb
               n="122"/>said to him, "As for thee, what art thou doing in our city? and why dost
            thou sit in a palace which is not thine own? Get thee out of our city, for thou art not
            our king. Long live our king Licinius ! "Then they stoned him and put him out of their
            city, and he went to his city. And in <milestone unit="folio" n="122b"/>seven days he
            died, and Severon his son reigned after him. And twenty days after the death of his
            father, he assembled a great army, about a hundred thousand fighting men. And he
            purposed in his mind that he would go to the city of Magdo, and lay it waste, and avenge
            by its means the insult [done] to his father, and his death. For he went to that city
            filled with anger and rage, and he threatened concerning it that he would swallow it
            like a dragon. For when those citizens had heard [of it] fear fell upon them, and they
            said to Irene, "My lady, perhaps it is for thy sake that our city is desolate and we are
            dying "; and they closed the gates of the city, and none might go out and none might
            enter for fear of the king; for there were a hundred thousand fighting men with him,
            besides many others who were allied with him, for they came because of the spoiling of
            the city. And when the blessed one saw that the citizens were disturbed and were
            weeping, she said to them, "Peace be to you. Fear not. I will go out and go on to meet
            him."</p>
         <p n="85">But they said to her, "We implore of thee, lady, we shall die and our city will
            be laid waste; but thou shalt not go out to any place; and thou shalt not go near him,
            lest he slay thee."</p>
         <p n="86">But a certain faithful man was there, whose name was Alexander. He said to the
            citizens, "You are making a <milestone unit="folio" n="123a"/> mistake by too great
            haste. This is she who has slain all that bad vermin by the power of God; and she has
            also raised up her father, and she has brought down an angel from above by her prayer;
            and she has done many signs. <pb n="123"/>Does she fear the rustle of the wing of this
            locust? For are not his threats weak beside the strength of this valiant woman? Fear not
            therefore." But when they heard these words, they opened the gates of the city and
            allowed her to go out.</p>
         <p n="87">And she went and reached the kings presence. And she saw his numerous troops
            surrounding him. And she turned to the east and raised her hands and her eyes<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n26"/>aloft. And she prayed and said, "O Lord God! whose
            are the heaven and the earth, as Thou didst hear the voice of Elisha the prophet, and
            didst strike the people with a phantom, show the wonder here also, and hearken to the
            voice of the prayer of Thy handmaid and show the power of Thy might this day, and strike
            this people with a phantom, and keep the light of day from their eyes, because they are
            going to lay waste an innocent city; and they threaten to destroy the life of many
            persons." And when she had finished her prayer, the Lord smote that people with a
               phantom.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27"/> And as for the king, his limbs were
            loosened, and his chiefs beheld that their light<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28"/>
            was taken from them. He said to Irene, "Irene, now I know that the power of God
            accompanies thee. Pray for <milestone unit="folio" n="123b"/> us to thy God, and we
            shall see the light."</p>
         <p n="88">And she bent the knee and prayed to God, and their eyes were opened, and they saw
            the light. And their limbs also which had been loosened, were healed. And the king and
            his great men entered the city, and the great army that was with him; and the blessed
            Irene. And in the morning he assembled the whole city and said to them persuasively,
            "Peace be unto you. Fear not, there will be no trouble to any man in your city. There is
            quiet and peace between me and you."</p>
         <pb n="124"/>
         <p n="89">And the next day the king said, "Call Irene to me," And they called her and
            brought her. And they said, "Lo! she is standing before thy majesty." The king said,
            "Irene, I have forgiven the fault of the city, but I will not forgive thee, because thou
            wert the hateful cause of the stoning of my father; and he was stoned, and he died. Now
            if thou desirest that I should not requite at thy hands the contumely and the blood of
            my father, sacrifice to the gods."</p>
         <p n="90">Irene said, "Thou art cursed by God [thou] and thy counsel. But do not thou
            trifle, but turn to the counsel of thy father, Satan. And what he advises, do it to me
            quickly and without delay, that thou also mayest know the power of God that is in
            me."</p>
         <p n="91">And the king was wroth with a very great wrath. And he commanded concerning her
            that she should be kept in the prison-house. And they carried her to the prisonhouse.
            And the king said to his great men, "With what torture ought we to kill her? "And they
            said to him what Satan had sown in their hearts, "Let thy majesty command them to bring
            three hundred of the best nails, and let them be fixed under her feet. And let sand be
            dropped into a sack and let her carry it on her shoulders. And let them put a muzzle in
            her mouth and let one of the soldiers lead her and conduct her for five miles, and make
            her return [for] five. With this torture she will sacrifice or die."</p>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="124a"/>
         <p n="92">And whilst she was in the prison, our Lord Jesus the Christ appeared to her, and
            a host of angels. And He said to her, "Irene, fear not, for I am with thee; and my
            Father, with the Holy Spirit, are helping with thy struggle. And all the armies of
            heaven are helping with thy conflict. And even the bones of the righteous fathers
            delight in thy victory." And our Lord set His seal upon her, and ascended up to heaven
            with His holy angels.</p>
         <pb n="125"/>
         <p n="93">And Irene was in the prison-house for fourteen days. And at the end of fourteen
            days the king called her and said to her, "Irene, sacrifice to the gods. Hearken to my
            voice, that thou die not very badly."</p>
         <p n="94">But she answered him not a word. And when the king saw that she gave him no
            answer, he was filled with a great anger. And the king commanded, [saying, ] "Bring me
            three hundred nails, and fasten them under her feet, and load her with a sack of sand,
            and thrust a muzzle in her mouth; and let a soldier lead her like a beast." And the
            servants of sin made her run five miles, and made her return five miles. But the blessed
            lamb of the Christ did not feel the pain in her feet, and the suffering did not reach
            her heart. And when they brought her into the city, many of the pagans were laughing at
            her and saying, "Where is Jesus? Is He not coming to save her now? "</p>
         <p n="95">But the blessed one saw an angel who was standing before her. And he held a rod
            of iron and struck it on the earth saying thus: "The engulfing of the enemies of
            righteousness to-day." And when the blessed one came and arrived at the place where she
            had seen the angel standing, the earth opened its mouth and swallowed up the <milestone
               unit="folio" n="124b"/> servants of sin, and many pagans. And the nails were taken
            away from her feet, and the sack of sand that she carried; and the muzzle was taken from
            her mouth, and they were swallowed up with the infidels. And when the king saw this sign
            of a wonder, he was amazed and astonished. And he turned round and said to the crowd of
            the infidels, "They had sinned some sin before the gods, therefore hath the earth
            swallowed them up." And in all these things the heart of the king was hardened, and that
            of his magnates, and they believed not in God. And the angel of God turned hastily
            towards the assembly of the wicked, and he slew many of them. But the number of those
            who were <pb n="126"/>engulfed with those who died was ten thousand; and those who were
            left cried to the Lord God, saying, "Have mercy upon us; oh God! and forgive us our sins
            by Thy grace, and be reconciled to us, according to Thy mercies; for Thou art the
            merciful God, who hast done many wonders by the hand of Irene." And three thousand souls
            believed in God at that moment.</p>
         <p n="96">And as the king did not wish to believe, the Lord smote him and slew him.</p>
         <p n="97">But the blessed lamb of the Christ went into the city, and taught many, and
            baptized them in the name of the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Spirit. And they
            brought near to her those who were sick with various and hateful diseases, and she cured
            them by the power of God. For the grace of God accompanied the holy Irene. And moreover
            they brought near to her those in whom there <milestone unit="folio" n="125a"/> were
            evil spirits, and she cured them by the power of God. And she chased away the demons.
            And they brought to her a certain six years old boy, in whom was an evil spirit, which
            withered him up.</p>
         <p n="98">And when she saw it she was grieved on account of his youth. And she asked the
            mother of the boy: "How old is this child? "And the boy's mother said: "Six years old,
            lady." And the blessed one, the handmaid of the Christ, took pity on the boy. And she
            lifted him up in her arms, and sealed him in the name of the Father, and the Son, and
            the Holy Ghost. And she prayed and said: "God who has created man in His image, the
            merciful, the pitiful, He who has said: ' I do not wish the death or destruction of men/
            O Lord God! whose are the heaven and the earth, rebuke Satan and all his temptations,
            and look on the tender age of this boy, and send him help from Thy sanctuary, and let
            all men know that Thou hast answered them who call upon Thee in truth; and shew <pb
               n="127"/>the sign of Thy miracle in him who has wronged this boy, and may this demon
            speak and make [himself] known to me."</p>
         <p n="99">And when the blessed one had prayed and finished her prayer, the angel of God
            bound the demon and set him before her. And when she saw the demon, she said to him,
            "Tell me, thou unclean demon, why hast thou subjugated this boy and spoilt his youth?"
            Said the demon: "I implore thee, my lady, I have surely been sent." Irene said: "God
            doth not tempt, and willeth not the death of man. Tell me, therefore, who hath sent
            thee." The demon answered: "Wicked men who treat each other badly." Irene said: "Shew me
            who it is that sent thee." <milestone unit="folio" n="125b"/> Said the demon: "I have
            told thee, my lady, that they are wizards, the enemies of the justice of God, and our
            friends. Therefore we are sent by them for vengeance. And we go wheresoever we are sent.
            And some men we corrupt, and some we paralyse; and some of them we put to death in ways
            that are bad and varied."</p>
         <p n="100">Irene said: "Bring them to me, those who have sent thee." The demon said: "My
            lady, whilst I am standing here I will tell thee their names."</p>
         <p n="101">Irene said: "Who are they?" The demon said: "I implore of thee, my lady, Amos
            and Euteles, they who have a bazaar near the great portico of the Temple of Fortune of
            the city, and who have also a bank."</p>
         <p n="102">Then she sent and had them both brought, and she said to them, "Hear ye what
            this demon saith? Look if he be speaking the truth. And I will not loose the demon;
            because a demon has never spoken the truth, and see if ye have sent him; and so far as I
            think, he speaks the truth from fear, for no demon is able to stand up before the
            servants of God and lie, for he fears lest they should destroy him."</p>
         <pb n="128"/>
         <p n="103">And the holy Irene turned towards all the people, and said: "Brethren, do not
            believe the demon, because he is a liar, and does not desire the quiet of men, but wars
            and contentions; because he is the enemy of justice. But I ask you to tell me the truth.
            Has it ever been heard by you about these men that they are malefactors? "</p>
         <p n="104">They said, "Yes, lady, they are bad, and their parents also followed these bad
            courses, and they have corrupted <milestone unit="folio" n="126a"/> and destroyed many
            people of the city."</p>
         <p n="105">And she said to these two bad men, "Verily ye have sinned like men and have made
            God angry, but now repent towards Him; and your sins shall be forgiven; and your debts
            shall be blotted out."</p>
         <p n="106">And they returned her an answer: "But as for us, lady, we do not know what thou
            hast said, and we cannot approach to that business." And when Irene saw that they denied
            about their deeds and that they did not want to confess and repent towards God, she said
            to them: "Ye yourselves know; I am freed from your blood." And she looked to heaven and
            said: "Lord Jesus the Christ, Son of the Living God, if it be true what they say about
            these men, and if they do not want to confess and repent, shew concerning them a sign of
            miracle in the sight of every one; and let those who are standing here see and know that
            Thou only art the God of truth." And immediately a fire was kindled in their hearts, and
            it took hold of their bodies, and they were burnt. For the burning came from themselves
            and amongst them, and they were like a flaming furnace. And they burned and became like
            burnt firebrands. And when they saw them a great fear fell amongst them. And after these
            things she lifted the boy in her arms, and looked to heaven and prayed. And she sealed
            him in the name of the Father, and Son, and Holy Spirit. And he was healed and she gave
            him quite whole to his mother.</p>
         <pb n="129"/>
         <p n="107">But when the great crowd who were standing there saw the death and destruction
            of the wicked people, and the healing of the boy, they gave praise to God and shouted,
            saying, "Great is the God of Irene/'</p>
         <p n="108">And after two days some people were carrying a certain <milestone unit="folio"
               n="126b"/> young man and were going out to bury him. And the blessed Irene saw that
            his parents were weeping, and were lamenting bitterly over him, because he was their
            only son. And she was grieved. And the father of the young man who had died, when he saw
            the holy Irene, came and fell on his face before her feet, saying to her, while
            prostrate, "I beseech thee, lady, have pity on the humiliation of my grey hairs. This
            was the only son I had. And if thou wilt, pray to God that he may live. For we also are
            Christians, lady, and disciples of the Word of thy holiness, and by means of thee we
            have known the Living God."</p>
         <p n="109">And she took pity on his old age, and went with him to those who were carrying
            the bier. And she spake to the bearers and they laid the bier down on the earth. And she
            turned to the whole crowd and said, "My fellow believers, offer prayer to God with me."
            And she stretched out her hands and looked<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29"/> towards
            heaven, and prayed, saying, "O Lord God, King of the ages, He who sitteth on the
            cherubim and the seraphim stand before Him: and the angels and the archangels and all
            the hosts of heaven serve Him with fear. O God who didst shew wonders by the hands of
            the prophets and of the holy fathers; Lord of the righteous, and Lover of the penitent;
            He whom the prophets sought for and whose faith the Apostles preached: in the created
            [world] by Jesus the Christ, the Son of the Living God; He who said, 'He that believeth
            on me, greater works than these which I do, shall he <pb n="130"/>do.'<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n30"/> He who gave life to the only son of the widow, and
            snatched the daughter of Jairus from death by His hand, <milestone unit="folio" n="127a"
            /> He who called Lazarus out of the grave, and brought him up out of Sheol, the
            voracious pit. And now, Lord, Thou art and Thou dost exist for ever. Shew, Lord, the
            power of Thy might in this dead man, and let him live, and stand up; because he also is
            the only son of his parents. And let these multitudes see [it] and praise Thy holy name.
            And let all the erring ones turn towards Thee."</p>
         <p n="110">And when she had finished her prayer, the dead man lived and arose and ran and
            came before her and adored her. But when these crowds saw it they were astonished and
            they praised God. And many believed in God on that day. And on that day, by the will of
            God, Timothy the holy priest came to the holy woman. And she saw him and rejoiced with
            great joy. And she ran and did obeisance to him as to the apostle of Jesus. And she led
            him and went to the castle where her father and her mother dwelt. And she said to the
            great crowd of the believers, "My brethren, be active, and come with me as far as the
            castle." And as they were on their way, it was told to Licinius her father, "Thy
            daughter and a priest of God are coming towards thee." And when he heard [it], he
            rejoiced with great joy. And when he saw the great crowd that was coming, he commanded
            that all the gates of the wall should be opened, and the gates of the castle itself. And
            the king and queen ran and went joyfully out to meet the holy priest, and Irene their
            daughter. For their mind exulted when they heard that their daughter was alive, and was
            coming towards them.</p>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="127b"/>
         <p n="111">And when they saw their daughter with the holy priest, they ran and did
            obeisance to him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31"/> And they wept and <pb n="131"
            />kissed and embraced their daughter lovingly, and praised God. For they had imagined
            that their daughter was dead. And when they saw her in life, they rejoiced and praised
            God. And the blessed one turned to her father and her mother, and said to them, "Peace
            be to you, my beloved parents. Be not troubled and weep not, for behold God hath given
            you His grace, and by means of the fruit of your blood ye have known God." And she
            turned to the holy priest and said to him, "I beseech of thee, my lord, priest of the
            living God, complete thy blessing and thy favour to my weakness; and baptize my father
            and my mother, and the many young men who are hoping to receive the symbol of the
            Christ": and she said to her father and to her mother, "Dear parents, behold [, this is]
            the day when your debts shall be wiped out, and ye shall be washed from the filth of
            your sins. Behold, our Lord Jesus hath sent the holy priest. Take the baptism and
            receive the symbol of the Christ; and partake of the marriage feast of the heavenly
            king." And they said, "And what may prevent it, O beloved daughter?"</p>
         <p n="112">And the priest took the oil, and blessed and anointed them, and he blessed upon
            and sanctified the water, and baptized the king and the queen and also the soldiers: and
            [of] the troops of the king four hundred persons who were with them, and fifty thousand
            persons of the many people who had come there. And after the holy priest had baptized
            them, the holy Irene greeted<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n32"/> her father and her
               <milestone unit="folio" n="128a"/> mother, and all the rest of the household. And the
            blessed one commanded them and said to them, "Be confirmed in what ye have received. Be
            valiant in Jesus, and be strong in the faith. Lo! ye have received baptism. Your bodies
            are cleansed, and ye are mingled with the sheep of Jesus. Your hearts are sanctified to
            be a dwelling<pb n="132"/>place of Jesus." And she said to them, "Abide in peace, and if
            it please the Lord Jesus, I will see you again." And she went out of the castle with the
            priest, and many people. But the king and the queen remained in the castle, and the four
            hundred persons who were with them, who had been baptized, praising God, and there was
            great joy in that city.</p>
         <p n="113">And afterwards two lepers drew near to her, who came from a far country. And she
            saw the dust that was upon their faces, and that their shoes were split, and she knew
            that they had come from afar. And she said to them, "Why have ye come to me? Behold, I
            am a weak woman, commonplace and feeble, and I possess nothing in this world, and I am a
            sinner." But they said to her, "O lady! thou doest well to humble thyself in [relation
            to] thine own will. But towards God thou art elect and great. And thou dost fulfil the
            word of Jesus thy Bridegroom; for thou hast heard that He said, 'Whosoever humbleth
            himself shall be exalted.'"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33"/></p>
         <p n="114">And those people threw themselves down on the ground before her feet, and they
            wept and said, "If thou wilt, lady, pray for us to God, and we shall be cleansed from
            our leprosy."</p>
         <p n="115">Then the holy one threw herself down before the Lord <milestone unit="folio"
               n="128b"/> and shed tears with sobs, and prayed, saying, "O Lord God, to whom belongs
            the heaven and the earth, hearken unto the voice of Thy handmaid. And in Thy compassion
            grant my request: and may Thy power come from on high on the bodies of these people, and
            may they be cleansed, and let many see [it] and praise Thy great and fearful name." And
            whilst she was praying, the angel of God came and stood before her. And he said to her,
            "Peace be unto thee, Irene, virgin of the Christ."</p>
         <p n="116">And when she saw the angel, she said, "Blessed be <pb n="133"/>Thou, O God, to
            whom belongs the heaven and the earth, for Thou hast heard the voice of Thy humble
            servant, and hast not turned away Thy face from me. But Thou hast sent Thine angel from
            on high from before Thy holy throne; and he has come to heal and to cleanse the bodies
            of these people." And immediately a fountain of water sprang up there. And when the
            blessed one saw it,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34"/> she praised God and said,
            "This spring is from the holy water of Jordan, of that which Elisha the prophet blessed;
            and the Lord of Elisha blessed [it] by His baptism."</p>
         <p n="117">And she said to these men, "Go in and wash in that water, confessing the Father,
            and the Son, and the Holy Spirit; and your bodies shall be cleansed, and shall become
            tender as infants." Then these men went with great fear into the fountain of water,
            saying, "We confess the name of the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Ghost." And they
            came out of the fountain with their bodies cleansed, and fear and astonishment took hold
            of the great crowd <milestone unit="folio" n="129a"/> that was there, and they praised
            God that the blessed Irene, the virgin of the Christ, had done these miracles and
            cures.</p>
         <p n="118">And she was three years in that city. And when Zedekiah and Severon his son were
            dead, Numerianus reigned after them, the son of Septinus. And he inquired about the
            blessed Irene. And he said, "Where is she?" And they said to him, "She is here in the
            city." And he sent soldiers, and commanded them, and said that they should " bring her
            to the city of Callinicus; and let her be kept there until I come." And the soldiers
            found her, those who went out after her; and they brought her to the city of Callinicus;
            and there she was carefully kept in the prison-house until the king should come there.
            And when he came, they informed him [saying], "Irene is there, she <pb n="134"/>whom thy
            Majesty asked for." And he commanded, "Bring her to me." And she came and stood before
            him. And when the king saw her, he was astonished.</p>
         <p n="119">And he said to his great men, "Hallo! this maiden is very like her father." And
            he said, "This girl is [the daughter] of Licinius; he forsook his kingdom, and renounced
            it; and now this city is without a king. On her account Zedekiah my brother was stoned
            and died. And because of her the angel of the Lord smote Severon his son and slew him.
            And I seek to requite their blood at her hands. And I fear lest a fate worse than that
            of my colleagues should befall me. Truly, as I see, this woman is a destroyer of the
            kingdom and also an overturner of kings. And I know not what I shall do to <milestone
               unit="folio" n="129b"/>her." And he turned and said to the advocates who were
            standing in his presence, "Advise me in your wisdom by what torment I shall destroy her
            from the world. She has killed my father,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35"/> and
            Zedekiah my brother; and she caused Severon his son to perish from the world. And what
            will she do to me? She is the extirpator of royalty." The magnates said to him, "Truly
            thou hast spoken well, O lord the king." Then the king commanded that they should bring
            her before him, and they brought her, and she stood before him.</p>
         <p n="120">The king said, "Irene, what dost thou say? Wilt thou sacrifice to the gods or
            wilt thou be obstinate? and dost thou persist in the folly of the Christians? "</p>
         <p n="121">Irene said, "Because thou hast repeatedly said that I am the overturner of
            royalty, I say to thee, that thou also, if thou dost not believe in God, in a very
            little while the judgment of God shall overtake thee also; and thou shalt die a
            frightful and uncommon death. And then thou shalt know that there is a God who rules in
            the heaven <pb n="135"/>and in the earth." And when the king had heard [it] he was
            filled with great rage; and he commanded, "Bring me men who are artificers in copper."
            And they came and stood before him. The king said to them, "Make me three very large
            cows." And they made them and brought them to him. And he commanded that they should be
            greatly heated. And these cows were heated for three days and three nights, until the
            copper was nearly melted. And when the cows were heated, he commanded, and they brought
            Irene before him. The king said, "Irene, what sayest thou? I have commanded that there
            should be <milestone unit="folio" n="130a"/> three cows of copper on thy account. And
            [here] they are. And I have commanded that they should be heated. And they are also
            heated frightfully. Now if thou wilt sacrifice to the gods, thou shalt be delivered from
            a frightful and terrible death. But if thou wilt not sacrifice, thou shalt be cast into
            the cows and shalt be burnt, and shalt die a very hard death. And if thou shouldst
            conquer the one by thy witchcraft, thou shalt be cast into the other; and if again thou
            shouldst conquer the second one by thy skill, thou shalt be cast into the third, and
            shalt perish. And very grievously shalt thou depart And we shall see if Jesus will come,
            He in whom thou believest, and will save thee from my hands. Approach, therefore, and
            sacrifice to the gods."</p>
         <p n="122">Irene said, "Be not troubled, O son of Satan; for however much thy father Satan
            hath excited thee against me, I am not afraid of thee, neither now do thy threats move
            me. See therefore that thou explain to me in the skill of thy deceitful teaching, the
            stripes and the torments of thy contrivances." Then the king was greatly enraged, and
            said to her, "Cursed child! slayer of its parents, extirpator of royalty, thou hast
            called me senseless, I will shew thee what sense there is in me, by means of the
            torments that <pb n="136"/>my mind shall devise against thee." And he commanded them to
            carry her out, and to heat these copper cows. And he commanded the heralds to go out
            into the city and proclaim that all men should come and see the punishment and
            procession of the infidel despiser of the gods. And when all the city was assembled, the
            king came and sat on his judgment-seat, and he commanded them: "Bring before me the
            audacious one, the parricide. 5, And she came and stood before him. The king said,
            "Irene, <milestone unit="folio" n="130b"/> choose between two things, either sacrifice
            to the gods, or go into the copper cow."</p>
         <p n="123">Irene said, "O senseless fool, and ignorant sinner! son of Satan the coiling
            serpent! I have said to thee once [for all] that I am a Christian; and I will not
            sacrifice to the infidel demons nor to the foul fiends; and I will not forsake Jesus the
            Christ, my Lord; and I shall not be forsaken by Him. And these cows which flame by means
            of thine evil skill, are to me fountains of cold water by the help of Jesus, and they
            are of no account to me. For thou shalt see quickly the power of the Lord Jesus to help
            that is with me. And as for thee, His wrath is ready to come upon thee by means of a
            terrible angel. And thou shalt die a fearful and uncommon death; not like thy
            predecessors, but thou shalt die the fearful death of terror. And thine [own] liver
            shall be thy food, and thy lung thy sustenance. And thy punishment shall be from thyself
            and in thyself. And thou shalt know that there is a God in heaven." Then the king waxed
            exceeding wroth, and was like a lion eager to rend. And he commanded them to throw her
            into the copper cow. And when she heard [it,] before the servants of sin had laid hold
            of her and led her out, she made the sign of Jesus on her breasts and between her eyes,
            and she ran boldly to the copper cow and went in. And immediately the fire was quenched;
               <pb n="137"/>and the handmaid of the Christ was set free like a ship on a peaceful
            sea; and waters flowed from the cow itself. But when the judge saw it, he said to the
            people, "Did I not tell you that she would conquer by her witchcraft? "</p>
         <p n="124">But all the people wept bitterly, when they saw the <milestone unit="folio"
               n="131a"/>beauty of her youth, and what torments she suffered.</p>
         <p n="125">Then she prayed in God's presence and said, "O Lord God, who dwellest in the
            highest heavens! hearken to my voice, and let Thy mercy come hither. See, because of Thy
            name I suffer these things. This I know, that Thou hast helped me and wilt help me. But
            because of these crowds, that they may see the sign of a miracle and may praise Thy
            name." And when she had said these things and had prayed, she saw the angel of God
            standing beside her. And he said to her, "Peace be to thee, Irene; fear not, for the
            Lord is with thee, and I have been sent for thy comfort." And she rejoiced and exulted
            at the sight of the angel.</p>
         <p n="126">And then the king commanded them to throw her into the second cow. Irene said,
            "O Satan, and son of Satan, and enemy of justice, if thou hast not been confounded by
            the first cow, thou shalt be confounded by this second one; and thou shalt despise
            thyself. And if again thou art not moved by the second, thou shalt be confounded by the
            end of the third, and shalt blush, when the wrath of the Lord shall come suddenly upon
            thee."</p>
         <p n="127">And he commanded them to throw her into the second cow. But when she heard it,
            she sealed herself in the name of the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Ghost. And she
            went into the cow rejoicing and exulting in the power of Jesus to help. And immediately
            the fire was quenched, and the flame was cooled, and the cow was melted like wax; and
            the blessed one was not hurt. And when the king again saw [it] he said to his magnates,
               <pb n="138"/>"Did I not tell you that she would conquer the fire by her witchcraft?
            "</p>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="131b"/>
         <p n="128">And the king commanded them to throw her into the third cow. But when she had
            heard it, she blessed God and said to the judge, "Thy torments are very insipid and thy
            fire is very cool. Thou art a serpent with many heads, and with thee are thy servants.
            For as for these cows, water instead of fire has come to them." And she went joyfully
            into the third cow in the strength of Jesus, laughing at them, for the pagans imagined
            that there her destruction would be. But when the blessed one entered the third cow, it
            walked as if it were animated in the flesh; that it might proclaim to the unbelievers
            about the grace of God. And that brazen cow walked for four stadia here and there. And
            all the people who were standing there for the spectacle were seized with astonishment,
            saying to one another, "Who has ever seen brass that walked like flesh?" And while they
            were saying these things, they looked and watched whence they should see the blessed
            one. But as for the cow its brass was melted like water; and it fell to the earth, and
            the blessed one appeared in the sight of all men. And they were amazed at this wonder.
            Even the king was greatly astonished that the fire had no power over her. And they all
            cried to the Lord and said, "There is none like unto Thee, CK Lord God, and there are
            none like unto Thy servants. Be merciful to us as in the abundance of Thy grace. Thou
            art He who hast done the miracle by the hand of Irene; and Thou hast shewn Thy might and
            Thy valour amongst the nations." And a hundred thousand souls believed in <milestone
               unit="folio" n="132a"/> God that day. And the few people who were left who were
            unbaptized, believed nevertheless in God.</p>
         <p n="129">And when the king saw that all the people believed in God, he was exceedingly
            wroth and bitter; and he opened <pb n="139"/>his mouth and blasphemed against God. And
            he said to Irene, "I swear by all the gods, that I will not spare thee, but I will cut
            thee up limb by limb; and I will make thee food for dogs." Then Irene laughed and said,
            "Thou and thine imaginations shall be confounded, and all thy contrivances against me,
            thou son of Satan." And when the king had heard [it] he gnashed his tusks like a wild
            boar against her, and blasphemed God. But suddenly the angel of the Lord struck him with
            a pain in his heart, and with an internal wound. And he went to his house screaming. And
            a fire was kindled within him, and he tasted no food, and his liver overflowed and
            swelled up, and his lung was nourishment for him, and worms came out of his mouth: and
            his kinsmen were afraid to come near him. And he yelled and burst asunder and died. And
            his body was decomposed and his bones were scattered. And then the earth did not receive
            his bones. And when he died, he commanded Bura the Eparch to try the virgin of the
            Christ. After the death of the tyrant and of those [who were] with him, the word of God
            had free course by means of the Blessed One; and God was glorified, and the faith became
            mighty, and many were baptized. And she was in the city of Callinicus for thirty days
            doing signs and <milestone unit="folio" n="132b"/> wonders; and she cured many in the
            name of Jesus. She made the deaf hear; she opened [the eyes of] the blind; she cleansed
            the lepers; and she healed all who were in pain; and she baptized many in the name of
            the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Spirit.</p>
         <p n="130">And at the end of thirty days the Eparch went to Tela of Mauzalat.<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n36"/> And he sent soldiers after her to Callinicus to
            bring her. And these soldiers<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37"/> found her. And they
            had heard from many of the citizens the signs and wonders <pb n="140"/>and miracles
            which she had done. And they were greatly astonished. And they approached and said to
            her, "Hail<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38"/> to thee, handmaiden of the Christ! the
               Eparch<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n39"/> sends for thee/'</p>
         <p n="131">Irene said, "And where is the Eparch?" The soldiers said, "In Tela of Mauzalat,
            my lady; and he awaits thee there."</p>
         <p n="132">And the blessed virgin of Jesus arose, and went with them, and entered the city
            of Tela. And it was said to the Eparch: "Behold, Irene has come." The Eparch said,
            "Bring her before me." And she came and stood before him. And when the Eparch saw her,
            he said, "Peace<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n40"/> be to thee, Irene."</p>
         <p n="133">Irene said, "Dost thou greet me with peace? but there shall be no peace upon
            thee. Because God has said, that there is no peace to the wicked."<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n41"/> The Eparch said, "Thou impudent and godless woman! Thou dost surely
            insult me. Approach now and sacrifice to the gods, or dost thou not know that I have
            received a commandment concerning thee from Numerianus<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n42"/> the king to judge <milestone unit="folio" n="133a"/>thee?" Irene
            said, "See, and give heed to thyself, lest thou shouldst follow after him who hast
            commanded thee." The Eparch said, "Approach and sacrifice to the gods, lest I destroy
            thee from off the world by varied tortures." Irene said, "Hearken, O Eparch, and I will
            tell thee. We are a spectacle to men and also to the angels. To men for derision, and to
            the angels for praise. And we are considered as dross by men. Now therefore I say unto
            thee, O Bura the Eparch! prepare for thyself instruments<pb n="141"/>of torture as thou
            wilt, and thou shalt see the power of God in the fortitude with which I shall endure the
            agony. But thou wouldst force me to sacrifice to the lifeless gods, who neither see nor
            hear, nor smell, nor walk, whose makers shall become similar to them, and all those who,
            like thee, trust in them.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43"/> And I would persuade and
            advise thee, to turn and to know the living God, who never dies; He who made thee out of
            nothing; lest thou shouldest die a bad death like thy predecessors."</p>
         <p n="135">The Eparch said, "I swear by all the gods, that I will <milestone unit="folio"
               n="133b"/> not spare thee, nor thy impudence; but I decree for thee these tortures
            that have not yet been seen in the world, nor have they entered into the heart of the
            judges; and they will terrify by their severity all who see them."</p>
         <p n="136">The Eparch said, "Bring me the smiths." And they came and stood before him. And
            he said to them, "Make me an arm-chair of iron, and let it be one cubit high in
            elevation; and make me two thin chains." And they made [them] and brought [them]. And he
            commanded them to make Irene sit down. And she came and stood before him. The Eparch
            said, "Irene, what sayest thou? wilt thou sacrifice to the gods or no?"</p>
         <p n="137">Irene said, "O Satan incarnate! son of the deceiver! how far wilt thou persist
            in thine audacity? Have I not <pb n="142"/>said to thee that I will not sacrifice to
            unclean demons, nor will I worship foul fiends; and I will not forsake my Lord and my
            God, Jesus the Christ; and I shall not be forsaken by Him: for He will deliver me from
            all thine inventions, O senseless fool! "</p>
         <p n="138">Said the Eparch to his servants, "Make her sit down in this iron chair, and bind
            her with these chains, and heap wood above it. And throw fat and wax and naphtha and
            sulphur and pitch and resin upon the wood, and kindle the fire." And the servants of sin
            did thus. And <milestone unit="folio" n="134a"/>when the fire had mastered the wood, and
            had risen above the chair twelve cubits, the Eparch said, "Let us see if Jesus will
            deliver her from my hands." And immediately, by the commandment of God, an angel
            descended from heaven, and seized Irene by her hand, and set her out of the chair. And
            the chair and the iron chains were melted like wax. And he took her out of the flame,
            and placed her on one side out of the fire, when the fire had not reached to her dress.
            And when the Eparch saw that she was standing outside of the flame he was greatly
            astonished; and he feared and trembled greatly. And he ran and fell on his face before
            her feet, weeping, and sought to persuade her, saying, "I implore thee, O lady,
            handmaiden of the Christ, have mercy upon me. Lo! I also believe in thy God, and
            henceforth I am a Christian. And henceforth I renounce all the gods of paganism, and let
            me not die a fearful death, lady."</p>
         <p n="139">But she said to him, "Did I not tell thee that thou wouldst speedily turn
            towards Jesus? "And he said to her, "I implore of thee, lady, pray for me, that I may be
            accepted and not rejected; and that what I have plotted against thee may not come into
            judgment against me." And Irene said, "Peace be to thee, fear not, let no anxiety come
            to thee." But when the crowds who surrounded the <pb n="143"/>Eparch saw that he
            believed in God, many also believed with him, and confessed God.</p>
         <p n="140">And she was there, in that city, for fifty days. And in it she won many to
            Jesus, and the Lord God sent the holy <milestone unit="folio" n="134b"/> priest to her
            in the city of Tela, and he baptized the Eparch and many who were with him who believed
            in the Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
         <p n="141">But Shabur the Persian king had come to Nisibis; and he had heard about the
            blessed Irene, that she was in Tela. And at the end of fifty days, he sent seven
            horsemen after her, and they brought her to Nisibis. And when she had entered the city
            of Nisibis, it was told to Shabur the king: "Irene is come." And he commanded them to
            bring her. And she came speedily and stood before him. But when Shabur the king saw her,
            he did not wish to interrogate her, for he said, "This is the destroyer of royalty." And
            he struck her with the sword which he held in his hand and killed her. The king said,
            "Is not this the famous one? Why has she not killed me? Where is Jesus her helper? Let
            him come now and succour her, if he can."</p>
         <p n="142">Then the Christian brethren came and carried away her holy body, and buried it.
            Said the king: "Lest Jesus should come and raise her up?"</p>
         <p n="143">After these things the king was silent; and found nothing further to say about
            her.</p>
         <p n="144">And she was for four days in the grave. And at the end of four days, an angel
            came down from heaven and raised her up. And he said to her, "Irene, thy struggle is
            finished, and the crown of thy victory is adorned. From henceforth nothing bad shall
            come near to <milestone unit="folio" n="135a"/> thy body; and thou shalt see nothing
            hateful in the world; because the course of thy labour is finished. Rise therefore and
            enter the city, and fear not; and make disciples <pb n="144"/>of many, according to thy
            custom. And king Shabur, who killed thee, will do obeisance to thee, and will try to
            persuade thee to remain in his city. And many will believe in God along with him on
            account of thee. Blessed and happy art thou among women, and great is thy reward in
            heaven, and glittering is the crown of thy victory at the marriage supper of the
            heavenly bridegroom, Jesus the Christ." And the angel went from her up to heaven.</p>
         <p n="145">And the blessed Irene took in her hand an olive branch, and she sang praises and
            psalms. And she went into the city and spake thus: "Let God arise, and let all His
            enemies be scattered; and let those who hate Him flee from before Him,"<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n44"/> and "There is none like unto Thee, O Lord God! and
            there are nothing like unto Thy works. For lo! Thou doest wonders to the dead, and men
            shall arise and praise Thee. O Lord, who is like unto Thee?"<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n45"/></p>
         <p n="146">And when the citizens saw her, they knew that she had risen from the dead, and
            they ran and did obeisance before her. And they shouted, saying, l( Great is the God of
            Irene. And there is no other, but He alone." And when there was a shout and a great
            uproar, the king heard it and was afraid. And he inquired what was the noise of the
            uproar in the city. The dwellers in his palace say <milestone unit="folio" n="135b"/>to
            him, "Because of Irene, who is risen from the tomb, they are thanking and praising God
            who has raised her." And when the king heard [it], he commanded them to bring her into
            his presence. And Irene came and stood before him, carrying the sprig of olive, and
            looking like the dove of Noah, which carried the tidings of peace to the world. Thus
            Irene also carried the olive-leaf, the tidings of her resurrection. And when the king
            saw her, he knelt and did obeisance before her. And he said to her, "Irene, great is thy
            God. And now I know that God dwells with thee. And whosoever opposes thee opposes
            himself. And <pb n="145"/>now, lady, I implore and seek to persuade thee, stay in our
            city, and do what thou wilt with authority and do not fear. Because God is with thee,
            and man is unable to hurt thee." And she was a long time in that city, teaching the word
            of God, and making many disciples. And great was the praise of God because of her. And
            the number of all those who believed in God and were baptized by her hand was a hundred
            and thirty thousand souls.</p>
         <p n="147">After these things she bade farewell to the king and to all the citizens; and
            went to the castle to see her father and her mother. Ten days before she went
               thither<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46"/> Licinius her father died; and she went
            to the castle and found him dead.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47"/> And she was
            grieved and remained there for three days. And after three days she bade <milestone
               unit="folio" n="136a"/> farewell to her mother; and arose, and went to the city. And
            she left her mother in peace, and was in the city for three days.</p>
         <p n="148">And after three days, by the commandment of God, a cloud took up the virgin of
            the Christ, and carried her to the city of Ephesus, and she was there; and she did many
            cures and miracles in the name of Jesus; and she made disciples of many, for the
            citizens held her as one of the Apostles of Jesus. And she was in that city and in its
            district for seven years.</p>
         <p n="149">And Apellianus her secretary heard it, and he arose and came to her to Ephesus.
            And when he saw her, he did obeisance to her. And they both rejoiced at the sight of
            each other. And Apellianus related to the citizens everything that she had endured from
            the kings, and they were very much astonished.</p>
         <p n="150">And on the following day she said to all the citizens, "O brethren and fathers,
            abide in peace. And be strong <pb n="146"/>and firm in the Christ And persevere and be
            established in your faith in the Christ. For to-morrow I shall depart. And ye have
            received me well, and your recompence is preserved in heaven. For ye have heard that our
            Lord said: 'He who receiveth a prophet in the name of a prophet, shall receive a
            prophet's reward; and he who receiveth a righteous man in the name of a righteous man,
            shall receive a righteous man's reward and he who receiveth a stranger for the sake of
            the Christ, the Christ will recompense him in heaven ten thousandfold'."<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n48"/> And when she had said these things, she finished
            her speech. But some of the citizens said, "She has said that she will depart, but where
            then is she going?" And they said further, "Perhaps she is going to die." Others said,
            "Nay, <milestone unit="folio" n="136b"/>but she will ascend to heaven." Others said,
            "Perhaps Jesus the Christ, her Bridegroom will send and guide her: for we do not know it
            because we are sinners. God knows what He will do to His handmaiden."</p>
         <p n="151">But the blessed Irene said to Apellianus her secretary, "Bring with thee six
            Christian men, believers, and come with me to a certain well-known place." And
            Apellianus brought six Christian men of the patricians of the city, and they went with
            her outside the city. And they found a certain coffin of marble that had been laid there
            in that place years before; in which man had never before been</p>
         <p n="152">And Irene said to Apellianus and to those with him, "Beloved and faithful
            brethren, abide in peace. Behold! I shall go into this coffin to-day. And do ye take its
            cover and lay it above it. And for four days let no man come near to the coffin. And she
            went into that coffin, saying, "Brethren, be at peace; and the grace of our Lord Jesus
            the Christ be with you all, amen."</p>
         <p n="153">And she said, "Let an artificer come and bring iron <pb n="147"/>clasps, and
            solder the coffin and also the lid with lead. And mark ye [it] with your signet rings;
            and seal it, and go ye into the city."</p>
         <p n="153">And she commanded them, saying to them, "When four days are finished, come ye
            out and open the coffin; and look, if ye find my body in it, well, good; but if
               <milestone unit="folio" n="137a"/> ye do not find my body in it, do not doubt, but
            know ye that my Lord Jesus, my Bridegroom, hath hidden away the body of His handmaiden
            where He willed. For I know not whither He will carry it; for I have heard that He said,
            ' In my Father's house are many mansions'."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50"/></p>
         <p n="154">And they did as she had said. And an artificer came and put clasps on the lid of
            the coffin, and soldered them with lead; and they all sealed them with their signet
            rings, and went into the city. And after four days, Apellianus drew near at the time of
            dawn, he and six Christian men, they with whose signet rings the coffin was sealed. And
            many of the citizens went out with them to the coffin; and they bent the knee and prayed
            there. And they opened the coffin, and they found the clothes of the virgin of the
            Christ folded up and lying in the coffin. And they did not find her body.</p>
         <p n="155">And they saw the angel of God who was standing there beside the coffin. And he
            said unto them, "Whom seek ye?" They say unto him, "Irene, my lord, perhaps thou knowest
            who has taken her away from here." But he said to them, "Lo! she is enjoying herself in
            the Paradise of Eden, at the marriage feast of the heavenly Bridegroom, Jesus the
            Christ, the Son of God." And fear took hold of them, and perturbation remained in their
            minds; and they went into the city praising and blessing God, about the wonder which
            they had seen. And many who heard it believed, and confessed the name of the <milestone
               unit="folio" n="137b"/>Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit.</p>
         <pb n="148"/>
         <p n="156">This is the martyrdom of Irene; this is the conflict of the virgin of the
            Christ. And she was made the messenger of peace on behalf of all believers.</p>
         <p n="157">And the cities in which she triumphed are: firstly, Magedo, the city in which
            she was born; secondly, Callinicus; thirdly, Tela of Mauzalet; fourthly, Nisibis;
            fifthly, Ephesus, in which was her good end.</p>
         <p n="158">And the kings who judged her: Licinius her father; secondly, Zedekia; thirdly,
            Severon his son; fourthly, Numerianus; fifthly, Bura the Eparch; sixthly, Shabur the
            Persian king, he in whose presence she finished the course of her conflict. Praise be to
            the Christ who gave power to His virgin; and she overcame all the wiles of the devil.
            May God the Christ give us a portion and an inheritance along with her in the kingdom of
            heaven! And may her prayer be for the sinner who composed and wrote her martyrology for
            ever and ever.</p>
         <p n="159">Here endeth the story of the blessed Irene.</p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">1 Literally "teaching."</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">2 Literally "temptation."</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">1 Literally "give."</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">2 Literally "one week of days."</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">2 Literally "one week of days."</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">1 Literally "that fear had fallen upon her.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">Jer. x. 11</note>
            <note xml:id="n8">Ps. cxv. 5</note>
            <note xml:id="n9">1 Or "power of germinating," see Gen. i. 29.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10">2 Literally "all these creatures."</note>
            <note xml:id="n11">Luke ii. 14</note>
            <note xml:id="n12">1 Literally "to enter his presence."</note>
            <note xml:id="n13">2 Literally "gnashing."</note>
            <note xml:id="n14">3 Literally "face."</note>
            <note xml:id="n15">1 Literally "glance.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16">Ps. i. 1</note>
            <note xml:id="n17">1 Literally, "glance."</note>
            <note xml:id="n18">1 Literally "air."</note>
            <note xml:id="n19">1 Literally "from their death."</note>
            <note xml:id="n20">Ps. xxii. 16</note>
            <note xml:id="n21">Ps. xii. 8</note>
            <note xml:id="n22">Ps. lv. 21</note>
            <note xml:id="n23">Ps. cxviii. 12</note>
            <note xml:id="n24">Ps. xxxvii. 15</note>
            <note xml:id="n25">1 Literally " begets."</note>
            <note xml:id="n26">1 Or "glance."</note>
            <note xml:id="n27">II Kings vi. 18</note>
            <note xml:id="n28">2 The MS. adds, "And the king's limbs were loosened along with his
               being bereft of light."</note>
            <note xml:id="n29">1 Literally, "and her look."</note>
            <note xml:id="n30">John xiv. 12</note>
            <note xml:id="n31">1 Literally, "to the holy priest."</note>
            <note xml:id="n32">1 Literally, "gave peace to."</note>
            <note xml:id="n33">Luke xviii. 14</note>
            <note xml:id="n34">1 Literally, "the fountain of water."</note>
            <note xml:id="n35">1 Cod. "her father."</note>
            <note xml:id="n36">1 "Mesembria" in the Sunaxaristes.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37">2 MS. "And the soldiers who went after her to Callinicus."</note>
            <note xml:id="n38">1 Or, "Peace."</note>
            <note xml:id="n39">2 Properly "Hyparch" passim. But as there is no other Syriac
               equivalent for the"E7rapx°s of Irene's biography in the 2uz>a£ap£(TT?7s, we believe
               that the translator means Eparch.</note>
            <note xml:id="n40">3 Or, "Hail."</note>
            <note xml:id="n41">Is. xlviii. 22</note>
            <note xml:id="n42">4 MS. "the king of Edom."</note>
            <note xml:id="n43">Ps. cxv. 8</note>
            <note xml:id="n44">Ps. lxvii. 1</note>
            <note xml:id="n45">Ps. lxxi. 19</note>
            <note xml:id="n46">1 Literally, "to the castle."</note>
            <note xml:id="n47">2 Literally, "that her father had died."</note>
            <note xml:id="n48">Matt. x. 41</note>
            <note xml:id="n49">John xiv. 2</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
