<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Euphemia</title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreading and initial markup of persons, places, and titles by </resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#anorth">Adelaide North</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title level="a">Euphemia</title>
                  <title level="m"> Select Narratives of Holy Women from the Syro-Antiochene or
                     Sinai Palimpsest as Written above teh Old Syriac Gospels by John the Stylite,
                     of Beth-Mari-Qanūn in A.D. 778. </title> Translated by Anges Smith Lewis
                  M.R.A.S. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>C. J. Clay and Sons</publisher>
                  <date>1900</date>
                  <citedRange unit="p" from="149" to="167">149-67</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <p>This transcription renumbers the original footnotes to run sequentially and includes
               marginal references for Biblical citations among the footnotes.</p>
            <p>This text is in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="149"/>
         <p n="1">Again, the martyrdom of the blessed Euphemia, which took place a mile from the
            town of Chalcedon, in the days of the Emperor Trajan Caesar.</p>
         <p n="2">When Priscus was Proconsul in Europe, there was a great assembly of Christians in
            the town of Chalcedon. And Priscus the Proconsul had a wicked friend, whose name was
            Apellianus. And he was a sophist in the <milestone unit="folio" n="138a"/> erudition of
            the Greeks. He was a worshipper of Ares. This Apellianus accused the Christians, saying,
            "O glorious warrior amongst men, and Proconsul wise of heart! let this be known to thy
            Highness. Because Ares is a great god, so all men should offer sacrifices and libations
            to him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> by command of the great Emperor/' And this
            pleased Priscus the Proconsul for the destruction and evil of the souls of those who
            were enchained in error. And he nailed up placards full of menaces and fierce threats in
            all the palace of his Highness, which were inscribed after this manner: "Men and
            friends, citizens of Chalcedon, be it known to you all that it is proper for you to
            hallow a day, that by command of the Emperor there may be offered a sacrifice to the
            great god Ares. But if any one should be found who remains in an evil mind, and preaches
            and teaches the religion of the Christians, I will destroy his body by severe tortures.
            And let this be the sign to you. When at the time of the sacrifices the horn shall sound
               <pb n="150"/>which assembles you all, ye shall all hasten reverently [and] eagerly to
            this temple of Ares and offer sacrifices, and know the great god Ares/' And every day
            Apellianus was assidious, that at the time that the horns should sound, and they should
            move tumultuously before the altar, as was their custom, an investigation should be made
            about every <milestone unit="folio" n="138b"/> man as to who had the greatest zeal. And
            he who blew<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> on the horn blew mightily, and
            collected all who had lost hope. But the Christians, those in whose souls God dwelt,
            were all assembled in one house, and they besought God by prayer and entreaty. And the
            blessed Euphemia was also constantly amongst them, she being the daughter of the senator
            Philophron. And Drusina her mother was with her. And she was a believer, and did much
            almsgiving, because she was looking for the hope and the promise of the Christ.
            Therefore Apellianus, being of the household of Satan, said to the Proconsul: "There are
            people here who shut themselves up in a single house, who are not willing to obey the
            commandment of the Emperor, nor the commandment of thy Highness. And if thou shouldst
            overlook it now, many will turn from the great reverence for the gods, and will go and
            join themselves to them, and will scatter and disperse our sacrifice with derision." And
            when the Proconsul had heard this, he commanded them to come into his presence. And when
            these blessed ones came, Euphemia came in the midst of them with a joyful countenance
            and in chaste attire, more than all those who were with her, while she illuminated by
            her splendour the faces of those who contemplated her.</p>
         <milestone unit="folio" n="139a"/>
         <p n="3">And when they came and stood before the judgment seat of the Proconsul, he<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> answered and said to them: "Let all of you be
            submissive and obedient to the com<pb n="151"/>mandment of the Emperor, and sacrifice to
            the great god Ares."</p>
         <p n="4">But they all together replied with one voice [and] with the blessed Euphemia,
            saying, "Be this known unto thee, O Proconsul. We are the servants of the Eternal God,
            the great King who dwells in the heaven of heavens, and of His true Son, our Lord Jesus
            the Christ, and of the Holy Spirit. He who hath stretched out the heaven and hath
            established the earth; and hath created all works. Him we all worship, being eager to
            offer ourselves to Him in the sacrifice which is pleasing to Him."</p>
         <p n="5">But when Priscus the Proconsul heard [this] he said to them, "I am astonished at
            each one of you. And I honour the prudence of your mind. Because I have more knowledge;
            and I see the loveliness of you all. Therefore be persuaded by me, and obey the Emperor.
            And take delight in the sacrifice of the gods; so that ye may have greater friendship
            from me; and that the Emperor may take knowledge of you; and that ye may have greater
            rank and office."</p>
         <p n="6">But when these brave men heard these things, they abated nothing of the splendour
            which suffused their faces; but the more were they exalted to the excellencies of the
            knowledge of God. And whilst the blessed Euphemia <milestone unit="folio" n="139b"/> was
            with them, and they were all assembled together in the likeness of a host of angels,
            they said to the Proconsul, "We, O Proconsul! are the servants of the Most High God; and
            we are eager that we may be known by Him in the faith which He has delivered to us; and
            that we may receive His promise which says: 'O good and faithful servant, thou hast been
            faithful over a little, behold, I set thee over much.'<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n4"/> And also to thee O Proconsul! does it not escape thee, that each one
            of those who have temporal authority is eager to please him who has given him <pb
               n="152"/>the authority, that by means of it he may find higher degrees? If therefore
            it be that those who are mortal and corruptible, are subject unto mortal and corruptible
            kings, because they receive and seek for transient and unprofitable degrees, how much
            more should we keep the covenant, which we have made with God, who is incorruptible, and
            we expect to inherit the promises in His presence, those which endure for ever, which
            are incorruptible and inalienable. Do therefore what thou wilt, for we are ready because
            of the expectation of the heavenly promises to give ourselves over readily to death; and
            we shall receive the treasures that are being kept for us in the presence of God
            Almighty."</p>
         <p n="7">And when Priscus the Proconsul heard these things he <milestone unit="folio"
               n="140a"/> changed his countenance; and commanded that each of them should be
            tortured with hard and bitter torments. And while these blessed ones were being tortured
            daily, they endured all the torments for the sake of the Christ, those heroes exulting
            with joy and encouraging each other to resist bravely in the struggle. And they
            encouraged the blessed and brave Euphemia that she might attain joyfully to the
            coronation of her confession of the Christ. And they said to her, "O brave and
            persevering one! adorn thyself with thy faith, and be courageous in thy sound mind. And
            like a wise woman who has put on the Christ, receive the victory with all the fathers,
            whilst thou holdest an unquenchable lamp. Be fortunate in being numbered with the five
            virgins, those who carried their lamps with joy before the bridegroom, He who will
            return a full reward in the kingdom of heaven." And when the nineteen days of the labour
            of the conflict of the blessed martyrs were fulfilled, and they were in the prison
            nourished by the Holy Spirit; on the twentieth day an idea occurred to Priscus the
            Proconsul, suggested by the <pb n="153"/>wicked Apellianus, whose mind was also like his
            name. And he prepared himself for the interrogation of the blessed martyrs. And whilst
            he was sitting on his judgment seat, he commanded and they called the noble ones, whilst
            the blessed Euphemia was in the midst of them like a lamp. And the Proconsul asked them,
            saying, "Tell me, O young men! Have ye felt these tortures and will ye be persuaded to
            sacrifice to the great god Ares ?" And they said to the judge as with one voice with the
            noble Euphemia: "How <milestone unit="folio" n="140b"/> long, O Proconsul! art thou
            possessed by vanity? when wilt thou not turn from the error which has taken hold of
            thee? that thou mayest know God thy Creator."</p>
         <p n="8">Then Priscus commanded those soldiers of Satan to strike the blessed ones on their
            cheeks and say to them, "Be persuaded and sacrifice to the great God Ares." And the
            soldiers did<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> as they were commanded. And when they
            had struck those blessed ones on their cheeks, their faces shone all the more; and those
            soldiers were powerless, and left off beating the blessed ones, and became as dead
            people.</p>
         <p n="9">And Apellianus, who was of the household of Satan, he who was perfect in the idea
            of the devil's error, said to the Proconsul, "Pronounce the condemnation of these
            people, and send them to the Emperor/' And this speech pleased the Proconsul and all his
            companions. And he commanded that they should be cast into the prison-house, and should
            be kept carefully until it should be the will of the Proconsul that they should be sent
            to the Emperor. And the number of them all w r as forty-nine. And the blessed Euphemia
            was with them also. And when they had come into the prison-house, Sudrinus the disturber
            and robber came like a thief and like a wolf who fell upon the flock, and snatched away
            the bravest and strongest of heart, <pb n="154"/>Euphemia alone, imagining that he would
            find her like a loosened garment. But the beloved of the Christ was covered with joy,
            and she raised her eyes to heaven <milestone unit="folio" n="141a"/> saying, "My Lord
            and my God, Jesus the Christ, Thou art my hope, and let not the work of Thy handmaiden
            who is before Thee perish."</p>
         <p n="10">And when Priscus heard [it] he said to her, "Honour thyself and know the
            splendour of thy race. And do not thyself destroy thyself: But thou hast been seduced by
            false words like a woman. Turn now and sacrifice to the great god Ares." But the noble
            and pure woman said, "The strength of athleticism is not weakened by the weak nature of
            a woman; but by the preservation of the body the defects of sickness are filled up, for
            by my nature I stand like a man, that I may be worthy to receive the promises of my
            fathers."</p>
         <p n="11">And Priscus the Proconsul was troubled in his mind that he was overcome by a
            woman. And he commanded that a machine should be arranged on wheels, and that the
            blessed one should be thrown amongst them; so that whilst she was stretched out on the
            machine, and was crushed by it, she should quickly give up the ghost. But when she was
            thrown amongst the wheels, she marked the sign of the Christ in the shape of a cross on
            her breast, saying, "O chief of iniquity! how many torments has the enemy of truth
            poured out in Priscus the murderer? Behold! he sits in accusation and imagines the art
            of the devil, celebrating the mysteries of his father Satan, as the enemy of the truth.
            O doer of evil and deceitful man! The torments of thine art do not touch the limbs of my
            soul; because I have the Christ helping me. And <milestone unit="folio" n="141b"/> I
            hope that by means of great and sore tortures I may show to all men the endurance of the
            struggle whilst I am worshipping."</p>
         <pb n="155"/>
         <p n="12">And when the blessed Euphemia said these things, those soldiers of wickedness
            turned the wheels upon her. And whilst every one of her limbs was broken with the
            crushing of the wheels, the health of her soul was longing and was offering thanks to
            God, saying, "Let Thy goodness and the light of Thy truth be with me. Thou who hidest
            with Thyself<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> those who call upon Thee<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> in truth, turn to Thy weak and stricken handmaiden
            and save me from this abyss of that wicked and bad and devilish one, and from the threat
            of Priscus, this hater of good things."</p>
         <p n="13">And when she had said these things, immediately an angel of the Lord descended
            from Heaven and broke these wheeled machines, and dislocated the limbs of these
            soldiers, so that they were supposed to be other people from their appearance. And the
            blessed and victorious one emerged without a single stain. And her cheerfulness was seen
            in the presence of all men. And the Proconsul said, "By the victorious fortune of the
            Emperor, and by the good-will of the gods towards us, I swear that if thou dost not
            sacrifice to the great god Ares, I will destroy all thy body with fire; and thy God
            shall not help thee, He whom thou dost hope to serve." But the blessed Euphemia answered
            and said unto him, "This fire with which thou threatenest me, is one which fills up a
            moment in burning and is immediately quenched. But I <milestone unit="folio" n="142a"/>
            am not weak enough to fear thy threats." Then the blessed one answered again and said to
            Priscus: "Have not these noble champions been thrown into prison for the love of the
            Christ by thy wicked command? I fear not thy fire, because the Christ is with me. He it
            is who helps me. But I trample upon thy threats."</p>
         <p n="14">And the Proconsul wondered and was astonished at her; and he commanded that the
            furnace should be kindled <pb n="156"/>until it should shoot up flames of fire to about
            forty-five cubits with great strength; and that other soldiers should bring Euphemia.
            And when they had brought her, she stood up resplendent, with a cheerful countenance and
            a whole body and said, "Blessed art thou, O God, who dwellest on high, and beholdest in
            the depth; Thou<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> whom the angels praise, and the
            archangels worship. I the little, lowly woman supplicate before Thee, because I am
            persuaded by the excellence of Thy grace, and I seal myself with Thy victorious name;
            that I may find the redemption of Thy Christ. Thou art He who didst manifest and send
            Thine angel to the three children in the <milestone unit="folio" n="142b"/> furnace. And
            Thou didst scatter from them the strength of the great flames, and didst change the
            threatening of the Babylonians to peace. Show also to my humility the help that is from
            Thyself, and deliver me from the mouth of this cruel lion; and from the net of this
            wicked hunter, and from the threatening of Priscus this Proconsul. For Thy name is
            glorious and holy for ever."</p>
         <p n="15">And when she had said these things, the Proconsul commanded those soldiers to
            bind her and to throw her into the fire. And the soldiers bound her carefully. And they
            laid hold of the blessed one. But one of the soldiers whose name was Sosthenes, whilst
            he was holding his girdle in his hand, approached the Proconsul and said to him,
            "Command, O Proconsul, that I be bound with this girdle. For I am not able to stretch
            out my hand against this blessed one. For behold! I see before my eyes great hosts
            carrying lamps of light, and looking out for when they may receive her."</p>
         <p n="16">And Victor, a soldier who had turned to the knowledge of the truth and had
            loosened the chains of the blessed one from her, when he said to the Proconsul, "I
            implore of <pb n="157"/>thee, O Proconsul, to absolve me from the commandment of thy
            violence; for it is hard for me to stretch forth my hands against this holy one. For
            behold! I have seen on the edge of the furnace men who were standing and <milestone
               unit="folio" n="143a"/> scattering the fire and watching that this blessed one should
            be kept without a blemish."</p>
         <p n="17">And the Proconsul commanded that those ones should be guarded, and that other
            soldiers should stand up. But one came whose name was Caesar, and another, Barbessus,
            and they caught up the blessed one, and flung her into the fire. And immediately the
            servants of the Only Son of God received her, the angels holding lamps of the light of
            peace. And they extinguished the flame of the fire. And that fire turned upon the
            soldier whose name was Caesar, and devoured him. And after the fire had devoured Caesar
            the soldier of the Proconsul, the blessed one stood up in the midst of the furnace, as
            in a beautiful temple of great glory. And she saw the Christ our glorious Lord; and she
            stretched out her hands towards Him and said, "Blessed art Thou, O Lord God of my
            fathers, who in Thy gracious and passionless Divinity hast not neglected Thy lowly
            handmaiden, and hast extended and exalted Thy true name in every place: and hast
            established the splendour of Thy faith. And hast chased away the tempest of wickedness;
            and hast illuminated and increased Thy righteousness by me. And in uprightness by Thy
            Holy Spirit Thou hast charmed away from us the cursed serpent, and by the skilfulness of
            Thy many miracles Thou hast crowned those who put their trust in Thee. Grant to me that
            by Thy will I may triumph in Thy presence; and that I may be worthy to be numbered with
            those who worship Thee in truth."</p>
         <p n="18">And when she had said these things, she went out from the furnace unhurt; being
            commended to those of the <pb n="158"/>soldiers who believed in the Christ; the King of
            truth, <milestone unit="folio" n="143b"/> And the Proconsul commanded, "Throw the
            blessed one into the prison-house that she may be guarded there with the prisoners, till
            the next day," whilst he was full of his threat of the wicked device as to how he should
            destroy the handmaid of God. But the blessed one went from his presence to the
            prison-house, giving glory to God.</p>
         <p n="19">And the noble soldiers of the Christ rejoiced in the triumph of the blessed one,
            and gave glory to God, saying, "Blessed be Thou, O God! for ever and ever, Amen. Grant
            to Thy servant, O Lord! that she may be worthy to testify with all the fathers, those
            who were worthy to be martyred and were put to death for the sake of Thy holy name."</p>
         <p n="20">THE SECOND INTERROGATION OF EUPHEMIA.</p>
         <p n="21">Again on the following day the Proconsul went forth and sat on his judgment seat;
            and he commanded them to bring Sosthenes and Victor before him, the soldiers who
            believed in the Christ. And he said to them, "Sacrifice to the gods." But they answered
            and said to him, "O Proconsul, we have surely erred from of old by the instigation of
            the enemy of mankind, whom thou worshippest; and for a certain time we have worshipped
            him, and we have destroyed our hope towards the true God. But we believe now in Him who
            has enlightened the dark eyes of our heart, by means of His handmaiden the blessed
            Euphemia. Who is able to wipe out the record of our debts. He who was with us in the
            trouble of the enemy of the truth, we believe that He is able to inscribe us [as]
               <milestone unit="folio" n="144a"/> citizens of the Holy City, in the Book of Life. Do
            then what thou wilt with eagerness, the works of thy father Satan, and torture us,
            because we do not assent to thine error, and we do not receive the commandment of the
               <pb n="159"/>Emperor, who commands that he be worshipped; because he is a servant of
            the living God, and we do not worship impure and false gods.''</p>
         <p n="22">And when the Proconsul had heard these things from them, he commanded that a
            [bear ?] should come, and that the blessed ones should be thrown to it, so that their
            bodies might be devoured by it. And the two were immediately thrown together to it. And
            they began to speak thus, and to give glory to the Lord Almighty, the Pure and Holy One.
            "He who hath established all works with wisdom; and by His powerful word assembleth the
            host of the seas; and by His commandment He hath established the earth; and He hath
            separated the darkness from the light; He who slew the murdering dragon, and loosed the
            bands of death by the murder of the Crucified One. Loose us also now from the pangs of
            corruption; and deliver us from the laceration of the manslayer, and grant to us that we
            may honour Thy holy name in peace without blemish and without spot of soul or of body."
            And immediately there was a voice from heaven, saying, "I have heard your prayer, and
            have received your intercession." And these ones, when they heard the voice, committed
            their souls the more to God. And when they were thrown to the wild, destroying beast,
            they immediately <milestone unit="folio" n="144b"/> committed their spirits to God, and
            received Him whom they loved with joy, because of whom the blessed ones had died.<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/></p>
         <p n="23">And when the Proconsul saw what had happened to the blessed ones, he arose
            immediately and went to his Praetorium. And the Christians, who happened to be there,
            took the bodies and wrapped them up and buried them<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"
            /> in the earth in a fair covering.</p>
         <pb n="160"/>
         <p n="24">And when it was dawn, the Proconsul arose, and went out that he might go and hear
            the blessed Euphemia. And when she emerged from the prison-house, she went like an
            innocent lamb of the Christ and said with a clear voice: "I give Thee glory, O Lord!
            with a new song upon this earth. I extol Thee, O Lord! with all my strength, I sing a
            psalm to Thee, giving glory to Thy name amongst all peoples. ,, And when she had prayed
            and had finished, she came and stood before the judgment seat of the Proconsul.</p>
         <p n="25">And the Proconsul began to interrogate her, saying to her, "How long wilt thou be
            a fool? and how long wilt thou destroy thyself in this manner? for the great god, the
            Emperor, desires to be reconciled to thee, if thou wilt also do his will, and wilt
            sacrifice to Ares, to whom he also sacrifices. Be persuaded therefore by me and
            sacrifice, that thou mayest live. And in the world thou shalt be a mother of many." But
            she laughed, and <milestone unit="folio" n="145a"/> answered, saying to him, "Truly I
            would have no mind and no sense, if I were to do what thou desirest; and were to hearken
            to the Emperor, and to worship those who are no gods by nature, and were to sacrifice to
            those dumb and voiceless idols, O wicked and senseless man! and were to renounce all the
            beauty that is in the Christ, and were to rush into the snare of Satan. Thou art eager
            to make me in thy fashion like unto thyself, who art the heir of hell and everlasting
            quenchless fire. And thou pervertest the servants of God from the truth. For the
            strength of the Christ is with me, and I believe that He helps me at all times."</p>
         <p n="26">And the Proconsul commanded that they should bring four great stones, and should
            fix great instruments at the corners of the stones, and that the blessed one should be
            thrown into the midst of them. And when these stones <pb n="161"/>were shaken by the
            instruments by being moved to and fro, they should tear the body of the blessed one.</p>
         <p n="27">And the instruments were arranged, and he commanded that she should go in amongst
            them chained. And when the lamb<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> of the Christ went
            in amongst these stones, she knelt on her knees, and implored with many tears and
            besought God, saying, "I beseech Thee, O Lord my God! and I pour out my soul before
            Thee, prostrate before Thee and I offer my lowliness, and I shed my tears, my back is
            ready for smiting, and I withdraw not my face from spitting.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n12"/> I call upon Thy name, and I take refuge in Thy true fear. Have mercy
            upon Thy handmaiden, and leave me<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> not to this
            destruction which the craft and <milestone unit="folio" n="145b"/> wickedness of the
            evil one has prepared against me. I may be stripped of all wicked things, my thoughts
            shall be purified from uncleanness, men shall be amazed at Thy help; let not his wiles
            have power on the spiritual cymbals of my soul. Let my purity<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n14"/> shine, O Lord! in the world, that Thy name may be glorified for
            ever." The noble woman said all these things while she was kneeling in her prayer. And
            the lictors worked till they were wearied, hanging on the contrivance of the wheels, and
            not one of them moved from its place; but they and the wheels became like fine chaff.
            And she was found as a lamb without blemish; and the judge and those who were with him
            contemplated the brightness of her face. And after all these contrivances which they had
            sought out in wickedness, the judge commanded them to dig a deep place, and to surround
            it with water as with a wall, and to cast evil beasts therein; and to shut up the noble
            woman there, and when the beasts should leap from the water, they should destroy
            Euphemia with vehemence.</p>
         <pb n="162"/>
         <p n="28">And when the blessed one knew it, she was prepared for the place, and the waters
            were pressed together; and the beasts were flung in before the wicked man commanded
            it.</p>
         <p n="29">And the holy Euphemia ran, and stood on the edge of the lake of water. And she
            sealed herself with the sign of the cross, and said to the judge with a loud voice, "O
            liar far from the truth! wily man, disciple of Satan, thou art well called by this name,
            saws (driven by) water are prepared for thee, which when they receive thee with anger,
            shall dislocate all thy limbs; because thou hast embittered the God who made thee, the
            Giver of life and <milestone unit="folio" n="146a"/>light, and hast contemned the
            worshippers of the Christ. And when the blessed one had said these things, she signed
            herself with the cross on the right hand and on the left, and cried to God her
            deliverer. And she looked up<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15"/> to heaven, "O Christ
            the light of my soul! be with Thy handmaiden to-day, and deliver me as Thou didst
            deliver Daniel in the den, and like Jonah in the belly of the fish."</p>
         <p n="30">And when she had finished speaking, she threw herself into the midst of the
            water. And when all these beasts perceived her, they ran to meet her with joy; and they
            carried her and lifted her up above the water. And they rocked her like a nurse her
            darling, for they were greatly restrained by the fear of God.</p>
         <p n="31">Then when the Proconsul saw the great and powerful miracles that had happened, he
            said to Apellianus, the pagan and sophist, "What is that power? and who is it that helps
            this woman? for as I have seen, the demons obey her, and she conquers every one by her
            sorceries." The Proconsul said, "And how do the gods endure to see these things, and
            they do not take vengeance."</p>
         <pb n="163"/>
         <p n="32">Apellianus said, "Because in their mercy they do not take vengeance."</p>
         <p n="33">The judge said, "Let swords and sharp stones be fixed in the earth, and let
            no[thing] be seen above them. And when Euphemia comes confidently, and is walking as on
            plain ground, she will trample on the swords, and will fall there on the stones and die
            like a wild boar." He commanded therefore, and his soldiers completed the contrivance of
            the wicked one. And when they had completed the arrangement according to the commandment
            of the Proconsul, the blessed Euphemia came with joy and cheer- <milestone unit="folio"
               n="146b"/> fulness, as one who had borne all these things, and yet did not fail of
            the truth of Jesus the Christ her Lord. And when she had borne all these afflictions,
            while these soldiers of wickedness were provoking her, that she might run to that place,
            the angels snatched her up and transported her over that place quite unhurt, and those
            soldiers fell into what they had fabricated for the blessed one; and they died by the
            work of their own hands.</p>
         <p n="34">And again the blessed one opened her mouth and gave glory and said, "Thou God,
            knowest what is in the hearts of all, Thou art He in whose presence are all secrets. O
            Giver of treasures that cannot be spoiled, and of heavenly promises, Who hast stretched
            out the earth and established it upon nothing, and by Thy word hast appointed all works.
            And Thou hast created the light, and caused it to shine upon all. Thou<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n16"/> who by Thy good-will didst send Thine only Son, our
            Lord Jesus the Christ from heaven to loose the bands of death; and to bind and to
            subjugate the chiefs and the worshippers of error. Thou<ptr type="noteAnchor"
               target="#n17"/> who art near to Thy worshippers, to those who stand in the conflict
            for the sake of Thy name. And Thou art a helper to them in all their <pb n="164"
            />afflictions. Help Thy handmaiden also now, and by the prayers of those blessed and
            holy ones who have been thrown into the prison because of Thy divine name,<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n18"/> and are hoping to finish their divine course,
            deliver me also, Thy handmaiden, and keep me in the one harmony with <milestone
               unit="folio" n="147a"/> Thy Holy Spirit, because Thou art God. For Thou keepest not
            anger and Thou dost save in the times of affliction."</p>
         <p n="35">And when the Proconsul saw these things, he commanded them to bring the holy
            woman before his judgment-seat. And he answered and said unto her, "Dost thou know, O
            Euphemia! that whilst thou art of a very great and distinguished family, thou hast been
            led into error and hast remained in it until now? And I who am a governor keeping what
            is right for the Emperor, thou standest against me, truly, like a wise and skilful
            woman. But nevertheless now at least be persuaded by me. And forgive me these insults
            and torments which I have made thee endure, and sacrifice to the gods, and be not a
            reproach of all men; and remain in thy distinguished family."</p>
         <p n="36">But the blessed one, because her mind was established in the Christ, answered and
            said to the tyrant, "Why do I see that thy face is full of bitterness and guile? O
            workman who composes with ornamented words! O wolf clothed in sheep's clothing while he
            does the works of destruction! and wicked robber, proffering words that are sweet to
            hear, but in their sequel they are more bitter than wormwood. I am not foolish to such a
            degree, that I should leave Him, the treasure of life, and should be allied to the
            bitterness of the devil. Therefore be not deceived, O Proconsul! because thou canst not
               <pb n="165"/>persuade me to sacrifice to foul fiends; and thou canst not force my
            will, that I should call those gods who are no gods. For how can they be called gods who
            have never been so? and how dost thou not perceive that thou <milestone unit="folio"
               n="147b"/>comparest with the life that is eternal a dead thing which never existed,
            and commandest us to offer a sacrifice to it. I am not persuaded by thy words, which are
            full of bitterness. Be eager therefore and do what thou wilt; for I am eager that I may
            be made worthy by means of thy wicked wiles of the everlasting victory. Where the Father
            is, where the Creator of the angels is, where the Giver of the crowns of victory is;
            there is the anointing of the truth; there is also the Christ who crowns His champions;
            there is also the Holy Spirit, He who strengthens those who endure afflictions for His
            sake."</p>
         <p n="37">And the Proconsul was angry when he heard these things, and he commanded that
            they should scourge the blessed one with rods, saying to her, "Be persuaded, and
            sacrifice to the gods." But whilst she was being scourged, she spake thus: </p>
         <p n="38">"Thy tortures do not come upon me, O wicked man! Thou art parted from life and
            thou hast no permanent abode. For thou art weak, because thy tyrannical power is
            conquered."</p>
         <p n="39">But Apellianus and the Proconsul with him recollected in their mind; and the
            judge commanded that they should bring sharp saws and pans of fire, and that the saws
            should, by the construction of their instruments cut up the blessed one and fling her
            limbs into the pans of fire, that thus she might be pounded to pieces like fine ashes.
            And when those instruments were arranged in that manner <milestone unit="folio" n="148a"
            /> of contrivance, they brought the blessed Euphemia, and threw her amongst the saws,
            and the saws were turned about, and were scattered; also the pans of fire that were <pb
               n="166"/>fixed amongst them were quenched, and no hurt came to her from any of these
            things, because the angels of God kept close to her for her assistance. And when the
            Proconsul and Apellianus his friend saw that this worshipper of the Christ was
            victorious over all their afflictions and torments, they took counsel amongst themselves
            how they might destroy the holy one, and they invited the city to the theatre which is
            called the arena where beasts are let loose for the Stadium. And when she stood in the
            midst of the Stadium, she began to say, "Thou art near, O Lord! to those who call upon
            Thee in truth. Receive my spirit to Thyself, as Thou didst receive the sacrifice of our
            father Abraham; so also do Thou receive the sacrifice of my spirit to Thyself." And
            whilst she said this, she sealed herself on all sides, calling on the name of the Father
            and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit. And four lions were loosed against her, with two
            other evil beasts. And these lions leapt upon her with a run. And they kissed the
            foot-prints of the blessed one. And the other beasts did so likewise. And thus was
            finished the martyrdom and the conflict of the blessed one. One of these beasts ran, and
            bit her on her shoulder only: and <milestone unit="folio" n="148b"/>immediately a voice
            was heard a voice from heaven saying, "Ascend on high O Euphemia! climb and stand in the
            place of the saints, and receive thy victory, and the reward of thy finished
            course."</p>
         <p n="40">And when this voice was heard, there was a great earthquake, so that all the
            place was shaken, and every one was seized with trembling. And the blessed one said,
            "Requite, O Lord! also this unclean Proconsul according to his wickedness, and enter
            into the conflict along with Thy holy servants, O Thou, my God and my Lord! and justify
            them." And when she had said these things, she committed her soul into the hands of her
            Lord. And her <pb n="167"/>father Philophron entered with her mother; and they took her
            holy body, and carried it far away, and they buried it in a lonely place, which they had
            arranged for it, which was about one mile distant from the city of Chalcedon.</p>
         <p n="41">And the Proconsul sent those blessed ones who had been thrown into prison with
            the Blessed One to the Emperor with an epistle; that the Emperor might command
            whatsoever he willed about them. And he commanded those cavalry soldiers that they
            should convoy them peacefully on the way; and keep them until they should go before the
            Emperor. For the Proconsul fell into a sore sickness, and was bitterly tormented
            according to the word of the Blessed One which she spake to him.</p>
         <p n="42">Here endeth the martyrdom of the Holy Euphemia.</p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">1 Literally, "to the great god Ares.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">1 Or "called."</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">2 MS. "the Proconsul."</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">Matt. xxv. 21</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">1 Cod. "did to the blessed ones."</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">1 MS. "He who hides with Himself."</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">2 MS. "Him."</note>
            <note xml:id="n8">1 MS. "He."</note>
            <note xml:id="n9">1 Literally, "had been crowned."</note>
            <note xml:id="n10">2 MS. "their bodies."</note>
            <note xml:id="n11">1 MS. "Calf."</note>
            <note xml:id="n12">Isa. l. 6</note>
            <note xml:id="n13">2 Literally "her."</note>
            <note xml:id="n14">3 Or "victory."</note>
            <note xml:id="n15">1 Literally "stretched her look."</note>
            <note xml:id="n16">1 MS. "He."</note>
            <note xml:id="n17">1 MS. "He."</note>
            <note xml:id="n18">1 Literally "the name of Thy divinity."</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
