<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Cyprian and Justa</title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofreading and initial markup of persons, places, and titles by </resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#anorth">Adelaide North</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title level="a">Cyprian and Justa</title>
                  <title level="m"> Select Narratives of Holy Women from the Syro-Antiochene or
                     Sinai Palimpsest as Written above teh Old Syriac Gospels by John the Stylite,
                     of Beth-Mari-Qanūn in A.D. 778. </title> Translated by Anges Smith Lewis
                  M.R.A.S. <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>C. J. Clay and Sons</publisher>
                  <date>1900</date>
                  <citedRange unit="p" from="185" to="203">185-203</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <p>This transcription renumbers the original footnotes to run sequentially and includes
               marginal references for Biblical citations among the footnotes.</p>
            <p>This text is in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="185"/>
         <milestone ed="S.P." unit="folio" n="170a"/>
         <ab n="1">Again, the martyrdom of <persName>Cyprian</persName> the wizard, and of <persName>Justa</persName> the virgin.</ab>
         <ab n="2">At the appearance of our Redeemer, <persName>Jesus the Christ</persName> from heaven upon the earth,
            and on the fulfilment of the words of the prophets, everything beneath the heaven was
            illumined, that they might be baptized into one <persName>God the Father Almighty</persName>, and into the
            <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>, and into the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName> in the belief of the truth.</ab>
         <ab n="3">Now there was a certain virgin whose name was <persName>Justa</persName>, and the name of her father
            was <persName>Aedesius</persName>; and of her mother <persName>Cledonia</persName>, in the town of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> which is near <placeName>Daphne</placeName>.
            And this blessed one listened to a certain deacon whose name was <persName>Praylius</persName>, from a window
            which was near her house. And when she heard the great deeds of <persName>God</persName>, and how our
            Redeemer the <persName>Lord Jesus Christ</persName> put on a body, and the heralding of the prophets, and His
            birth from <persName>Mary</persName>, and the worship of the Magi; and about the appearance of the star and
            the praise of the angels, and the signs of the miracles that were done in His name and
               <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="74a"
            />by His power; and of the redemption of the cross; and of His resurrection from the
            dead; and of His glory in the presence of the disciples; and of the living words of His
            gospel to His apostles; and of His ascension to <placeName>Heaven</placeName>; and of His being seated on the
            right hand; and of His imperishable kingdom; and of the bliss that passeth not away, and
            of the deathless life.</ab>
         <ab n="4">[And when the blessed one had heard these things, she <pb n="186"/>marvelled
            greatly in the belief of the truth, and the eye of the maiden sparkled with the love of
            the <persName>Holy Spirit</persName>. She longed greatly and sought that she might again see the deacon
            <persName>Praylius</persName>; but she could not (do it).]<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> She answered
            and said to her mother, <quote>Hearken to thy daughter, my mother, and turn from error, and
               thou shalt escape from everlasting torment; as thou hast heard that the scriptures of
               our <persName>Lord Jesus Christ</persName> say, He who hath made the heaven and the earth and all that is
               therein. For sculptures are nothing. They are of stone, and of wood, and of gold, the
               work of men's hands, images, deaf, and blind, and lifeless.</quote> Then her mother said to
            her, <quote>Nay, my daughter, let not thy father hear this in thy thoughts.</quote> But the blessed
            one answered and said to her mother, <quote>Know ye, O my father and my mother, that
               henceforth I am a Christian, and I worship the <persName>Christ</persName> my Redeemer, because by means of
               this deacon I have learnt the way of life. And henceforth there is no God except <persName>the
                  Father</persName>, and <persName>the Son</persName>, and the <persName>Holy Ghost</persName>. And He gives life to the <milestone
                  ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="74b"/> men who
               believe in Him, and He has redeemed them from the destruction of the wicked, and has
               made them to inherit deathless life.</quote> When she had said these things, she signed herself
            in the Threefold name, and began to pray in the name of our <persName>Lord Jesus Christ</persName>. But her
            mother told her father everything that the blessed one had said. Then immediately
            numberless hosts of angels appeared to them, holding lamps of fire in the chamber.<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> And in the midst of them they saw the <persName>Christ</persName>,
            saying, <quote>Come to Me, I will make you enter the kingdom of heaven. With all the holy ones
               who have done well in My presence.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="5">And when <persName>Aedesius</persName>, the father of the girl, saw that sight, he was seized with
            great wonder. And he arose in the morning, and led his wife, and his daughter, the
            blessed <pb n="187"/>one, and they went to the church with that deacon, beseeching him
            to present them to the bishop. And when he presented them, the Bishop received them. And
            they fell at his feet and besought him that he would give them the seal of the <persName>Christ</persName>.
            But he was unwilling to give it to them, until the deacon related to him about the
            vision of the <persName>Christ</persName> which he had seen, and about the faith and the love to the <persName>Christ</persName>
            of the maiden.</ab>
         <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="75a"/>
         <ab n="6">But <persName>Aedesius</persName> shaved his hair because he was a priest of the gods; and he fell at
            the feet of the Bishop, and he gave to the three the seal of the <persName>Christ</persName>. And the
            holy <persName>Aedesius</persName> was deemed worthy of the priesthood, and he lived a short time, and went
            to rest in the true faith. And the holy virgin went at all seasons to the church of the
            <persName>Christ</persName>. But a certain man, a lawyer of a great family, who was evil in his deeds, and
            who was enchained in the worship of error, of dead images, saw the blessed one going at
            all seasons to the house of <persName>God</persName>. And when he saw her, he was captivated by the love of
            the maiden, and he sent many people after her, that he might take her to wife. But she
            said to them all with a loud voice, <quote>I am betrothed to the <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote> And the wicked man,
            by the mad impulse of <persName>Satan</persName>, assembled a great crowd, and watched her as she went to the
            house of <persName>God</persName>. And he wished to lead her away by force. And when they came to lead her
            forcibly away, those who were with the maiden cried with a loud voice. And when those
            who were in their house heard these things, they came out grasping swords. And those who
            had come to seize the handmaiden of <persName>God</persName> by force, fled.</ab>
         <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="75b"/>
         <ab n="7">But the holy one sealed herself with the sign of the <persName>Christ</persName>, and she seized the
            insolent man and flung him on the ground. And she struck him on the face. And she
            tore his clothes and left him stupified, as her sister <persName>Thecla</persName> <pb n="188"/>had done to
            the insolent <persName>Alexander</persName>. And she went forthwith to the house of <persName>God</persName>.</ab>
         <ab n="8">But he went in a great rage to <persName>Cyprian</persName> the wizard, and promised him two talents of
            gold, if mayhap he might entrap the holy maiden with his sorcery, whilst the madman did
            not know that the power of the <persName>Christ</persName> is unconquerable.</ab>
         <ab n="9">But when <persName>Cyprian</persName> the wizard had heard these things, he was grieved for the young
            man, and called up a certain cruel demon by his sorcery. And it answered and said to
            him, <quote>Why hast thou called me?</quote> And <persName>Cyprian</persName> said to it, <quote>That I may please a certain
               maiden of the Galileans, if thou canst bring her to me.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="10">But the demon, ashamed, promised that it would bring her to him, whilst he was
            unable to conquer the truth. <persName>Cyprian</persName> answered and said to it, <quote>Tell me, what are thy
               works, in which thou confidest, and I will send thee away.</quote> The accursed demon answered
            and said to him, <quote>I am a rebel against <persName>God</persName>, and I obey <persName>Satan</persName>. And I made <persName>Eve</persName> to sin, and
               I have driven <persName>Adam</persName> out of <persName>Paradise</persName>. <milestone ed="Add.12,142"
                  edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="76a"/>And I have robbed him of
               bliss and of delight. And I have taught <persName>Cain</persName> to kill his brother. And I have polluted
               the earth with blood. And I have increased adultery and sorcery. And I have made all
               lasciviousness and drunkenness. And I have incited silly laughter. And I have taught men
               to worship images. And I have counselled that the <persName>Christ</persName> should be crucified. And I have
               shaken the whole city. And I have overturned walls. And I have divided houses.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="11">And when the demon had said these things that had been done by it, it said to the
            wizard, <quote>I have done all these things, and am I unable to conquer this?</quote> Then <persName>Cyprian</persName>
            said to him, <quote>Take this root and sprinkle it round about the house of the maiden. And I
               will take her mind <pb n="189"/>away from her, and immediately she will obey thee.</quote> And
            when he had said these things to the demon, he went straight to the house of that
            maiden. But the blessed one stood up to pray the None in the night to <persName>God</persName> the lover of
            the penitent. And when she became aware of the arrival of the demon, she prayed all the
            more to the <persName>Living God</persName>, because her mind was satiated with the love and the power of the
            Cross, and she signed herself with the sign of the <persName>Christ</persName>. And she called with a loud
            voice, saying, <quote>O <persName>Lord, Almighty God</persName>! Father of our <persName>Lord Jesus the <milestone
                     ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="76b"/>Christ</persName>,<ptr
                     type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> Thou who didst kill the man-slaying serpent, and
               didst deliver those who were bound by <persName>Satan</persName>, O <persName>Lord God</persName>! who didst create man in Thine
               (own) image, and didst leave him in the paradise of delights to enjoy himself in Thy
               commandments, — and he was thrown down by the deception of the serpent. And when he
               sinned thus Thou didst not forsake him, but by the power of Thy cross Thou didst cure
               his wounds, and didst make him whole, by means of the <persName>Christ</persName>, the Redeemer of the
               worlds, He by whom the created things were made, and the heavens were set in order, and
               the earth was stretched out; and the waters of the great deep were separated, that all
               natural things should confess to Thee, O <persName>God</persName>! O <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>, redeem Thy
               handmaiden; and let not the temptation of the enemy come near me. To Thee, O <persName>Lord</persName>! I
               have made a vow that I would be a virgin to Thine only Son, the <persName>Lord Jesus Christ</persName>.
               Redeem Thy handmaiden, because I have loved Thee and will love Thee, with<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> all my heart, and with<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                     target="#n5"/> all my soul, and with<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> all my
               strength. Thou, O <persName>Lord</persName>! hast made the light of Thy love to shine on my soul. I beseech
               Thee, O <persName>Lord</persName>! leave me not to the hands of the Wicked one, that I may not transgress the
               promise that I have made to Thee. <pb n="190"/>Chase away the thought of the rebel from
               my mind; and keep me in Thy truth.</quote> And when she had said these things, she signed
            herself with the sign of the <persName>Christ</persName>, and <milestone ed="Add.12,142"
               edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="77a"/>she puffed at the demon; and
            he went away ashamed; and he stood before <persName>Cyprian</persName>; and <persName>Cyprian</persName> said to him, <quote>Where is
               the woman for whose sake thou hast been sent?</quote> The demon answered and said to him, <quote>Do
                  not ask me, for I cannot tell thee. For I saw a certain sign and I have run away.</quote> But
            <persName>Cyprian</persName> laughed at him; and he again called by his sorcery a stronger demon than the
            first one. And the cursed one boasted, and said to <persName>Cyprian</persName>, <quote>I knew thy commandment and
               also the cowardice of him who was before me. Send me O my father! and I will do thy
               will.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="12">And <persName>Cyprian</persName> said to him, <quote>Take this root, and throw it outside the house of the
               maiden, and I will come and persuade her.</quote> And when the demon had come to the place
            which <persName>Cyprian</persName> had told him of, the handmaiden of <persName>God</persName> stood up to pray the Sext of the
            night, saying thus, <quote>At midnight I have arisen, and I will praise Thee for Thy righteous
               judgments. <persName>God</persName> of all! <persName>Lord</persName> of the heights and of the depths, who hast confounded <persName>Satan</persName>
               by Thy power, and hast put him down under the feet of Thy disciples. May the
               confirmation of Thy mercy remain with me, O <persName>God</persName>! who didst receive the sacrifice of
               <persName>Abraham</persName>; and didst hear the prayer of <persName>Daniel</persName>; and didst overthrow <persName>Bel</persName>, and didst slay
               the dragon; and didst shew the knowledge of Thy divinity to the Babylonians, <persName>God</persName>, who by
               means of Thine Only Son, the <persName>Lord Jesus Christ</persName>, didst dispose everything, and didst
               bring out everything that was concealed in darkness to the light; and didst bring to
               life even those who were dead. And now, O <persName>Lord</persName>! in the abundance of Thy grace neglect me
               not, O <persName>Merciful One</persName>! but keep my soul and my body near to <pb n="191"/>Thy holiness.
               Keep also the lamp of my virginity, that it may not go out; that I may enter with the
               Bridegroom, the <persName>Christ</persName>, to the marriage feast; and may commit to Him my virginity in
               purity and holiness.</quote></ab>
         <milestone ed="S.P." unit="folio" n="173b"/>
         <ab n="13">And the demon went away from her ashamed, and appeared to <persName>Cyprian</persName>. And <persName>Cyprian</persName>
            answered and said to it, <quote>Where is the woman on whose account thou hast been sent?</quote> It
            answered and said to him, <quote>I cannot tell thee. For I saw a certain sign and I was
               afraid, and ran away.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="14">Then <persName>Cyprian</persName> called one whom he thought to be stronger than they, who was the
            father of the demons, and said to him, <quote>Who is this slight thing by whom thy power has
               been conquered?</quote> The demon answered and said to him, <quote>I will bring her to thee, be
                  ready at once.</quote> <persName>Cyprian</persName> answered and said to it, <quote>What is the sign of thy victory?</quote> The
            demon answered and said to him, <quote>I will enfeeble her with much fever for six days, and
               at midnight I will make her ready for thee.</quote></ab>
         <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="78a"/>
         <ab n="15">And the demon went and appeared to the maiden in the form of a maiden, her
            companion. And it went in and a sat down on the bed as if it had been a woman, and the
            evil one began to talk to the handmaiden of <persName>God</persName> in the manner of penitence. <quote>I beseech
               thee, O handmaiden of <persName>God</persName>, receive me, that I may be with thee. The <persName>Christ</persName>, thy <persName>Lord</persName>,
               hath sent me to thee. For I also am a virgin like thee, and shew me what is the struggle
               for virginity, or what recompense there is to those who keep it in purity. For I have
               seen thee that thou art greatly afflicted in the conflict.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="16">But the holy maiden, the servant of <persName>God</persName>, answered and said to her, <quote>The
               tongue<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> of man cannot describe the reward of the
               virginity which is for the sake of the <persName>Christ</persName>; <pb n="192"/>for it<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n8"/> is very great. <persName>God</persName> has promised to those who love Him and preserve
               their virginity, what eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, nor hath it arisen in the heart
               of man. Who is able to comprehend the blessings which <persName>God</persName> has promised to those who love
               Him and preserve their virginity in purity? The struggle for virginity in this world is
               for a little while; but the blessings which are preserved for it in that world are
               neither transitory nor corruptible.</quote></ab>
         <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="78b"/>
         <ab n="17">But the wicked demon began to speak with guile to the handmaid of <persName>God</persName>, saying to
            her, <quote>Behold, I have heard that <persName>Eve</persName> was a virgin in <placeName>Paradise</placeName>, and was not blest. And
               when <persName>Adam</persName> had known her, and she had given birth to children, she received the knowledge
               of good and of evil. And by her means the world was peopled; and there was the
               succession of races and of tribes.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="18">But when the holy virgin heard these things, she rose up to pray because of the
            words of the crafty one. And the cursed fiend kept close to her, lest perchance there
            might be an opportunity for him to capture her. But the blessed handmaid knew the
            craftiness of <persName>Satan</persName>, and was much troubled because she had perceived that he was a
            deceiver; and she hastened to prayer in the presence of <persName>God</persName>. And she sealed herself with
            the sign of the cross. And she puffed at that demon in the power of <persName>Jesus the Christ</persName>.
            And he fled ashamed from beside the handmaiden of <persName>God</persName>, and went sadly to him who had
            sent him. But the holy one was strengthened by the power of the <persName>Christ</persName>, and rested from
            the dispute with the crafty one, and gave thanks to <persName>God</persName> who had helped her in the
            struggle. And straightway the fever left her. And she <milestone ed="Add.12,142"
               edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="79a"/>began to say, <quote>Praise be to
                  Thee, O <persName>Christ</persName>! who strengthenest those who seek refuge with Thee and who <pb n="193"
                  />dost illuminate (with) Thy glorious beams those who are blind in the darkness of evil,
                  Thou, O <persName>Lord</persName>! in the abundance of Thy mercy, deliver me not up to be vanquished by a
                  stranger to righteousness. But help Thy handmaiden who hopes in Thee. For my flesh
                  shudders for fear of Thee, and I have been afraid of Thy judgments. Give glory to Thy
                  holy name, that those who hate me may see and be ashamed. For Thou, O <persName>Lord</persName>! hast helped
                  me, and hast comforted me with Thy threefold power.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="19">And the demon had gone and had appeared to <persName>Cyprian</persName> the wizard. And it replied,
            saying to him, <quote>I too, have again been vanquished by one weak woman.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="20"><persName>Cyprian</persName> answered and said, <quote>Where is the power of thy victory? tell me.</quote> The
            demon answered and said to him, <quote>Ask me not, for I am unable to tell thee. For I saw a
               sign and I was shaken and fled. But if thou art willing that I should tell thee the
               truth, swear to me, and I will tell thee.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="21"><persName>Cyprian</persName> answered and said to him, <quote>What have I that I can swear by to thee?</quote></ab>
         <ab n="22">The demon said, <quote>Swear to me by the great power that abides with me.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="23"><persName>Cyprian</persName> said to him, <quote>No, by thy great power, I will not go away from thee.</quote></ab>
         <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="79b"/>
         <ab n="24">And the demon had become trustful and said to him, <quote>I saw the sign of Him who was
               crucified. And I shook, and I was afraid, and I ran away.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="25"><persName>Cyprian</persName> said to him, <quote>Is therefore He who was crucified greater than thou art?</quote>
            The demon said, <quote>Be patient and listen to me and I will tell thee truly. All that robs
               and deceives is allied to us, and becomes our comrade in that fearful place. For that
               torment is bitter. For they boil copper and place it on the limbs of both men and women.
               <pb n="194"/>And thus by hard boiling they are<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/>
               tortured before the tribunal of Him who was crucified. And the angels also afflict them
               with severity.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="26"><persName>Cyprian</persName> said, <quote>Therefore I also wish that I could be a friend to Him who was
               crucified; that I also may not fall into His hard condemnation.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="27">The demon said, <quote>And hast thou not sworn to me by my great power that thou wilt
               not deal falsely?</quote></ab>
         <ab n="28"><persName>Cyprian</persName> said, <quote>By what have I sworn to thee and have dealt falsely?</quote></ab>
         <ab n="29">Saith the demon, <quote>By my great power.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="30"><persName>Cyprian</persName> said, <quote>I reject thee and I scorn thy great power. For this night I have
               surely learned that I can take refuge in the prayer and the intercession of a virgin.
               And I supplicate by the power of the cross. And by it all thy lying power is humbled.
               For I also sign myself with the cross, and deny thee and all thy power.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="31">And when he had spoken thus, he sealed himself with the sign of our Redeemer, and
            said, <quote>Glory be to Thee, O <persName>Christ</persName>! <milestone ed="Add.12,142"
                  edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="80a"/> O invincible Power!</quote></ab>
         <ab n="32">And immediately <persName>Satan</persName> fled.</ab>
         <ab n="33">And <persName>Cyprian</persName> said, <quote>Henceforth I believe in the <persName>Christ</persName>, and He redeems from all
               the power of the <persName>Evil one</persName>.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="34">But the demon went away ashamed. And <persName>Cyprian</persName> took the tablets of his sorcery and
            made the four men of his household carry them; and thus he went to the house of <persName>God</persName>; and
            he fell at the feet of the presbyter <persName>Euthymius</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/>
            and said to him:</ab>
         <ab n="35"><quote>O blessed servant of <persName>God</persName>! I implore thee that I may become a soldier of <persName>God</persName> and
               of our <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>; and that I may be inscribed in the book of the believers —
               those who serve Him.</quote> But the presbyter <persName>Euthymius</persName> imagined that perhaps he was seeking
            to deceive <pb n="195"/>those who were in the church. So the holy one said to <persName>Cyprian</persName>,
            <quote>Let it suffice thee that thou hast deceived so many people who are without. Take heed
               to thyself, and do not come into the church of <persName>God</persName> with guile. For the power of the
               <persName>Christ</persName> is invincible.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="36"><persName>Cyprian</persName> answered and said, <quote>Of a truth, my lord, I, too, know that it is
               invincible. For this night I sent demons against the holy virgin <persName>Justa</persName>. And she
               conquered them by her prayer and by her love to the <persName>Christ</persName>. But take the books of my
               sorcery, with which I have done all <milestone ed="Add.12,142"
                  edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="80b"/>the evil, and burn them in
               the fire. And take pity on me, and let me belong to the flock of the <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="37">And when the holy <persName>Euthymius</persName> had heard these things from that wizard, he took his
            tablets and burnt them in the fire. And he blessed him and began to say to him, <quote>Be
               constant in the house of <persName>God</persName> at the time of prayer.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="38">And <persName>Cyprian</persName> went to his house rejoicing; and he broke all the images that
            belonged to him. And all night he beat his hands on his face and on his breast, saying,
            <quote>I have dared to withstand Thy power, <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>! in all the wicked things
               that I did. And how may I bless Thee with the mouth wherewith I cursed the men who
               called upon Thy name.</quote> And he threw dust upon his head, and flung himself on his face
            upon the earth, and wept for seven days. And after the seven days, he got up early as
            great Saturday began, and he went to the house of <persName>God</persName>. And as he was going on the road,
            he said in his prayer:</ab>
         <ab n="39"><quote>O <persName>Christ</persName>! O Helper of those who call upon Thee in truth! If I am worthy to
               become Thy servant, shew me some place where I may enter Thy holy house, and may
               <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="81a"
               />hear from the reading of Thy holy scriptures, O <persName>Lord</persName>! that Thou hast received me.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="40">And when he had entered the house of <persName>God</persName> he heard <pb n="196"/>the chorister<ptr
               type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> say, <quote>Thou hast seen (it) O <persName>God</persName>! be not silent.</quote>
            And then, <quote>O <persName>Lord</persName>! be not far from me.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12"/> And again
            he heard <persName>Isaiah</persName> who said, <quote>Behold my servant shall deal prudently, and shall be exalted,
               so that many shall be astonished at him,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> and
            again <persName>David</persName> saith, <quote>Mine eyes have prevented the watches that I might meditate on Thy
               word.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/></ab>
         <ab n="41">And again <persName>Isaiah</persName> has said, <quote>Fear not, O my servant <persName>Jacob</persName>, and <persName>Israel</persName>, whom I have
               chosen.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15"/> And again the Apostle, who says, <quote>The
                  <persName>Christ</persName> hath redeemed us from the curse of the law.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16"
                  /> And again <persName>David</persName> hath said, <quote>Who shall relate the wonderful works of the <persName>Lord</persName>?</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" 
                     target="#n17"></ptr> And again the Gospel, which hath said, <quote>That
                        whosoever believeth in me should not perish, but should have eternal life.</quote><ptr
                           type="noteAnchor" target="#n18"/> And again they proclaimed, <quote>That whosoever did not
                              receive the sign should go out.</quote> And <persName>Cyprian</persName> sat at the threshold of the door, and one
            of the deacons said to him, <quote>Rise and get thee out.</quote> But <persName>Cyprian</persName> answered and said unto
            him, <quote>I am a bond-servant of the <persName>Christ</persName>; and thou sayest to me, <quote>Get thee out!</quote></quote></ab>
         <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="81b"/>
         <ab n="42">And that deacon said to him, <quote>Thou art not yet initiated, <persName>Cyprian</persName>.</quote> And <persName>Cyprian</persName>
            said to him, <quote>As the <persName>Christ</persName> liveth, He who confounded the demons, and hath had mercy on
               me and on the maiden, I will not go out until I am initiated.</quote> And <persName>Asterius</persName> the deacon
            went and informed the Bishop. And the Bishop called <persName>Cyprian</persName>. And he repeated to him the
            words of the holy scriptures. And he prayed, and thus he baptized him in the name of our
            <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName>.</ab>
         <ab n="43">And after eight days he became a preacher of the hidden mysteries.</ab>
         <ab n="44">And when it was Pentecost, he was full of the grace of <persName>God</persName>, and healed demons and
            pains in the name of <pb n="197"/><persName>Jesus the Christ</persName>. And until one year was completed, he
            became the assessor of the Bishop. And for sixteen years he held the sacred throne. And
            after these things the holy <persName>Euthymius</persName> summoned the Bishops who were round about, and
            said to them things that were worthy of the Church of <persName>God</persName>, and he, while still living,
            gave him the throne of the bishopric. And after a few days, the holy <persName>Euthymius</persName> went to
            rest in the <persName>Lord</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19"/> and confided to him the flock of
            the <persName>Christ</persName>. For the holy <persName>Cyprian</persName> had put many things in order, and had made the holy
            <persName>Justa</persName> <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="82a"
            />a deaconess, and he enlightened many, and delivered them from all the heresies of
            destruction; and increased the Church of the <persName>Christ</persName>; fulfilling the words of the
            prophets, fulfilling also the commandments of the <persName>Christ</persName>, whilst he laboured concerning
            the belief of the truth. He looked on the people who were scattered, and on the wolf
            whilst he was robbing.</ab>
         <ab n="45">And the holy <persName>Cyprian</persName> taught many (people) of the city by letters. But the Lord of
            evil, crafty <persName>Satan</persName>, incited the sons of error to calumniate the holy one before
            <persName>Eutolmius</persName>, Count of the East, and they said to him, <quote><persName>Cyprian</persName> is the teacher of the
               Christians; and he makes void the glory of the gods by his many sorceries, with a
               certain virgin, and disturbs all the world by his letters, and makes women virgins.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="46">And the Count was filled with rage, and he commanded the judges to bind <persName>Cyprian</persName>
            and the maiden carefully, and to bring them to the city of <placeName>Damascus</placeName> and produce them
            before him. And when they had come before the Count he said to them, <quote>Art thou the
               teacher of the Christians? who of old hast turned away many from the praise of the gods,
               and hast deceived many by Him who was crucified? exalting Him more than the gods?</quote></ab>
         <pb n="198"/>
         <ab n="47">But the holy <persName>Cyprian</persName> said, <quote>Why hast thou given thyself to the likeness of
               wickedness? and to the madness of the evil one? For I, as thou hast said, was captive to
               the enemy of justice, whilst I was the teacher of the pagans; and I slew many by every
               kind of sin. And when the <persName>Christ</persName> redeemed me, He helped me also by means of this maiden.
               A certain lawyer from the house of <persName>Claudius</persName> fell in love with her. And when he could not
               find (a way) to do evil to the handmaiden of <persName>God</persName>, desiring to capture her for his wife,
               he came to me and begged me to do the business of love for him. And I, confiding in the
               books of my sorcery, sent the demons against her. And she made them flee by the sign of
               the <persName>Christ</persName>. And thus (it was) until the third one. I even sent their chief, and that
               holy maiden overthrew them by the same sign of <milestone ed="Add.12,142"
                  edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="83a"/>the <persName>Christ</persName>. And when I saw
               what had happened, I adjured that demon that he should tell me for what reason he could
               do nothing with the power of the maiden. And when the demon was burnt by the angel he
               told me all the truth. And he said to me again, I am the discoverer of all bad things.
               And I recollected myself and gave the tablets of my sorcery to the Bishop, my
               predecessor, whilst all the chief men of the city were present. And he burnt them in the
               fire. I would also persuade thee now to withdraw thyself from the madness of images, and
               come to the house of <persName>God</persName>, and thou shalt know the power of the <persName>Christ</persName>, which is
               invincible.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="48">Then the Count was enraged against the blessed one. And he commanded that he
            should be hung up and combed. Also concerning the holy virgin, he commanded that she
            should be beaten<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20"/> with rough thongs on her face;
            the two being hung opposite to each other. And the maiden began to say, <quote>Glory be to
               Thee, O true <persName>Christ</persName>! <pb n="199"/>that Thou hast brought me who am unworthy near, to
               fulfil Thy will. And I am beaten<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21"/> because of Thy
               name, which exalts its worshippers.</quote> And when the lictors were weary of beating the
            blessed one, she praised <persName>God</persName> all the more. <milestone ed="Add.12,142"
               edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="83b"/></ab>
         <ab n="49">But the Count commanded them to cease from her. And when <persName>Cyprian</persName> was being combed
            he did not feel the combs.</ab>
         <ab n="50">The Count answered and said to him, <quote>Sacrifice and escape from the tortures, and
               thou shalt not die miserably.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="51">The holy <persName>Cyprian</persName> replied and said to him, <quote>Why dost thou exalt thyself against
               <persName>God</persName> and withdrawest from Him? and dost not wish to draw near to the gospel of the
               <persName>Christ</persName>? For thou wilt not keep me back from the path of life. For I am running that I
               may attain to the heavenly-minded who inherit the kingdom, and may be made worthy, by
               means of those tortures which thou art bringing to me, of bliss that can never pass
               away.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="52">The Count said, <quote>And wilt thou inherit the kingdom of heaven because of these
               tortures? I will bring greater ones than these to thee.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="53">And he commanded that they should conduct him to the prison-house, and the holy
            <persName>Justa</persName> with him. And he commanded that they should be guarded with diligence. And when
            they entered the prison-house, it shone by the grace of our <persName>Lord Jesus the Christ</persName> who
            was with them.</ab>
         <ab n="54">And after a few days the Count commanded that they should bring them before his
            judgment seat. And the <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14"
               unit="folio" n="84a"/>Count answered and said to the blessed ones, <quote>Do not be
                  deceived by the faith and the sorcery of a mortal man, and lose your lives.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="55">But <persName>Cyprian</persName> answered and said to him, <quote>This death has won eternal life for those
               who love Him.</quote></ab>
         <pb n="200"/>
         <ab n="56">The senseless Count answered and said, <quote>Heat the frying-pan and throw into it
               pitch, and wax, and bitumen, and fling the blessed ones into it<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n22"/> when it boils.</quote> And when they had thrown him in, he was not at all
            hurt.</ab>
         <ab n="57">Then the Count commanded, and they brought the blessed <persName>Justa</persName> to the frying-pan.
            And when she drew near, the <persName>Evil one</persName> cast fear into her mind, and she began to be
            afraid. But the blessed <persName>Cyprian</persName> cried and said to her, <quote>Come, O handmaiden of <persName>God</persName>! for
               thou hast shown me the path of life; and thou hast opened to me the door of heaven; and
               thou hast shown me the glory of the <persName>Christ</persName>. Thou hast been strengthened against the
               demons. Even their chief thou hast reckoned as nothing by the power of the cross. And
               how shouldst thou fear the fire.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="58">And the blessed one signed all her body, and ascended into the fiery frying-pan.
            And both of them rejoiced and exulted in the frying-pan as amongst refreshing dew.</ab>
         <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="84b"/>
         <ab n="59">And <persName>Cyprian</persName> answered and said, <quote>Glory be to <persName>God</persName> in the highest, and peace on the
               earth; and goodwill to upright and faithful men.</quote> And he said again, <quote>Because <persName>Satan</persName> is
                  fallen from heaven, and is trampled beneath the feet of all those who believe in the
                  King, the <persName>Christ</persName>, our Redeemer. For He hath bound the <persName>Evil one</persName> in darkness and all who
                  obey him. I praise Thee, O <persName>God</persName>! for all in which Thou hast deemed us worthy to suffer
                  contempt for Thy sake. I implore of Thee, O merciful <persName>Lord</persName>, to receive our sacrifice for
                  a sweet savour of Thy greatness.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="60">And the Count heard, and laughed, and said, <quote>I curse you and all the skill of
               your sorcery.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="61">And <persName>Athenus</persName> his colleague and profane friend said to the Count, <quote>Let thy Highness
               command me, my lord, and I will approach the boiling pan in the name of the gods; and I
               will overcome the great power of the <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote> <pb n="201"/>And the Count said to him,
            <quote>Approach.</quote> And when he approached the frying-pan, he lifted up his voice and said,
            <quote>Great is the god <persName>Zeus</persName>! and the father of the gods <persName>Asclepius</persName>, who giveth health unto
               men.</quote> And when he <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14"
               unit="folio" n="85a"/>came near to the boiling of the flame he fell, and all his
            limbs were split like wax before the fire. But the grace of <persName>God</persName> preserved the holy
            <persName>Cyprian</persName> and the maiden without a spot; because they praised <persName>God</persName>.</ab>
         <ab n="62">And the Count was troubled and said, <quote>What shall I do? He who was my priest and
               friend has died miserably. What I shall do to these wicked people I do not know.</quote>
            <persName>Terentinus</persName> answered and said to him, <quote>Have nothing to do with these people whom thou
               dost call wicked. And do not withstand the truth. For the power of the Christians is
               invincible. But send them to the Emperor, shewing him the matter of their crime.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="63">And the Count wrote the report about it thus:</ab>
         <ab n="64"><quote>To the great <persName>Emperor Caesar</persName>, who ruleth by land and by sea, <persName>Diocletian</persName>,
               greeting. Against the commandment of thy Majesty have these men arisen. And I have
               apprehended them: <persName>Cyprian</persName>, who is the teacher of the Christians, and the virgin, who is
               named <persName>Justa</persName>. And from the reports, my lord, thou wilt learn into how many tortures and
               afflictions I have thrown them; and they <milestone ed="Add.12,142"
                  edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="85b"/>would not be persuaded by me
               to obey thy laws, my lord, and I have sent them to thine august Majesty.</quote> And when the
               Emperor had read these reports about the blessed ones, he was greatly astonished at
               their endurance, and his friends implored him and said to him, <quote>Do not withstand the
                  great power of <persName>God</persName>.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="65">And when the Emperor had heard [it] he said: <quote>To <persName>Cyprian</persName> who is the teacher of
               the Christians with the virgin <persName>Justa</persName>, who have chosen the vain heresy of those who are
               called Christians; and have forsaken life, and <pb n="202"/>have chosen death. Therefore
               I command concerning them, that their heads be taken off with the sword.</quote></ab>
         <ab n="66">And while the blessed ones were being led off to death, to a certain place in
            which they were to reach their consummation, they asked the lictors that a little time
            might be given them, in which they might pray.</ab>
         <ab n="67">And the holy <persName>Mar Cyprian</persName> began to pray, saying, <quote>Remember, O <persName>Lord</persName>! Thy Church, in
               every place, and all Thy faithful and true servants, and be Thou near to those who love
               Thy name.</quote></ab>
         <milestone ed="Add.12,142" edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="86a"/>
         <ab n="68">And he made the sign of the <persName>Christ</persName> over his whole body, and he placed the virgin
            <persName>Justa</persName> on his right hand: and he persuaded these lictors that she should be beheaded
            before him. And so the lictors did.</ab>
         <ab n="69">And the holy <persName>Cyprian</persName> said, <quote>Glory be to Thee, O <persName>Christ</persName>, the Strengthener of Thy
               worshippers!</quote></ab>
         <ab n="70">And a certain great man was there whose name was <persName>Theoctistus</persName>, a faithful man; and
            he approached and greeted the holy martyr as he was being slain with the sword. And
            <persName>Balbus</persName>, the colleague of the Emperor, commanded concerning him, that his head should be
            taken off with the sword.</ab>
         <ab n="71">And when they had been crowned, and the blessed <persName>Theoctistus</persName> with them, the bodies
            of the blessed ones were thrown to the wild beasts. And they did not approach them for
            many days.</ab>
         <ab n="72">But a sailor, a certain faithful man, when he heard about the end of the holy
            ones, because he was a kinsman of <persName>Theoctistus</persName>, took faithful men of his own with him.
            And he made them sit for six days and six nights, until they had snatched away the
            corpses of the blessed martyrs <milestone ed="Add.12,142"
               edRef="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/14" unit="folio" n="86b"/>from the custodians, because
            the bones of the blessed ones were much more precious to them than gold, or silver, or
            costly pearls. And they carried them to the city of <pb n="203"/><placeName>Rome</placeName> with their
            memoirs. And they gave them to a certain woman whose name was <persName>Rufina</persName>, of the
            distinguished family of the Claudians. And this faithful woman <persName>Rufina</persName> carried the bones
            of the holy martyrs and laid them in an honourable place wrapped in pure linen, and with
            fragrant spices. And every one who approached the blessed ones received health and help
            from them.</ab>
         <ab n="73">And these things were done in the consulate of <persName>Diocletian</persName>, in the city of
            <placeName>Nicomedia</placeName>, on the fifteenth of the month which is called Haziran, our <persName>Lord Jesus the
               Christ</persName> reigning in heaven and on earth.</ab>
         <ab n="74">Here endeth the Martyrdom of <persName>Cyprian</persName> the wizard, and of <persName>Justa</persName> the virgin, and of
            the faithful <persName>Theoctistus</persName>.</ab>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1" target="#a1" n="1">1 From the Sinai palimpsest.</note> 
            <note xml:id="n2" target="#a2" n="2">1 From the Sinai palimpsest.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" target="#a3" n="3">1 MS. <hi rend="doubleQuote">he.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n4" target="#a4" n="4">2 Literally, <hi rend="doubleQuote">from.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n5" target="#a5" n="5">2 Literally, <hi rend="doubleQuote">from.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n6" target="#a6" n="6">2 Literally, <hi rend="doubleQuote">from.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n7" target="#a7" n="7">1 Literally, <hi rend="doubleQuote">mouth.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n8" target="#a8" n="8">1 Literally, <hi rend="doubleQuote">its reward.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n9" target="#a9" n="9">1 MS. <hi rend="doubleQuote">he is.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n10" target="#a10" n="10">2 Syriac Palimpsest <hi rend="doubleQuote">Anthimus</hi> <foreign rend="italics">passim</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11" target="#a11" n="11">1 Or <hi rend="doubleQuote">the Psalmist</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n12" target="#a12" n="12">Ps. xxxv. 22</note>
            <note xml:id="n13" target="#a13" n="13">Is. lii. 13</note>
            <note xml:id="n14" target="#a14" n="14">Ps. cxix. 148</note>
            <note xml:id="n15" target="#a15" n="15">Is. xliv. 2</note>
            <note xml:id="n16" target="#a16" n="16">Gal. iii. 13</note>
            <note xml:id="n17" target="#a17" n="17">Ps. cvi. 2</note>
            <note xml:id="n18" target="#a18" n="18">John iii. 16</note>
            <note xml:id="n19" target="#a19" n="19">1 Literally, <hi rend="doubleQuote">Christ.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n20" target="#a20" n="20">1 Literally, <hi rend="doubleQuote">swallow.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n21" target="#a21" n="21">1 Literally, <hi rend="doubleQuote">I swallow.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n22" target="#a22" n="22">1 Literally, <hi rend="doubleQuote">the frying-pan.</hi></note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
