<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Pearl 2</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Hymns on the Pearl</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/The_Pearl/Hymn_II"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/The_Pearl/Hymn_II
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 2</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Whereunto art thou like? Let thy stillness speak to one that hears; with silent mouth
               speak with us: for whoso hears the stammerings of thy silence, to him thy type utters
               its silent cry concerning our Redeemer.</ab>
            <ab>Thy mother is a virgin of the sea; though he took her not [to wife]: she fell into
               his bosom, though he knew her not; she conceived thee near him, though he did not
               know her. Do thou, that art a type, reproach the Jewish women that have thee hung
               upon them. Thou art the only progeny of all forms which art like to the Word on High,
               Whom singly the Most High begot. The engraven forms seem to be the type of created
               things above. This visible offspring of the invisible womb is a type of great
               things.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> Thy goodly conception was without seed, and without wedlock was thy pure
               generation, and without brethren was thy single birth.</ab>
            <ab>Our Lord had brethren and yet not brethren, since He was an Only-Begotten. O solitary
               one, thou type exact of the Only-Begotten! There is a type of thine in the crown of
               kings, [wherein] thou hast brothers and sisters.</ab>
            <ab>Goodly gems are thy brethren, with beryls and unions as thy companions: may gold be
               as it were thy kinsman, may there be unto the King of kings a crown from thy
               well-beloved ones! When thou camest up from the sea, that living tomb, thou didst cry
               out. Let me have a goodly assemblage of brethren, relatives, and kinsmen. As the
               wheat is in the stalk, so thou art in the crown with princes: and it is a just
               restoration to thee, as if of a pledge,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> that from that depth thou shouldest be
               exalted to a goodly eminence. Wheat the stalk bears in the field; thee the head of
               the king upon his chariot carries about.</ab>
            <ab>O daughter of the water, who hast left sea, wherein thou wert born, and art gone up
               to the dry land, wherein thou art beloved: for men have loved and seized and adorned
               themselves with thee, like as they did that Offspring Whom the Gentiles loved and
               crowned themselves withal.</ab>
            <ab>It is by the mystery of truth that Leviathan is trodden down of mortals: the divers
               put him off, and put on Christ. In the sacrament of oil did the Apostles<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> steal
               Thee away, and came up. They snatched their souls from his mouth, bitter as it
               was.</ab>
            <ab>Thy Nature is like a silent lamb in its sweetness, of which if a man is to lay hold,
               he lifts it in a crucial form by its ears, as it was on <placeName>Golgotha</placeName>. He cast out
               abundantly all His gleams upon them that looked upon Him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Shadowed forth in thy beauty is the beauty of the Son, Who clothed Himself with
               suffering when the nails passed through Him. The awl passed in thee since they
               handled thee roughly, as they did His hands; and because He suffered He reigned, as
               by thy sufferings thy beauty increased.</ab>
            <ab>And if they showed no pity upon thee, neither did they love thee: still suffer as
               thou mightest, thou hast come to reign! <persName>Simon Peter</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> showed pity on the Rock; whoso
               hath smitten it, is himself thereby overcome; it is by reason of Its suffering that
               Its beauty hath adorned the height and the depth.</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">Pearls, he means, have their beauty by nature and so are like Christ;
               other stones must be graven and so are like created natures.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">Job xli. 4; Ps. lxxi. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">See Note on Hymn V. 4 (below).</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">Cephas; i.e., Rock.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
