<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Pearl 3</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Hymns on the Pearl</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/The_Pearl/Hymn_III"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/The_Pearl/Hymn_III
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 3</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Thou dost not hide thyself in thy bareness, O pearl! With the love of thee is the
               merchant ravished also, for he strips off his garments; not to cover thee, [seeing]
               thy clothing is thy light, thy garment is thy brightness, O thou that art bared!</ab>
            <ab>Thou art like <persName>Eve</persName> who was clothed with nakedness. Cursed be he that deceived her and
               stripped her and left her. The serpent cannot strip off thy glory. In the mysteries
               whose type thou art, women are clothed with Light in <placeName>Eden</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Very glistening are the pearls of <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName>, as it is written, Who gave thee to
               <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> [the land] of black men.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> He that gave light to the Gentiles, both to the
               Ethiopians and unto the Indians did His bright beams reach.</ab>
            <ab>The eunuch of <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName> upon his chariot<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> saw <persName>Philip</persName>: the Lamb of Light met the dark
               man from out of the water. While he was reading, the Ethiopian was baptised and shone
               with joy, and journeyed on!</ab>
            <ab>He made disciples and taught, and out of black men he made men white.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> And the dark
               Ethiopic women<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> became pearls for the Son; He offered them up to the Father, as a
               glistening crown from the Ethiopians.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>The Queen of <placeName>Sheba</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> was a sheep<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> that had come into the place of wolves; the lamp
               of truth did <persName>Solomon</persName> give her, who also married<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> her when he fell away. She was
               enlightened and went away, but they were dark as their manner was.</ab>
            <ab>The bright spark which went down home with that blessed [Queen], held on its shining
               amid the darkness, till the new Day-spring came. The bright spark met with this
               shining, and illumined the place.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>There are in the sea divers fishes of many cubits, and with all their greatness they
               are very small; but by thy littleness the crown is made great, like as the Son, by
               whose littleness <persName>Adam</persName> was made great.</ab>
            <ab>For the head is thy crown intended: for the eye thy beauty, for the ear thy
               goodliness. Come up from the sea, thou neighbour to the dry land, and come and
               sojourn by the [seat of] hearing. Let the ear love the word of life as it loveth
               thee!</ab>
            <ab>In the ear is the word, and without it is the pearl. Let it as being warned by thee,
               by thee get wisdom, and be warned by the word of truth. Be thou its mirror: the
               beauty of the Word in thine own beauty shall it see: in thee it shall learn how
               precious is the Word on High! The ear is the leaf: the flesh is the tree, and thou in
               the midst of it are a fruit of light, and to the womb that brings forth Light, thou
               art a type that points.</ab>
            <ab>Thee He used as a parable of that kingdom, O pearl! as He did the virgins that
               entered into it, five in number, clothed with the light of their lamps! To thee are
               those bright ones like, thou that art clad in light!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Who would give a pearl to the daughter of the poor? For when it hangs on her, it
               becomes her not. Gain without price that faith, all of which becomes all the limbs of
               men. But for no gold would a lady exchange her pearl.</ab>
            <ab>It were a great disgrace if thou shouldst throw thy pearl away into the mire for
               nought!</ab>
            <ab>In the pearl of time let us behold that of eternity; for it is in the purse, or in
               the seal, or in the treasury. Within the gate there are other gates with their locks
               and keys. Thy pearl hath the High One sealed up as taking account of all.</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">I.e. with the mysteries typified in the pearl, women are clothed with
               light at Baptism.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">Job xxviii. 19 (Pesh.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">Acts viii. 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">Jer. xiii. 23; Is. i. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">Ps. lxviii. 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">1 Kings x. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">Why St. E. contemplates the queen as a sheep appears from his remarks
               on the place. The following are a part of them <quote>It was not the fame of Solomon only,
               but also the Name of the Lord, which called to this queen, who sought to know the God
               of Solomon, who set out upon a dangerous long journey, and brought presents fit for a
               king.…Our Lord also extolled this queen in the Gospel, and praised her zealousness,
               when He rebuked the sluggishness of the Jews.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n8">This was a tradition of the Jews, a tradition based in part on
               Canticles i. 5.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
