<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Pearl 4</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Hymns on the Pearl</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/The_Pearl/Hymn_IV"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/The_Pearl/Hymn_IV
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 4</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <p>The thief gained the faith which gained him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> and brought him up and placed him in
               paradise. He saw in the Cross a tree of life; that was the fruit, he was the eater in
               Adam’s stead.</p>
            <p>The fool, who goes astray, grazes the faith, as it were an eye,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> by all manner of
               questions. The probing of the finger blinds the eye, and much more doth that prying
               blind. the faith.</p>
            <p>For even the diver pries not into his pearl. In it do all merchants rejoice without
               prying into whence it came; even the king who is crowned therewith does not explore
               it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <p>Because Balaam was foolish, a foolish beast in the ass spoke with him, because he
               despised God Who spoke with him. Thee too let the pearl reprove in the ass’s
               stead.</p>
            <p>The people that had a heart of stone, by a Stone He set at nought,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> for lo, a stone
               hears words. Witness its work that has reproved them; and you, ye deaf ones, let the
               pearl reprove today.</p>
            <p>With the swallow<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> and the crow did He put men to shame; with the ox, yea with the
               ass,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> did He put them to shame; let the pearl reprove now, O ye birds and things on
               earth and things below.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <p>Not as the moon does thy light fill or wane; the Sun whose light is greater than all,
               lo! of Him it is that a type is shadowed out in thy little compass. O type of the
               Son, one spark of Whom is greater than the sun!—</p>
            <p>The pearl itself is full, for its light is full; neither is there any cunning worker
               who can steal from it; for its wall is its own beauty, yea, its guard also! It lacks
               not, since it is entirely perfect.</p>
            <p>And if a man would break thee to take a part from thee, thou art like the faith which
               with the heretics perishes, seeing they have broken it in pieces and spoiled it: for
               is it any better than this to have the faith scrutinised?</p>
            <p>The faith is an entire nature that may not be corrupted. The spoiler gets himself
               mischief by it: the heretic brings ruin on himself thereby. He that chases the light
               from his pupils blinds himself.</p>
            <p>Fire and air are divided when sundered. Light alone, of all creatures, as its
               Creator, is not divided; it is not barren, for that it also begets without losing
               thereby.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <p>And if a man thinks that thou art framed [by art] he errs greatly; thy nature
               proclaims that thou, as all stones, art not the framing of art; and so thou art a
               type of the Generation which no making framed.</p>
            <p>Thy stone flees from a comparison with the Stone [which is] the Son. For thy own
               generation is from the midst of the deep, that of the Son of thy Creator is from the
               highest height; He is not like thee, in that He is like His Father.</p>
            <p>And as they tell, two wombs bare thee also. Thou camest down from on high a fluid
               nature; thou camest up from the sea a solid body. By means of thy second birth thou
               didst show thy loveliness to the children of men.</p>
            <p>Hands fixed thee, when thou wast embodied, into thy receptacles; for thou art in the
               crown as upon a cross, and in a coronet as in a victory; thou art upon the ears, as
               if to fill up what was lacking; thou extendest over all.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n">Luke xxii. 42.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Zech. ii. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Matt. xxi. 42.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Jer. viii. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Is. i. 3.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
