<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Pearl 1</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Hymns on the Pearl</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/The_Pearl/Hymn_I"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/The_Pearl/Hymn_I
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 1</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <p>On a certain day a pearl did I take up, my brethren; I saw in it mysteries pertaining
               to the Kingdom; semblances and types of the Majesty; it became a fountain, and I
               drank out of it mysteries of the Son.</p>
            <p>I put it, my brethren, upon the palm of my hand, that I might examine it: I went to
               look at it on one side, and it proved faces on all sides. I found out that the Son
               was incomprehensible, since He is wholly Light.</p>
            <p>In its brightness I beheld the Bright One Who cannot be clouded, and in its pureness
               a great mystery, even the Body of our Lord which is well-refined: in its
               undividedness I saw the Truth which is undivided.</p>
            <p>It was so that I saw there its pure conception,—the Church, and the Son within her.
               The cloud was the likeness of her that bare Him, and her type the heaven, since there
               shone forth from her His gracious Shining.</p>
            <p>I saw therein His trophies, and His victories, and His crowns. I saw His helpful and
               overflowing graces, and His hidden things with His revealed things.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <p>It was greater to me than the ark, for I was astonied thereat: I saw therein folds
               without shadow to them because it was a daughter of light, types vocal without
               tongues, utterances of mysteries without lips, a silent harp that without voice gave
               out melodies.</p>
            <p>The trumpet falters and the thunder mutters; be not thou daring then; leave things
               hidden, take things revealed. Thou hast seen in the clear sky a second shower; the
               clefts of thine ears, as from the clouds, they are filled with interpretations.</p>
            <p>And as that manna which alone filled the people, in the place of pleasant meats, with
               its pleasantnesses, so does this pearl fill me in the place of books, and the reading
               thereof, and the explanations thereof.</p>
            <p>And when I asked if there were yet other mysteries, it had no mouth for me that I
               might hear from, neither any ears wherewith it might hear me. O thou thing without
               senses, whence I have gained new senses!</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <p>It answered me and said, “The daughter of the sea am I, the illimitable sea! And from
               that sea whence I came up it is that there is a mighty treasury of mysteries in my
               bosom! Search thou out the sea, but search not out the Lord of the sea!</p>
            <p>“I have seen the divers who came down after me, when astonied, so that from the midst
               of the sea they returned to the dry ground; for a few moments they sustained it not.
               Who would linger and be searching on into the depths of the Godhead?</p>
            <p>“The waves of the Son are full of blessings, and with mischiefs too. Have ye not
               seen, then, the waves of the sea, which if a ship should struggle with them would
               break her to pieces, and if she yield herself to them, and rebel not against them,
               then she is preserved? In the sea all the Egyptians were choked, though they
               scrutinised it not, and, without prying, the Hebrews too were overcome upon the dry
               land, and how shall ye be kept alive? And the men of Sodom were licked up by the
               fire, and how shall ye prevail?</p>
            <p>“At these uproars the fish in the sea were moved,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> and Leviathan also. Have ye then
               a heart of stone that ye read these things and run into these errors? O great fear
               that justice also should be so long silent!”<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> 4. “Searching is mingled with
               thanksgiving, and whether of the two will prevail? The incense of praise riseth along
               with the fume of disputation from the tongue, and unto which shall we hearken? Prayer
               and prying [come] from one mouth,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> and which shall we listen to? “For three days
               was Jonah a neighbour [of mine] in the sea: the living things that were in the sea
               were affrighted, [saying,] “Who shall flee from God? Jonah fled, and ye are obstinate
               at your scrutiny of Him!”</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n">Hos. iv. 3; Zeph. i. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Eccles. viii. 11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">James iii. 10.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
