<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" 	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Pearl 6</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">Hymns on the Pearl</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/The_Pearl/Hymn_VI"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/The_Pearl/Hymn_VI
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Hymn 6</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Would that the memory of the fathers would exhale from the tombs; who were very
               simple as being wise, and reverend as believing. They without cavilling searched for,
               and came to the right path.</ab>
            <ab>He gave the law; the mountains melted away; fools broke through it. By unclean ravens
               He fed Elijah at the desert stream; and moreover gave from the skeleton honey unto
               Samson. They judged not, nor inquired why it was unclean, why clean.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>And when He made void the sabbaths, the feeble Gentiles were clothed with health.
               Samson took the daughter of the aliens, and there was no disputing among the
               righteous; the prophet also took a harlot, and the just held their peace.</ab>
            <ab>He blamed the righteous,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> and He held up and lifted up [to view] their
               delinquencies: He pitied sinners,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> and restored them without cost: and made low the
               mountains of their sins:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> He proved that God is not to be arraigned by men, and as
               Lord of Truth, that His servants were His shadow; and whatsoever way His will looked,
               they directed also their own wills; and because Light was in Him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> their shadows
               were enlightened.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>How strangely perplexed are all the heretics by simple things! For when He plainly
               foreshadowed this New Testament by that of the Prophets, those pitiable men rose, as
               though from sleep, and shouted out and made a disturbance. And the Way, wherein the
               righteous held straight on, and by their truths had gone forth therein, that [Way]
               have these broken<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> up, because they were besotted: this they left and went out of;
               because they pried, an evil searching, [yea,] an evil babbling led them astray.</ab>
            <ab>They saw the ray: they made it darkness, that they might grope therein: they saw the
               jewel, even the faith: while they pried into it, it fell and was lost. Of the pearl
               they made a stone, that they might stumble upon it.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>O Gift, which fools have made a poison! The People were for separating Thy beauteous
               root from Thy fountain, though they separated it not: [false] teachings estranged Thy
               beauty also from the stock thereof.</ab>
            <ab>By Thee did they get themselves estranged, who wished to estrange Thee. By Thee the
               tribes were cut off and scattered abroad from out of Sion, and also the [false]
               teachings of the seceders.</ab>
            <ab>Bring Thyself within the compass of our littleness, O Thou Gift of ours. For if love
               cannot find Thee out on all sides, it cannot be still and at rest. Make Thyself
               small, Thou Who art too great for all, Who comest unto all!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>By this would those who wrangle against our Pearl be reproved; because instead of
               love, strife has come in and dared to essay to unveil thy beauty. It was not graven,
               since it is a progeny which cannot be interpreted.</ab>
            <ab>Thou didst show thy beauty among the abjects to show whereto thou art like, thou
               Pearl that art all faces. The beholders were astonied and perplexed at thee. The
               separatists separated thee in two, and were separated in two by thee, thou that art
               of one substance throughout.</ab>
            <ab>They saw not thy beauty, because there was not in them the eye of truth. For the veil
               of prophecy, full as it was of the mysteries; to them was a covering of thy
               glistering faces: they thought that thou wast other [than thou art], O thou mirror of
               ours! and therefore these blind schismatics defiled thy fair beauty.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Since they have extolled thee too much, or have lowered thee too much, bring them to
               the even level. Come down, descend a little from that height of infidelity and
               heathendom; and come up from the depth of Judaism, though thou art in the Heaven.</ab>
            <ab>Let our Lord be set between God and men!<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> Let the Prophets be as it were His
               heralds! Let the Just One, as being His Father, rejoice! that Word it is which
               conquered both Jews and Heathens!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>Come, Thou Gift of Holy Church, stay, rest in the midst of Her! The circumcised have
               troubled Thee, in that they are vain babblers, and so have the [false] doctrines in
               that they are contentious. Blessed be He that gave Thee a goodly company which bears
               Thee about!</ab>
            <ab>In the covenant of Moses is Thy brightness shadowed forth: in the new covenant Thou
               dartest it forth: from those first Thy light shineth even unto those last. Blessed be
               He that gave us Thy gleam as well as Thy bright rays.</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n">Hos. i. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Matt. ix. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Luke xviii. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Cant. ii. 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Or, pierced—perhaps a word of intentionally uncertain meaning, so as to
               suit with <quote>the way</quote> in either sense of it.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">1 Tim. ii. 5.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
