<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Epistle to Lausus</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/Chapter_1"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/Chapter_1
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The Epistle of <persName>Palladius</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n111-1"/> the Bishop of the city of <placeName>Helenopolis</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n111-2"/> which he made (or
            wrote) to <persName>Lausus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n111-3"/> the prefect<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n111-4"/> who asked him to write for him an account of the lives and
            deeds of the Fathers who were monks; and he wrote thus:</head>
         <salute><persName>Palladius</persName> the Bishop to <persName>Lausus</persName> the prefect: greeting (or peace).</salute>
         <p>I ascribe blessing to thy beautiful desire, for we may begin [this] epistle with
            blessing, because whilst many men are devoted unto vain things, and build buildings of
            stone wherein there is no profit, thou hast shown thyself strenuous to learn concerning
            the building of the words of the narratives of holy men. For there is One alone Who hath
            no deed of doctrine (or learning) that is to say, God, Who is over everything, for He
            existeth of Himself, and there is no other being who existed before Him. Now all
            rational beings are learners, because they are beings who have been made and created.
            The ranks of the celestial hosts who existed first of all, and the orders of beings who
            are the most exalted of all possess teachers in the Trinity, Who is exalted above
            everything. The orders of beings of the second group learn from the beings of the first
            group, and those which belong to the third group learn from those of the second group,
            which is above them, and in this manner each of the later groups learneth from that
            which is above it, even down to the lowest group of all; for those among them who are
            superior in respect of knowledge and excellence teach knowledge unto those who are
            inferior to them. Therefore those who imagine that they have no need of teachers, and
            who will not be convinced by those who teach them things of good, are sick with the want
            of the knowledge which is the mother and the producer of pride. Now those who are
            princes and the foremost ones among these in respect of destruction are those who
            intentionally (or wilfully) fell from sojourning in heaven, and from the service
            thereof, and these are the devils who fly in the air because they forsook the heavenly
            Teacher and rebelled.</p>
         <p>For polished words and sentences, or words strung together in admirable order, are not
            doctrine, for these things are for the most part found with evil-doers and sinners; but
            this is doctrine, which is the correction of the natural habits and disposition, and the
            leading of a life of spiritual excellence according to rule, by which I mean the
            possession of the faculty which shall make a man superior to affliction and to emotion,
            and to timidity, and to wrath; and which shall make him to possess freedom of speech
            before every man, and which shall, through the fervour of Divine Love, produce works
            that shall be like unto coals of fire. For if doctrine be not this, the Great Teacher
            would not have said unto <persName>His disciples</persName>, <quote>Learn of Me, for I am meek and lowly in heart</quote>
            (St. Matthew 11:29), for He did not instruct (or order) His <persName>Apostles</persName> merely in the
            beauty of speech, without at the same time making manifest a proof (or work) in His own
            Person. And He caused grief unto no man except those who spurned doctrine, and those who
            hated their teachers. It is meet that the soul which leadeth its life in God should
            either learn in faith that which it knoweth not, or should learn wisely that of which it
            hath knowledge; but if it will do neither of these things it is, if it be possible, sick
            through madness.</p>
         <p>The beginning of instruction (or discipline) is the fullness which is of doctrine, and
            density of speech is a helper of the fear of God, and for these things the soul of him
            that loveth God hungereth continually. Be strong then, and play the man. Farewell. And
            may God grant thee the gift of pursuing at all times the knowledge of <persName>Christ</persName>.</p>
      </body>
      <noteGrp>
         <note xml:id="n111-1"></note>
         <note xml:id="n111-2"></note>
         <note xml:id="n111-3"></note>
         <note xml:id="n111-4"></note>
         <note xml:id="n112-1"></note>
         <note xml:id="n112-2"></note>
         <note xml:id="n113-1"></note>
         <note xml:id="n113-2"></note>
         <note xml:id="n113-3"></note>
         <note xml:id="n113-4"></note>
      </noteGrp>
   </text>
</TEI>
