<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Counsels to Lausus</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/Chapter_3"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/Chapter_3
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Counsels to <persName>Lausus</persName></head>
         <p>Let the following be before thy mind in all [thine] acts, and thou shalt sin in no
            particular.</p>
         <list>
            <item n="1">To do good to the fool and to bury the dead; both are alike.</item>
            <item n="2">It is meet that a man should put on armour over the breast, and the word of
               our Redeemer <persName>Christ</persName> [over] grief; armour and shield will hide the breast, but [only]
               faith and action [can hide] the soul.</item>
            <item n="3">As it is possible to see the skill of the painter on a small tablet, so a
               small gift [sheweth] the greatness of the disposition of the soul.</item>
            <item n="4">Have no confidence in the belief that that which is placed outside thy soul
               is thy possession.</item>
            <item n="5">Clothes and raiment drape statues, but habits and manners drape men.</item>
            <item n="6">An evil word is the beginning of evil deeds.</item>
            <item n="7">Speak thou according to what is right, and where it is right, and concerning
               the things which are right, and hearken not unto that which is not right.</item>
            <item n="8">It is better to shake a stone vainly than [to utter a vain] word, and it is
               better to be under subjection to the Barbarians than to evil passions.</item>
            <item n="9">The excellence of a horse is made apparent in battle, and the disposition of
               a friend is put to the test in tribulation.</item>
            <item n="10">It is impossible to divide the sea, and it is also impossible to still the
               waves thereof, although for them it is always easy [to still themselves].</item>
            <item n="11">The wise and God-fearing man is he who hateth that which is not
               right.</item>
            <item n="12">The gentle and gracious man is he who treadeth pride under foot; but he who
               is set upon that which is the contrary of this is one who is governed by
               arrogance.</item>
            <item n="13">Constant prayer is the strength, and the armour, and the wall of the
               soul.</item>
            <item n="14">Wine maketh warm the body, and the word of God [warmeth] the soul.</item>
            <item n="15">Know thou that not even much time will bring oblivion upon one act which
               thou wouldst hide.</item>
            <item n="16">The believing mind is a temple of God which it is meet for a man to adorn
               daily and to burn incense therein, inasmuch as it is God Who dwelleth there.</item>
         </list>
         <p>And numbers upon numbers of books at divers times and in various ways have they left
            unto the habitations of men, and some of them are according to the Mind which is above
            and Divine Grace, and were [written] for the edification and protection of those who
            wished to [follow] carefully after the faith and the doctrine of our Redeemer, and some
            of them are according to the adulation of the children of men, and the corrupt mind
            which is mad after the lusts of the body, [and some of them] are for the consolation of
            those who destroy vainglory; but others are from some vain madness and the agency (or
            operation) of that evil <persName>Devil</persName> who hateth the things which are good, and [their writers]
            made use of arrogance and hatred, and in order to corrupt the children of men whose
            minds have been laid waste and who have no understanding they introduced [them] that
            they might defile the purity of <persName>the holy Catholic Church</persName>, and hinder its pure life and
            deeds of ascetic excellence.</p>
         <p>And, moreover, it hath seemed to me—I who fall short of the hope which is in <persName>Christ</persName>, and
            who am shamefaced before the command of thy great mindedness—O thou man who lovest
            doctrine, that I ought first of all to narrate to thee the story of how I was reared,
            and concerning the gradual growth of my mind of such excellence as I possess towards
            God. I lived a life of rule and was in a monastery of solitary brethren for the first
            part of my life, that is to say until the thirty-third year of my age, and I served the
            office of Bishop for twenty years; thus the whole period of my life hath included
            fifty-six years.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/></p>
         <p>It is, therefore, absolutely necessary, inasmuch as it hath seemed to me that thou art
            very anxious to hear the triumphs of the holy Fathers, because of the divine and
            spiritual profit [which is therein], that I should tell thee in writing [concerning] the
            men and the women, of whom some I have myself seen, and concerning others of whom I have
            heard from believing men, and concerning others whom I have met with when I was
            travelling about in the land of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and in <placeName>Libya</placeName>, and in the <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName>, and also in the
            region of <placeName>Syene</placeName>, and among those who are called <persName>men of <placeName>Tabenna</placeName></persName>, and afterwards in
            <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>, and in <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, and in <placeName>Syria</placeName>, and among these in the countries of the
            <placeName>West</placeName>, and among the <persName>Romans</persName>, and among <persName>the people of the <placeName>Campagna</placeName></persName>. And I must also set
            down in writing with careful exactitude the history of everything which appertaineth
            closely to these men from the very beginning and set before thee as an example that
            which will be a most excellent memorial and a benefit of the soul, that is to say, a
            sure and certain binding up, so that by means of it thou mayest be able to dispel from
            thy soul all the slumber of error, which cometh into being through irrational desire,
            and all the doubts of the soul in respect of faith, and sluggishness in respect of the
            things which are useful, and all loathing and littleness of soul concerning habits of
            virtue, that is to say, keenness of wrath and perturbation and animal ferocity and empty
            fear.</p>
         <p>Then shalt thou flee from the vain and corrupt delight of this world, and through [thy]
            constant eager desire thou shalt draw nigh to the hope which is in God; and thou shalt
            govern thyself in the desire of the fear of God, and those who are with thee, and those
            who are under thine authority, and moreover, unto him that feareth God thou wilt become
            king. For through these triumphs all those who have become friends of <persName>Christ</persName> shall
            hasten to be united unto Him, and they shall also look for the loosing of the soul from
            the body, for it is well known that daily [they will do this], even as it is written, <quote>I
            am constrained by the good desire which I possess [to wish] to become free and to be
            with <persName>Christ</persName></quote> (Philippians 1:23). And exceedingly excellent is all that which is said,
            <quote>Make ready thy works for [thy] going forth, and prepare thy field</quote> (Proverbs 24:27).
            For he who remembereth death continually, [and keepeth in his mind the knowledge] that
            he must most certainly die, will neither be negligent of nor commit sin in respect of
            great matters, even according to what is said, <quote>In all thy words remember thine end, and
            thou wilt never commit sin</quote> (Ecclesiasticus 7:31). And beside all these things I will
            add this also, so that thou mayest not belittle the tradition of this our faulty
            history, and mayest not hold in contempt the simplicity and want of polish of the
            language [thereof]; for this matter appertaineth not to the divine doctrine (or
            teaching), that we should compose speech with wise skill, but we should strengthen the
            mind with sure and certain words of understanding, according to that which is said,
            <quote>Open thy mouth with the word of truth, and judge every man in a sound manner</quote> (Proverbs
            31:9); and moreover <quote>thou shalt not forget the narratives of the old men, because they
            also have them from their fathers</quote> (Ecclesiasticus 8:9).</p>
         <p>I therefore, O thou lover of doctrine, thou godly man, have lighted upon many things
            with the holy men, not through making use of ordinary thought, but by making journeys
            [among them] which have lasted thirty days, yea, even thirty days twice told. And [I say
            it], as before God, that in travels and journeyings I would have trodden the whole of
            the territory of the <persName>Greeks</persName> so that I might have the opportunity of conversing with each
            of the lovers of God, and I would have undertaken the labour of a journey such as this
            gratefully so that I might be able to traffic for a profit (or benefit) which I did not
            possess. For if that man who was far more excellent than I am, and perhaps far more
            excellent than the whole world, and who in his life and works, and in his knowledge, and
            in his wise opinions of the Spirit, and in his faith which was in <persName>Christ</persName>, surpassed
            many, I mean the blessed man <persName>Paul</persName>, who in order that he might see <persName>James</persName>, and <persName>Cephas
            (Peter)</persName>, and <placeName>John</placeName> made a journey from <placeName>Tarsus</placeName> to <placeName>Judea</placeName>, and it is well known that he
            related the fact of this journey somewhat as a boast when he was declaring abroad and
            revealing his labours in order that he might stimulate those who were living lives
            sluggish and indolent in respect of spiritual excellence, and when he said, <quote>I went up
            to <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> (Galatians 1:18) that I might see <persName>Cephas (Peter)</persName>,</quote> not that he was denying
            the spiritual excellence of <persName>Peter</persName> of which he had received [information] by report, but
            because he was longing for converse with him also. [Now, if this <persName>Paul</persName> had need of
            converse with <persName>Peter</persName>], how much more did I, who am a debtor of ten thousand talents, need
            to do this (i.e., to visit the holy men), for the sake of the benefit, not for the sake
            of any good which I could do them but for the sake of the advantage which I the sinful
            man should myself gain? And moreover, the things which writers have written down about
            the holy Fathers, I mean <persName>Abraham</persName>, and <persName>Isaac</persName>, and <persName>Jacob</persName>, and <persName>Moses</persName>, and <persName>Elijah</persName>, and the
            other saints, were not composed and narrated to glorify them, but that those who should
            peruse them might profit thereby.</p>
         <p>Therefore, O chaste and believing man, <persName>Lausus</persName>, thou servant of God, knowing these
            things, and having also instructed thyself in many others, be convinced by our discourse
            also and let the matters thereof be laid up in thy God-fearing mind as in a secure
            storehouse which is not wont to be disturbed by evil things of divers kinds, either
            visible or invisible, and which only constant prayer and the converse which concerneth
            the service of the soul can make to be moved.</p>
         <p>For many of these brethren who in the fear of God won spiritual excellence, and who
            waxed great in ascetic labours and lovingkindness, and who were famed (or boasted)
            because of their perfect chastity and virginity, and who protracted to great length
            their meditations upon the Holy Scriptures, and placed their trust upon [their]
            strenuousness in spiritual doctrine, were never held to be worthy of the state of
            impassibility, because they served with a mind which possessed not discretion and
            employed only the form of the fear of God, and because they were diseased with the love
            of external converse, wherefrom are produced all vices which enter [into a man] from
            without, and which eradicate that which is the mother of the service which taketh place
            in the soul.</p>
         <p>Be strong, therefore, in all wisdom, and nourish not thy soul in the riches which thou
            hast made (or gotten), having made them sufficiently little by means of the gifts to
            those who are needy, so that the ministration which ariseth therefrom may perfect the
            service of excellence, for [this] cometh into being neither through any urging
            whatsoever, nor through the foolish thoughts of any form whatsoever for the sake of
            vainglory. And do not bind thyself to [do] anything under a penalty [secured] by oaths
            as many men do, as for example those who for the sake of vainglory strive eagerly
            neither to eat nor to drink, for though by the force of [such] oaths they may bring
            their feeble will into subjection, through this same thing they fall miserably, either
            by means of pleasures and the loathing [which followeth thereafter], or through the
            sickness of the body, or else through the delightful gratification of some lust they
            bring forth falsehood. And as thou receivest [what is good] according to reason, so
            according to reason shalt thou make thyself to be remote [from what is evil], and thou
            shalt never sin at all; for by the word of God shall all motions of fear be
            extinguished, and thou shalt draw nigh unto the things which bring [thee] profit, and
            shalt trample down those which would cause [thee] loss. For for the righteous the Law
            was not laid down.</p>
         <p>It is better to drink wine in moderation than to drink water immoderately, and it
            appeareth to me that those who drink wine in moderation are holy men, and that those who
            pridefully use water in an immoderate fashion are depraved and pleasure-loving. Do not
            therefore ascribe blame or praise to the eating [or not eating] of food, or to the
            drinking [or not drinking] of wine, but ascribe praise, or woe, unto those who make use
            properly or improperly of meat and drink. <persName>Joseph</persName> in olden time drank wine with the
            <persName>Egyptians</persName>, and was in no way injured in his mind thereby, for he took good heed unto
            [the admonitions of] his understanding; but <persName>Pythagoras</persName>, and <persName>Diogenes</persName>, and <persName>Plato</persName>, and
            with them also the <persName>Manichaeans</persName>, and other sects of philosophers [did not], and they came
            thereby to such a pitch of licentiousness and vainglory that they even forgot the God of
            the universe and worshipped soulless images. On the other hand, the blessed <persName>Apostle</persName>
            <persName>Peter</persName> and those who were with him drew nigh to wine and made use thereof, and because of
            this the <persName>Jews</persName> reproached our Lord, the Redeemer of all [men] and their Teacher, and made
            complaints against Him, saying, <quote>Why do not Thy disciples fast like <persName>John</persName>?</quote> (St. Matthew
            9:14; St. Mark 2:18.) And again they lifted themselves up (?) against the disciples and
            blamed them, saying, <quote>Why doth your master eat and drink with tax-gatherers and
            sinners?</quote> (St. Matthew 9:11; 10:18, 19.) Now they did not make their complaints about
            bread and water only, but also about wine and delicate viands, for it is evident that
            they only wanted to lay blame upon the disciples in everything.</p>
         <p>Thereupon our Redeemer made answer, and said, <quote><persName>John</persName> came in the path of righteousness,
            neither eating nor drinking</quote>—now it is well known that flesh and wine [are here referred
            to], for it was impossible for him to live without food of other kinds—<quote>and ye say that
            he hath a devil in him; and the Son of Man hath come, eating and drinking, and [ye] say,
            <quote>Behold a glutton and a winebibber, a friend of tax-gatherers and sinners!</quote></quote> What then
            is it right for us to do, so that we may neither go after those who make complaints [of
            our acts], nor after those who praise them? For we must either fast with <persName>John</persName> according
            to discretion, even though the <persName>Jews</persName> said that there was a devil in him, and that he was
            certainly mad, or we must drink wine with <persName>Christ</persName> with knowledge, if the body shall have
            need thereof, even though the children of men shall say concerning us, <quote>Behold a glutton
            and a winebibber.</quote> For in very truth neither the eating of food nor the abstaining
            therefrom is anything, but the faith and love which are made perfect in works; for when
            a man followeth after faith wholly by actions, he who eateth and drinketh is blameless
            for faith’s sake, for everything which is not of faith is sin. But perhaps one of those
            who love the carnal lusts, or perhaps one of those who sin not, will say that if they
            eat in faith, or if they do anything else by the irrational thought of the carnal
            appetite, or through a corrupt intent, those who support themselves on faith commit sin.
            Now our Redeemer made a distinction, saying, <quote>By their fruit ye shall know them</quote> (St.
            Matthew 7:20); and the fruits may be recognized by the word of God, and by spiritual
            wisdom, according to the word of the blessed <persName>Apostle</persName>, who said, <quote>Love, peace, gladness,
            long-suffering, gentleness, goodness, faith, meekness, patient endurance</quote> (Galatians
            5:22, 23)—these are the fruits of the Spirit according to the word of the <persName>Apostle</persName>.</p>
         <p>Whosoever then is eager to possess these fruits will never, without reason and without
            thought on any occasion, eat flesh, or drink wine, or dwell with a man with evil intent.
            Moreover, the blessed <persName>Paul</persName> saith, <quote>Whosoever is about to strive in a contest preserveth
            his mind free from every other thought, and thus keepeth his body healthy, and maketh
            himself to be remote from the things which would make him fat</quote> (Compare 1 Corinthians
            9:25, 27). But if he fall into sickness, or into severe sufferings, or he become a
            companion unto afflictions which fight against him externally, he must then make use of
            meat and drink by way of a binding up, and a healing medicine for the things which work
            tribulation for him. Let us then keep ourselves remote from the evil things which are
            wrought in the soul, I mean anger, and envy, and vainglory, and dejection, and evil
            discourse, and the suspicion which is not seemly, for whilst a man is giving thanks unto
            God he cannot commit sin.</p>
         <p>Now therefore, having spoken sufficiently concerning these things, I have another
            entreaty to bring nigh unto the love of doctrine which is in thee, that is to say, I
            would that thou didst flee with all thy strength from the converse of men from whom thou
            canst gain no benefit, although their outside skin be ornamented with various patterns;
            even if they be orthodox they will cause thee to suffer loss, and if they be heretics
            that loss will be very much greater. And although they appear to be exceedingly aged,
            and their bodies be shrivelled and withered, and it may seem to thee that thou canst not
            in any way be injured by them because of the beautiful dispositions which are in them,
            that which is in them and which appeareth to thee to be a small matter, will do thee an
            injury; for thou shalt become lax in thy mind in respect of them, and whilst laughing at
            them thou wilt become unduly exalted, and that thou shouldst be driven to arrogance
            would be a loss for thee. Follow then after the mind of pious men and women who shine
            with the light which entereth in through the windows, so that by means of these, like a
            book the lines of which are extremely close together, thou mayest be able clearly to see
            what is in thy heart by comparison with them, either of sluggishness or strenuousness.
            For there are very many things which testify concerning spiritual excellence, [such as]
            the colour of the face which blossometh with ascetic labours, and the manner in which
            the apparel is put on, and a peaceable manner, and a mode of speech which is not
            inflated, and modesty of the countenance, and a discourse which is not crooked, and
            cheerfulness of the mind, and an understanding which is full of knowledge; by these
            things both thine own fair beauty will be made strong, and also all those who follow
            after the goal of the fear of God, even though they be [living] in a state of negligence
            or in some other similar [vice]. For, according to the word of the wise man, the
            behaviour of a man, and the gait of his legs, and the laughter of his mouth testify
            concerning him (Ecclesiasticus 19:30).</p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n118-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n118-2"></note>
            <note xml:id="n119-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n119-2"></note>
            <note xml:id="n119-2"></note>
            <note xml:id="n119-4">There is some mistake in the numbers here give, for 33+20=53; we should read <!-- Syriac needed -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n120-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n121-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n121-2"></note>
            <note xml:id="n121-3"></note>
            <note xml:id="n121-4"></note>
            <note xml:id="n122-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n124-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n124-2"></note>
            <note xml:id="n124-3"></note>
            <note xml:id="n125-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n125-2"></note>
            <note xml:id="n125-3"></note>
            <note xml:id="n126-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n126-2"></note>
            <note xml:id="n127-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n127-2"></note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
