<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Abba Isidore</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_1"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_1
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 1. The History of Abba <persName>Isidore</persName> [Bishop of <placeName>Hermopolis Parva (Damanhur)</placeName> in
            <placeName>Lower Egypt</placeName>].</head>
         <p>By the help of our Lord I will, therefore, begin [to write] for thee, [O <persName>Lausus</persName>,] the
            histories of the holy Fathers, and I will omit nothing concerning them which I will not
            make known in [my] discourse, neither the histories of those who lived in cities, nor of
            those who lived in villages or in caves, nor of those who became famous in the desert.
            Nay, I will even add to my discourse the histories of those who lived among the general
            assembly of a community, for no special country or place wherein they lived and wherein
            they perfected the life of ascetic excellence needs to be sought out, for [everywhere]
            they led the pure life and conversation of chastity and integrity, and performed the
            deeds of the simple mind wherein, through the help of <persName>Christ</persName>, they wrought and fulfilled
            the lives and deeds of angels.</p>
         <p>Now at first, when I went to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> in the second consulship of the Emperor
            <persName>Theodosius</persName> the Great, who now because of the orthodoxy of his faith in <persName>Christ</persName> sojourneth
            with the angels, I met in the city a wonderful man who was adorned in every respect with
            the most beautiful qualities of speech, and knowledge, and life and conversation, whose
            name was <persName>Isidore</persName>. He was a priest and was the overseer (i.e., manager or secretary) of
            the hospital,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n129-1"/> of the church of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and it was said of him that in his early
            youth he had lived in a monastery in the desert, and that he triumphed in the contest of
            the ascetic life: I saw, moreover, his cell in the mountain of <placeName>Nitria</placeName>. I met him when he
            was an old man seventy years of age, and when he had lived fifteen years longer he
            departed from this world. Now to the end of his life this holy man never put on either a
            linen tunic or even a head-covering; he never washed, and he never ate flesh, and he
            never ate a full meal seated comfortably at a table;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n129-2"/> and yet, through Divine grace, his
            body shone. He possessed a sound and healthy body, and he was, by the grace of <persName>Christ</persName>,
            so fully endowed with strength that those who beheld him and who did not know him would
            not be persuaded that he lived a life of self-denial, and they thought and said that he
            must lead a life of great luxury and that he must eat abundantly of rich meats. Now, if
            I were to undertake to declare the marvellous character of his life and deeds, and
            wished to recount the excellence of his soul, and to make manifest every fact concerning
            them, all time would not suffice [for me to declare them], nor would paper [suffice for
            me to write them]. For this man was so lovingly merciful and so full of peace that, by
            the reason of orthodoxy of his faith in <persName>Christ</persName>, even his enemies who did not believe
            were put to shame by him, from his early youth up, and at his good deeds and at the
            abundance of his graciousness were put to the blush; for he was gracious unto every
            man.</p>
         <p>Now he possessed the gift of the spirit and the knowledge of the Holy Scriptures, and
            the comprehension of divine learning, and he kept the commandments [so strictly] that at
            noon, the time when the brethren were wont to take their food, the mind of this holy man
            was carried away as it were in a slumber, and the greater number of the brethren were
            marvelling at his example and knowledge, and many, many times they tried to persuade him
            to relate unto them the things which he saw, and entreated him to tell them concerning
            the marvellous state which had come upon him, but he could not be persuaded [to do so].
            Finally he was constrained by the power of their love, and he answered and said unto
            them, <quote>My mind departed and was carried away by contemplation, and I was snatched
            away by the similitude of a thought, and I was fed with the food of glory, which,
            however, it is impossible for me to describe.</quote></p>
         <p>Now I knew this man, and on several occasions he burst into tears at the table; and when
            I asked him, <quote>What is the cause of these tears?</quote> he said unto me, <quote>I
            am ashamed of myself because, being a rational being, I eat the food of an irrational
            creature; I desire to live in Paradise, where I should enjoy the food which is
            imperishable. for [although] we have received that power which is from <persName>Christ</persName>, yet am
            I drawn to partake of the food which perisheth. I would partake of the food which is
            spiritual, and I would that I were in the Paradise of delights in the dominion which
            God hath given unto me; and behold I am eating the food of the beasts.</quote></p>
         <p>And unto this man were known all the members of <persName>the Roman Senate</persName> and the free-born women
            of the nobles [of <placeName>Rome</placeName>], because in former times he had gone with Bishop <persName>Athanasius</persName> to
            that city, and he had also been there with the holy man Bishop <persName>Demetrius</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n130-3"/> And <persName>Isidore</persName>, having great riches, and wanting
            nothing, was wont to give abundantly and without sparing to the poor and needy. And when
            he had ended his days and came to die, he made no will whatsoever; and he left no money
            to any man, and he left nothing to his brethren. To his sisters who were virgins he also
            left nothing, and he made no provision at all for them, but committed them to the care
            of <persName>Christ</persName>, saying, <quote>He who created you will provide for your living and also
            whatsoever things of which ye have need, even as He hath [provided] for me.</quote>
            Now with his sisters was a company of about seventy sisters.</p>
         <p>Now when I had come unto him to be his disciple, and I was persuading him to hold me
            worthy of the rank of those who lived in a monastery, being in the vigour of my early
            manhood and needing not the word only but also the labour of the body, and severe
            physical exercises, even like the young unbroken animal, I besought him to teach me his
            beautiful way of life and to let me dwell by myself, for I was heedful of nothing, being
            in the vigour of my early manhood, and I had no great need of doctrine, but only [to
            learn] to subdue the passions of the flesh. Then, like a good teacher, he took me
            outside the city unto a place which was six miles distant, and wherein there was restful
            solitude, and he handed me over unto an anchorite whose name was <persName>Dorotheos</persName>,</p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">Read <!-- Syriac needed -->. I.e. he was the man to whose hands the faithful committed the money
               which they subscribed to support the sick poor of the congregation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">Or, he never enjoyed a full meal.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">Bishop of <persName>Pessinus</persName> in <placeName>Galatia Secunda</placeName>, and friend of <persName>St Chrysostom</persName>,
               whose letter to <persName>Innocent I</persName> he took to <placeName>Rome</placeName>; he was in <placeName>Rome</placeName> again in 405.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
