<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Virgin Potamiaena</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_3"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_3
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The History of the Virgin Potamiaena</head>
         <p>There was a certain young virgin [called Potamiaena] who was exceedingly beautiful and
            she was a Christian; she was the handmaiden of a certain worldly man who was given over
            to a life of pleasure, and she lived in very great luxury, and her master flattered her
            greatly, wishing to destroy her. And being unable to bring her into subjection to his
            will, he at length was seized with madness, and he became furiously angry with her and
            delivered her over to a certain prefect who lived at that time in Alexandria (i.e.,
            Basilides), saying, <quote>She is a Christian, and she revileth the government, and uttereth
            blasphemies against the Emperor.</quote> And he promised to give him much money saying, <quote>If she
            can be persuaded to do my will, keep her for me without disgrace and punishment, but if
            she persisteth in her obstinacy of heart, punish her with every kind of torture thou
            pleasest, and let her not remain alive to laugh at me and at my luxurious way of life.</quote>
            And when they brought the valiant woman before the throne of the judges, she was greatly
            moved, but she was not persuaded; and the prefect tortured the body of the virgin of
            Christ with many different kinds of tortures. Then again after these things he thought
            out a crafty plan, and invented a method of punishment by torture which was as follows.
            He commanded them to bring a huge cauldron which was full of pitch, and to light a
            fierce fire under it, and when the pitch was melted and was boiling, the judge cried to
            her, saying, <quote>Go thou and submit thyself to the will of thy lord, and know thou if thou
            doest not this thing thou shalt straightway fall into this cauldron.</quote> Now when she heard
            this, she sealed her soul, and answered and said, <quote>Thou judgest with iniquity, O judge,
            for thou commandest me to become subject unto fornication. I am the handmaiden of
            Christ, and it is meet that I should stand before His throne without blemish.</quote> And when
            the judge heard this, he was straightway greatly troubled and filled with wrath, and he
            commanded them to bring her and to cast her into the cauldron. Then the virgin said unto
            him, <quote>I adjure thee, by the head of the Emperor, if thou condemnest me to this thing of
            thine own self, to command them to put me into the cauldron little by little, without
            stripping my apparel from me, so that thou mayest know the patient endurance which I
            have through Christ for the sake of my purity.</quote> And as they were dipping her little by
            little into the cauldron, for a very short space of time, immediately the pitch reached
            her neck it became cold; thus she delivered her soul unto God, and she was crowned with
            a good martyrdom. And a great congregation of holy men and women were made perfect
            (i.e., they suffered martyrdom) at that time in the church of Alexandria, and they
            became worthy of that land which the meek inherit. [Potamiaena was martyred, with her
            mother Marcella, in the reign of Septimius Severus.]</p>
         <p>Here end the triumphs of Isidore, and Dorotheos, and the Virgin Potamiaena</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
