<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Maiden Alexandra</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_5"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_5
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The History of the Maiden Alexandra</head>
         <p>There was a certain maiden of Alexandria whose name was Alexandra, and she left the city
            and shut herself up in a tomb until the end of her life; she used to receive her food
            and whatsoever she needed through a window, and no man and no woman saw her face,
            neither did she see the face of any man, for twelve years. And a few days afterwards she
            yielded up her soul, and she lay down and went to her rest in peace. Now when her
            serving woman went to visit her according to her wont, she knocked at the window, but
            Alexandra gave her no answer, and straightway she knew that she was dead, and she came
            and made known unto us concerning her mistress. And we took off the door of her cell and
            we found her body dried up.</p>
         <p>Now the blessed woman Melha also related unto us the story of Alexandra, saying, <quote>I have
            [never] seen her face to face. And I stood outside the cell, close to the window, and
            entreated her to tell me for what reason she had shut herself up in the grave. And
            Alexandra answered and said unto me, <quote>Inasmuch as the thought of the love of God was
            present in my mind, I prayed before the Lord, and I entreated Him to permit me to offer
            unto Him my virginity in the state in which it had been born with me. Now a certain
            young man regarded me in his thoughts, and looked upon me, and desired me, and sought to
            destroy me. But because I did not want to grieve him, or to say what was evil unto him,
            or to be to him an occasion of sin, I chose rather to shut myself up alive in this grave
            than to cause a man who was made in the form of the image of God to stumble.</quote> And I said
            unto her, <quote>How canst thou bear [to] live here not seeing the face of any man without
            being driven to despair?</quote> Then she answered and said unto me, <quote>I occupy myself with my
            prayers and with the work of my hands, and I have no idle moments. From morn until the
            ninth hour I weave linen, and recite the Psalms and pray; and during the rest of the day
            I commemorate in my heart the holy fathers, and I revolve in my thoughts the histories
            of all the Prophets and Apostles, and Martyrs; and during the remaining hours I work
            with my hands and eat my bread, and by means of these things I am comforted whilst I
            await the end of my life in good hope.</quote></quote> These things we have heard from the blessed
            woman Melania who told the story of the maiden Alexandra. But in this history I must not
            underrate those who have toiled in the faith of Christ, to the glory of the perfect and
            to the admonition of those who hear.</p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n138-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n138-2"></note>
            <note xml:id="n138-3"></note>
            <note xml:id="n138-4"></note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
