<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Abba Macarius and a certain Virgin</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_6"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_6
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The History of Abba <persName>Macarius [the Alexandrian]</persName> and a Certain Virgin</head>
         <p>There was in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> a certain virgin who though meek in appearance was of a haughty
            disposition. Now she was exceedingly rich and had possessions <pb n="140"/>without number, but she
            never relieved the poor, and the strangers, and those who were in misery, and she never
            gave a drachma to the Church, and notwithstanding the frequent rebuke with which the
            Fathers rebuked her, she never allowed any portion of riches to leave her. And this
            woman had kinsfolk, and she adopted her sister’s daughter, to whom she used to promise
            by day and by night [to give her] all that she had, for she had fallen from heavenly
            love. Now, it is a customary thing which belongeth to the deception of Satan that he
            produceth avarice under guise of love of family, for that he hath no genuine care for
            kinsmanship is well known from the fact that he taught murder in order that he might
            make war [between] brethren, and is admitted by the Holy Book. (Compare St. John 8:44.)
            And, if he imagined that he implanteth solicitude for kinsfolk in [the hearts of] men,
            [it must be remembered] that he is not moved to do this on their behalf because of [his]
            love for them, but only that he may minister unto his own will, for manifestly he
            knoweth the sentence of judgement which hath been passed, that the wicked shall not
            inherit the kingdom of God (1 Corinthians 6:9). For if a man be moved by spiritual
            understanding and by divine desire, he will be able to care for his kinsfolk if they be
            in want without bringing himself into contempt; but if he devoteth the whole of himself
            to the care for his kinsfolk, and he bringeth himself into contempt by making himself to
            labour under poverty, he will fall from the divine law. And the divine man <persName>David</persName> singeth
            in the Psalms concerning those who possess themselves of the solicitude of the fear of
            God, and he saith, <quote>Who shall go up into the mountain of the Lord?</quote> (Psalm 24:3.) Now,
            inasmuch as he saith, <quote>Who,</quote> he maketh known concerning the smallness of the number [who
            shall go up]. And [again he saith], <pb n="141"/><quote>Who shall stand in His holy place? He whose hands
            are clean and whose heart is chosen, and who giveth not himself unto poverty</quote> (Psalm
            24:3, 4). For those who devote themselves to poverty are those who think that the soul
            is dissolved with this body.</p>
         <p>Now this virgin, who was so in name only, became a stranger unto the various kinds of
            [spiritual] excellence. And there was a certain priest whose name was <persName>Macarius</persName> (or
            <persName>Isidore</persName>) who wished to cut away as with iron and to lighten the weight of the
            possessions of those who loved money, and he had the care of, and was the governor (or
            secretary) of a house for the poor who were sick and infirm in their bodies. And this
            man thought out the following plan whereby he might entrap the virgin. From his youth up
            he had been a skilful workman in the cutting of gems, and he went to her and said,
            <quote>Certain very precious emeralds and gems have fallen into my hands, and whether they
            have been stolen or not I do not know; their value cannot be ascertained, because they
            are above price, but the man who hath them will sell them for five hundred dînârs. If
            thou wishest to take them thou wilt be able to recover the price of five hundred dînârs
            from [the sale of] one of the gems, and the rest thou wilt be able to employ in the
            adornment of thy sister’s daughter.</quote> Now when the virgin heard this she was perturbed,
            and she fell down at his feet making entreaty unto him, and saying, <quote>I beseech you to
            let no other person take them.</quote> <persName>Macarius</persName> saith unto her, <quote>Come to my house and see
            them,</quote> but she would not consent to this; and she poured out for him five hundred
            dînârs, and said unto him, <quote>According to what thou dost require even so take, but I do
            not wish to see the man who is selling them.</quote></p>
         <pb n="142"/>
         <p>And having taken the five hundred dînârs he spent them on food and on things for the use
            of those who were hungry, and on the poor. And when much time had passed, inasmuch as he
            was a famous man in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>—now this blessed man was well known for his love of God,
            and for the merciful disposition which was in him, and he was almost one hundred years
            old, and we also knew him and had tarried in his house with him—the virgin was ashamed
            to call the matter [of the five hundred dînârs] to his mind. But finally she found him
            in the church and said unto him, <quote>I beseech thee [to tell me] how thou hast disposed of
            the gems for which we gave thee the five hundred dînârs.</quote> And he answered and said unto
            her, <quote>When thou gavest me the money I gave it for the price of the gems; if thou wishest
            come and see them in my house, for there are they deposited. Come and see them, if it
            pleaseth thee [so to do], and if thou wilt not then take thy money.</quote> So she went with
            him joyfully. Now the place to which [she went] was a house of the poor; in the upper
            parts thereof were lying women whose bodies were destroyed, and in the lower parts were
            men. And when they had come there <persName>Macarius</persName> brought her in through the door, and said
            unto her, <quote>Which wouldst thou see first, the emeralds or the gems?</quote> She saith unto him,
            <quote>Whichever thou pleasest.</quote> Then he took her up to the upper parts of the house and
            showed her the women whose faces and bodies were diseased and deformed, and said unto
            her, <quote>These are the gems</quote>; and he brought her down to the lower parts, and showed her
            the men, and said unto her, <quote>These are the emeralds. If these please thee [good and
            well]; but if not take thy money.</quote> Then was the virgin ashamed, and she went forth and
            departed, and by reason of her grief she fell into a sickness, because <pb n="143"/>it was through
            God and of her own will that she had in this wise performed the matter. Finally,
            however, she came to herself, and was exceedingly grateful to the priest, and as for the
            maiden for whose wedding feast she was laying up her riches, she died.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
