<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Concerning the Monks who lived in Nitria</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_7"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_7
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Concerning the Monks Who Lived in Nitria</head>
         <p>Now having held converse with many of the saints, and having gone round about among the
            monasteries which were nigh unto Alexandria for three years, and having met about two
            thousand of the great and strenuous men who lived there, and who were adorned with the
            excellence of spiritual lives, I departed from there and came to Mount Nitria. Now
            between this mountain and Alexandria there lieth a certain lake which is called
            <quote>Mareotis,</quote> which embraceth a space of seventy miles. And having seated myself in a boat
            I crossed this lake in a day and a half, and I came unto the mountain to the south,
            whereunto is joined the desert which reacheth unto Cush (Ethiopia). In this mountain of
            the Mazaki and of the Mauritanians there live excellent men who are adorned with divers
            kinds of ascetic virtues; and every monk leadeth the ascetic life as he wisheth and as
            he is able, either by himself or in a community. Now in this mountain there are seven
            bakers who make bread and who minister unto them, and unto the chosen men of the inner
            desert, of whom there are six hundred, and also unto the people of that mountain. And
            when I had dwelt in this mountain for a year, and had profited by the fathers, the pious
            and blessed men, I mean Rabbâ Barsîs [i.e., Arsisius], and Bûsîrîs, and Petâ-Bast, and
            Agîôs, and Khrônîs, and Serapion, the elder, and had learned from them also concerning
            the ancient and first spiritual fathers [who had lived there], I entered into the inner
            desert wherein is Mount Nitria.</p>
         <p>In this mountain is a great church, and in the courtyard thereof are three palm trees,
            in each of which hangeth a whip. One of these is for the correcting of the monks who
            transgress through folly; the second is for the punishing of the thieves if they be
            found falling on the place; and the third is for the chastising of the strangers who
            flock there and who transgress in any matter whatsoever. And it is the same with anyone
            who shall commit any offence, they bring him to the palm tree and punish him, and he
            receiveth upon his back the number of stripes which they have appointed unto him.
            Adjoining the church is a house in which the strangers who arrive there may lodge, and
            if any man wisheth to work [there] one year, or two, or until he departeth of his own
            accord [he may do so]; and every week of days they permit him to rest, so that he may do
            nothing, but they give him work during the remaining days of the week, either among the
            bakers, or in the refectory. And if there was among these anyone who was sufficiently
            educated they used to give him a book to read, but they did not allow him to hold
            converse with any man until the sixth hour. There were also in this mountain physicians
            for the use of the sick, and those who sold cakes; and they also used wine which was
            sold there. All these people worked at the weaving of flax with their hands, and there
            was no needy man there. Now when the evening cometh thou must rise up to hear the
            praises, and the Psalms, and the prayers which are sent up to Christ by the people from
            the monasteries which are there, and a man might imagine, his mind being exalted, that
            he was in the Paradise of Eden.</p>
         <p>Now the monks only came to church on the Sabbath and on the First Day of the week.
            Belonging to this church there were eight priests and governors, but as long as the
            first one lived none of the others ministered in the church; he neither judged nor spake
            with any man, and they lived with him a life of silent contemplation. Now this great man
            Arsisius and many of the ancient holy men whom we saw were followers of the rule of the
            blessed man Anthony, and Arsisius himself told me that the holy man Ammôn, who was from
            Nitria, and whom he knew, and whose soul was taken up and carried by the angels into
            heaven, even saw Anthony. And Arsisius also spake to me concerning the blessed man
            Pachomius, who came from Tabenna of Hekhâm, and who possessed the gift of prophecy and
            who became the governor and head of three thousand men; of this man I will relate the
            virtues at the end [of this book].</p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n143-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n143-2"></note>
            <note xml:id="n144-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n144-2"></note>
            <note xml:id="n144-3"></note>
            <note xml:id="n144-4"></note>
            <note xml:id="n145-1"></note>
            <note xml:id="n145-2"></note>
            <note xml:id="n145-3"></note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
