<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Blessed Man Pambo</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_10"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_10
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The History of the Blessed Man <persName>Panbô</persName> [Died A.D. 393]</head>
         <p>In this mountain there also lived the blessed man <persName>Pambô (or Panbîs)</persName>, who was the teacher
            and master of the Bishops <persName>Dioscorus</persName>, <persName>Amônis (Ammonius)</persName>, <persName>Eusebius</persName>, <persName>[Euthemîs] (Eutymius)</persName>, and
            <persName>Origen</persName> the nephew of <persName>Dracontius</persName>, a marvellous man. Now this man <persName>Panbîs</persName> possessed [the
            power to utter] words <pb n="150"/>of prophecy, and splendid triumphs, yet with all these he despised
            gold and silver, even as the Word demandeth. Now the following things [concerning him]
            were related unto me by the blessed woman <persName>Melhâ (i.e., Melania)</persName>:</p>
         <p>When I first came from <placeName>Rome</placeName> to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> I heard concerning the life and deeds of
            <persName>Pambô</persName>, inasmuch as the blessed man Isidore, who also brought me unto him in the desert,
            told me about him. And I brought unto him a basket which was filled with stamped silver
            (i.e., coined money) three hundred pounds [in weight], and I begged him to accept some
            of my possessions for his needs. He was sitting and plaiting the leaves of palm trees,
            and as he was doing this he merely blessed me, and said, <quote>God give thee thy reward!</quote>
            Then he said unto his steward, whose name was <persName>Origen</persName>, <quote>Take and distribute [this] among
            all the brethren who are in the <quote>Island</quote> and in <placeName>Libya</placeName></quote>; for these monasteries are
            exceedingly poor, and he commanded the steward not to give unto any man who dwelt in
            <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, for those who dwell therein have [abundant] means of subsistence. Now I stood
            there and I expected to be treated with honour or to be praised for the greatness of the
            gift, but when I heard nothing from him, I said unto him, <quote>Master, knowest thou how much
            money it is, and that there are three hundred pounds [in the basket]?</quote> Then <persName>Pambô</persName>,
            without lifting up his gaze, said unto me, <quote>My daughter, He unto whom thou hast offered
            thy money hath no need [to know] the weight. For He who weighed the mountains in a
            balance knoweth how much is the weight of thy silver. If thou hadst given the money unto
            me thou wouldst have done well to have informed me concerning the weight thereof; but
            since thou hast given it to God, Who did not despise the two mites of the widow, [what
            need hast thou to tell Him?] Hold thy peace.</quote></p>
         <p>Now our Lord so directed that in the day on which I entered the mountain this blessed
            man died without <pb n="151"/>having been ill, for he died whilst he was sewing together palm leaves
            for mats, without fever and without sickness. And he was seventy years old. Now he was
            sewing together palm leaves for a mat, and coming to the end of it he sent and called
            me. And when he had finished sewing it, he said unto me, <quote>Take this mat from my hands,
            so that thou mayest keep me in remembrance, for I have nothing else whatever to leave
            thee</quote>; and having given it unto me he straightway died. And I wrapped his body in linen
            swathings, and buried him, and then I departed from the desert; and I shall treasure the
            mat as a sacred relic until the day of my death.</p>
         <p>Now at the time of the death of this holy man <persName>Pambô</persName> there were standing before him
            certain famous men, <persName>Origen</persName> the priest and steward, and <persName>Ammonius</persName>, together with the
            remainder of the brethren, and they told [me] that at the time of his death, he said,
            <quote>From the day wherein I came into this desert and built this cell in which I have lived
            [until this day] I know not that I have [ever] eaten the bread of idleness (or bread)
            which did not come from the labour of mine own hands; and my soul repenteth not that I
            have ever spoken an empty word in my life; thus I go to God like one who hath, as yet,
            not made a beginning in the fear of God.</quote> And <persName>Origen</persName> and <persName>Ammonius</persName>, the servants of
            <persName>Christ</persName>, in telling us the story of his life, bore witness concerning him that he was
            never asked a question by any man about a saying from the Book, or about the rules and
            labours of the ascetic life which he did not either answer immediately, or say, <quote>I have
            not as yet understood the matter.</quote> Now there were times when he spake these words [only]
            after three months’ consideration of a matter; and he used to make answer with such
            understanding that every man received <pb n="152"/>the things which were said by him with as great
            reverence as if they had [been said] by God. Now this excellence was also attributed to
            <persName>Anthony</persName> the Great and to the rest of the holy men. Among other things which are said
            concerning the holy man <persName>Pambô</persName> is the following. The blessed man <persName>Pîôr</persName> once went to
            <persName>Pambô</persName>’s cell and took with him some bread, and <persName>Pambô</persName> made a complaint, saying unto him,
            <quote>Why hast thou done this?</quote> Then Abbâ <persName>Pîôr</persName> made answer, saying, <quote>Let [this thing] be not
            grievous unto thee</quote>; but <persName>Pambô</persName> was silent and sent him away. And after some time Rabbâ
            <persName>Pambô</persName> went to the cell of Abbâ <persName>Pîôr</persName>, and he took with him bread which had been dipped in
            water; and being asked, <quote>Why hast thou done this?</quote> the blessed man <persName>Pambô</persName> said unto him,
            <quote>Let it not be grievous unto thee that I have also dipped the bread in water.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
