<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Blessed Man Benjamin</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_12"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_12
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The History of the Blessed <persName>Benjamin</persName></head>
         <p>And there was also in the mountain of <placeName>Nitria</placeName> a marvellous man whose name was <persName>Benjamin</persName>,
            who attained to a high state of perfection in the ascetic life, for he had fasted and
            toiled for eighty years. Now he was held to be worthy of the gift of the craft of the
            physician, and from every wound (or stripe) upon which he laid his hand, and which
            <persName>Christ</persName> blessed or gave [him the power to heal], straightway every pain departed. And
            this man, who was worthy of such a gift, collected water in his body for eight months
            before his death, and he was so much swollen that he might well have been called a
            second <persName>Job</persName>. And <persName>Dioscurus</persName> took us, that is to say, the blessed <persName>Origen</persName> and myself, and
            said unto us, <quote>Come ye and see a new <persName>Job</persName>, who whilst [suffering from] such a severe
            disease of the body as this healeth others.</quote> And <persName>Benjamin</persName> gave thanks concerning his
            affliction beyond measure, and glorified God continually, and his soul rejoiced and was
            glad in the hope which it laid up for the saints. Now when we had gone and seen the
            swelling of his body we found that it had become so large that a man could not with all
            his hand encircle one of his fingers; and being unable to look upon such a terrible
            affliction through disease we turned away our eyes. Then the blessed man <persName>Benjamin</persName> said
            unto us, <quote>My sons, pray that the inner man may not collect water. Even when this my body
            was in health it in no wise helped me, and now that it is sick it in no wise hindereth
            me.</quote> Now during the [last] eight months of his illness they made a broad chair for him,
            and he used to sit therein always, because he was not able to lie down upon a bed by
            reason of the necessity of his belly and of the other <pb n="156"/>[members of his] body. And whilst
            he himself lived in such suffering through all his affliction he was healing others, and
            it is for this reason that I am compelled to narrate to you concerning the affliction of
            this righteous man, so that when such an affliction as this happeneth unto the righteous
            we may not hold the matter to be hard. Now when this blessed man died, the whole of the
            framework of the doorway had to be removed to enable them to bring out his body from his
            cell, for his body was very large indeed.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
