<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Apollonius the Merchant</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_13"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_13
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The History of <persName>Apollonius</persName></head>
         <p>And again another man, whose name was <persName>Apollonius</persName>, used to dwell in this Mount <placeName>Nitria</placeName>;
            and he was a merchant who had come there to learn to lead the life and conversation of
            an anchorite. Now this man found no handicraft at the exercise of which he could employ
            himself, and he could neither fast nor keep vigil like the other ascetics to any great
            extent. During the twenty years which he lived in this mountain it was his rule of life
            and triumph that by his own labour and toil he used to buy from <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> everything
            which was required by the brethren, and the things which were needed for the healing of
            the sick, and carry them to the sick. And it was a marvellous thing to see him going
            about among the monasteries and cells of the brethren each day, from the earliest dawn,
            when he set out, until the ninth hour, and he used to stand by the door and say, <quote>Is
            there, peradventure, anyone sick here?</quote> And he carried about pomegranates, and dried
            cakes, and <pb n="157"/>raisins, and eggs, and the things which are necessary for the sick. Now he
            found this rule of life easy to acquire, and to continue until his old age, and he was
            able to attend to the affairs of the five thousand brethren who were dwelling in the
            mountain. And when he died he left whatever he had unto another man like unto himself,
            and he begged him to carry out this ministration, because the [place where the monks
            lived] was a desert and was destitute of the things of the world.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
