<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Histories of Paesius and Isaiah</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_14"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_14
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The Histories of the Natural Brethren Paesius and Isaiah</head>
         <p>And there were also there two brethren, whose names were Paesius and Isaiah, who were
            the sons of a certain merchant who traded in Spain; and when their father died they
            divided his inheritance between them, and there came to each of them money which
            amounted to five thousand dînârs, and furniture, and raiment, and slaves, and property
            of all kinds. And these blessed men took counsel together and meditated together and
            said unto each other, <quote>By what manner of trafficking shall we live in this world? If we
            continue to exercise the trade of our father, we shall only double our labour and toil
            for [the benefit of] others; and perhaps [our wealth] will fall into the hands of
            thieves by land or of pirates by sea.</quote> And whilst they were being troubled by such
            thoughts as these they answered and said unto each other, <quote>Let us come to the way of
            truth, and let us acquire the life and conversation of the Christians, whereby we shall
            both keep the benefit of what our father hath left us, and get possession of our soul.</quote>
            And this proposition concerning the labour of the dwellers in the monasteries was
            pleasing unto them, and each of them found in his discipleship the power to judge as to
            what work he should embrace. And having divided their father’s inheritance they both
            possessed the eager care to please God by the various kinds of labours of life of the
            mourner. One of them divided everything which had come to him and gave it to the
            churches and monastic habitations, and distributed it among the poor and needy; and he
            learned a handicraft at which he could work and earn [his] daily bread, and he was
            constant in prayer and fasting. The other brother did not distribute [his possessions],
            but he built himself a monastery and gathered together unto him a few brethren and
            providing therefor became a care unto him. All strangers and poor folk, and all the aged
            men and sick folk who thronged unto him he used to receive and relieve their wants. And
            every first day of the week, and every Sabbath, he used to prepare three tables and
            relieve the wants of every one who happened to be present there; and thus he spent all
            his possessions.</p>
         <p>Now, when the two brothers died abundant blessing was ascribed unto them by the whole
            brotherhood, but the one brother pleased some of them [most], and the other the others;
            and although the brethren praised both brothers, a dispute arose among them concerning
            the superior merit of one or the other of the two brothers. Then the brethren went to
            the blessed Pambô and related the matter unto him, and wished to learn which rule of
            life and labour was the greater and more excellent. And Pambô said unto them, <quote>They are
            both perfect. One man made manifest the work of Abraham by his hospitality, and the
            other the self-denial of Elijah.</quote> And again the brethren said unto him, <quote>How is it
            possible for the two to be equal in merit? We praise and magnify him who embraced
            poverty, for we find that he did the work of the Gospel in selling everything that he
            had and giving it to the poor, and that every day, and at every season, both by day and
            by night, he took up his cross and followed after his Lord by his fasting and his
            prayers.</quote> And again the other brethren contended with them, saying, <quote>The other brother
            showed such supreme compassion on those who were strangers and on those who were
            afflicted that he would even sit in the highways and gather together the passers-by who
            were in trouble; and not only did he relieve his own soul, but he also brought a
            lightening unto many souls that were heavy laden, and he would make ready the dead for
            the grave and bury [them].</quote> And the blessed Pambô said unto them, <quote>Again I say unto you
            that both are equal [in merit], and I will tell you how each of them became so. Unless
            the one had fasted he would not have been worthy of the goodness and compassion of the
            other, and again, the other in relieving the wants of strangers also lightened his own
            load, for although a man may think that he hath trouble in receiving [them] yet he also
            gaineth rest of body. But tarry ye here a few days so that I may learn [the answer] from
            God, and come ye [back] to me and I will declare [it] unto you. And after a few days
            they came unto him, and they asked him to tell them what had been revealed unto him; and
            he answered and said unto them, “I have seen them both standing in the Paradise of Eden,
            as it were in the presence of God.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
