<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Blessed Nathaniel</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_16"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_16
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The History of the Blessed Nathaniel [Died About 376 A.D.]</head>
         <p>And there was also another man among the aged ones whose name was Nathaniel, and him I
            never met in his life, for he died fifteen years before I entered into this mountain;
            but I have met those who dwelt with him for a long time. And having made enquiries of
            these I learned concerning the triumphs of the man, and they also shewed me his cell
            wherein at that time no man was living, because it was nigh unto the world; but Abbâ
            Nathaniel built it long ago when the monks were few in number.</p>
         <p>Now they used to relate concerning this man that his patient endurance in his cell was
            such that he never moved from his place to go outside the door of his habitation for the
            disposition of his will. At the beginning he was laughed at by the Evil One, who mocketh
            at and leadeth astray every man, and he made Nathaniel to feel weariness in his first
            cell, and he went and built himself another cell in the neighbourhood of the city. Now
            after he had built the other cell and had dwelt therein, some three or four months later
            the devil, who had waged war against him from the beginning, came by night holding in
            his hand a sling like a hunter, and he was dressed in the garb of the Romans, and he was
            slinging [stones] with the sling which he was holding. Then the blessed man Nathaniel
            answered and said unto him, <quote>Who art thou who doest these things in the place wherein I
            dwell?</quote> The devil said unto him, <quote>I am he who made thee to flee from thy first cell, and
            I have come that I may make thee to flee from this place.</quote> Now when he knew that the
            devil was laughing at him because he had departed from his first [cell], straightway he
            turned and went back thereto, and he lived in his first cell for the space of thirty and
            seven years in such strict abnegation that he never passed outside the door, and
            meanwhile he was warring with the devil. And the wicked devil made him to experience so
            many afflictions and troubles in order to drive him out of his cell that it would be
            impossible for [any] man to recount them. But the Evil One watched [and obtained his
            opportunity] in the arrival of the Bishops who came to Nathaniel (now they were all holy
            men), and whether the ordering of the matter was due to the will of God, or to the
            temptation of the Evil One, we know not, but he made Nathaniel to fall away somewhat
            from his intention. For when the Bishops had prayed and had gone forth, Nathaniel did
            not escort them the distance of one step, and the servants who were with them said [to
            him], <quote>Dost thou possess the faculty of pride that thou wilt not accompany the Bishops?</quote>
            Then Nathaniel said unto them, <quote>I died once and for all to my lords the Bishops, and to
            the whole world, and I have a secret matter concerning which it is God only Who knoweth
            my heart, and why I did not go forth and escort them.</quote></p>
         <p>Then that devil, who was still making a mock of this self-abnegation, nine months before
            Nathaniel’s death took upon himself the form of a young man who was about twenty years
            old, and he was following after an ass which was carrying bread in the bed of the river.
            Now when it was far into the evening the young man passed close to the cell, and
            pretended that the ass had fallen down under its burden, and he began to cry out, and
            said, <quote>Abbâ Nathaniel, help me, and come and render me assistance.</quote> And Nathaniel heard
            the voice of the young man who he thought was crying out, and he opened the door, and as
            he was standing inside, he spake with him, and said unto him, <quote>Who art thou? And what
            dost thou want me to do for thee?</quote> And the young man said unto him, <quote>I am such and such
            a young man, and I am carrying bread to such and such a brother because he wisheth to
            make a love feast, and the day which dawneth to-morrow will be the Sabbath, and [bread
            for] the Offering will be necessary. I beg of thee, therefore, not to tarry in assisting
            me, lest the hyenas come and devour both me and the ass.</quote> Now there were many hyenas in
            that place.</p>
         <p>Then the blessed Nathaniel stood still in great astonishment, and he was much troubled
            in his mind by the mercy which had revealed itself to him, and he meditated within
            himself, saying, <quote>It is either through the command of God that I must fall, or through
            my will [having reached] its limit.</quote> Finally he meditated within himself and said, <quote>It
            is better for him who hath guarded for all these years the limit of his will, and hath
            not passed over his door, to remain in the same condition which will put the Evil One to
            shame than to go out</quote>; and he prayed to God. Then he made answer unto him whom he
            believed to be a young man crying out, and said unto him, “Young man, hear me! I believe
            that the God Whom I serve will send thee help if it be needed by thee, and that neither
            the hyenas nor anything else will harm thee; but if thou art a temptation may God
            discover thy craftiness!" And he shut the door and held his peace. And that devil was
            put to shame, and by reason of his wickedness he took the form of a whirlwind and the
            forms of wild asses which dance about and skip and break wind. This is the [story of
            the] triumph of the blessed Nathaniel, and this is the [story of] his labour and his
            ending.</p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n164-1"/>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
