<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The Histories of Macarius the Egyptian, and of Macarius
               the Alexandrian</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_17"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_17
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The History of the Two Exalted and Excellent Men, Macarius the Egyptian, the Disciple
            of Mar Abba Anthony, and Macarius the Alexandrian</head>
         <p>Concerning the holy and immortal fathers, that is to say Macarius the Egyptian, and
            Macarius the Alexandrian, who were men to be feared and who were invincible athletes,
            and concerning the strife of their life and deeds, and conversation, it is exceedingly
            right and good that we should tell the story. Perhaps it will not be accepted by the
            unbelievers, and therefore I find it difficult to relate their history, and to set it
            down completely in writing, lest by so doing I should be accounted a liar; and that the
            Lord destroyeth those who speak falsehood the Holy Spirit maketh clearly manifest. Now,
            as I myself do not put to the lie the help of Christ, do not thou, O Lausus, thou
            believer in men, become an unbeliever in the triumphs of the holy fathers which are
            spoken of, but adorn thyself more and more with the deeds and conversation of these
            glorious men who were in very truth, even as they are called, blessed men.</p>
         <p>The athlete of Christ, the first Macarius, was by race an Egyptian, and the second
            Macarius, although he was second to him in the matter of age, was nevertheless first in
            the opinion of the monks (or solitaries); and this man, whose name also was Macarius,
            which is interpreted <quote>blessed,</quote> was from the city of Alexandria, and he was [one] of
            those who sold dried fruit and wine.</p>
         <p>In[1] another manuscript I have found a different version [of the history of the two
            Macarii which I have used] in the preparation of [this] history, and I set this down
            here also; now it reads as follows:</p>
         <p>And as concerning the two blessed men whose names were the same, inasmuch as their rule
            of life and conversation were of an exceedingly exalted character, perhaps many will not
            believe [what I write]. I, however, am afraid lest I may understate and belittle their
            triumphs in any way whatsoever, and lie concerning them, for it is written, <quote>Thou wilt
            destroy those who speak falsehood</quote> (Psalm 12:3). The Holy Spirit hath passed this
            sentence upon me, therefore, O beloved and faithful men, believe ye me. Now one of these
            two blessed men was an Egyptian by race, and the other was an Alexandrian who sold dried
            fruits. First of all I will tell the story of the ascetic excellences of Macarius the
            Egyptian, the whole of whose years were ninety; he was thirty years old when he went up
            to the desert, and [he] lived therein for sixty years. And he was given the gift of
            [performing] mighty deeds in such a remarkable manner that he was called by the fathers
            <quote>the aged youth,</quote> because straightway and quickly he ascended to the highest grade of
            ascetic excellence and gifts, and to the power of interpreting the Scriptures, and to
            spiritual foresight. And the gift of possessing power over devils was also given to him,
            and he was also esteemed worthy of the priesthood. With this blessed man there lived in
            the further (or inner) desert, which is called <quote>Scete,</quote> two disciples; one of these was
            his servant, for many folk were wont to come unto him to be healed, and the other
            remained always in a cell which was nigh unto Macarius. And when much time had passed
            by, Macarius looked and said unto him that ministered unto him (now his name was John,
            and he afterwards became the elder in the place of the blessed man), he answered, I say,
            and said unto him, <quote>Hear me, O John, and receive the rebuke with which I rebuke thee.
            For thou art suffering temptation, and behold the spirit of the love of money (i.e.,
            avarice) tempteth thee, for even so have I seen. And I know that if thou wilt listen
            unto me thy end in this place shall be praised, and no harm shall draw nigh unto thy
            habitation. But if thou wilt not hearken unto me, because of the love of money which
            moveth thee, the leprosy of Gehazi (2 Kings 5:27) shall come upon thee at the end.</quote> And
            it came to pass some fifteen or twenty years after the death of the blessed man, John
            forgot his commandment, and because he used to steal from the poor, his body became so
            covered with leprosy that there was not in the whole of it one sound spot large enough
            for a man to lay his finger upon. Thus the prophecy of the blessed Macarius concerning
            John actually came to pass.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
