<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Blessed Man Pachomius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_20"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_20
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The History of the Blessed Man <persName>Pachomius</persName></head>
         <p>And there was also another man whose name was <persName>Pachomius</persName>, who was seventy years old and
            who dwelt in that mountain which is called Scete; unto him I once went when lustful
            thoughts concerning women were afflicting me, and when my mind was dark and obscured by
            the thoughts of lust, and by the visions and heaviness of the nights, and when I was
            well nigh departing from the desert, for lust laid upon me many things [hard to bear].
            Now I did not reveal unto my neighbours and unto the brethren who were living with me my
            tribulations, and not even unto my master Evagrius; but I went forth and I began to
            wander about in the desert, and I saw one of the old men who had grown old in the
            place—now they were all perfect fathers—and after this I saw this blessed old man
            <persName>Pachomius</persName>, and I found that he was superior to them all in his life, and deeds, and in
            his understanding. And I took courage to reveal unto him the strife of my mind, and he
            spake unto me thus: <quote>Do not imagine that this is a strange matter in any way. This thing
            hath not happened unto thee through <pb n="190"/>thine own negligence, and the place itself in which
            thou livest is a witness for thee, for it is restricted in the matter of things of every
            kind, and there is no woman therein; this lust hath fallen upon thee through [thy]
            strenuousness. For this warfare of lust and also of fornication is of a threefold
            [character]; sometimes it setteth our body against us when it is healthy and well fed,
            and at others lust itself, with the natural passion which is implanted in us [attacketh
            us], and at others the Evil One himself because of his envy. And I have watched many
            times, and I have found that it is even as I have said unto thee.</quote> And he said unto me,
            <quote>I, the old man whom thou seest, have lived in this cell for forty years, and I have
            taken the utmost care for my life and for the redemption of my soul, and even in this
            period of great old age, wherein thou seest that I am, I am greatly tormented by
            lust.</quote></p>
         <p>And he assured me with an oath, saying, <quote>When I was fifty years old lust placed itself
            [upon] me for twelve years, never going away from me either by day or by night, and I
            thought in my mind that God had forsaken me, and therefore (for to such an extent had
            lust gained dominion over me) I determined in my heart that I would either suffer death
            through dumb beasts, or that I should become a laughing-stock or a man condemned through
            the lust of the body. And I went forth and wandered round about in the desert, and I
            found a den of hyenas, and I laid myself down naked at the entrance thereof that they
            might come out and devour me. And when it was evening—as it is written, <quote>He hath made
            the darkness, and it becometh night, wherein all the beasts of the forest do move (Psalm
            104:20), and the lions roar to <pb n="191"/>break [their prey]</quote>—the hyenas, both male and female,
            came out, and they all sniffed at (or smelt) me, and licked my body from my head to my
            feet, and while I was thinking that they would eat me they went away from me; and there
            I remained the whole of that night, and they ate me not. And again I thought that God
            had had compassion upon me, and straightway I returned and came to my cell. And that
            devil of lust, having forborne with me a little, returned once again, and moreover he
            attacked me more fiercely than before, and he did so with such vigour that by reason of
            my affliction I well nigh cursed myself. Now, this devil of lust used to take the form
            of an Ethiopian damsel whom I saw in my early manhood gathering canes in the summer, and
            he came in her form and sat upon my knees, and he used to set me on fire with lust to
            such an extent that I imagined I was having intercourse with her, and when through the
            burning of my heart and the madness thereof, I gave her the cheek, straightway she would
            lift herself up from me and take to flight. And from the time when I touched her my hand
            was so polluted that for the space of two hours [afterwards] whensoever I brought my
            hand near me I was unable [to free it] from her foulness. But again I went forth because
            of my affliction, and I began to wander about in the desert, and I found a small asp,
            and I took it and placed its head upon the members of my body, and I squeezed the head
            of the asp so that it might bite me and I might die, and so find relief, but it bit me
            not. And after this I heard a voice which came to my ears and said unto me, <quote>Depart,
            <persName>Pachomius</persName>, and be strong; I have allowed thee to be overcome in order that thou mightest
            <pb n="192"/>not imagine that thou wast a mighty man and a man of perfection, and that thou hadst
            triumphed through thine own life and deeds, but that thou mightest know thine infirmity,
            and the feebleness of thy nature, and that thou mightest not rely upon thine asceticism
            but mightest confess the help of God and cry out to Him always.</quote> And having heard these
            words I returned to my cell, and I dwelt therein with great boldness of heart, and I
            never again had anxious care concerning this warfare of lust, but I continued in peace
            for the rest of my days after this warfare. Now, the devil of lust, seeing that I no
            longer meditated about the matter, never again approached me.</quote> With these words about
            the striving against Satan the holy man <persName>Pachomius</persName> confirmed me, and he made me strong to
            play the man more and more, and to be mighty in the warfare against the devil of
            fornication, and he dismissed me and said unto me, <quote>Be strong and mighty in our
            Lord.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
