<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Blessed Man Valens, the
               Palestinian</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_22"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_22
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of <persName>Valens the Palestinian</persName></head>
         <p>And there was a certain man whose name was <persName>Valens</persName>, who was by race a Palestinian and by
            education a Corinthian; now the blessed <persName>Paul</persName> ascribed to the <persName>Corinthians</persName> (1 Corinthians
            4) as a special attribute the passion of pride and inflatedness. And having come to the
            desert and dwelt with us for many years, at length he arrived at such a degree of
            vaunting that he was laughed at by the devils; and from this state he went astray,
            little by little, until he was derided by them, and they became able to make him think
            that angels were appearing unto him. Now therefore one day, according to what they
            relate concerning him, as he was working in the dark at the labour of his hands, the
            needle wherewith he was sewing together the palm leaves fell down [on the ground], and
            although he searched for it he could not find it; and a devil lit a fire for him until
            he found it, and because of this thing he became the more proud. And at length he became
            so proud, and allowed such arrogant thoughts to rise up in his mind that he despised and
            thought scorn of the Holy Mysteries of the Body and Blood <pb n="196"/>of <persName>Christ</persName>. And moreover, it
            came to pass that certain men of discernment came and brought unto the church some dried
            fruits as a [means of obtaining a] blessing, and the blessed <persName>Macarius</persName>, our elder,
            received [them] and sent [them] to the brethren, that is, some to every man in his cell,
            and among the brethren he also sent [some] to <persName>Valens</persName>. And <persName>Valens</persName> took the man who had
            been sent to bring the fruit to him, and heaped insults upon him and smote him, saying,
            <quote>Go and say unto <persName>Macarius</persName>: <quote>I am neither inferior unto thee nor am I more of a servant
            than art thou, that thou shouldst send me a blessing.</quote> </quote></p>
         <p>Now <persName>Macarius</persName> knew that he had been laid hold upon by error, and he rose up and went unto
            him at the turn of the day that he might persuade him, and he said unto him, <quote><persName>Valens</persName>,
            <persName>Valens</persName>, thou hast made thyself a laughing-stock, and hast fallen into error; receive
            then correction</quote>; but seeing that he was unwilling to hearken unto his admonition and
            reproof he left him and departed. And having become more confirmed in his pride, and
            having reached the summit thereof, that devil, who had completely led him astray, went
            and made unto himself a form wherein he resembled our Redeemer; and he came unto him by
            night, together with phantoms of angels in great numbers who marched along bearing lamps
            and wax candles, and they advanced with chariots and carriages of fire, as if that devil
            were <persName>Christ</persName> Himself. Then one of the angels came forward unto him, and said unto him,
            <quote><persName>Christ</persName> loveth greatly thy life and deeds, and thy boldness of speech, and He hath come
            to see thee. Get thee forth from thy cell, and do nothing whatsoever except such things
            as I shall tell thee. When thou seest Him afar off <pb n="197"/>fall down and worship Him, and go
            back to thy cell.</quote> Now therefore when <persName>Valens</persName> had gone forth and seen the ranks [of
            phantoms] bearing lamps of fire, and Anti<persName>christ</persName> himself sitting upon a chariot of
            fire—now he was distant from him about a mile—he fell down and worshipped him. And
            <persName>Valens</persName> was so much injured in his mind that at the turn of the day he was sufficiently
            mad to come into the church and to say before all the brotherhood who were assembled
            therein, <quote>I have no need to become a partaker in the offering, for this day I have seen
            <persName>Christ</persName> Himself.</quote> Then the fathers tied him up and put iron fetters upon him for about
            the space of one year, and in this way they made him whole; and he was praying
            continually, and they humbled him and brought him down from the exalted conception which
            he held concerning himself by means of sundry and divers works of a lovely and humble
            character, and thus they rooted out from him pride, even as it is written, <quote>Each
            opposing sickness must be healed by medicines which are contrary and opposite
            thereto.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
