<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Blessed Man Hero, the
               Alexandrian</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_23"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_23
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of <persName>Hero the Alexandrian</persName> [Bishop of <placeName>Diospolis</placeName> about A.D. 365]</head>
         <p>And there was also my neighbour, a man whose name was <persName>Ahrôn (Hero)</persName>, who was by race an
            Alexandrian; now his early manhood was exceedingly glorious, and he was enlightened in
            his mind, and his intellect was keen, and the habits of his life were pure. This man, I
            say, after [performing] many labours was also seized by the passion of boasting and
            pridefulness, <pb n="198"/>and he wavered and fell; and he evolved in his mind and imagined great
            things against the fathers, and he reviled also the blessed <persName>Evagrius</persName>, saying, <quote>Those who
            allow themselves to be persuaded [into accepting] thy doctrine certainly go astray and
            err, for [men] require no other teacher than <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote> And he put forward and urged in
            witness of his words, with foolish intent, the speech from the Gospel (which our
            Redeemer also spake), <quote>Ye shall call no man master on the earth</quote> (St. Matthew 23:8). And
            his understanding became so greatly blinded that at length on him also iron fetters
            fell, and he was fast bound, because he would neither be persuaded nor would he receive
            or be a partaker of the Holy Mysteries, although he loved the truth greatly. Now, the
            food upon which he lived was too little and the habits of his life were immeasurably
            strict, for, according to what those who were continually with him used to relate, on
            several occasions he only partook of a meal once in three months, the participation in
            the Mysteries only being sufficient for him; but if it happened that he came across some
            wild herbs by chance [he would eat them].</p>
         <p>Now I myself, with the blessed man <persName>Albinus</persName>, received an experience of him when we were
            going to <placeName>Scete</placeName>. <placeName>Scete</placeName> was forty miles distant from us, and we partook of two meals and
            drank water three times [on the way], whilst he tasted nothing at all during his journey
            with us. He travelled on foot, and he was repeating [passages] from the Scriptures by
            heart; during the time that he went with us, he repeated [passages] from the Scriptures
            and sang fifteen Psalms, and he repeated the Beatitudes and the Epistle to the Hebrews,
            and [the book of] <persName>Isaiah the Prophet</persName>, and a portion of <pb n="199"/><persName>Jeremiah</persName>, and after [that] the
            Gospel of [Saint] Luke, and after [that] the Proverbs; and in spite of all this we were
            unable to overtake him as he trudged along. Now therefore this man was at length
            persecuted by lust as by a fire, and he was never again able to dwell in his cell, but
            he went to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and by reason of his pride it happened unto him, through Divine
            Providence, even as it is said, <quote>One good is rooted up by another.</quote> Nevertheless, having
            fallen willingly into a state of indifference, he finally found redemption. Now he was
            present continually at the shows of the theatres and circuses, and he was never absent
            from the public drinking rooms of the taverns; and thus whilst he was leading this life
            of prodigality and drunkenness he fell and was brought to a standstill in the miry ditch
            of the lust of women. At length he went to one of those women who are at the head of the
            grade of harlots, and because of his passion with all boldness he held converse with
            her, and these things having thus been done by him there broke out in the place of his
            nature a carbuncle which grew with great vigour, and his sickness waxed sore upon him
            for a space of six months, and his members rotted away and they had to be cut off. By
            these means he became finally cured, but he remained without members; and afterwards he
            went back again to the integrity of [his] nature, and to divine thoughts. [And he came
            to the desert] and confessed all these things to the fathers, and though he remained not
            a long time [there] he did not flee from leading the ascetic life, nor from weeping
            because of what had happened to him, nor from offering up the repentance which was meet.
            And after a few days he died and departed from this world.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
