<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Blessed Man Ptolemy, the
               Egyptian</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_24"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_24
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of <persName>Ptolemy the Egyptian</persName> who was in <placeName>Scete</placeName></head>
         <p>And there was also another man whose name was <persName>Ptolemy</persName>, and he was by race from <placeName>Egypt</placeName>,
            and he observed a rule of life which no man is able to describe, or rather it is very
            difficult to relate the story of his life. He dwelt away beyond <placeName>Scete</placeName> in that [district]
            which is called <quote>Klimax.</quote> Now the place which is thus called it is impossible for a man
            to dwell in by reason of its ruggedness, and it was distant from the stream of water
            wherefrom the brethren used to draw twelve miles. Now this man <persName>Ptolemy</persName> used to take many
            vessels for water, and carry [them] to a certain spot where much dew fell, and in
            December and January he used to collect it, for in those countries the dewfall is
            abundant. And having gathered together for himself water in sponge[s] from time to time
            they were squeezed out by him, and the water which he had collected from the dew ran
            out, and this he was in the habit of doing during the fifteen years which he dwelt
            there. Now this man, having for much time been deprived of doctrine (or teaching), and
            of the meetings with the holy fathers, and of the intercourse of edifying speech, and
            especially of participation in the Mysteries, went as wholly astray from the straight
            path as if he had said, <quote>The matters of service, that is to say, the Holy Mysteries, are
            nothing at all.</quote> And from this state he senselessly departed and went on until at length
            he went into <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and delivered himself over to prodigal and riotous living, and he
            <pb n="201"/>never more spake a word of excellence unto any man. And his madness came upon <persName>Ptolemy</persName>
            also because of the senseless and exalted opinion which he held of himself, even as it
            is written, <quote>Those who are not under the law of the governors shall fall like
            leaves.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
