<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Virgin in Jerusalem</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_26"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_26
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of a certain Virgin who was in Jerusalem</head>
         <p>And moreover, I saw a certain virgin in Jerusalem who had been clothed in sackcloth for
            three years, and she had secluded herself in a solitary cell, and had never permitted
            herself to enjoy any of the desirable things wherein there is pleasure. Now this woman,
            having been forsaken by the Divine Providence, because of her immeasurable pride and
            arrogance fell into the ditches of fornication, and she opened the window of the
            habitation in which she had secluded herself, and received [therein] the man who
            ministered unto her, and she had intercourse with him. And because she did not continue
            to persevere in faith and in the ascetic life with a perfect will, and with a mind which
            possessed Divine love, but [departed therefrom] for the sake of men, that is to say, for
            the sake of vainglory, doing so, moreover, with an evil intent and with a corrupt and
            lascivious mind—for her own thoughts having been cut off, since they had been robbed of
            the Divine understanding, she came to the condition of casting blame upon others—the
            guardian of chastity did not remain with her.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
