<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Virgin in Caesarea</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_27"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_27
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of <persName>the Virgin who was in <placeName>Caesarea</placeName> of <placeName>Palestine</placeName></persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/></head>
         <p>And again there was a certain virgin who was the daughter of an elder in <placeName>Caesarea</placeName>, and
            having been beguiled and led astray by a man, he who led her astray taught her to bring
            an accusation against a certain reader of the church of the city. And the time having
            arrived when it was known [unto all] that she was with child, and being called upon by
            her father to confess her matter, she made an accusation against that reader. Now her
            father, the elder, because he believed [her] implicitly, made known <pb n="203"/>the matter unto the
            Bishop, and the Bishop was a holy man, and a fearer of God, and one who did not hastily
            pass sentence of death or punishment upon any man, and then only when it was revealed
            unto him by God whether he who was accused before him was indeed guilty [or not]. So the
            Bishop went and shut himself up until the matter was made plain [unto him]; and because
            God informed him that the reader had never been nigh unto the woman he held him to be
            innocent, and condemned the virgin.</p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">See Chapter xxix.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
