<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Virgin who fell and repented</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_28"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_28
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of a certain Woman who fell and repented</head>
         <p>There was a certain virgin who was a nun, and who dwelt with two other nuns, and she had
            led a life of abstinence and voluntary self-denial for nine or ten years. And having
            been beguiled and led astray by a certain singer of Psalms, she tripped, and fell, and
            conceived, and gave birth to a child; now she hated with the fullest hatred him that had
            beguiled her. [And she repented within herself with a perfect repentance,] and she
            followed after repentance with such vigour that she went beyond the bounds of what was
            seemly, and she continued to observe fasts with such self-denial and strictness that she
            well nigh died of hunger. In her prayers she used to make supplication, saying, <quote>O God,
            Who dost support and sustain all creation, and Who desirest not the death and
            destruction of those who err and commit sin, if Thou wishest me to live before Thee,
            shew me a marvellous thing in this matter, and gather in this fruit of sin which I have
            brought forth, lest, because I cannot again attain to chastity, I kill myself through
            reproach and disgrace.</quote> And having made supplication for this thing, she was hearkened
            unto, and he who had been born unto her did not remain very long alive. And from the day
            wherein she fell and onwards she neither saw him that had beguiled her and led her
            captive, nor held converse with him, but she gave herself to frequent fasting and to
            ministering unto the women who were sick and smitten with disease for the whole of a
            period of thirty years; and thus her repentance was accepted by God, and He at length
            revealed unto a certain holy old man concerning her, saying, <quote>Such and such a woman is
            very much more pleasing unto Me by her penitence than by her virginity.</quote> Now I write
            down these things in order that, if any man be observing a correct rule of life of any
            kind whatsoever which is pleasing unto God, he may take heed lest he fall, and that even
            if he be tripped up in a snare and fall he may not come to despair, and remain in his
            fallen condition, but that by leaning upon the staff of the hope of the Divine Mercy,
            and by arraying himself through repentance in the apparel of simplicity and humility he
            may again become strong enough to stand up, for we should not despise those who truly
            repent.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
