<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of another Virgin who fell and
               repented</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_29"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_29
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of another Virgin who fell and repented</head>
         <p>A certain virgin, the daughter of an elder in Caesarea of Palestine, having been
            beguiled and led astray by a man, fell, and he who had beguiled her instructed her to
            make an accusation against a certain reader of the church of the city. And the time
            having arrived when her conception became known, and being called upon to confess her
            matter by her father, she made the accusation against that reader, and the elder, her
            father, thereupon, like one who believed [her] implicitly, made the affair known to the
            Bishop. Then the Bishop laid his hand upon the shrine, and commanded that the reader
            should be called, and his affair having been enquired into, like one who was confident
            in his own integrity, he was unwilling to confess [that he had done the wrong]; for how
            was it possible for him to accuse himself of that which he had not done? And the Bishop
            becoming angry said unto him, <quote>Wilt thou not confess, O wretched and polluted man, thou
            guilty one who art full of uncleanness?</quote> And the reader made answer unto him, saying,
            <quote>Master, I have neither knowledge nor feeling about this matter, for my thoughts and
            mind are clean in respect thereof, and [no thought] concerning this woman hath ever
            entered my mind. But if thou wishest to hear that which hath never taken place [I will
            say that] I myself committed the offence</quote>; and having spoken thus, the Bishop
            straightway removed the reader from his position. Then the reader drew nigh and
            entreated the Bishop, saying, <quote>Master, since I have tripped up and fallen, give the
            command that the woman be given unto me to wife, for I am no longer a cleric, and she is
            not a virgin</quote>; so the Bishop gave the woman to the reader to wife, because he thought
            that he was held by love of her, and that he could not cut the affair concerning her out
            of his thoughts.</p>
         <p>And when the reader had received the woman from the Bishop, he placed her in a religious
            house for women, and he begged the woman who ministered unto the wants of the sisters to
            take great care of her straightway. Now a short time afterwards the day arrived wherein
            she must give birth to her child, but the poor creature was not able to bring it to the
            birth, and although she could hardly bear the cruel and violent pains of her birth-pangs
            which were bringing her to the house of the dead, her child did not come forth. And one,
            two, three days passed by until the seventh [day arrived], and by reason of her great
            and frequent sufferings the woman was nigh to come unto Sheol; and she neither ate, nor
            drank, nor slept, but she was crying out and saying, <quote>Woe unto me, for I am dying, and I
            made an accusation of fatherhood against such and such a reader.</quote> Now the women who were
            standing before her having heard these words made them known to her father, who,
            however, fearing lest he should be blamed severely because he had made an accusation of
            fatherhood against the reader, held his peace concerning the matter for another two
            days; and meanwhile the young woman neither gained relief from her sufferings nor died.
            Now therefore when the nuns could no longer bear the pain of her violent shrieks, they
            ran and told the Bishop, saying, <quote>Such and such a woman hath for some days past been
            crying out and confessing that she made an accusation of fatherhood against the reader.</quote>
            Then the Bishop sent deacons unto him with the message, <quote>Pray thou that the woman who
            made an accusation against thee may have relief</quote>; but the reader answered them never a
            word. Now he had not opened his door since the day on which the accusation had been made
            against him, but he entreated God and made supplication unto him that the matter might
            become known and the truth revealed. Thereupon the father of the woman went to the
            Bishop, and prayer was offered up in the church, but even by these proceedings the woman
            did not obtain relief. Then the Bishop rose up and went to the reader, and knocked at
            the door and the reader opened [it] to him, and he went in to him and said, <quote>Eustathius,
            rise up and unloose that which thou hast fastened.</quote> And at once the reader knelt down
            with the Bishop, and they prayed to God, and straightway the woman gave birth to her
            child. Thus were the supplication of this man and his constant persistence in prayer
            able to clear away oppression and to chastise and rebuke also the woman who made the
            false accusation, for from that day onwards she fulfilled the days of her life with good
            works; and we should learn to be constant in prayer and to recognize the power thereof
            when it is offered unto God with the deep feeling of the whole heart.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
