<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Blessed Thais or Thaisis</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_30"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_30
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed Woman <persName>Thais</persName> or <persName>Thaisis</persName></head>
         <p>And now I desire to narrate unto you the excellent history and the great repentance of
            the blessed woman <persName>Thais</persName> or <persName>Thaisis</persName>, for speech concerning her is most excellent, and it
            is full of encouragement and penitence of soul unto those who love God. Now this woman
            had a mother who, because her daughter was beautiful of face, made her to take up a
            position in the market, and the rumour of her beauty travelled unto every place, and
            those who were living afar off desired greatly to see her; and no man who looked <pb n="208"/>upon
            her was satisfied with the sight of her face, because she burned like a flame of fire
            into the hearts of those who saw her, and many by reason of their mad love for her sold
            whatever property they had to her parents that they might have commerce with her. Now
            when <persName>Bessarion</persName>, the servant of God, heard these things concerning this woman and that
            through her beauty she was dragging many to destruction, he arrayed himself in the
            apparel of a man who was in the world, and took with him one dînâr and went unto her,
            and when he saw her he brought forth the dînâr and gave it to her; and having taken the
            dînâr she said unto him, <quote>Let us go into a room,</quote> and he said unto her, <quote>Yea, let us go
            in.</quote> And having gone in, the blessed man <persName>Bessarion</persName> saw the couch which was laid out, now
            it was a very high one, and the woman said unto the old man, <quote>Come, get up on this bed</quote>;
            and he said unto her, <quote>Hast thou not inside this chamber another room?</quote> and she said
            unto him, <quote>Yea.</quote> Then he said unto her, <quote>Let us then go in there.</quote> And <persName>Thais</persName> answered
            and said unto him, <quote>If it be that thou art ashamed of men [seeing thee, know] that no
            man can see [us] in this chamber; but if it be God of Whom thou art afraid He can see us
            in whatsoever place we enter.</quote> And the blessed man <persName>Bessarion</persName> hearing these words, said
            unto her, <quote>My daughter, dost thou know that God existeth?</quote> And she said unto him, <quote>Yea,
            I know that God existeth, and [that there will be] kingdom, and judgement.</quote> Then the old
            man said unto her, <quote>If thou knowest that God is, and [that there will be] kingdom and
            judgement, why dost thou destroy men in this manner?</quote> And straightway the woman cast
            herself at his feet, and said unto him, <quote>I know that there is repentance for those who
            sin. But <pb n="209"/>I beseech thee, master, to tarry with me for three hours, and whatsoever thou
            wishest to do unto me that do because of all the evil things which have been wrought by
            me</quote>; and having told her in what place he would await her he left her and went away.</p>
         <p>Then in that same hour the woman took everything which she had gained by fornication and
            burnt it with fire in the midst of the city, and she said, <quote>Come, O all ye who have had
            commerce with me, and see that I am burning before your eyes every possession which I
            have gathered together by means of sin</quote>; and the things which were burned were [worth]
            three hundred pounds of gold, and there were there also goods and apparel of all kinds;
            and after she had burned up everything she went to the blessed man <persName>Bessarion</persName>. And when
            <persName>Bessarion</persName> saw her he took her by her hand and led her along and brought her to a
            religious house of sisters, and he shut her in a little cell, leaving her only one small
            window in the wall through which a woman passed in food to her. And the blessed
            <persName>Bessarion</persName> said unto the head of the house, <quote>Give her a pound of dry bread each day, and
            water according to her need.</quote> Then the blessed woman <persName>Thais</persName> said unto the venerable
            <persName>Bessarion</persName>, <quote>With what petition dost thou command me to pray unto God? That He should
            forgive me my sins?</quote> The blessed <persName>Bessarion</persName> said unto her, <quote>Thou art neither worthy to
            pray unto God, nor to make mention of His Name with thy lips, nor to stretch out thy
            hands unto Him; for thy lips are unclean and polluted, and thy hands are contaminated
            with impurity; thou shalt only sit down and gaze towards <placeName>the East</placeName>, and thou shalt say
            nothing except, <quote>O Thou who didst create me, have mercy upon me.</quote> </quote> And having dwelt in
            that cell for a space of about three years, the blessed <persName>Bessarion</persName> had mercy upon her,
            and the blessed man went to Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> that he might learn from him whether God <pb n="210"/>had
            forgiven her her sins or not. Then having spoken concerning her unto <persName>Anthony</persName> that
            blessed man called unto his disciples, and said unto them, <quote>Let each one of you shut
            himself in [his] cell all night, and pray ye unto God that we may see unto whom shall be
            revealed the matter concerning which the blessed <persName>Bessarion</persName> hath come unto us [this
            day].</quote></p>
         <p>And when they all had done as they had been commanded and when a long time had elapsed,
            the blessed <persName>Paul</persName>, the chief of the disciples of Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName>, looked into the heavens and
            saw a couch which had been spread with great splendour, and three angels who were
            carrying three lamps were standing before that couch, and a crown of glory was laid
            thereupon. And having seen all this glorious sight, he said, <quote>This couch can only be for
            my father <persName>Anthony</persName>.</quote> Then a voice came unto him from heaven, saying, <quote>This couch is not
            for <persName>Anthony</persName>, thy father, but for <persName>Thais</persName> the harlot</quote>; and the blessed <persName>Paul</persName> rose up early
            in the morning and related the vision which he had seen. And the blessed Mâr <persName>Bessarion</persName>
            came back from Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName> in great joy, and he went to the religious house of the
            sisterhood, and he opened the door that he might bring the woman out from the cell
            wherein she was secluded; but she made entreaty unto him, saying, <quote>Leave me here until
            my death, for my sins are many.</quote> Then the blessed man said unto her, <quote>Behold the
            merciful God hath had compassion upon thee, and He hath accepted thy repentance</quote>; and
            then she wished to go forth from her cell. And she answered and said unto him, <quote>Believe
            me, O Father, from the day wherein I entered this cell I have made all my sins a mighty
            burden and I have set it before my eyes, in suchwise that as the breath of my nostrils
            hath not separated itself from me, so my sins have not separated themselves from me
            until this hour.</quote></p>
         <pb n="211"/>
         <p>And the blessed <persName>Bessarion</persName> answered and said unto her, <quote>God hath not forgiven thee thy
            sins because of thy repentance, but because of the thought which thou hadst—that thou
            wouldst deliver thyself over unto <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote> Now this blessed woman <persName>Thais</persName> lived
            (literally, made) after her repentance fifteen days, and she departed unto our Lord in
            peace. Thus was the crowning of the blessed <persName>Thais</persName>, who was lost and was found, and was
            dead and who came to life by the grace of <persName>Christ</persName>, unto Whom belong mercy, and
            compassion, and glory, and honour, for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
