<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Blessed Man Dorotheos</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_32"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_32
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed <persName>Dorotheos</persName></head>
         <p>Now there was there besides this man <persName>Elijah</persName>, the chosen man <persName>Dorotheos</persName>, who had grown old
            therein leading a life of excellent and sublime ascetic rule; and as he did not wish to
            dwell in the nunnery by the side of the women, as <persName>Elijah</persName> had done, he shut himself up in
            a certain upper chamber, but left therein a window which faced and looked into the
            interior of the nunnery; and when he knew that it was proper to do so he used to open it
            or shut it. He always sat by the window, and he shewed the women that he knew <pb n="214"/>everything
            which they were doing, and by these means they were rebuked and prevented from
            quarrelling. And thus he grew old in that upper chamber, and no women ever went up to
            him, and he was unable to go down to them, for there was no ladder, and in this manner
            of life he brought his days to an end according to the will of God by the help of His
            grace.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
