<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Blessed Man Pachomius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_33"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_33
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed Pachomius the Great, and of the Sons of his Monastery, and of the
            Nunneries which were in the Thebaid</head>
         <p>In the country of Thebes, and in the district thereof which is called Tabenna, there was
            a certain blessed man whose name was Pachomius, and this man led a beautiful life of
            ascetic excellence, and he was crowned with the love of God and of man. Now therefore as
            this man was sitting in his cell, there appeared unto him an angel who said unto him,
            <quote>Since thou hast completed thy discipleship it is unnecessary for thee to dwell here;
            but come, and go and gather together unto thyself those who are wandering, and be thou
            dwelling with them, and lay thou down for them such laws as I shall tell unto thee</quote>; and
            the angel gave him a book (or tablet) wherein was written the following: <quote><list>
                  <item n="1">Let every man eat and drink whensoever he wisheth, and according to
                     the strength of those who eat and drink impose work; and thou shalt restrain
                     them neither from eating nor fasting. Furthermore, on those who are strong thou
                     shalt impose severe labours; and upon those who are of inferior strength and
                     upon those who fast thou shalt impose light labours.</item>
                  <item n="2">And thou shalt make for them a cell, and they shall dwell together
                     three by three.</item>
                  <item n="3">And they shall partake of food all together in one chamber (or
                     house).</item>
                  <item n="4">And they shall not take their sleep lying down, but thou shalt make
                     for them seats so that when they are sitting down they shall be able to support
                     their heads.</item>
                  <item n="5">At night time they shall put on garments without sleeves, and their
                     loins shall be girded up, and they shall be provided with skull-caps; and they
                     shall partake of the Offering on the Sabbath and on the First Day of the Week,
                     wearing skull-caps without any nap upon them, and each skull-cap shall have in
                     the front thereof a cross [worked in] purple.</item>
                  <item n="6">And thou shalt establish the monks in four and twenty grades, and to
                     each grade give a letter of the Greek alphabet from Âlâf to Tâw (i.e., from A
                     to Z); every grade a letter.</item>
               </list></quote></p>
         <p>And the blessed Pachomius performed and fulfilled [these things] according as he had
            been commanded by the angel; and when the head of the monastery asked him that was next
            to him concerning the affairs of the brethren, the man said unto him, <quote>The voice of
            Alphâ [and] the voice of Bîtâ salute the head [of the monastery].</quote> Thus the whole of
            that assembly of brethren had letters of the alphabet assigned to them, according to the
            designation of the four and twenty letters. To those who were upright and simple he
            assigned the letter yôdh (i.e., ι), and to those who were difficult and perverse he
            assigned the letter ksî (i.e., ξ), and thus according to the dispositions and according
            to the habits and rules of life of the orders [of monks] did he assign letters unto
            them.</p>
         <p>And he (i.e., the Angel) commanded that <quote>a monk who was a stranger and who had a
            different garb from theirs should not enter in with them to the table; the man who
            sought to be accepted as a monk in that monastery was obliged to labour there for three
            years, after which he was to receive the tonsure. When the monks were eating together
            they were to cover up their faces with [their] head-coverings, that they might not see
            each other eating, and might not hold converse together over the table, and might not
            gaze about from one side to the other.</quote> And he commanded that during [each] day they
            should repeat twelve sections of the Psalter, [and during [each] evening twelve sections
            of the Psalter], and during [each] night twelve sections of the Psalter, and that when
            they came to eat they should repeat the Great Psalm.</p>
         <p>And the blessed Pachomius said unto the angel, <quote>The sections of the Psalter which thou
            hast appointed unto us [for repetition] are far too few</quote>; and the angel said unto him,
            <quote>The sections of the Psalter which I have appointed [are indeed few], so that even the
            monks who are small (i.e., weak) may be able to fulfil the canons, and may not be
            distressed thereby. For unto the perfect no law whatsoever is laid down, because their
            mind is at all seasons occupied with God, but this law which I have laid down for those
            who have not a perfect mind is laid down for them, so that although they fulfil only
            such things as are prescribed by the canons they can acquire openness of face.</quote> Now very
            many nuns hold fast unto this law and canon.</p>
         <p>And there were living in that mountain about seven thousand brethren, and in the
            monastery in which the blessed Pachomius himself lived there were living one thousand
            three hundred brethren; and besides these there were there also other monasteries, each
            containing about three hundred, or two hundred, or one hundred monks, who lived
            together; and they all toiled with their hands and lived thereby, and with whatsoever
            they possessed which was superfluous for them they provided (or fed) the nunneries which
            were there. Each day those whose week of service it was rose up and attended to their
            work; and others attended to the cooking, and others set out the tables and laid upon
            them bread, and cheese, and vessels of vinegar and water. And there were some monks who
            went in to partake of food at the third hour of the day, and others at the sixth hour,
            and others at the ninth hour, and others in the evening, and others who ate once a day
            only; and there were some who ate only once a week; and according as each one of them
            knew the letter which had been laid upon him, so was his work. Some worked in the
            paradise (i.e., the orchard), and some in the gardens, and some in the blacksmith’s
            shop, and some in the baker’s shop, and some in the carpenter’s shop, and some in the
            fuller’s shop, and some wove baskets and mats of palm leaves, and one was a maker of
            nets, and one was a maker of sandals, and one was a scribe; now all these men as they
            were performing their work were repeating the Psalms and the Scriptures in order.</p>
         <p>And there were there large numbers of women who were nuns, and who closely followed this
            rule of life, and they came from the other side of the river and beyond it, and there
            were also married women who came from the other side of the river close by; and
            whensoever anyone of them died, the [other] women would bring her and lay her down on
            the bank of the river and go away. Then certain brethren would cross over in a boat and
            bring her over with the [singing of] psalms and with lighted candles, and with great
            ceremony and honour, and when they had brought her over they would lay her in their
            cemetery; without elder or deacon no man could go to that nunnery, and then only from
            one Sunday to the other (i.e., they could go only on Sundays). Now it happened that a
            certain tailor, who was a stranger, came to that nunnery looking for work, and one of
            the sisters went forth to talk with him, and she said unto him, <quote>We have our own
            tailor</quote>; and one of the sisters saw her speaking with him, and she held her peace and
            informed no one concerning the matter. And after a short time the two women had a
            dispute about a certain matter, and the sister who had seen the other talking to the
            tailor went and brought an accusation against the other before all the sisters, saying
            about her in an evil manner, <quote>This is the Satan who hath sown the strife among us</quote>; and
            then many of the women having heard [these things] believed [them]. And the sister, not
            being able to endure the accusation wherewith she had been accused without cause, by
            reason of her distress went and cast herself into the river and was drowned; and when
            the sister who had made the accusation against the other perceived this, seeing that she
            had calumniated her evilly, and that she had caused the sisters pain in a most serious
            manner, she also secretly drowned herself. And the elder who had been made [guardian] of
            them, knowing this matter, commanded one of them that none of the sisters who had
            believed that sister who had made the accusation against her companion should receive
            the Offering, and he was not reconciled unto them, and prevented them from
            [participating in] the Offering for seven years.</p>
         <p>Now in that same nunnery there was a certain sister who was a virgin, and she made
            herself an object of contempt, and she had had a devil in her; and the [other] sisters
            used to treat her so contemptuously that they would not even allow her to eat with them.
            And the woman herself was well content at this [treatment], and she would go into the
            refectory and serve the food and wait upon the whole company [there], and she became the
            broom of the whole nunnery; and indeed she made manifest that which is written [in the
            Book of] the blessed Apostle (1 Corinthians 3:18), who said, <quote>Whosoever wisheth to
            become a wise man in this world, let him become a fool in order that he may become
            wise.</quote> And this woman used to throw over her head a roughly cut piece of cloth, whilst
            the other women wore veils, well cut and well made, according to the rule which they
            had, and in this garb she used to minister in the refectory, and they would not allow
            her to sit down with them at the table. And whilst she was eating they never looked at
            her, and she never touched a whole loaf of bread, but used to eat the broken bits and
            crusts [that fell] from the tables, and [she drank] the rinsings of the basins and of
            the hands, and they sufficed her; and she neither reviled anyone of them, nor murmured,
            nor spoke superfluous words, though they constantly reviled her, and struck her, and
            thrust her away with harsh words and blows.</p>
         <p>Now at that time the blessed Pitêroum (Piterius), that man of wonder, appeared, and he
            dwelt in the region which was called <quote>Porphyry Mountain,</quote> and an angel appeared unto him
            and said, <quote>Why holdest thou in thy mind the proud opinion that thou art more excellent
            in ascetic practices than many? If thou wishest to see a woman who is more excellent
            than thou, go to the nunnery which is in Tabenna, and behold thou shalt find there a
            woman [with a roughly cut piece of cloth thrown over her head] who is far superior to
            thee in ascetic practices; and this woman is far more excellent than thou art, for
            although she ministereth as a servant to a great congregation her whole heart is set
            upon God, whilst as for thee, though thou dwellest here, thy mind wandereth about in
            many countries.</quote> And when the man who had never gone forth from his monastery had heard
            those things, he went quickly to the nunnery, and he besought their visitor (or
            inspector) that [he might be allowed] to see the nuns; and when he had gone inside the
            house they all came that they might be blessed by the blessed man (Piterius), but the
            woman who had made herself a creature of contempt did not show herself at all. Then the
            blessed man Piterius said unto them, <quote>Have all the sisters come, for there is one
            lacking?</quote> and they said unto him, <quote>Master, we have one more, but she is a woman of no
            account, and she is in the refectory.</quote> And Piterius said unto them, <quote>Bring her that I
            may see her also</quote>; and they went to bring her, but she did not wish to come, for she
            felt that the matter of herself would be certainly revealed unto him. Now since she did
            not wish to go to the blessed man they dragged her along and brought her unto him by
            force, saying unto her, <quote>Mâr Piterius wisheth to see thee</quote>; and when she had come, the
            blessed man looked and saw the roughly cut piece of cloth which was thrown over her
            head, according to the sign which the angel had given concerning her. Then he bowed down
            before her, and said unto her, <quote>Bless me, Mother,</quote> and she fell down at his feet, saying
            unto him, <quote>Bless thou me, master.</quote> When the sisters saw [this] they were all struck with
            wonder, and said unto him, <quote>Let there be no disgrace to thee, master, for she is a
            creature of no account.</quote> Then the blessed man Piterius answered [and] said unto them,
            <quote>Ye yourselves are creatures of contempt, but this woman is your Mother and mine, and I
            entreat God that He will give unto me a portion with her in the day of judgement.</quote> Now
            when all the sisters heard this from the blessed man Piterius, they fell down at her
            feet, and offered unto her regret for everything which they had been accustomed to do
            unto her; for some of them used to throw the rinsings of the vessels over her, and
            others used to buffet her, and she endured many insults from them all. So the blessed
            Piterius prayed over them and went forth from that place. And a few days afterwards,
            because the blessed woman could not endure the honour and the praises of all the
            sisters, and the penitence which they showed unto her, she went forth from that house
            altogether, but where she went and where she died no man knoweth.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
