<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">An Apology, and Preface, and Admonition</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_34"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_34
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>An Apology, and Preface, and Admonition</head>
         <p>Now therefore, O my brother, it sufficeth for me that I have called to mind all these
            things, and that I have handed them on in writing; for this thing did not happen without
            [the Will of] God, because thou wast moved in thy mind to command me to make this
            compilation and also to hand down in writing an account of the lives and acts of the
            holy fathers. And, according to the command of the love of God which is in thee, I will
            write down also the upright lives of holy women who have prospered in the good works of
            patient endurance, and afterwards I will also write down the account of the stumblings
            of those who have fallen away from a straight rule of life through the pride which
            seized upon them, and through the wicked and vain opinion that came upon their souls,
            and who were tripped up, and stumbled, and fell through their weakness and the war of
            the Adversary, although not of their own will, for after their fall they triumphed still
            more gloriously, and acquired rectitude. And I will do this for the benefit of those who
            are about to meet with this compilation, so that they may set the edifice of their
            building upon the firm ground of humility with zeal and care, and may fly from pride,
            and may take refuge in humility; and it shall be my object to write with extreme care
            concerning the humility of the holy men, and concerning their long-suffering, and
            concerning their patient endurance, and the questions which they asked each other,
            together with their answers, and the sundry and divers things which I shall be able to
            call to mind concerning the lives of the holy fathers. And, O thou faithful servant of
            Christ, having lighted upon this book with pleasure, and having derived therefrom
            sufficiently a demonstration of the Resurrection, and of the lives and labours of the
            holy fathers, and also of their patient endurance, and being able to grow up in a good
            hope, and to advance easily in virtues, turn thyself round for once, so that thou mayest
            see that which is behind thee, and seeing my feebleness do thou pray for me. And take
            good heed to guard thy soul, even as I know thou [hast been able to do] from [the time
            when] thou didst hold the consular power of Titianus unto this day; and again as I found
            thee when thou wast the prefect and officer of the bed-chamber of the God fearing king.
            For the man who hath such power as this, and who is able to enjoy himself with wealth in
            abundance, must not forget the fear of God, and he must take the greatest care possible
            to emulate Christ, Who heard from the Calumniator [these words], <quote>All these things will
            I give unto thee if thou wilt fall down and worship me</quote> (St. Matthew 4:9). Therefore
            take good heed unto thyself, and be vigilant, so that thou mayest at all times be
            exalted over the neck[s] of thy secret and invisible enemies. Amen.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
