<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Virgin who hid Athanasius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_35"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_35
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The Triumphant Deeds and Exploits and Histories of Holy Women</head>
         <head>Of the Virgin of <persName>Alexandria</persName> who hid <persName>Athanasius</persName></head>
         <p>Now therefore it is necessary for us to remember also the chosen and mighty women unto
            whom God also gave an equal measure of strength of will as unto men, so that they might
            have no cause for being feeble in the performance of the labour of ascetic excellence. I
            have seen large numbers of widows who were exceedingly glorious and excellent in the
            performance of ascetic virtues, and among the chaste virgins whom I saw in <persName>Alexandria</persName>
            there was one whom I estimated to be seventy years old, and all the clergy testified
            concerning her that when a young woman, about twenty years old, she possessed exceeding
            beauty, and she was more looked at than many women, and because of her beauty she fled
            lest she should become the cause of stumbling unto men. Once when the <persName>Arians</persName> were
            plotting against the blessed <persName>Athanasius</persName>, the Archbishop of <persName>Alexandria</persName>, and were acting
            craftily in respect of him that they might do him harm through the prefect <persName>Eusebius</persName>, and
            through the wicked men who were his partisans in the days of the Emperor <persName>Constantine</persName> the
            Less (i.e., <persName>Constantius</persName>), and were spreading abroad infamous reports about him, and were
            accusing him of many things which were unseemly for Christians to do, <persName>Athanasius</persName> fled
            that he might not be condemned in their wicked and corrupt hall of judgement, and he
            told no man, neither kinsmen, nor friends, nor ecclesiastics, nor any other men [where
            he was going]. And as soon as certain men from <pb n="226"/>among the magistrates had entered into
            the episcopal palace suddenly, and begun to search for him and to enquire for him, he
            rose up at midnight, and took his tunic, and fled to this virgin who, being greatly
            astonished and struck with wonder at the matter, was moved exceedingly. And the blessed
            <persName>Athanasius</persName> said unto her, <quote>Because I am sought for by the <persName>Arians</persName>, who are making
            unseemly accusations against me, and because I do not want to spread about an unseemly
            opinion of myself, and I wish not to prepare a great punishment for those who would be
            condemned for my sake, and be made guilty for me, I determined to betake myself to
            flight, and God gave me a revelation this night, saying, <quote>There is no other person with
            whom thou canst find deliverance except this virgin.</quote> </quote> Now therefore because of her
            exceedingly great joy she removed from herself and set aside all thoughts [of shame],
            and she became wholly [the servant] of our Lord, and she hid that holy man for the whole
            period of thirty years, that is to say, until the death of <persName>Constantine</persName>. She used to wash
            his feet, and she prepared everything of which he had need, and she attended to his
            bodily wants, and whatsoever he needed that she provided, and she borrowed books and
            brought [them] to him; and no man in <persName>Alexandria</persName> knew during that whole period of thirty
            years where the blessed <persName>Athanasius</persName> was. And when the death of <persName>Constantine</persName> (i.e.,
            <persName>Constantius</persName>) was announced, and <persName>Athanasius</persName> also heard thereof, he rose up and came by
            night and he was suddenly found to be in the church, and all those who saw him marvelled
            as they looked carefully at him, for he was like unto a man who had risen from the
            grave. And he made an apology to those who truly loved him, and spake unto them, saying,
            <quote>I did not flee unto you, for <pb n="227"/>the reason that there might not be unto you an occasion
            for swearing [false] oaths. And moreover, because of the search and enquiry which they
            were sure to have made for me I fled unto that woman concerning whom no man could
            suspect of harm, for she is young and beautiful. And I have gained two things, my own
            life and hers; I have helped her in many things, and I have taken care and preserved
            myself.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
