<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Piamon the Virgin</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_36"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_36
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of <persName>Piamon</persName> the Virgin</head>
         <p><persName>Piamon</persName> was a virgin who lived all her days with her mother, and she spent her nights in
            constant vigil, and she ate food at the time of evening, and she laboured at the
            [weaving of] linen; and she was held to be worthy of the gift of knowing what was going
            to happen before it happened. Now it happened on a time that there was in <placeName>Upper Egypt</placeName> a
            certain village which was fighting with another village, for the villages quarrelled
            with each other concerning the division of the waters [of the <placeName>Nile</placeName>], and they fought so
            violently that frequently murders were committed, and men were beaten to death. And the
            village which was stronger than the village of this virgin rose up against it in fierce
            wrath, and there came against the inhabitants of her village a crowd of boastful and
            violent men carrying staves and spears to kill them; and the angel of the Lord appeared
            unto her, and revealed unto her the craft of those who were ready to fall upon them
            secretly. Then she sent and called the elders of the <pb n="228"/>church of her village, and said
            unto them, <quote>Go ye forth to meet the inhabitants of that village, for behold they are
            coming against you, lest peradventure ye and the village perish; and make entreaty unto
            them that perhaps they may be turned aside from their daring attack, and they may spare
            the village.</quote></p>
         <p>Now the elders of the village were afraid, and they fell down at her feet and made
            supplication unto her, saying, <quote>We do not dare to go forth to meet them, for we are well
            acquainted with their miserable nature and their arrogance; but if thou wishest to spare
            the village and thine own house, do thou thyself go forth to meet them.</quote> And the virgin
            would not undertake to go forth, but she went up upon the roof, and stood up there in
            prayer the whole night long, without once kneeling down, and she made bowings and
            entreaties unto God, saying, <quote>O Lord, Thou Judge of the earth, Who hast no pleasure in
            whatever is iniquitous, O my Lord, when the prayer which Thine handmaiden prayeth and
            her supplication reach Thee, let Thy power transfix [the enemy] in the spot wherein they
            are</quote>; and straightway, on that very day, at a distance of three miles from the village
            they became fettered, and stood still, being unable to move [from] the spot. And it was
            revealed unto them also that they were hindered from moving by the supplication of that
            woman, and thereupon they sent to the inhabitants of the village, and made peace with
            them, and became reconciled unto them, and they also sent a message unto them, saying,
            <quote>Give ye grateful thanks unto God, for it was the prayers of <persName>Piamon</persName> which prevented us
            [from coming to you].</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
