<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Mother Talida</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_37"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_37
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of our Blessed <persName>Âmmantîlîda (Emmâ Talîdâ)</persName>, the Old Woman of <placeName>Antinoe</placeName></head>
         <p>Now in the city of <placeName>Antinoë</placeName> there were twelve nunneries, and the women thereof conducted
            themselves according to a rule of beautiful spiritual excellence; here I saw the aged
            handmaiden of <persName>Christ</persName> whose name was <quote>Mother Talîdâ,</quote> who had dwelt in the holy house,
            according to what she herself and those who were her associates told me, for eighty
            years. And there lived with her sixty virgins who followed the path and rule of the
            ascetic life in purity, and they led a life of happiness under the teaching of this good
            old woman, whom they loved, and on whom they depended; and because of the great
            affection which they poured out upon her, the key was never taken away from any one of
            them, as is customary in other religious houses for women, and through her divine
            doctrine she changed them into a state of incorruptibility. Now this old woman arrived
            at such a state of impassibility that when I entered into her presence and sat down by
            her side, she stretched out her hands and laid them upon my shoulders, in the boldness
            and freedom which she had acquired in <persName>Christ</persName>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
