<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Virgin Taor</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_38"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_38
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Virgin Taor</head>
         <p>Now in this nunnery there was a certain virgin whose name was Taor, who was the disciple
            of a certain old woman of ascetic excellence, and who had lived therein for thirty
            years; and she would consent to receive neither beautiful apparel, nor a veil, nor
            sandals, saying, <quote>I do not require [them], for I am not compelled to go down into the
            market.</quote> Every First Day of the Week the other women used to go down to the church to
            partake of the Offering, but this virgin used to remain by herself in the nunnery
            dressed in rags, and she would sit at her work at all hours. And by these means she
            acquired such a sagacious, wise, and ready appearance that every man who was wont to
            abhor the sight of women would have been nigh to being snared and falling at the sight
            of her, had it not been that shamefacedness, which is the guardian of chastity, was ever
            with her, and that she ordered her gaze in a chaste manner by means of shame and
            fear.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
