<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Melania the Great</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_41"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_41
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Holy Woman Melania the Great</head>
         <p>Melania, the holy woman who is worthy of all blessings, was of Spanish origin, and she
            grew up in Rome, for she was the daughter of Marcellinus, a man who had held consular
            rank. Now her husband was a man who performed a large number of duties under the
            Government, and she became a widow when she was twenty-two years old. Now this woman,
            having been held worthy to be seized upon by divine love, revealed the matter to no man,
            for she would not have been permitted to perform her own will, because she lived in the
            time of the rule of Valens (A.D. 364–378); and having arranged that he should be named
            the procurator of her son’s affairs, she took everything which she possessed which could
            be easily moved and carried off, and placed it in a ship with tried servants, both men
            and women, and sailed hastily to Alexandria, where she sold her property and changed it
            into gold. And she went into the mount of Nitria, and saw the fathers, that is to say,
            Pambô, and Arsenius, and Serapion the Great, and Paphnutius of Scete, and Isidore the
            Confessor and Bishop of Hermopolis, and Dioscurus; and she remained with them for half a
            year, and she went round about through all that desert, and saw all the holy men and was
            blessed by them. And when Augustus, who was in Alexandria, sent into exile to Palestine
            and Caesarea, Isidore, and Pissimius, and Adelphius, and Fîsânîs, and Paphnutius, and
            Pambô (now with these also was Ammonius, that is to say, twelve holy bishops), this
            blessed woman clave to them, and she ministered unto them of her own possessions. And
            when the servants whom she used to send unto them were stopped, this brave woman
            (according to what the holy men Pîsânîs, and Paphnutius, and Isidore, and Ammonius
            related unto me, for I used to hold converse with them) used to clothe herself in the
            garment of one of her servants, and carry unto them late in the evening the food which
            they needed.</p>
         <p>Now when the governor of Palestine learned this thing, wishing to fill his purse, and
            hoping and expecting to make profit by her, he seized her and cast her into prison,
            being unaware that she was a woman of noble rank. Then she sent unto him a message,
            saying, <quote>I am the daughter of such and such a man, [and the wife of such and such a
            man], and I am the handmaiden of Christ. Do not treat lightly my poor garb and estate,
            for I have the power to exalt myself if it pleaseth me to do so, and thou hast no
            authority either to hamper me in this fashion or to carry off any of my property. Now,
            in order that thou mayest not dare to do anything in ignorance, and so fall under
            condemnation, behold, I send thee [this] message; for it is meet that towards senseless
            and foolish men we should act in a masterful manner, and with pride, even as our noble
            rank enableth us to do, and should treat them as fools and men of no understanding.</quote> And
            when the governor learned this thing he apologized to Melania, and entreated her to
            forgive him, and he fell down and did homage unto her, and gave orders that she should
            have the power to visit holy men without hindrance.</p>
         <p>And after the return of these blessed men from exile, this holy woman built a house in
            Jerusalem, wherein she dwelt for twenty-seven years, and wherein she had a congregation
            of sisters, who were in number about fifty; and moreover, the honourable nobleman
            Rufinus, who came from Italy and belonged to the city of Aquileia, clave unto her her
            whole life long, and he led a life of glorious works, and finally he was held to be
            worthy of the office of elder. Now among men one would not quickly find one who was more
            understanding, and gracious, and pleasant than he. And Rufinus and Melania during the
            whole of that period of twenty-seven years received and relieved at their own expense
            all those people who came unto Jerusalem to pray, bishops, and dwellers in monasteries,
            and virgins, and they edified and benefited all those who thronged to them. Now they
            healed the schism of the Paulinists, who were in number about four hundred monks, and
            they all were heretics who fought against the Holy Spirit; and having made entreaty unto
            them they turned them back unto union with the Church. And they loaded with their gifts
            all the clergy who were in the cities, and they provided with food all those who were
            strangers and needy [therein]. In this manner they ended their lives, and they never
            became a stumbling-block unto [any] man. Now as concerning the possessions of which she
            stripped herself, and the things (i.e., money) which she distributed, being hot as fire
            with divine zeal, and blazing like a flame with the love of Christ, I alone am not able
            to recount, for it belongeth also unto those who dwell in the country of the Persians
            [to declare it]; for there was no man who was deprived of her alms and gifts [whether he
            came from the] east, or the west, or the north, or the south. She lived in exile for
            thirty-seven years, and her possessions sufficed for her to give alms to churches, and
            to religious houses, and to strangers, and to those who were in prison. And meanwhile
            her relatives and her kinsfolk were sending [money] unto her continually, and her own
            son, and those who had charge of her property also sent some of their own money unto
            her; and she never lacked anything, and during the whole of the time in which she was in
            exile she never consented to the acquisition of a span of land. And she was never drawn
            to long for her son, and the love for her only child neither parted her nor divided her
            from the love of Christ, but through her prayers her son attained unto perfect
            discipline and unto the ways and habits of excellence; and he became the son-in-law of
            honourable and noble people, and there also came upon him much power and divers
            positions of great honour; now he had two children, one boy and one girl.</p>
         <p>Now after a long period of time had elapsed, when she heard that the daughter of her son
            and her husband wished to be sanctified, and fearing lest they should fall into the
            hands of the heretics who would sow in them evil doctrines, and lest they should grow up
            in a life of dissolute luxury, that old woman, who was then sixty years old, embarked
            once again in a ship, and sailed from Caesarea, and after twenty days arrived in Rome.
            And whilst she was there she converted and made to become a Christian a man called
            Apronianus, who was of exceedingly high rank and was also a pagan; and she moreover
            persuaded him by means of most perfect admonition and exhortation to become sanctified,
            and also his wife, who was her own sister and whose name was Avita, to receive the garb
            of the followers of the ascetic life, and to become prosperous in all patience in the
            labours of the life of abstinence and self-denial. And she also strengthened by means of
            her excellent counsels the daughter of her son, whose name was Melania, and her husband,
            whose name was Pinianus, and she also converted her daughter-in-law, whose name was
            Albînâ; and she persuaded all these to sell everything which they possessed and to give
            [the money] to the poor; and she brought them out from Rome, and led them into the quiet
            and peaceful haven of the life and labours of asceticism.</p>
         <p>And she contended with all the women of senatorial rank and with the women of high
            degree, and strove with them as with savage wild beasts, for the men tried to restrain
            her from making the women do even as she had done, that is to say, to prevent her from
            converting them and making them to forsake their worldly rank and position. And she
            spake unto them thus, <quote>My children, four hundred years ago it was written that that time
            was the last time (1 St. John 2:18). Why do ye hold fast thus strenuously to the vain
            love of the world? Take ye heed lest the day of Antichrist overtake you, and keep not
            fast hold upon your own riches and the possessions of your fathers</quote>; and having set free
            all these she brought them to the life of the ascetic and recluse. As for her [grand]
            son Publicola, who was a child, she converted [him] and brought [him] to Sicily; and she
            sold the whole of the residue of her possessions and taking the price [thereof] came to
            Jerusalem, and, having distributed it in a wise fashion and arranged all her other
            affairs, after forty days she died at a good old age, being crowned with an abundance of
            gratification and happiness; and she left in Jerusalem a house for religious folk and
            money for the maintenance thereof.</p>
         <p>Now therefore when all those who clave unto her had gone forth from Rome the great
            barbarian whirlwind, which had also been mentioned in ancient prophecies, came upon the
            city, and it did not leave behind it even the statues of brass which were in the
            market-places, for it destroyed by its barbaric insolence everything whatsoever; and it
            so thoroughly committed everything to destruction that the city of Rome, which had been
            crowned and adorned for twelve hundred years with edifices and buildings of beauty,
            became a waste place. Then those who without contention had been converted by means of
            her admonition, ascribed glory unto God Who, by means of a change in temporal affairs,
            had persuaded those who did not believe her; for whilst the houses of all the latter
            were plundered, the houses of those only who had been persuaded by her were delivered,
            and they became perfect burnt-offerings unto the Lord, through the care and solicitude
            of the blessed woman Melania. And it happened by chance that I and they once travelled
            together from Aelia to Egypt, and we were accompanying on our journey the gentle virgin
            Sylvania, the sister of Rufinus, a man of consular rank, and Jovinianus was also with
            us; now he was at that time a deacon, but subsequently he became bishop in the Church of
            God of the city of Askelon, and he was a God-fearing man and was exceedingly well versed
            in doctrine. And it came to pass that a fierce and fiery heat overtook us on the way,
            and we came into Pelusium that we might rest therein; and Jovinianus, who is worthy of
            admiration, came by chance upon a trough for washing, and he began to wash his hands and
            his feet in a little water that by means of the coolness thereof he might refresh
            himself after the intensity of the blazing heat. Then having washed himself he threw on
            the ground a sheep-skin whereon he might rest from the labour of the journey. And
            behold, the mighty one among women stood up over him like a wise [mother], and in her
            simplicity rebuked him by her words, saying, <quote>Seeing that thou art still in the heat of
            youth how canst thou have confidence that by means of carefulness [on thy part] thou
            wilt be able to resist the [natural heat of] the constitution of the body which still
            burneth in thy member[s]? And dost thou not perceive the injurious effects which will be
            produced in thee by [this washing]? Believe me, O my son, for I am this day a woman
            sixty years old, from the time when I first took upon myself this garb water hath never
            touched more of my body than the tips of the fingers of my hands, and I have never
            washed my feet, or my face, or any one of my members. And although I have fallen into
            many sicknesses, and have been urged by the physicians, I have never consented nor
            submitted myself to the habit of applying water to any part of my body; and I have never
            lain upon a bed, and I have never gone on a journey to any place reclining on a
            cushioned litter.</quote></p>
         <p>Now this wise and blessed woman also loved learning, and she turned the nights into days
            in reading all the books of the famous Fathers, I mean to say the works of the blessed
            Gregory and of the holy man Stephen, and of Pierius and of Basil also, and of other
            [writers], more than two hundred and fifty thousand sayings; and she did not read them
            in an ordinary fashion or just as she came to them, and she did not hurry over them in
            an easy and pleasant manner, but with great labour and with understanding she used to
            read each book seven or eight times. And because of this she was enabled, being set free
            from lying doctrine, to fly by means of the gift of learning (or doctrine) to great
            opinions, and she made herself a spiritual bird, and in this wise was taken up to Christ
            her Lord. And may He in His mercy grant unto us through her prayers the power to act
            mightily, even as she did, and may we see her with all the saints who love Him, and with
            them may we lift up praise to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit for
            ever and ever.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
