<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Melania the Younger</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_42"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_42
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed Woman Melania the Younger</head>
         <p>Now inasmuch as I have already promised above to relate the history of Melania the
            Younger it is meet that I should pay [my] obligation, for it is not just that I should
            consign to oblivion a young woman who, though so very young in her years, by reason of
            her indefatigable zeal and knowledge was very much wiser than the old women, or that I
            should omit to make manifest by words the history of one who, though a girl in stature,
            was old in the mind of the fear of God. Now therefore the parents of this maiden drew
            her by force into marriage, and they united her unto one of the nobles of Rome, but she
            kept in mind continually the words which had been spoken unto her by her aged relative,
            and kept herself as was fitting, and became strengthened especially in the fear of God.
            And she had two sons, and as both of them died she came to be possessed of such a hatred
            of marriage that she said unto her husband, whose name was Pinianus, the son of Severus,
            a man of consular rank, <quote>If thou wishest to live with me a life of purity I will regard
            thee as the husband and lord of my life; but if, inasmuch as thou art a young man, this
            is too hard for thee, take everything which I have and leave only free to me my own
            body, for in this way I shall be able to fulfil my desire which is in God, and I shall
            become the heir of the excellences of that woman after whose name I have been called.
            For if God desired me to lead the life of this world He would never have taken away the
            children to whom I gave birth.</quote></p>
         <p>And when they had been for a long time debating the matter, at length God had mercy upon
            that young man, and He placed in him the zeal of the fear of God to such a degree that
            he also sought to be excused from all the material things of this world, and thus was
            fulfilled the word which had been spoken by the Apostle, saying, <quote>How knowest thou, O
            woman, whether thou shalt give life to thy husband [or not]? Or how knowest thou, O man,
            whether thou shalt give life to thy wife [or not]?</quote> (1 Corinthians 7:16.) Now when she
            was married to her husband she was about twelve [or thirteen] years old, and she lived
            with him for seven years, for she was twenty years of age when she withdrew from the
            world. First of all she bestowed all her raiment of silk upon the holy altars, which
            also did Olympias, the handmaiden of Christ, and the remainder of her apparel of silk
            she cut up, and made it suitable for the service of the church in other ways. Her silver
            and gold she entrusted to an elder whose name was Paul, who was a monk from Dalmatia,
            and she sent it by sea to the countries of the East, I mean to Egypt and to the Thebaïd,
            to the amount of ten thousand darics; and she sent in this manner ten thousand darics to
            Antioch, and to the countries which were nigh thereunto, but to Palestine she sent
            fifteen thousand darics. To the churches which were in the islands, and to the people
            who were in exile she sent ten thousand darics, and to those who were in the West, I
            mean in the churches, and in the monasteries there, and the houses for the reception of
            strangers, and to all those who were in want she distributed [her gifts] with her own
            hands. And I speak as before God [when I say] that she must have given away four times
            these [amounts besides], and that she snatched away [her money] from Alaricus her
            confidential servant as from the mouth of a lion. Of those who wished to be free among
            her servants she gave freedom to about eight thousand in number, and on the remainder
            who had no wish to have their freedom, and who preferred rather to remain in the service
            of her brother, she bestowed three thousand darics. All the villages which she had in
            Spain, and in Aquitania, and in the island of Tarragon, and Gaul she sold, as well as
            those which she had in Sicily, and in Campania, and in Africa, and received [the
            proceeds thereof] in her own hands, so that she might give them to the monasteries, and
            churches, and all those who were in want. Such was the wisdom of Melania, this lover of
            Christ, and such was the mature and divine opinion which she adopted in respect of the
            weighty burden of these riches.</p>
         <p>And her manner of life was thus. She herself ate once a day, though at the beginning she
            ate once in five days, and the young women whom she had converted and who lived with her
            she commanded to partake of food every day. And there lived with her also the mother of
            Albînâ, who observed the same rule of life, and who distributed her possessions among
            the needy after the manner of Melania; and sometimes they dwelt in the plains of Sicily,
            and sometimes in the plains of Campania, and they had with them fifteen men who were
            eunuchs, and a proportionate number of virgins who ministered as servants.</p>
         <p>And Pinianus, who had once been her husband, was now one who helped in the work of
            ascetic excellence, and was her associate, and he dwelt with three hundred men who were
            monks and read the Holy Scriptures, and he enjoyed himself in the garden, and conversed
            with the people. Now these men who were with him helped and relieved us in no slight
            degree, and we were very many in number, when we were going on our way to Rome on behalf
            of the blessed man John the Bishop, for they received us with the greatest good will and
            they supplied us with provisions for the way in great abundance, and they sent us on our
            way in joy and gladness.</p>
         <p>And their kinsman, whose name was Pammachius, a man of consular rank, withdrew from the
            world as did they, and he lived a life which was pleasing unto God, and during his
            lifetime he distributed his possessions among the needy, and left them [to them] after
            his death; and thus he departed unto our Lord. In like manner the man Macarius, and
            Constantinus, who was the assessor to the prefects in Italy (now they were well known
            men and men who merit mention), arrived at the highest pitch of ascetic excellence which
            I describe even as it is; and they abide in the body at this present and lead a life of
            glorious and divine deeds, and are awaiting the perfect life which is full of
            happiness.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
