<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Olympias</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_43"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_43
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed Woman Olympias</head>
         <p>Now the holy and chaste woman Olympias, whilst journeying in the footsteps of this woman
            Melania, was emulating her in the excellence of her divine life and labours, and she was
            seized with a fervent desire of travelling in the path which leadeth to heaven, and in
            every respect she made herself cling close to the Divine Books. This woman was in the
            flesh the daughter of Count Seleucus, but, if we say what is true, in the spirit she was
            the daughter of God. Now she was the daughter of the son of Ablavius, a man who had held
            consular rank in Constantinople, and she was for a few days the daughter-in-law of
            Nebridius, the sub-prefect of Constantinople, but in truth she was not the wife of the
            man, for they say concerning her that she died in purity and in her virginity, and that
            she only lived according to the Divine Word in chastity, wherein was mingled true
            humility, and that she made herself a friend of and ministered unto all those who were
            needy. Now her abundant riches sufficed for this work, and it is impossible to reckon up
            that which she used to distribute to every one with a sincere intent; for there is not a
            city, or a district, or a desert place, or an island, or a shore which did not enjoy the
            gifts of this glorious woman. And she gave gifts also to the churches for their
            maintenance, and to the houses wherein strangers were received, and also to the prisons
            and, moreover, to those who were in exile, and, so to speak, on the whole world this
            blessed woman scattered her alms broadcast. And she leaped upon and ascended the
            uppermost part of the lofty mountain of humility, wherein nothing whatsoever was to be
            seen of the acts and deeds of vainglory or of deceitful action (or appearance), but the
            life of simplicity, and the common garb, and the emaciated body, and the submissive
            mind, and the understanding which is without arrogance, and the lowly heart, and the
            watching of vigil, and the spirit which is without anxious care, and the love which hath
            no limit, and friendship without end and the holding in contempt the operation of the
            feelings, and the restraint from everything [harmful], and the mind which is simple
            towards God, and the hope which never faileth, and the lovingkindness which is
            unspeakable, and the thoughtful care of all poor folk.</p>
         <p>Now this woman suffered many temptations through the agency of that evil devil, who
            loveth hateful things and who hath never had experience of things which are good, and
            she endured great contendings for the sake of the name of Christ. And she gave herself
            unto tears which were without measure both by day and by night, and she submitted
            herself unto all sorts and conditions of the children of men for the sake of God, and
            she bowed down reverently before the holy Bishops, and she paid homage to the elders,
            and she entreated in an honourable manner the clergy, as well as the orders of monks who
            dwelt in the monastic houses, and she received with welcome the virgins, and she visited
            the widows, and she reared the orphans, and she strengthened [those who were in a state
            of] old age, and she had care for the sick and she mourned with the sinners, and she led
            the erring into the right path, and she tended every one, and she converted many women
            among those who did not believe, and prepared them for life. She left behind her to the
            world a beautiful remembrance, and she changed the slavery into freedom of all the
            members of her household, who were about a myriad in number, and she shewed unto them
            honour in the same degree as to her noble family; and if, as is right, we must tell the
            truth, she made them to become of more account than herself.</p>
         <p>It was impossible for any man to see apparel worse than hers on anyone, for the garments
            of this brave woman were not as good as those of the people who cover themselves with
            the oldest rags; and the food which she offered to her body was of such an inferior
            class that on account of its poorness it was rejected even by her servants. By this
            woman who was clothed in Christ, no blame was ever found in anyone, not even in her
            neighbours, all through her life—which was not a life—by reason of the repentance and in
            the vehement tears wherewith she burned; one may perchance see a fountain which, owing
            to the violence of the heat, hath dried up, but no man ever saw the eyes of this woman,
            which were fixed upon Christ, lacking tears. But of what use is it for us to tell and to
            devote myself so strenuously to narrate [things] concerning her? For the contendings of
            this woman, who was perfect in excellence, were so exceedingly numerous that they were
            more in number than those which were declared concerning her, and men would only imagine
            concerning me that I was narrating from hearsay great things which were not true about
            this woman Olympias, who became a vessel of honour of the Divine Spirit, and who was
            above [all] passions. Nevertheless I was a spectator of her excellence and of her
            angelic acts and deeds, and I was, as it were, a member of her household, and her
            kinsman in the Spirit, and she made, by my counsel, [gifts] unto many from her
            possessions. And this woman who never thought about the things which were in the flesh,
            suffered many vain calumnies for the sake of the truth, and those who were living in
            Divine fear in Constantinople rightly deemed that she should be numbered with the
            confessors, because even unto the death she persisted in striving for righteousness’
            sake, and in [performing her works] she received perfection, and she waited hopefully
            for the never-withering crown, which was full of all blessings in the everlasting
            mansions on high, with all the saints who were like unto her, and she sought after the
            reward of her good deeds with freedom (or boldness) of speech.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
