<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Candida</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_44"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_44
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed Woman Candida</head>
         <p>And after the manner of the blessed woman Candida, the daughter of the blessed man
            Trajan, the general, also laboured, and she arrived at the perfection of ascetic
            excellence; and she offered unto the Bishops, who were the ministers of the Mysteries of
            Christ, the homage which was meet for them, and she provided suitably for the
            performance of all the service of the church, and supplied the clergy with gifts, unto
            each man according to his grade. She converted her daughter and placed her in the ranks
            of the virgins, and she offered unto God this gift of the fruit of her womb, and sent
            [her] before her, and finally she herself also became like unto her daughter in the
            chastity of her purity, and she distributed her wealth among the poor and needy. And I
            know that night after night this brave woman used to rise up [from her bed] and grind
            corn, and heat the oven, and make bread for the Offering, and bake it with her own
            hands, and she was wont to say that she did this in order to reduce the strength of her
            body, for, she added, <quote>Because I am unable to receive any benefit from fasting I have
            taken upon myself this labour for watching, so that I may do away with the greedy
            appetite of Esau.</quote> Now she separated herself from every kind [of meat] where there is
            blood, fish alone excepted, and she made use of oil and vegetables, but these only on
            festival days; and on all other days she used to live on dry bread dipped in vinegar,
            and it sufficed her. And she awaited with hope the Resurrection which was to be full of
            happiness, in return for these stern labours, and she hoped to enjoy the everlasting
            delights which God hath prepared for those who love Him.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
