<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Juliana</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_46"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_46
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed Woman Juliana</head>
         <p>And again, there was a certain virgin, whose name was Juliana, in Caesarea of
            Cappadocia, and it was said concerning her that she was a believing woman, and a woman
            of understanding, and that in the time of the persecution when the writer Origen was
            fleeing from the heathen she received [him] and hid him [in her house] for two years;
            and she fed and kept him at her own expense, and made him to be satisfied and content
            with her ministration. Now I have found these things set down in a certain book which
            was in the handwriting of Origen himself, and I found this book in the possession of the
            excellent virgin Juliana in Caesarea who had hidden it, and who used to say that she
            received it from Symmachus, the expositor of the Jews. And I have not set down [in
            writing] the story of the excellences of these glorious women for any ordinary purpose,
            but that we may learn that by every means whatsoever we may, if we wish, find sundry and
            divers occasions for [obtaining spiritual] advantage.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
