<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Heronion and Bosphoria</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_47"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_47
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of Heronion and his Wife [Bosphoria]</head>
         <p>In Ancyra, a city of Galatia, I met a man whose name was Heronion, an <quote>Apakomots,</quote> and
            an enlightened man, and his wife whose name was Bosphoria (or Dosphoria), and of their
            mode of living and acts I experienced an example. Now these folk had such a firm hope in
            the happiness (or good things) which were to come, that they neglected even their
            children, for they awaited with hope the actual [fulfilment] of the things to come, and
            they distributed among the poor and needy the income which they derived from their
            villages, notwithstanding the fact that they had four male and two female children. To
            these [children] they never gave anything whatsoever, except to the daughters who had
            married husbands. And finally, they used to say, <quote>After we are dead everything will be
            yours, but during our lifetime the income which we derive from our villages we shall
            take for ourselves.</quote> Now they used to divide their moneys among the churches and
            monasteries, and houses for the receiving of strangers (or hospitals?) and among the
            poor and needy. And besides these things they performed the following act of excellence.
            There was a great famine, and every man shut up (or restrained) his mercy, but these
            folk opened the storehouses which they had in their villages, and gave [food] to eat to
            those who were famished, and through this act the heretics who were living in that
            country were changed and were turned unto the [true] knowledge when they saw their
            unspeakable lovingkindness; and they gave praise unto God for the simplicity of their
            faith. And other examples of their excellence were the following: The modest garb,
            common and simple apparel, food eaten but rarely, and then only in such quantity as was
            sufficient [to maintain] life; and they lived meanwhile in a state of chastity which was
            acceptable unto God. They dwelt in the fields several days [at a time], loving a life of
            silent contemplation, and they fled from the tumult of cities and from the evils which
            are begotten of them, lest when they were living among a crowd of people something might
            come upon them to disturb them, and they might fall from the[ir] divine state of mind.
            For this reason these blessed men were doing all these excellent things, because that
            with the eyes of the understanding they had already looked upon the good things which
            had been for ever prepared for them.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
