<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Magna</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_48"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_48
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed Woman <persName>M창ghan창 (Magna)</persName></head>
         <p>In this city of <placeName>Ancyra</placeName> there were also many other virgins who led lives of ascetic
            excellence, and they were two thousand, or more, in number; and they kept themselves in
            restraint and served God with great humility. And among them were also famous women who
            triumphed with glorious strenuousness in the contending of the fear of God, and of those
            was <persName>M창ghan창 (Magna)</persName>, the chaste and proved wife; now I know not whether I ought to describe her as
            a virgin or as a widow, for this woman, owing to the pressure which <pb n="253"/>was put upon her by
            her mother, was yoked unto a husband. But she used to make pretences to her husband in
            divers ways, and she avoided his embraces by urging the bodily sickness which she had on
            her as an excuse, and thus she was, according to what the members of her household said,
            preserved spotless from him. Now, after a short time the man died, and he left
            everything which he had unto her alone, and she exchanged the things of time for those
            which were everlasting, and she offered herself wholly to God and devoted herself unto
            the things which belonged unto the life which is to come; and thus she lived a life in
            the great chastity of the fear of God, and even the Bishops were put to shame by the
            sight of her. Now the rest of the building (i.e., the edifice of her spiritual
            excellences,) she made perfect in the furnace of the love of voluntary poverty, and
            whatsoever there remained unto her she gave, as it is written, gladly unto the churches,
            and monasteries and houses for receiving poor strangers, and unto the orphans and
            widows; and she abode continually in the church and served God, and awaited the hope
            which was to come.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
