<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Monk Misericors</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_49"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_49
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Monk [<persName>Misericors</persName>] who lived in <placeName>Ancyra</placeName></head>
         <p>And moreover, we found in this city a certain monk, and we met him at the time when he
            had [just] received the laying on of hands as an elder; formerly he had been a
            husbandman, but he had laboured in the life of a solitary recluse (or monk) for twenty
            years, and he had lived in close intercourse with the <pb n="254"/>Bishop of the city, who was a holy
            man. He was such a benevolent man that even in the night time he would go roundabout and
            visit those who were poor and needy, and he was so indefatigable in his work that he
            neglected neither the prison-house, nor the house of the sick (i.e., hospital), nor the
            houses of the rich and poor, but he helped every one. He urged the rich with words which
            were full of mercy, and exhorted them to fair deeds, and he toiled with anxious care on
            behalf of the poor and needy, in respect of those things which were meet for them. Those
            who were struggling in contention he brought nigh unto peace, and those who were naked
            he clothed with raiment, and he laboured for the sick and brought them the bindings up
            which conduced to [their] healing. Now there existed in this city of <placeName>Ancyra</placeName> that which
            existeth rightly in large cities, that is to say, in the porch of the church thereof
            there lay a great number of poor folk, who were in the habit of going about begging for
            their daily bread, and among them were certain men who had wives; and it fell out on the
            night of a certain day that one of these women was about to give birth to a child. And
            by reason of the pain which was darting through her, and the severe anguish of the
            birth-pangs, she cried out loudly, and the blessed man heard her outcries from the
            church as he was praying; and the blessed man ceased praying, and went forth to see
            [what was happening], although it was winter. And seeing that there was no man nigh unto
            her in her necessity, he himself filled the place of midwife, and he abhorred not the
            shame which attacheth unto those who give birth to children; for the great act of
            lovingkindness which he was about to perform did not grant unto him the perception of
            such things.</p>
         <pb n="255"/>
         <p>Now of this blessed man the garments (or possessions) were so utterly poor that they
            were worth nothing at all, for by reason of the great lovingkindness which dwelt in him
            he took no pains at all to acquire any possession whatsoever. For if anyone gave him a
            book he straightway went and sold it, and unto those who enquired of him concerning it,
            saying, <quote>Why didst thou sell [the book]?</quote> he said, <quote>How am I to persuade the Master (or
            Teacher) that I have in truth learned His handicraft, unless I make use of His testimony
            as to the true [meaning] of His handicraft?</quote> And this holy man thereupon persisteth in
            this course of action until this day, and he hath left behind him unto all those who
            dwell in that country a never-fading remembrance. And he is happy in the expectation of
            the good things which are for ever, and he waiteth to receive the reward of the labours
            of his triumphs in the kingdom from Him Who said, <quote>I was an hungered and ye gave Me to
            eat. I was naked and ye clothed Me</quote> (St. Matthew 25:35, 36).</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
