<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of John of Lycus</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_50"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_50
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of <persName>John of <placeName>Lycus</placeName></persName>, a City of the <placeName>Thebaid</placeName></head>
         <p><persName>John</persName>, who lived in the city of <placeName>Lycus</placeName>, and who had learned in his youth the craft of the
            carpenter, and whose brother was a dyer, afterwards, when he was about five and twenty
            years old, took upon himself the garb of monkhood; and having lived in divers
            monasteries for five years, he finally departed by himself to the mountain which is in
            <placeName>Lycus</placeName>, to the lofty eminence which is on the top of the mountain, and made three cells
            for himself there. Now he built and <pb n="256"/>prepared these for himself in the first year after
            he went to the mountain and went up into it. The first cell was for the needs of the
            body, in the second he laboured at the work of his hands and took his food, and in the
            third he said his prayers, and during the three (or thirty) years in which he was in
            seclusion there he was wont to receive whatsoever was necessary for him through the
            window from him that ministered unto him.</p>
         <p>Now this blessed man was worthy [to receive] from God the gift of being able to declare
            things before they came to pass, and on several occasions he made known things before
            they happened unto the blessed Emperor <persName>Theodosius</persName>, I mean he foretold that he would
            conquer <persName>Maximus</persName> the rebel and would return from <placeName>Gallia</placeName>, and he also announced to him
            beforehand concerning the defeat of <persName>Eugenius</persName> the rebel, and thus the fame of this holy
            man went forth greatly, and he was held to be a man of spiritual excellence. Now
            therefore when we were in the desert of <placeName>Nitria</placeName>, I and the members of the following of
            the blessed <persName>Origen</persName> wished to gain exact information concerning the state of spiritual
            excellence to which the man [had attained]. Thereupon the blessed <persName>Evagrius</persName> said, <quote>I am
            very desirous of learning from some one who is skilled in the investigation of the mind
            and understanding what manner of man [<persName>John of <placeName>Lycus</placeName></persName>] is; for although I myself am unable
            to see him, still I can learn from another man [concerning] his qualities of excellence
            if he be able to narrate them, but I cannot go so far as [his] mountain.</quote> Now when I had
            heard these things I said nothing whatsoever to any man, and I held my peace for a day,
            but on the morrow I shut up my cell, and having confided myself <pb n="257"/>to the hands of God I
            set out on my journey to go to the <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName>, where I arrived after eighteen days, on some
            of which I walked on my feet, and on others I sailed on the river. For it was the period
            of the year when the river riseth, and when many folk fall sick, the which also happened
            unto me. And when I had gone [to <persName>John of <placeName>Lycus</placeName></persName>] I found that he had shut himself up in
            the place wherein he lived in seclusion, and I took up my abode with the brethren in a
            great house which contained about one hundred men, and which the brethren had built a
            long time; for though they shut in <persName>John</persName> during the other days of the week on Saturday
            and Sunday they used to open his window.</p>
         <p>When therefore I had learned the rule concerning his seclusion, I waited until the
            Saturday, and at the second hour I drew nigh and found him sitting in the opening in the
            wall (or window), wherein he waited to administer comfort and consolation unto those who
            thronged unto him. And having saluted me he said unto me through an interpreter, <quote>Whence
            art thou, my son? And why hast thou come? Thou appearest to me to belong unto the
            congregation of <persName>Evagrius</persName>.</quote> And I said unto him, <quote>I am a stranger from [the country of]
            the Galatians,</quote> and I confessed that I also belonged unto those who were the followers
            of <persName>Evagrius</persName>. Now whilst we were conversing together behold, <persName>Alipius</persName>, the governor of the
            country, came unto him, and as the governor turned to him <persName>John</persName> ceased to talk to me and
            I left them for a little space and gave them opportunity to talk, and I rose up [and
            departed] from the mountain. And when they had passed much time in their converse I
            became impatient and angry, and I murmured against that excellent old man because it
            seemed as if he had treated me lightly <pb n="258"/>and had paid honour to the governor; and being
            offended in my mind at this [treatment] I made up my mind to go away because of his
            disregard of me. Then <persName>John</persName> called unto his interpreter, whose name was <persName>Theodore</persName>, and
            said unto him, <quote>Go and say unto that brother, <quote>Be not angry and impatient, for I will
            dismiss the governor immediately, and [then] I will speak with thee.</quote> </quote> Thus it appeared
            to me that, like a spiritual being, he had knowledge of secret things, and I made up my
            mind to remain.</p>
         <p>And when the governor had departed <persName>John</persName> called unto me and said unto me, <quote>My son, why
            wast thou vexed with me? What hast thou found which is worthy of [being considered] an
            offence? Thou hast imagined things which are not to be found in me, and which are not
            creditable unto thyself. Dost thou not know that it is written, <quote>Those that are whole
            have no need of a physician (St. Matthew 9:12; St. Mark 2:17; St. Luke 5:31); only those
            who are in very evil case have need of him.</quote> Thee I can find whensoever I wish, and if I
            myself do not comfort thee the brethren and the other fathers will do so. But this
            governor who hath come to us is tightly bound unto <persName>the Calumniator</persName> by means of the
            affairs of this world, and, having obtained respite for a brief space from the vain
            labour of [his] abominable servitude, he fleeth like a slave from his master and cometh
            to be helped; therefore it would not be seemly to leave him, and to be constant in
            attention unto thee, for thou art at all seasons occupied with the cultivating of thy
            life.</quote></p>
         <p>And having said these things I entreated him to forgive me, and I became certain in my
            mind that he was a spiritual man. Then with a smile he patted my left cheek with his
            right hand, and said unto me, <quote>Many temptations will rise up for thee to endure, and
               moreover, for many years [past] thou hast struggled <pb n="259"/>to go forth from the desert, and
            thou strugglest even to this day, but thou hast been afraid; and the causes thereof,
            which were thought [by thee to arise from] the fear of God, hath the Evil One himself
            sowed in thy mind; and although thou didst drive away thy thought from thee thou hast
            kept him with thee. For he sowed in thee the thought of desire, which was also pleasant
            unto thee, that is to say, thou didst care greatly to bring out of the world thy father
            and also thy sister that they might take upon themselves the garb of the monastic life.
            Now there still remain to thy father seven other years of life, therefore continue to
            abide in the desert, and do not on account of these thoughts desire to go to thy
            kinsfolk, for it is written, <quote>No man who hath put his hand on the ploughshare and
            looketh back is useful to the kingdom of heaven</quote> </quote> (St. Luke 9:62). Now, therefore,
            being helped by these words whereby I triumphed I gave thanks and praise unto God Who
            had quieted and laid to rest in me the cause which was urging me to go forth from the
            desert.</p>
         <p>Then afterwards he said unto me with a smile, <quote>Wishest thou to become a bishop?</quote> And I
            said unto him, <quote>I have already been made one</quote>; and he said unto me, <quote>Where?</quote> Then I
            answered and said unto him, <quote>I am the bishop of the public eating-houses, and of the
            taverns, and of tables, and of wine-pots, for I am a visitor of them. And if the wine
            hath gone sour I know enough to observe it, and that which is fit [to drink] I drink.
            Similarly I visit the cooking pot and if it needeth salt, or any seasoning whatsoever, I
            season it with sauces and then I eat thereof. For this, that is to say, my visiting, is
            my episcopate, and it is the love of the belly and gluttony which hath <pb n="260"/>made me the
            visitor of these.</quote> And with a smile he said unto me further, <quote>Quit these [words] of
            jesting, for a bishop thou must needs be, and thou wilt have to labour and to be
            troubled greatly; now if thou wishest to flee from tribulations and temptations go not
            forth from the desert, for in the desert no man will make thee a bishop.</quote></p>
         <p>And when I had departed from him I came to the desert, that is, to my place wherein I
            dwelt, and having related these things unto the blessed fathers, who after two months
            went and held intercourse with him, I forgot his words. And three years afterwards I
            fell sick with a sore sickness which was caused by my kidneys and stomach, and I was
            sent to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> by the brethren who believed that I was collecting water (i.e.,
            becoming dropsical), and the physicians counselled me to leave <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and for the
            sake of the air (or climate) to go to <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, where the air (or climate) was
            temperate and light and would be beneficial to my body. From <placeName>Palestine</placeName> I went to
            <placeName>Bithynia</placeName>, where, for what reason I know not, whether by the care and solicitude of men,
            or whether by the Will of God, Who is exalted above all things, I was held to be worthy
            of the laying on of hands for the episcopacy, which was far above my deserts, and I
            became an associate in the temptation (or trial) which rose up against the blessed <persName>John
            Chrysostom</persName>, Bishop of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. And having been secluded for a period of about
            eleven months in a dark cell I remembered that blessed man who had told me of the things
            which had happened to me before they came to pass. Now the blessed man <persName>John</persName> related the
            things unto me, according to my opinion, that by means of the narrative he might incite
            my mind and bring me to continue to dwell in the desert; and he said unto me, <pb n="261"/><quote>Behold, I
            have passed eight and forty years in this cell, and I have never seen the face of a
            woman [during the whole time], and no man hath either seen me eat or drink.</quote></p>
         <p>Now the handmaiden of <persName>Christ</persName> <persName>Poemenia</persName> came unto the blessed man and begged that she might
            see him, but the blessed man would not allow her to do so; and he sent unto her other
            spiritual words to give her consolation, and he commanded her that when she was going
            down from the <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName> she should not turn aside to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, saying, that if she did
            so, she would certainly fall into temptations. But <persName>Poemenia</persName>, forgetting this [advice] and
            never letting it enter her mind [again], turned aside to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> that she might see
            the city, and on the way, by the side of the city <placeName>Nicius</placeName>, she stopped her ship that she
            might rest herself. And when her servants had disembarked, through some untoward
            circumstance strife broke out between them and the people of the country, who were
            truculent men, and they cut off a finger of one believing man, and another they killed,
            and without knowing it they drowned the holy Bishop <persName>Dionysius</persName> in the river. And they
            made the venerable woman to endure many revilings and threatened to do much violence
            unto her; and they beat all her servants with many severe stripes, and they would hardly
            allow them to proceed on their way.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
