<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Possidonius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_51"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_51
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed Man Possidonius</head>
         <p>Now the things which [are narrated] concerning the holy man Possidonius the Theban are
            so many that it is impossible to describe them all; he was so gentle, and gracious, and
            patient, and enduring, and his soul had so much goodness in it that I do not know that I
            ever met another man who was like unto him. For I lived with him in Bethlehem for a
            year, at the time he was living beyond the Monastery of the Shepherds, which was close
            to the town, and I observed in him many qualities of excellence, of which I will relate
            [an example of] one or two. He told me one day when I was living by the side of
            Porphyrites, [saying], <quote>I have not spoken to a man for a whole year, and I have not
            heard the speech of one. I have not eaten bread, but the insides of palm leaves soaked
            in water and, whenever I could find it, wild honey. Once, however, the time came when
            these things failed me, and I was in sore tribulation because of it. And I went forth
            from the cave that I might go to the habitations of men, and having journeyed on the
            whole day I was scarcely two miles distant from the cave. And I turned [and looked]
            behind me, and I saw, as it were, a horseman whose appearance resembled that of a
            knight, and he had upon his head the similitude of a helmet, and thinking that he was a
            Roman I turned back to the cave, and I found outside it a basket of grapes and new, ripe
            figs, and I took them and went with them into the cave rejoicing; and that food sufficed
            to be a consolation unto me for a period of two months.</quote></p>
         <p>And the blessed man wrought in Bethlehem the following miracle. A certain woman had
            conceived, and she was possessed of an unclean spirit, and being near to the bringing
            forth of her child she was greatly afflicted by birth pangs and was violently tortured
            by that spirit; and as she was writhing by reason of the workings of that devil, her
            husband came and entreated the holy man to go and pray over her, and we went into [her
            house] therefore that we might pray together. And having stood up and prayed, after he
            had knelt down twice he cast out that unclean spirit; when he stood up he said unto us,
            <quote>Pray ye, for straightway the devil shall go forth.</quote> But there was a certain sign, the
            fulfilment of which [he wished] to shew us, and therefore when that devil had gone
            forth, he overturned the whole of the courtyard wall unto its very foundations; now that
            woman had not spoken a word for a period of about six years, but after that devil had
            gone forth she brought forth her child and spake.</p>
         <p>And, moreover, I also saw [an example] of the prophecy of this blessed man. There was a
            certain elder, whose name was Hieronymus, who dwelt in these parts, and he was
            exceedingly well versed in the art and practice of grammar and of eloquence, and he was
            greatly skilled in the Latin language; but he possessed the vices of envy and
            evil-eyedness to such a degree that the excellence of his very great skill and ability
            was entirely hidden. Now the blessed man Possidonius had dwelt with him for many days,
            and he told me that the free-woman Paula, who had taken care of him, departed from this
            world before her time in order that she might escape from his envy, and, according to my
            opinion, it was on account of this man that none of the holy men would live in these
            districts; and the envy of this man continued to such a degree that it overtook his own
            brother, which thing took place even as he had foretold. And he also persecuted the
            blessed man Oxyperentius, who came from Italy, and the wonderful men, Peter the Egyptian
            and Simeon, who were seen by me. And Possidonius the Great himself told me that for the
            whole period of forty years he had not tasted food made of bread, and that wrath against
            any man did not abide with him as long as the half of the day.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
