<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Chronius of Phoenix</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_52"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_52
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of Chronius who was from the Village Of Phœnix</head>
         <p>There was a certain man whose name was Chronius, who came from the village which was
            called Tomârtâ (i.e., Phœnix) which was nigh unto the desert; and when he had gone away
            a little distance from human habitations, and had departed from his village, having
            measured out along the road with his right foot about fifteen thousand paces, he prayed
            and dug in that spot a pit, and he found [therein] good and sweet water. Now the well
            was about seven fathoms in depth; and he built there a little habitation wherein to
            dwell, and from the day wherein he shut himself up in that place, he prayed to God that
            he might never return to a region inhabited by men. Now when he had dwelt there some few
            years, he was esteemed worthy to become a priest unto the brotherhood, for there were
            gathered together unto him about two hundred brethren. And these excellent things are
            said concerning him: that during the whole of the period of sixty years, wherein he was
            performing the ministrations of the altar, he never once went out of the desert, and
            that he never ate bread which he had not [earned by] the labour of his hands.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
