<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Diocles</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_56"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_56
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of <persName>Diocles</persName></head>
         <p>This man <persName>Diocles</persName> was originally [one] of those who were greatly skilled in grammar, but
            afterwards he became learned in philosophy. And having arrived at the period of the
            twenty-eighth year of his life, he was called by the Grace of God, and he departed and
            removed himself from the house of instruction, and delivered himself over to the promise
            of <persName>Christ</persName>; and having dwelt in caves for the space of thirty-five years, he said unto
            us, <quote>The mind which removeth itself from the meditation of God falleth into lust.</quote> Now
            he used to say that lust was that of a savage, animal, and bestial character, for he
            said unto us, <quote>The mind which falleth away from the meditation of God becometh either a
            devil or a beast</quote>; and we asked him to explain this saying unto us, and he did so, and
            said, <quote>The mind which maketh itself to be remote from the contemplation of God must,
            perforce, be delivered over either to the devil of lust, <pb n="276"/>who leadeth [it] into
            lasciviousness, or to the evil devil of wrath, wherefrom are produced the animal
            passions.</quote> And he said, <quote>The feeling of lasciviousness is a bestial thing, but the
            feeling of wrath appertaineth to the devil.</quote> And making answer I said unto him, <quote>How is
            it possible for the human mind to be with God continually and uninterruptedly?</quote> And he
            said, <quote>The mind of that soul which liveth in the thought or the fear of God, no matter
            what it may be, is with God.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
