<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Innocent the Priest</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_60"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_60
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of <persName>Innocent</persName> the Priest</head>
         <p>Concerning the matters of the blessed priest <persName>Innocent</persName>, who [lived] in the Mount of
            Olives, I think that thou must have heard from many people, but thou mayest also learn
            from us not a few things, for we lived with him for a period of three years. Now
            therefore this man was exceedingly simple, and he was [one] of the nobles of the palace
            in the kingdom of the Emperor <persName>Constantine</persName>; he withdrew himself from the partnership of
            marriage, but he had a son whose name was Paule, who served in the household [of the
            Emperor]; and this son was caught in a transgression with the daughter of a certain
            priest, and <persName>Innocent</persName> was exceedingly wroth with him. Then <persName>Innocent</persName> made entreaty unto
            God, saying, <quote>O our Lord, give thou unto him such a spirit that he will not be able to
            find time to sin in the lust of the body,</quote> for he thought that it would be better and
            more excellent in every way for his son to be delivered over to a devil rather than to
            fornication. And this actually came to pass to the youth, and he liveth to this day in
            <placeName>the Mount of Olives</placeName> loaded with irons, and admonished by a devil. Now this man <persName>Innocent</persName>,
            <persName>the father of <persName>Paule</persName></persName>, because he was of a most merciful disposition—though if I were to
            tell [the whole truth] I should say that he appeared to me to be lacking in sense—on
            very many occasions stole [things] and hid them from the brethren, and gave them unto
            those who were in want; but he was a simple man and had no wickedness in him; and he was
            held to be worthy of the gift [of the possession of power] over devils.</p>
         <p>For a certain maiden, in whom was a devil, came unto him, and whilst we were looking at
            her the <pb n="281"/>devil smote her, and threw her down upon the ground and made her body to writhe
            and twist about; and when I saw [this] I wished to dismiss that maiden in order that she
            might go to her mother, because, on account of the cruelty (or violence) of that devil,
            I thought that she could never be healed. And whilst I was pondering those things the
            old man <persName>Innocent</persName> came, and he saw her mother standing, and weeping, and tearing her face
            with her nails, and plucking out her hair, because of the great madness, and the
            gnashing of the teeth, and the contortions of her daughter. When, therefore, that
            blessed old man saw her, his mercy revealed itself because he was grieved on account of
            her tribulation, and he took the maiden, and went into his martyrium, which he himself
            had built, and wherein was preserved a blessed [relic] of <persName>Saint John the Baptist</persName>, and
            having prayed there and made supplication unto God from the third unto the ninth hour,
            he gave the maiden [back] to her mother, and she was healed on that day, and he drove
            away from her the devil and [his] struggles [with her]. Now the strugglings and
            contortions of the maiden were such that when she spat, she spat upon her side [instead
            of away from her]; to this extent was her body twisted.</p>
         <p>And, again, a certain old woman lost a sheep, and she came to him weeping [about it],
            and he took her, and said unto her, <quote>Shew me the place where thou didst lose it</quote>; and
            they came, therefore, to a place which was near the grave of Lazarus, where he stood up
            and prayed. Now certain boys had stolen the sheep and had already killed it. And
            <persName>Innocent</persName> having prayed, and the boys being unwilling to confess that the flesh of the
            sheep was buried in a vineyard, a raven suddenly appeared, though wherefrom no man
            knoweth, which had taken a piece of flesh from the carcass, and stood over the place
            where it was; and when the old man saw this he perceived that the sheep was buried
            there. Then those boys fell down and did <pb n="282"/>homage to him, and they confessed that they had
            taken the sheep, and paid the price thereof to its mistress.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
