<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Elpidius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_61"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_61
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed <persName>Elpidius</persName></head>
         <p>In those caves which, in ancient times, certain men had hewn out of the rock in the
            valley of the river near <placeName>Jericho</placeName>, wherein those who had fled from before <persName>Joshua</persName>, the son
            of <persName>Nun</persName>, had gone up and hidden themselves, there dwelt <persName>Elpidius</persName>; now he was a
            Cappadocian, who had been converted in the monastery of <persName>Timothy the Chorepiskopos</persName>, and
            he was a wonderful man and was also held to be worthy of consecration to the priesthood.
            And he came and dwelt in one of these caves, and he shewed such patient persistence in
            his self-abnegation, that he surpassed and eclipsed many [thereby]; for he followed for
            five and twenty years his rule of life, and during that time he only ate food on the
            Sabbath day, and on the First Day of the week, and he dwelt like the chief and the king
            of the bees among the cells of the whole brotherhood. And he used to rise up continually
            during the night and pray; and I myself also dwelt with him. And he made that mountain
            to be so peaceful and to contain so many inhabitants that it resembled a city, and
            during the night season a man might see the various works, and the labours of all kinds
            which appertain to the ascetic life, being performed there. One night, when this man
            <persName>Elpidius</persName> was reciting the service, now we were with him, a scorpion stung him, and he
            crushed the insect, without either leaving the place where he was or being in any way  
            moved as a man usually is when he is suffering from the sting of a scorpion. And one day
            as he was holding in his <pb n="282"/>hand a vine branch, a certain brother took it away from him;
            and as he was sitting by the side of the mountain, he dug a hole and pushed the vine
            branch into it, like a man who is planting [vines]; and although it was not the time for
            planting, the vine branch sprouted, and grew very large, and spread its branches abroad
            until it covered the whole church. Now the name of that brother was <persName>Aenesius</persName>, a wonderful
            man.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
