<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Eustathius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_62"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_62
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed Man <persName>Eustathius</persName></head>
         <p><persName>Eustathius</persName> was a brother of <persName>Elpidius</persName> whom [we have mentioned] above, and this man
            followed so strenuously after the acquisition of impassibility, and made his body so dry
            (i.e., emaciated) by the labours of vigilant prayer, that the [light of] the sun could
            be seen between his ribs. And of him the following story is told by the brethren who
            were continually with him, that is to say by his disciples: He never turned himself
            towards the west, because close by the side of the door of his cave was a mountain
            which, because of its mighty bulk, was very hard [to ascend]; and he never looked at the
            sun after the sixth hour of the day, because the door of his cell was hidden by the
            shadow of the mountain so long as the sun was declining towards its place of setting.
            And moreover he could never see those stars which appear in the western part of the sky,
            and for five and twenty years from the time when he entered the cave wherein he dwelt he
            never went down from the mountain.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
