<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Sisinnius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_63"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_63
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed Man Sisinnius</head>
         <p>Now this holy man Elpidius had a certain disciple whose name was Sisinnius, who was a
            slave by birth, though a free man in the faith; by race he was a Cappadocian, and it is
            necessary that we should make known the fact that he was so, for the sake of the
            glorifying of Christ Who hath made us worthy to be accounted His kinsmen, and to be
            exalted to that true family, which is full of happiness, of the kingdom of heaven. Now
            therefore when this man Sisinnius had passed some time with Elpidius, and had struggled
            to lead the ascetic life strenuously for a period of seven years, he at length shut
            himself in a grave for three years, and he endured such privations therein that neither
            by day nor by night did he sit or lie down, and he never went out here from. And this
            man was held to be worthy of possessing the gift of authority over devils, and now that
            he hath come into his own country he hath been held to be worthy of the gift of the
            priesthood; and he hath made congregations of men and of women, which, according to a
            sure testimony, lead lives of purity and chastity. He hath trampled upon the lust which
            is in men, and he hath bridled the voluptuousness of the women, so that there hath been
            fulfilled that which is written, <quote>In Christ Jesus there is neither male nor female</quote>
            (Galatians 3:28). And he was also a great lover of strangers and of voluntary poverty,
            which was a reproach unto those who were rich and miserly.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
