<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Sabas of Jericho</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_66"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_66
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of Sabas, the Layman of Jericho</head>
         <p>And there was a certain layman from Jericho whose name was Sabas, and he had a wife, and
            this man loved the monks so much that during the night season he used to go round about
            in the desert, and pass by the cells of the solitary monks therein, and outside the cell
            and habitation of each one of them he would set down a bushel of dates and vegetables,
            which would be sufficient for his wants, for the monks who lived by the side of the
            Jordan did not eat bread, and thus this man Sabas supplied the wants of the monks. One
            day as he was carrying along a load [of food] for the usual needs of the monks, through
            the operation of the Evil One, who is the Adversary of the monks, a lion met him, which
            terrified him, and wished to make him to cease from his ministrations to those holy men,
            and schemed to prevent him from performing his benevolent intent for their comfort. And
            the lion having overtaken him about a mile from the place where the monks were, and
            having seized him by his hand in order to turn him aside from his business, He Who by
            the hand of Daniel shut the mouth[s] of the lions, shut the mouth of this lion also
            (Daniel 6:22; Hebrews 11:33), and the beast did this lover of alms no harm whatsoever;
            and although the lion was exceedingly hungry he only took a very little of the things
            which Sabas was carrying for the old men, and then he departed. And it is manifest that
            He Who gave this man his life also satisfied the hunger of the lion.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
