<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Serapion of the Girdle</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_67"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_67
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Of the Blessed Man Serapion of the Girdle</head>
         <p>And again there was a certain blessed man whose name was Serapion, who was called
            Serapion of the <quote>girdle,</quote> because during his whole life he neither put on nor was
            clothed with anything except the girdle wherewith he was girt about; and he led a life
            of the strictest self-denial and poverty. And though he was a wholly unlearned man he
            could repeat all the Scriptures by heart. And by reason of the greatness of his
            self-denial and the repetition of the Scriptures he was unable to live in a cell,
            because he could not make use of anything which belonged to [this] world; but he went
            round about at all seasons and taught the multitudes, and he sold himself voluntarily,
            and he preached, and taught, and turned many people unto God. And this form of
            self-denial was of his own choosing, and [it was by such means as this that he made] his
            preparation [for heaven]; now there are very many ways of leading a stern life of
            self-denial. And many of the venerable fathers relate concerning him that on one
            occasion he took a fellow monk, who sold him to some comic actors for twenty dînârs in a
            city of the heathen, and having received these dînârs he tied them up [in a bag] and
            sealed them, and kept them carefully; and then he became subject to and ministered in
            all humility to those actors who had bought him until he had taught them and made them
            Christians, and had freed them from following the business of the theatre. And he never
            ate anything except dry bread and water, and his mouth never once ceased from uttering
            [the words of] the Scriptures.</p>
         <p>Now the man [who was the master of the actors] was the first to become converted and
            enlightened by the word of God, and the next was his wife, and finally their whole house
            was converted. During the first years after the actors had bought him, and when they did
            not know who he was, he used to wash their feet with his hands, and having taught them
            and baptized them he made them to be remote from their occupation in the theatre, and
            they led a God-fearing life in all righteousness; and they held him in reverence, and
            honoured him, and marvelled at his radiant life. Finally they said unto him, <quote>Come, O
            our brother, we will set thee free from this servitude, even as thou hast set us free
            from the slavery of heathenism.</quote> Then he answered and said unto them, <quote>Since God hath
            helped [me], and your souls have been set free and they have life, I will tell you my
            story (or thing) and my contending. I undertook this kind of work in order that your
            souls might have life. By race I am an Egyptian, and a free man [but] I am a monk
            [vowed] to self-denial and poverty, and for the sake of our Lord I sold myself to you in
            order that your souls might be set free from the impurity of this world; since now our
            Lord hath worked through my meekness, and your souls live, take your gold, and I will go
            to another place, so that I may be able to benefit others also.</quote> And they begged and
            entreated him, saying, <quote>Remain with us, and thou shalt be unto us a father and a master,
            and a director</quote>; but he would not hearken unto their entreaty. And again they answered
            and said unto him, <quote>Give the gold to the poor, and let it be a pledge of life for us;
            and we entreat thee to see us if it be only once a year.</quote></p>
         <p>Then, this man having gone round about came to Hellas, and stayed in Athens three days,
            and no man gave him a morsel of bread; now he carried nothing with him, neither purse,
            nor wallet, nor head-cloak, nor anything whatsoever. And when the fourth day had come,
            he waxed exceedingly hungry, and he went and stood up upon a certain high place where
            all the free men of the city were gathered together, and he began to clap his hands, and
            to cry out with a loud voice, saying, <quote>O men of Athens, send [help].</quote> And at [the sound
            of] his voice they all marvelled, and the free men and the soldiers ran to him, and said
            unto him, <quote>What aileth thee? Whence comest thou? What hath happened unto these?</quote> Then he
            answered and said unto them, <quote>By race I am an Egyptian, and being a long way from my
            true country I have fallen into the hands of three creditors; now two of these have
            departed from me, having taken that which was theirs, and now they have no debt against
            me about which to chide me, but the third will not leave me.</quote></p>
         <p>And the philosophers made enquiries of him who these creditors were, and they said unto
            him, <quote>Shew us who thy creditors are, and who it is that is afflicting thee, and we will
            entreat them [to desist]; shew us who they are, so that we may help thee.</quote> And he
            answered and said unto them, <quote>From my youth up the love of money, and fornication, and
            the appetite of the belly have oppressed me; from the first two of these, that is, the
            love of money and fornication, I have been freed, and they no longer oppress me, but I
            am wholly unable to set myself free from the appetite of the belly. Behold, it is now
            the fourth day since I have eaten anything and the belly constraineth me, for it
            demandeth that which is its usual debt, and unless this debt [be paid] I shall not be
            able to live.</quote> Then certain of the philosophers thought that he had schemed this crafty
            device in order that he might gain some benefit, and one of them took a dînâr and gave
            it unto him, and having taken it he spent [part of] it in buying bread in their
            presence; and he took one [loaf of] bread, and straightway departed from the city, and
            did not come back to it again. Thus the philosophers knew that he was indeed a wonderful
            man, and they paid the price of the loaf of bread which he had taken, and received back
            the dînâr.</p>
         <p>And having departed to another city he heard there concerning a certain other man, who
            was the chief of the whole city, and who was a Manichaean, with all his house, and who
            had several associates [in the city]. Then the monk, according to his former plan, sold
            himself to this Manichaean, and in two years he was able to turn this man and his wife
            [from their error], and to bring them into the Catholic Church; and after they had
            learned who he was, they never again regarded him as a slave, but they honoured him as a
            father, and as a master, and they ascribed praise unto God.</p>
         <p>And on another occasion he determined to go to Rome, and he embarked in a ship which was
            going thither that he might go with them (i.e., with the sailors). Now when the sailors
            of the ship saw that he boldly embarked in the ship carrying nothing with him, neither
            bread, nor anything [else], nor provisions for the journey, they thought that one of
            their number must have taken his baggage and placed it in the ship, and because of this
            thought they received him unquestioningly. And having embarked, when the sailors had
            sailed from Alexandria [a distance of] about five hundred stadia, each one of those who
            were sitting in the ship began at the time of sunset to eat, and the sailors also ate in
            their presence; and they observed that the monk did not eat on the first day, and
            thought that [he did not do so] because of sea-sickness, and thus also was it on the
            second day, and on the third day, and on the fourth day. Now on the fifth day, whilst
            all those who were on the ship were eating their meal he sat in his place and was
            silent, and as they were looking at him they said, <quote>Why dost thou not eat?</quote> and he
            replied, <quote>I have nothing [to eat].</quote> Then they began to make enquiries and to cry out
            among themselves, <quote>Who among you has taken his things, or his provisions for the way?</quote>
            And when they saw that no man had taken anything from him [they began to] dispute with
            him, and to say unto him, <quote>O man, how is it that thou hast embarked on the ship without
            provisions and money? Where wilt thou obtain the money to give us for thy passage?</quote> And
            he said unto them, <quote>I have thought nothing whatsoever about it, [for] an Egyptian has no
            anxious care about anything; but carry me back whence ye took me and cast me out [if you
            wish].</quote> Now even if he had given them one hundred dînârs they would not have been able
            to take him back [to Alexandria], and he therefore remained in the ship, and they fed
            him until he arrived in Rome. And having come to Rome he made enquiries and learned what
            monk or nun was there, and he found Rumnîn (or Dômnîn), the disciple of Evagrius, whose
            bed, after his death, cured every kind of sickness. And having seen him, and spoken with
            him he was greatly edified by him, for he was a man who was greatly skilled in the
            labours of the ascetic life, and in speech, and in knowledge, and he learned from him
            what monk, and nuns were in Rome, in order that he might see them.</p>
         <p>[Here some editor of Palladius remarks, <quote>In another manuscript the following is
            written</quote>:]</p>
         <p>And the venerable fathers relate concerning him that he once heard that there was in the
            city of Rome a certain nun who led a life of the strictest seclusion, who had never seen
            a man, and who used to think concerning herself that she was perfect. Then this blessed
            man threw himself into a ship and came to Rome, and having learned where she lived he
            went and spake with the old woman who ministered unto her, and said unto her, <quote>Get thee
            in and say unto the virgin, I desire to see thee most eagerly, because God hath sent me
            unto thee</quote>; and he waited two days and then saw her. And when he saw her he said unto
            her, <quote>Sit thee down,</quote> and she said unto him, <quote>I will not sit down, but will depart.</quote> And
            he said unto her, <quote>Whither goest thou?</quote> and she said unto him, <quote>To God.</quote> And he said
            unto her, <quote>Art thou living or dead?</quote> And she said unto him, <quote>I believe, by God, that I
            am dead, for who that liveth in the body is not able to depart [therefrom]?</quote> And he said
            unto her, <quote>If thou art dead, as thou sayest, do thou that which I do</quote>; and she said unto
            him, <quote>Tell me what can happen, and I will do it.</quote> And again he said unto her, <quote>To one
            who is dead unto the world it is easy to do everything except commit sin,</quote> and he
            further said unto her, <quote>Come down, and get thee out of thine house</quote>; then she said unto
            him, <quote>I have not gone out of it for five and twenty years, why should I go out of it
            now?</quote> And he said unto her, <quote>If thou art indeed dead unto the world, and the world is
            dead unto thee, it is the same thing unto thee whether thou goest forth or dost not go
            forth; come, get thee out.</quote> And she went out.</p>
         <p>And after she had gone forth, she followed him to a certain church, and he said unto her
            in the church, <quote>If thou wishest me to believe that thou art dead to the world and art
            not alive, in order that thou mayest be pleasing unto the children of men, do what I do,
            and then I will believe thee, and I shall know that thou art a dead woman, even as thou
            sayest.</quote> And she said unto him, <quote>Tell me what it is meet for me to do, and I will do
            it.</quote> Then he said unto her, <quote>Cast off thy garments and put [them] on thy head, and walk
            through the midst of the city, and I will do likewise, and will go in front of thee in
            this guise.</quote> And the nun said unto him, <quote>I should offend many folk by such a remarkable
            act as this, and then they would say, <quote>This woman hath gone mad, and hath a devil.</quote> </quote>
            And he said unto her, <quote>What need hast thou to consider [their words] even if they should
            say, <quote>She hath gone mad, and hath a devil?</quote> For, according to what thou thyself sayest,
            thou art a dead woman unto them.</quote> And the nun said unto him, <quote>If there be any other
            thing [except this] tell me, for I cannot come to such a measure of disgrace as this.</quote>
            Then he said unto her, <quote>Do not imagine in thy mind that thou art more perfect than
            anyone else, or that thou art dead to the world; for I am far more dead to the world
            than thou art, and I can show thee that I am indeed so, and that I can boldly do this
            thing without [feeling] shame or disgrace.</quote> Then having broken her spirit and humbled
            her pride, he departed from her. And there were many things of the same kind which this
            same Serapion did in the world, for he despised both worldly shame and the glory which
            passeth away; he died at the age of sixty years, and was buried at a good old age, being
            adorned with all virtues.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
