<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Eulogius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_68"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_1/The_Paradise_of_Palladius/The_Histories_of_the_Holy_Men/History_68
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>The Triumph of the Blessed Man <persName>Eulogius</persName>, who ministered unto the <persName>Arian</persName>, whose Body
            was destroyed for the sake of <persName>Christ</persName></head>
         <p>The following story was related unto me by <persName>Cronius</persName>, the priest of <placeName>Nitria</placeName>, [who
            said]:—When I was a young man I abhorred the monastery, and I fled from it, and from the
            head of the monastery <pb n="294"/>who was my instructor, and having lost my way and gone round
            about, I came unto <placeName>the Monastery of Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName></placeName>; now he used to dwell between the
            mountains of <placeName>Babylon</placeName> and <placeName>Herakleia</placeName>, in a parched desert which led to the <placeName>Red Sea</placeName>, about
            thirty miles from the river [Nile], and I was there in that monastery wherein dwelt
            those disciples of his who buried him when he died, now their names were <persName>Macarius</persName> and
            <persName>Amatus</persName>, in a place which was called <placeName>Espîr</placeName>. And I remained there for five days, so that I
            might be able to see the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, for they used to say that he was in the habit
            of coming to this monastery from the Inner Desert once every five, or ten, or twenty
            days, according as God directed and brought him, to give help unto the souls who
            thronged into his monastery, and who awaited him there, in order that they might be
            relieved by him. And the brethren also were assembled there and waited for him also,
            each one of them having his own individual matter [to lay before him].</p>
         <p>Now among them was a certain man from <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, whose name was <persName>Eulogius</persName>, and with him
            was another man, an <persName>Arian</persName>, whose body was destroyed (i.e., he was a leper), and they had
            come because of this matter. And this man <persName>Eulogius</persName> was a scholastic, and he was the most
            educated of all the learned men [of this time], but the love of the living God had
            suddenly come into his mind, and he made himself to be remote from the world, and he
            distributed all the money which he had among the poor, and he left himself only a small
            sum which was just sufficient for his bodily needs, for he was unable to work or to
            enter into a monastery with many monks in it, and besides this lassitude was contending
            with him, and he sought a little companionship.</p>
         <pb n="295"/>
         <p>Now [he went forth] seeking to buy something which he wanted in the city, and he found
            in the market a certain man who was an <persName>Arian</persName>, and whose whole body was destroyed; he had
            neither hands nor feet, but his tongue was sharp, and he employed it unsparingly upon
            every man whom he met. And when <persName>Eulogius</persName> had seen him, and looked at him, he lifted up
            his eyes and his mind towards God, and he prayed and made this covenant between himself
            and God, saying, <quote>O our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, in Thy Name, O my Lord, I will take this man,
            who is sick in his body, and I will relieve [his wants] all the days of my life, so that
            through him my soul may live before Thee; but I beseech Thee to give me power to endure
            in my ministrations to him.</quote> And having prayed, he drew nigh unto the man, and said unto
            him, <quote>I beseech thee, O man, to let me take thee unto my house and to relieve thy
            wants.</quote> And the sick man said unto him, <quote>Why not?</quote> Then <persName>Eulogius</persName> said unto him, <quote>I will
            therefore bring an ass, and carry thee off,</quote> and he promised him [saying], <quote>I …</quote>; and he
            went and brought an ass and carried him to the place where he lived, and he took care of
            him with the greatest diligence. And for a period of fifteen years <persName>Eulogius</persName> relieved his
            wants with the greatest and most careful attention, and he even washed him with his own
            hands, and he did everything he could to alleviate the affliction of his sickness.</p>
         <p>Now after fifteen years a devil began to stir in that <persName>Arian</persName>, and he began to revile
            <persName>Eulogius</persName>, and to offer resistance to him, and he cursed him and hurled after him insults
            and abuse, saying, <quote>O thou runaway [slave], who hast eaten thy lord, thou hast stolen
            the riches of other folk and art spending them upon me, <pb n="296"/>and thou thinkest to have life
            through me! Cast me out into the street, for I wish to eat flesh.</quote> And <persName>Eulogius</persName> brought
            him flesh, and again he cried out, and said, <quote>Thou wilt not persuade me [to remain here]
            by these means; I wish to go forth into the street, and I desire to see the world. By
            Jupiter, carry me out and cast me where thou didst find me. If I only had hands I would
            strangle myself.</quote> Now [he spake] thus through the madness of the devil which was with
            him. Then <persName>Eulogius</persName> rose up and went to the neighbouring monks and said unto them, <quote>What
            shall I do? for this deformed man hath brought me to despair. I would set him free, only
            I have given [my] right hand in covenant to God, and I am afraid [to do so]; but on the
            other hand, if I do not cast him out he will bring upon me bad nights and bitter days.
            What to do with him I know not.</quote> And they said unto him, <quote>[<persName>Anthony</persName>] the Great is still
            alive, go to him; take the man with thee in a ship, and go thou up to him, and carry the
            man to his monastery, and wait there until he cometh from the desert and then tell him
            thy business. And whatsoever word he shall say unto thee thou shalt perform, for God
            shall speak unto thee through him.</quote> Then <persName>Eulogius</persName> was persuaded by them, and he placed
            the man in a small boat, and he carried him to the monastery wherein were the disciples
            of <persName>Anthony</persName>.</p>
         <p>And it came to pass that on the very day after <persName>Eulogius</persName> had arrived there that great man
            came from the inner desert to his disciples in the late evening, and he was clothed in
            [his] skin cloak. Now whensoever he came to his monastery he was in the habit of calling
            out to his disciple <persName>Macarius</persName>, and saying unto him, <quote>O brother <persName>Macarius</persName>, have any
            brethren come this day from anywhere?</quote> And <persName>Macarius</persName> would say, <quote>Yea.</quote> Then <persName>Anthony</persName> would
            say, <quote>Are they <persName>Egyptians</persName> <pb n="297"/>or <persName>Jerusalemites</persName>?</quote> Now he had given <persName>Macarius</persName> this sign:—<quote>When
            thou seest brethren who are simple and innocent say they are <persName>Egyptians</persName>; but when thou
            seest brethren who are venerable and are skilled in speaking, say they are
            <persName>Jerusalemites</persName>.</quote> Therefore according to his custom <persName>Anthony</persName> asked <persName>Macarius</persName>, <quote>Are they
            Egyptian brethren or <persName>Jerusalemites</persName>?</quote> and <persName>Macarius</persName> said, <quote>They are neither <persName>Egyptians</persName> nor
            <persName>Jerusalemites</persName>.</quote> Now when <persName>Macarius</persName> would answer, <quote>They are <persName>Egyptians</persName>,</quote> <persName>Anthony</persName> would say
            unto him, <quote>Cook them a mess of lentils that they may eat, and then dismiss them, and let
            them go in peace</quote>; and he would say a prayer on their behalf, and would straightway send
            them away. And when <persName>Macarius</persName> would answer, <quote>They are <persName>Jerusalemites</persName>,</quote> <persName>Anthony</persName> would sit
            down the whole night, and would converse with them to the benefit of their lives.</p>
         <p>And on that night he sat down, and called unto them all, and he discoursed without any
            man having told him the name of one of them, and it was dark and the night had come; and
            suddenly he cried out three times, thus, <quote><persName>Eulogius</persName>, <persName>Eulogius</persName>, <persName>Eulogius</persName>.</quote> And <persName>Eulogius</persName>
            the scholastic answered him never a word, because he thought that <persName>Anthony</persName> was calling
            some other person, and again <persName>Anthony</persName> cried out to him, <quote>Unto thee I speak, O <persName>Eulogius</persName>,
            who hast come from <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.</quote> Then <persName>Eulogius</persName> said unto him, <quote>Master, what commandest
            thou [me to do? Tell me], I beseech thee.</quote> And <persName>Anthony</persName> said unto him, <quote>Wherefore hast
            thou come?</quote> And <persName>Eulogius</persName> answered and said unto him, <quote>Let Him that hath revealed unto
            thee my name declare unto thee for what purpose I have come.</quote> Then <persName>Anthony</persName> said unto
            him, <quote>I know why thou hast come, nevertheless declare [it] before the brethren in order
            that they may hear.</quote> And <persName>Eulogius</persName> answered and said unto him, <quote>I found this <persName>Arian</persName> in the
            street (or market), and I gave the <pb n="298"/>right hand to God (i. e., made a covenant with God),
            that I would minister unto him, [that] I might live because of him, and he because of
            me. And behold I have ministered unto him for the last fifteen years, and now, after all
            these years he stirreth [himself] up against me, and causeth me tribulation, and I have
            had it in my mind to cast him out; therefore I have come unto thy holiness so that thou
            mayest advise me what I should do, and that thou mayest pray on my behalf, for I am
            greatly oppressed and am in sore straits.</quote> Then <persName>Anthony</persName> said unto him angrily and in a
            hard voice, <quote>If thou sendest him away, He who created him will not send him away; if
            thou dost cast him out, God, Who is better and more excellent than thou, will gather him
            [to Himself];</quote> and when <persName>Eulogius</persName> heard these words he set a bridle on his mouth and was
            silent.</p>
         <p>And having left <persName>Eulogius</persName> [<persName>Anthony</persName>] came to chastise the <persName>Arian</persName> with his tongue, and he
            cried out and said unto him, <quote>O thou deformed <persName>Arian</persName>, thou art worthy neither of heaven
            nor of earth. Wilt thou not cease to contend against God? Knowest thou not that he who
            ministereth unto thee is <persName>Christ</persName>? How canst thou dare to utter these words against our
            Lord? Was it not for <persName>Christ</persName>’s sake that <persName>Eulogius</persName> gave himself to thy service?</quote> Then
            having made the man sorrowful, he ceased from <persName>Eulogius</persName> and the <persName>Arian</persName>, and spake unto all
            the brethren who were there, unto every man according to his business. And he called
            unto <persName>Eulogius</persName> and the <persName>Arian</persName> and said unto them, <quote>Turn ye not unto any [other] place, but
            depart and separate not yourselves from one another, and return ye to the cell wherein
            ye have lived so long a time, for behold God will send upon you [your] end. And behold,
            this trial hath come upon you because the end of both of you is nigh, and because ye are
            esteemed worthy of crowns. Therefore do not ye act in a contrary manner, and let not the
            angel come <pb n="299"/>after you and not find you in your place[s], [lest ye be deprived of your
            crowns];</quote> so the two of them departed and came to their cell. And in less than forty
            days <persName>Eulogius</persName> died, and in less than three days afterwards the <persName>Arian</persName> died. Now this
            Chronius, who related unto us the narrative of this matter, tarried for a time in the
            monasteries which were in the Thebaïd, and he came down to the monasteries which were in
            <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>; and it happened that the brethren were gathered together commemorating the
            death of <persName>Eulogius</persName> after forty days, and the death of the <persName>Arian</persName> after three days. And
            when Chronius heard he marvelled, and he took down a Book of the Gospels, and set [it]
            down among the brotherhood, and then related what had happened; and he took an oath and
            said, <quote>In all this affair I was the interpreter for Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> because he did not know
            Greek; but I know both languages, [and I acted interpreter for both sides, turning Greek
            into Egyptian for <persName>Eulogius</persName>, and Egyptian into Greek for <persName>Anthony</persName>.]</quote></p>
         <p>Here endeth the first Book of the histories of the holy Fathers which were compiled by
            <persName>Palladius</persName></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
