<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="3"/>
         <head>
         <title>The Life of Saint <persName>Anthony</persName></title> by <persName>Athanasius, Archbishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName></persName>.
         <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#3"/> Let us begin now, by the help of our 
         Lord, and write first of all the history of the 
         life and acts of the saint and mighty one of God,
         the blessed Mar <persName>Anthony</persName> which was composed by 
         Saint <persName>Athanasius</persName>, the Archbishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>. May 
         our Lord help and strengthen the writer to write,
         and [the reader] to read and to perform everything which
         is commnaded (herein). Amen. O Lord, 
         help me, and bring me to the end [of the work]!
         Amen.</head>
         <p>
            Marvellous care and the merciful exhortation of
            your understanding for the monkish brethren who are
            in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> have moved me with solicitude [to hope]
            that by constant meditation on the following stories your
            mind may be drawn to perfection, so that you may
            not be repeating with your mouth[s] only these triumphs,
            and others which are like unto them, but that also in
            your persons you may be preachers of the example
            of these lives and deeds. Now, your careful solicitude
            is seemly and is most acceptable, and in this respect
            you have become ministers of the exalted Will, for it
            is right that this sight should not depart from the
            mirror of your career, and that ye should know at
            once the craftiness of the Enemy, that is to say, what
            form it taketh, and what it is, and with what it bringeth
            [a man] to nought. And this thing hath been wrought
            at this time by God, for behold, monasteries which
            <pb n="4"/>flourish like the flowers and sweet scents of the springtime 
            have been scattered throughout the whole earth,
            and the sign of the solitary ascetics ruleth from one
            end thereof unto the other. It is then beautiful for
            us to take hold of and to embrace this power of
            discernment <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#4"/>which your mind hath conceived,
            and to be the ministers of the fervour of your love
            with joy and solicitude. For who could be negligent
            of this service and be blameless, inasmuch as those
            who have invited me [to write] the history of the
            triumphs of a righteous man are themselves righteous?
            And may the Giver of gifts (blessed be His honour!)
            Himself open the door of our entreaty, and may we
            snare each one of the stories which we have been
            deputed by your love to write, not for our own sake,
            but for the sake of your most excellent entreaty, and
            for the sake of the warlike [thoughts] which are in
            you, that we may fulfil your labour, and for the sake
            of the work of him who triumphed by these acts and
            deeds, in order that his triumphs may never die among
            his sons in our Lord; and finally for his name's sake,
            that in this history we may also magnify the glory of
            God [and shew forth] how great is the might which
            He giveth unto those who fear Him.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now, we have been deputed by your love to write
            down the triumphs of the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, and to
            send the history of them to you<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4-1"/> in writing [which
            will shew] how the beginning of his discipleship came
            to pass, and what manner of life? he led before this,
            and with what manner of life<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4-2"/> he brought his days to
            a close, and whether all the words which have been
            spoken concerning him and have come to our hearing
            are true; and straightway with joy I have devoted
            myself to the fulfilment of your command. And in the
            mere writing of a commemorative history of the blessed
            <pb n="5"/><persName>Anthony</persName> I also shall gain great benefit, for I am convinced, 
            O my beloved, that by the narrating of these
            histories two things will be effected; we shall increase
            the renown of the man of God in honour and wonder,
            and we shall begin to instruct your minds step by
            step,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5-1"/> for the acts of the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> are a perfect
            example for the solitary ascetics. Now, as concerning
            what ye have heard about him aforetime, O my beloved,
            from those who [lived] with him, or (from those) who
            heard [them] from those who were with him continually,
            or from those also unto whom word of him was handed
            down by tradition <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#5"/>ye shall have no doubt
            whatsoever. Ye have only heard a little out of a great
            quantity, and only just as much as the mind (or, memory)
            is able to narrate, and mine own mind also testifieth
            that such is the case, and in compiling the present
            history I have also learned that such is the case. For
            when I thought that I had collected and enumerated
            a large number of stories, suddenly a great many
            others, which were far more numerous than those which
            had already been collected by me, sprang up, and
            made my mind to swim;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5-2"/> but as many as I was
            able to remember and to collect my mind hath,
            with joy, committed to writing. And as for you, cease
            ye not to ask questions and to enquire [concerning
            the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>], especially those who come by
            river from the <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName>, that is to say from Inner
            <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, for it may happen that from those from whom
            ye expect to hear nothing ye may increase your knowledge 
            greatly. For when a man belongeth unto those
            who have knowledge he repeateth a story which he
            knoweth, and though we may think and be convinced that
            we have collected too many, [we find that our] narrative
            is immeasurably short. Now many of those who openly
            received [the accounts] of the wonderful things which
            <pb n="6"/>
            were wrought by his hands have departed from this
            world; and of those who are still living how many
            are there who have not revealed unto us concerning
            the things which were spoken with him or which were
            done near him! And what man would wish to narrate
            unto his companions only a few stories out of many?
         </p>
         <p>
            And when I had received (your) letter, and had read
            and seen the force thereof, and what it demanded, I
            was wishful to send and bring certain solitary ascetics
            who were always with him, so that, peradventure,
            between them and me I might be able to fulfil your
            desire. But because the time in which ships could
            travel from <placeName>Egypt</placeName> to the <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName>, and from the <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName>
            hither, was unfavourable, and the bringer of the letter
            was in haste, and because I knew that I had been
            with Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> continually, I made it to be a care
            unto me to write myself unto your love, and tell you
            what I was able to learn about, whatsoever happened
            for a long time, and [how] I poured water upon <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#6"/>
            his hands, observing carefully the word of the truth,
            lest a man should hear what was superfluous and should
            be in doubt, or should despise and belittle that which
            he heard.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now, by race the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> was an <persName>Egyptian</persName>,
            and he was descended from a noble family, and was,
            indeed, an owner of slaves. His forefathers were believers, 
            and from his earliest childhood he was brought
            up in the fear of our Lord; and when he was a child
            and was being reared among his own kinsfolk he knew
            nothing of his father or of what went on among his
            own people. He was so quiet, and his mind was so
            humble that he did not even trouble his parents with
            the work of [asking] questions. He was exceedingly
            modest (or shamefaced), and he was honest beyond
            measure. He was unable to learn to read or to write
            because he could not bear the rough behaviour of the
            boys [in the school]; his whole desire was to be even
            according to what is written about <persName>Jacob</persName>, <quote>He was a
            <pb n="7"/>simple man, and a dweller in tents</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#7n-1"/> He clung closely
            to his parents, and when they came to church he would
            [run] before them in the flow of his affection, and he
            was not like an [ordinary] child, the course of whose
            customary attendance is broken by the play hour of
            childhood,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#7n-2"/> and he never neglected [the observance of]
            any of the seasons of the Church; he neither neglected
            [them] in his childhood, nor held them lightly in his
            early manhood. And from the time when he was a
            child and knew how to distinguish between good and
            evil, his going to church was not a mere matter of
            custom, but was the result of] discerning understanding.
            And moreover, he did not wait for his own people
            (or parents) to be admonishers unto him, because by
            his life and acts he became a teacher unto them. For
            they learned by the experience [of] his childhood that
            he did not live among them like an ordinary simple
            child, and they accepted the proof of the rectitude of
            his early manhood; he paid them honour after the
            manner of a full-grown man, and they regarded him
            as the master of the house (i. e., steward).
         </p>
         <p>
            Now when the time had arrived and they brought
            their days to an end, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#7"/>and they departed from
            this world, he was left behind with one little sister,
            when he was about eighteen or twenty years old, and
            it happened from sheer necessity that he had to be
            the ruler of the house and of his sister. And when
            as yet not six months had passed since the death of
            his parents, and when, according to his wont, he was
            continually in the church, it came to pass one day
            when he was in the church that a righteous idea
            entered his mind, and that he began to meditate within
            himself how the blessed <persName>Apostles</persName> forsook everything
            and followed after our Redeemer; and how the others
            who succeeded them and walked in their footsteps
            <pb n="8"/>sold everything which they possessed and laid [the
            money which they received] at the feet of the <persName>Apostles</persName>,
            that it might be spent upon the poor; and how great
            was the blessing of those who had in this wise obeyed
            the voice of our Redeemer. Now whilst he was meditating 
            these and such like things, the Lesson was
            being read, and at the end of all [the passages from]
            the Scriptures, the Gospel was read, and he heard our
            Lord Who said unto the rich man, <quote>If thou wishest to
            be perfect, go and sell everything which thou hast,
            and give to the poor, and take thy cross, and come
            after Me, and there shall be unto thee treasure in
            heaven</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8-1"/> And the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> received the word
            of the Gospel as a sign, and he reflected that this
            reading had not taken place as a matter of chance,
            but in order that the righteous idea which had taken
            up its abode in him might be confirmed. And straightway 
            he went out from the church, and departed and
            set in order his house and the possessions which he
            had inherited from his parents. Now he had three
            hundred fields, a great estate [which produced] abundant
            crops, and these he remitted to the people of his village,
            so that they might trouble neither himself nor his sister;
            but the remainder of his other possessions which were
            in <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#8"/>the house he sold, and gathered in money
            not a little, which he distributed among the poor, but he
            laid by a little which was sufficient for his sister's wants.
         </p>
         <p>
            And when, on another First Day of the week, he
            had again entered the church at the time of [the reading 
            of] the Gospel, he inclined his ear carefully to see
            what word would come forth for him; and as he was
            inclining his ear the word of our Lord to His disciples
            was immediately read out, saying, <quote>Take no thought
            for the morrow</quote>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#8n-2"/> And straightway he received the
            <pb n="9"/>commandment readily, and he went out and distributed
            that which remained to him for his sister among the
            poor. Now unto his sister he spake words of love,
            and of truth, and of the fear of God, and he made
            her mind to be after the manner of his own; and he
            delivered her over to certain chaste nuns who were
            to be found at that time. And when he had made
            an end of these things he forthwith became a solitary
            monk, and he took no care for anything whatsoever
            except his soul, and he began to train himself in the
            strictest abstinence and self-denial. Now he dwelt alone
            in a house which was by the side of the village, for
            as yet there were no monasteries for ascetics in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>,
            and among the monks there was no man who had any
            knowledge of the inner desert; but everyone who
            wished to have a care for his soul used to seek out
            a habitation of this kind. Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> did not betake
            himself to the mountain at a great distance from the
            village, but only at a sufficient distance therefrom so
            that he might be somewhat apart from the habitation
            of men. And at that time there was in another village
            on their borders a certain blessed old man, who from
            his youth up had lived a life of solitary asceticism, and
            this man the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> saw, and was envious<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-1"/>
            of his fair deeds. First of all he also began to live by
            the side of the village, in places which were free from
            the feet [of men], and whilst living in this abode his
            mind was rent with doubt about the fair works [of the
            ascetic life], and he gave his soul no rest, for he was
            constant <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#9"/>in meditation about the truth. And
            he used to ponder within himself [and say], <quote>How did
            the righteous men of old live? With what manner of
            triumphs did they please God? And who can make
            me worthy of even a sight of these?</quote> And as a result
            of this meditation which arose from love of the righteous
            men he began to ask and enquire, <quote>What was the</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <pb n="10"/><quote>condition of the righteous men? And who shall inform
            me concerning them?</quote> And whilst asking questions
            that he might learn something about any of the righteous
            men who were in [that] place, in the fervour of his
            love he used to go forth strenuously to seek him;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-1"/> and
            he did not at first return to his own place, without first
            of all accepting the person of the man of God. And
            he was like unto the wise bee which hovereth and
            resteth over plants of every kind which are filled with
            honey that it may fill its habitation with the goodness
            of the earth. In this manner he himself also received
            from the sight of each of the righteous men provision<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-2"/>
            for the marvellous way; and thus was his mode
            of life at the beginning of his ascetic career. And
            his thoughts were exceedingly well trained by him at
            the beginning of his life of] righteousness, so that he
            might not in any wise be anxious about his family, or
            be fettered by the love of kinsfolk, or be held fast
            by the affairs of this temporary life; from all [these]
            he purged himself that he might be a pure offering
            unto God. Now he used also to labour with his hands,
            because he had heard [the words], <quote>If a man doth not
            work he shall not eat;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-3"/> with a very little [of the
            produce] of the work of his hands he used to provide
            himself with food, and the rest he spent upon the poor.
            And he prayed continually, for he had heard [the
            words], <quote>Pray, and let it not be tedious unto you;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-4"/> and
            he was wont to listen to the reading of the Scriptures
            in such wise that not one word might fall to the ground,
            and henceforth he kept in his mind the remembrance
            of the commandments which he heard, and they became
            unto him even as the Scriptures.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now by these acts and deeds the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>
            <pb n="11"/>was shewing love to his soul and, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#10"/>even as
            it is written, <quote>He found favour with God and with
            man;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-1"/></quote> for when it happened that he went [to visit]
            the righteous men, he hearkened unto them and was
            subject unto them wholly and in everything, and the
            love with which they loved him was such that if it
            happened that he tarried in paying his visit to them
            they were wont to send after him with anxious
            care. They observed how greatly he was the object
            of [God's] mercy, and how great a measure of the
            love of the things which were spiritual was found with
            him, and they saw how easy it was for him to gain
            a reward by trafficking in the riches of heaven. Therefore 
            each one of them, according to the measure of
            his power, took him by his hand. And they looked
            and saw that he was to be perfected as a chosen
            vessel, and they observed when as yet he himself saw
            it not that he had adapted for himself a glorious rule
            of life among the righteous men. For what joy is
            there unto which graciousness is not found to be yoked?
            Or what humility is there wherewith those who possess
            it are adorned in which it doth not dwell? Or what
            love is there, which is the foundation of all the commandments, 
            which it doth not rule?. And what man
            is there who, when he imagineth himself to be merciful, 
            is not carried away thereby, and with whom it is
            not the chief thing? Wrath, and jealousy, and calumny
            as from him .......<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-2"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            Now Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> was the storehouse of fasting,
            and of prayer, and of ascetic practices, and of patient
            endurance, and of love, and of righteousness, which is
            the mother of [them all, but towards those who were
            young monks like himself he was not envious, except
            in one matter only, that is to say, he would not be
            second to any of them in fair works. And he con<pb n="12"/>trived 
            in every possible manner not to give offence
            to the wicked man, on the contrary, [he wished] that
            those who were yoked together with him might be
            drawn to his opinion (or mind) by his carefulness and
            graciousness, and that they might go forward<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-1"/> in their
            career. And he worked matters in such a manner
            that they were not only not envious of him, but they
            <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#11"/>rejoiced in him and gave thanksgiving for
            him. Now by reason of these triumphs every man used
            to call him <quote><persName>Theophilus</persName></quote>, which is, being interpreted,
            <quote>God-loving</quote>, and all the righteous gave him this name;
            and some of them loved him like a brother, and some
            of them like a son.
         </p>
         <p>
            And when the Enemy, the hater of the virtues and
            the lover of evil things, saw all this great perfection
            in the young man, he could not endure it, and he
            surrounded himself with his servants,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-2"/> even as he is
            wont to do, and began [to work] on <persName>Anthony</persName>; at the
            beginning of his temptations he approached him with
            flattery, and cast into him anxiety as to his possessions,
            and solicitude and love for his sister, and for his
            family, and his kinsfolk, and the love of money, and
            lusts of various kinds, and the [thought of the] rest
            [of the things of the life of [this] world, and finally of
            the hard and laborious life which he lived, and of the
            weakness of body [which would come upon him] with
            the lapse of time; and, in short, he stirred up in him
            the power of the thoughts so that by means of one
            [or other] of them he might be flattered, and might
            be made to possess shortcomings and be snared by
            his incitements.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now when the Enemy saw that his craftiness in
            this matter was without profit, and that the more he
            brought temptation unto Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> the more
            strenuous he was in arming himself against him with
            <pb n="13"/>the armour of righteousness, he attacked him with the
            vigour of early manhood which is bound up in the
            nature of our humanity, and with the incitements of
            passion he used to trouble him by night,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-1"/> and in the
            day time also he would vex him and pain him with
            the same to such an extent that even those who saw
            him knew from his appearance that he was waging
            war against the Adversary. But the more the Evil
            One brought unto him filthy and maddening thoughts
            the more Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> took refuge in prayer and
            in abundant supplication, and amid them [all] he remained
            wholly chaste. And the Evil One was working [upon
            him] every shameful deed according to his wont, and
            at length he even appeared <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#12"/>unto Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> 
            in the form of a woman, and the rest of the
            things which appertain unto pride he was performing
            readily.
         </p>
         <p>
            But the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> knelt down upon his knees
            on the ground, and prayed before Him Who said,
            <quote>Before thou criest unto Me I will answer thee</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-2"/> and
            said, <quote>O my Lord, this I entreat of Thee; let not Thy
            love be blotted out from my mind, and behold, I am,
            by Thy grace, innocent before Thee.</quote> And again
            the Enemy multiplied in him the thoughts of lust until
            Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> became as one utterly burnt up, not
            through the Evil One, but through himself; but he
            girded himself about with the threat of the thought
            of the Judgment, and of the torture of <persName>Gehenna</persName>, and
            of the worm which dieth not. And whilst meditating
            on thoughts which were against the Evil One, he
            prayed for thoughts which would be hostile to him.
            Thus, to the reproach and shame of the Enemy, these
            things could not be performed; for he who imagined
            that he could be [as] God was made a mock of by
            a young man, and he who boasted (of his power) over
            <pb n="14"/>flesh and blood was vanquished by a man who was
            clothed with flesh.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now in all these things our Lord, Who put on a
            [human] body for our sakes, was his helper, and He
            strengthened him to become a shield against the Evil
            One, so that according to this act of grace which was
            wrought on our behalf, before any of the blessed men
            lived by the merit of his agony He taught us in what
            it is meet that we should boast. For when one repeated
            too often these triumphs which were wrought for him,
            Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> answered and said, <quote>It was not I who
            worked, but His grace which was with me.</quote> Now
            when the Enemy saw that he was vanquished in this
            fight, and that his craftiness was driven away and
            brought to nought by the thought (or mind) of the
            righteous man, he gnashed his teeth, and cried out
            that he would shew the righteous man his inner nature
            in an external form, that, peradventure, by means of
            fear and terror he might find an opportunity to perform
            his will. And he appeared unto Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> in the
            form of an Indian youth, and he began to say unto
            him, <quote>Whom seest thou? I have come, and behold I
            will stand up, and I will overcome thee, and I will
            bring thee low, even as I do many.</quote> And whilst he
            was saying <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#13"/>these words, the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> 
            signed himself with the Sign of the Cross, and
            ceased to tremble, and the Enemy saw the Sign of
            the Cross, and straightway was terrified. And when
            the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> saw that he was terrified, he began
            to ask him a question, saying, <quote>Who art thou, by
            whose voice such words as these are heard by me?</quote>
            Then the Enemy began [to say] unto him after the
            manner of a man who roareth, <quote>I, even I, am the
            lover of error and of fornication, and it is I who
            cast the incitements of these [thoughts] and flatteries
            [into the mind of man]. It is I who have taken
            upon myself to lead many astray, and I fight against
            every man, and I am against righteousness, and I
            <pb n="15"/>am, even as the Prophet called me, the <quote>spirit of
            fornication</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-1"/> for through me have gone astray all
            those who have stumbled. It is I who have injured
            thee on several occasions, and thou hast been held in
            contempt [by me] in everything.</quote> And the blessed
            <persName>Anthony</persName> gave thanks unto the Lord, and gained great
            encouragement, and said, <quote>What power thinkest thou
            that thou hast in thee, O Enemy, to resist the might
            of the Cross? Well hast thou appeared in the form
            of an <persName>Indian</persName>, for thou art black in thy nature, and
            thou art feeble in thy strength even like a youth who
            hath been overcome by punishment. Thou art esteemed
            as nought by me, and I tremble not at thy wiles; for
            the Lord helpeth me, and I shall look upon mine
            enemies.</quote> Now when that black being heard these
            words, straightway his appearance vanished from the
            sight.
         </p>
         <p>
            This is the first strife which Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> [waged]
            against his Enemy, or rather, this is the first assistance
            which came on behalf of <persName>Anthony</persName> from our Redeemer,
            Who vanquished sin in His own body, that the
            righteousness of the Law might be fulfilled in us, and
            that we might not walk after the flesh but after the
            spirit. But although the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> saw the
            Enemy made powerless and brought low, he neither
            neglected his prayer nor ceased from his [wonted]
            course [of life], for he knew well that his contest was
            against a crafty being, who although he had been
            vanquished would not cease [to trouble], and who,
            whenever he could find an opportunity through some
            small negligence, would suddenly rise up and vanquish
            <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#14"/>him that had on several occasions gained
            the victory over him. For Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> knew that
            there was no cessation to his wrongdoing, and that
            he wandered about like a roaring lion seeking whom
            he might break; and he had learned from the Scrip<pb n="16"/>tures 
            that the snares of the Adversary were many, and
            he was persuaded of himself that his work was thus,
            and with strenuousness and with an object he was
            working in the fear of God.
         </p>
         <p>
            And he pondered in his mind that although the
            Enemy had not been able to snare him with lusts of
            divers kinds, he had still other means (or causes)
            whereby he was wont to make our humanity to sin;
            for the nature thereof yearneth to sin always. Now
            it is especially right for us in the time of our victory,
            when we have our mind with us, to oppress and bring
            our body into subjection to the will of freedom and
            of righteousness, lest whilst we are imagining that we
            are victors [in one group of things] we find that we
            are vanquished by others which are their opposite.
            And Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> was in this mind, and [he was
            meditating] these thoughts always, and day by day he
            was adding labour unto his former deeds of asceticism;
            and many were wondering at the greatness of the
            patient endurance which he possessed, and how long-suffering 
            he was in his afflictions. For behold, the
            freedom of his spirit (or soul), and the thought of his
            mind, by reason of the great length [of time] which
            they were practised by him, as it were renewed him,
            and changed him from one thing to another; and he
            used to derive [as] a base some small matter from
            the example of others, and take it and polish it in
            his own person, and with him it became so beautiful
            that the spectators thereof imagined that it was to be
            found with him alone. For he was a perfect handicraftsman 
            in matters which related to the fear of God,
            and wheresoever he saw that one of the heavenly works<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-1"/>
            of uprightness was being practised by a man who was
            not honouring it according to what it was, he would
            take it, and polish it in his own person, and would
            make manifest how great its beauty was.
         </p>
         <pb n="17"/>
         <p>
            And Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> kept vigil to the utmost, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#15"/>
            and to such an extent that the greater number of his
            days dawned on him without his having had any sleep.
            He was wont to eat at eventide daily, but on occasions
            he passed three days, or four days, or whole weeks
            at a time (without eating). His food was bread and
            salt, and his drink was water, and in the matter of
            wine, and flesh, and other dainty meats he declared
            [them] to be so superfluous, that they were not even
            used by ordinary monks. What he slept upon was a
            mat made of palm leaves only, but for a very long
            time he used to make the bare ground his bed. He
            was, moreover, exceedingly careful not to anoint himself 
            with oil, for he used to say that oil rendered the
            body soft and made the members thereof effeminate,
            and for this reason [he] required young men to distil
            upon themselves from their minds within the oil of
            strenuousness. He was also mindful of the word of
            the <persName>Apostle</persName> which he spake, saying, <quote>When I am weak
            (or sick), then am I strong."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17-1"/> And he possessed a
            wonderful mind, for he never pondered and thought
            how far he had advanced in discipleship, but each day
            he kept in mind that he had only just begun at the
            beginning thereof; for he remembered the word of the
            <persName>Apostle</persName> which he spake, <quote>That which is behind me I
            forget, and I stretch forward unto the things which
            are before me,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17-2"/> and also the word of the Prophet
            <persName>Elijah</persName> which he spake, "As the Lord liveth, before
            Whom I stand this day.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17-3"/> Therefore he prepared himself 
            to be worthy to stand always before the Majesty,
            even as the man who stood on that day before the
            Lord; and he used to say to himself, <quote>It is right that
            a monk should know that in his manner of life (or,
            habitation) and in his acts and deeds he must be an
            <pb n="18"/>alien unto the world, and an associate (or son of the
            yoke) of the angels who watch.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18-1"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            And after these things he dwelt also in another
            frame of mind, and, having pondered in his mind that
            he would go forth from the village, he departed and
            took up his abode in a tomb which was situated in
            a mountain which lay close by the village;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18-2"/> and he
            commanded one of <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#16"/>his acquaintances to bring
            him a morsel of bread from time [to time].<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18-3"/> And
            having done these things and entered into the tomb
            and shut the door upon himself, straightway the Adversary, 
            together with a multitude of devils who were
            his associates, burst in upon him there, for he was
            afraid to let Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> go from the village altogether, 
            and he began to say unto him, <quote>How great
            is that which thou endurest! And to what limit wilt
            thou drive thyself? Thou hast come and hast entered
            into the place of our abode. What man is there who
            hath ever done the like? And when<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18-4"/> was it ever
            heard that men ought to live among the tombs? We
            have been driven out of the village, and we shall
            also be driven out from among the tombs. Now
            therefore will we take vengeance upon thee, for it is
            thou who hast made fools of us.</quote> Then they began
            to smite him with blows, and they smote him so
            severely that at length he fell [on the ground], and
            nothing but his breath was left in him; and Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> 
            used to relate that the blows with which the
            devils smote him were more severe than those of the
            children of men. But God brought help unto him, and
            would not deliver him over to death, for He put it
            into the mind of him that used to visit him to come
            quickly, and to open [the door of] the tomb according
            <pb n="19"/>to his wont, and he saw the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> who was
            like unto a dead man by reason of the blows; and
            straightway he lifted him up and brought him to the
            church in the village. And there collected about him
            no small mass of people, and they gathered together
            and sat by his side as if he had been a dead man.
            Now by the sweet rest of sleep the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>
            was refreshed, [and he was relieved from his affliction,
            and he came to himself, and he turned round and saw
            that all the people were asleep, and that only his friend
            who was sitting watching by his pillow was awake;
            and he made a sign to him, and he drew nigh unto
            him, and Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> said unto him quietly, <quote>Come,
            do [an act of] righteousness (or charity) lest the heart
            of the people should think and mankind should
            imagine that there is still power left in the Evil One,
            and that they should be afraid to lift up the heel
            against him.</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            And the man hearkened unto him, and whilst the
            people were quiet <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#17"/>and asleep, he lifted him
            up and carried him to the tomb, and shut the door
            as usual. Then Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> prayed as he was lying
            down, for he had no power in him to stand up, and
            when he had multiplied [his prayers, he said with a
            loud voice, <quote>Where are ye, O children of <persName>Gehenna</persName>?
            Here am I, even I, <persName>Anthony</persName>, and I will not depart
            from this place until your destruction from this place
            shall be [effected]: for although ye multiply tortures I
            shall not be remote from the love of <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote> And
            next he said with a loud voice, <quote>Though a whole
            camp [of devils] encamp against me my heart shall
            not fear;</quote> such were the words which this man, this
            athlete, proclaimed in his striving. Then the heart of
            the Enemy of righteousness melted within him, and he
            cried unto the dogs his kinsfolk, and whilst emitting
            smoke said unto them, <quote>Do ye not say unto me, What
            shall we do unto this man, this insolent fellow, who
            hath treated us wholly with contempt and disdain?
            <pb n="20"/>His heart is not afraid of the quaking terror, his
            hearing is not perturbed by words (or voices), his
            eye is not terrified by visions, and his body hath no
            fear of blows. Who among you can give [me] counsel
            as to what shall be done?</quote> And thereupon they contrived 
            the following plan.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now it is very easy for the Enemy to make apparitions 
            and appearances of such a character that they
            shall be deemed real and actual objects, and [straightway]
            phantasms of this kind made the similitude of an earthquake, 
            and they rent asunder the four corners of the
            house, and they entered therein in a body from all
            sides. One had the form of a lion, and another had
            the appearance of a wolf, and another was like unto
            a panther, and all the others were in the forms and
            similitudes of serpents, and of vipers, and of scorpions.
            The lion was roaring as a lion roareth when he
            is about to slay; the bull was ready to gore [him]
            with his horns; the panther was prepared to spring
            [upon him]; and the snake and the viper were hissing,
            and they appeared to be in the act of hurling themselves 
            upon him; and the sounds which they made and
            the forms in which they shewed themselves were terrible. 
            Now the blessed man <persName>Anthony</persName> was not disturbed
            (or, frightened) by their commotion, and his mind
            remained in an unruffled condition.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-1"/> And as he was
            lying down he laughed <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#18"/>at these phantoms,
            and said, <quote>Thus there is no power in you. Ye have
            taken unto yourselves the forms of wild beasts, and
            if there had been any power whatsoever to do harm
            in you, for one of you only to come [against me]
            would have been sufficient; but because our Lord hath
            cut off the things which incited you, and the goad
            of your wickedness hath no strength therein, ye lay
            plots and snares thinking that peradventure ye will be
            able to make men quake by fear only. And moreover,
            <pb n="21"/>whosoever hath had experience of your feebleness
            [knoweth] that ye have obtained as your helpers the
            mere forms and appearances of wild beasts.</quote>
            And <persName>Anthony</persName> also spake unto them in very great
            boldness of heart, saying, <quote>If ye have indeed received
            power over me, or if it be in your power to do me
            harm, hesitate ye not to do it, only draw nigh speedily
            and do ye whatsoever ye lust to do; but if ye be
            unable to do anything, wherefore do ye weary yourselves 
            in vain? For our faith in our Lord is a seal
            and a wall unto us.</quote> Now our Lord was not unmindful 
            of the athlete <persName>Anthony</persName>, and He appeared unto him
            after his victory. And the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> lifted up
            his eyes, and he saw a roof-curtain drawn aside, and
            a ray of light descended therefrom upon him; and
            straightway the devils dispersed in terror, and the
            sufferings of his body were relieved, and the blessed
            man felt the help of our Lord [nigh unto him], and
            understood.
         </p>
         <p>
            Then having waited for a space, and having recovered 
            somewhat from his tribulations, and having enjoyed
            rest from the graciousness of the revelation of our Lord,
            he lifted up his voice, and said, <quote>O my Lord, I adore
            Thine help: where wast Thou before these sufferings
            and tribulations came upon me?</quote> And straightway
            a voice came to him, saying, <quote>Here was I by thy side,
            O <persName>Anthony</persName>, and I have never left thee, for I remained
            that I might look upon thy strife; but inasmuch as
            thou hast triumphed completely, and hast not been
            broken down with sadness in thy tribulations, I will be
            unto thee a Guide and a Comforter, and I will make
            thee to be renowned as a faithful servant throughout
            all the earth.</quote> And when these words had been heard
            by him straightway [peace] came upon his body, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#19"/>
            and he had rest from his afflictions. Then he rose up
            and bowed the knee, and prayed, and gave thanks
            unto God Who had visited him; and from that time
            onwards he perceived that he had very much greater
            <pb n="22"/>strength in him than formerly. Now at that time <persName>Anthony</persName> 
            was about five and thirty years of age.
         </p>
         <p>
            And it came to pass that on the following morning
            he departed from the tomb and went forth to that
            solitary old monk who used to dwell by the side of
            the village, and he tried to persuade him to go with
            him to the desert, but he excused himself from this,
            for one thing because of his old age, and for another
            because he had not been in the habit of living in the
            desert, and indeed at that time none of the monks
            lived there. And straightway <persName>Anthony</persName> rose up and
            prayed with the old man, and he besought him to join
            his prayers unto his that God might make his way
            prosperous before him; and (afterwards) he went forth
            [alone] into the desert. And once again the Enemy
            went forth after him, and when <persName>Anthony</persName> was exhausted
            by reason of the distance (of the way), he began to
            contend with him. Now when the blessed man <persName>Anthony</persName> 
            had journeyed along the road [and had arrived]
            at the skirt of the desert, he perceived that the Enemy
            had cast down before him a large silver tablet,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#22n-1"/> but
            the blessed man knew that these things were of the
            wiles of the Evil One, and he made him to know that
            this example of his handicraft which had been fashioned
            by him could not cause him to err. And looking at
            the tablet he answered and said, <quote>Assuredly the Evil
            One [wisheth to do me evil] by means of this tablet.
            How can it have come in the desert? This is no
            frequented road, and there is no inhabited land near,
            and thieves do not dwell in this country; it is the
            handiwork of the Evil One. Thou shalt not, O [Enemy],
            pervert my mind by this thing; may thou and it go
            to perdition.</quote> And having made an end of his words
            the silver tablet was consumed and disappeared like
            smoke before the fire of the words of the blessed man
            <persName>Anthony</persName>.            
         </p>
         <pb n="23"/>
         <p>
            But again the Evil One shewed him some gold,
            and it was real gold, and <persName>Anthony</persName> fell into anxious
            thought and pondered, [saying], <quote>What is this thing?
            It is either a piece of the handiwork of the Evil One,
            or it is a temptation from God, and a trial <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#20"/>from
            Him (may His Honour be blessed!) Who hath restrained 
            me from the blandishments of the Evil One, (who
            saith), Behold, I will shew him real gold;</quote> but the
            blessed man was not overthrown thereby, and he
            esteemed the gold as filth. [And <persName>Anthony</persName> said unto
            the Evil One]. <quote>Choose thou some other kind of handiwork 
            and snare, for out of this one have I delivered
            myself.</quote> Now whence that gold came or how it got
            there <persName>Anthony</persName> telleth us not, and we, even after most
            careful thought are unable to afford any information
            on the matter; but [what <persName>Anthony</persName> saw] was gold, and
            gold in large quantities, for the blessed man marvelled
            at the great abundance thereof.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now when the Evil One saw that he had protected
            himself by the Sign of the Cross and was praying,
            and that he did not remove himself from his place,
            he stepped aside and passed away quickly in the form
            of a flame of fire, and he neither turned nor looked
            at him. And <persName>Anthony</persName> was particularly well armed for
            this species of warfare and [he fought] valiantly, and
            he set out again on the road whereon he had been
            travelling. And having arrived at the desert he went
            up into a mountain wherein there were serpents; but
            inasmuch as the snakes found there were very numerous,
            he departed from that place and came to the border
            [of the desert] to dwell<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23-1"/> and took up his abode there.
            And the snakes, which were there when the righteous
            man set his foot upon that spot, speedily gave place unto
            him, and each one of them made the greatest possible
            haste to escape from him, as if he had been one whose
            <pb n="24"/>smell was distracting to them, and they knew that this
            man was not [one] of the people of that country.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now therefore the blessed man <persName>Anthony</persName> took up
            his abode there by himself, and he shut himself in; and
            he laid in a supply of bread once every six months
            (for the <persName>Egyptians</persName> were in the habit of making at one
            time bread sufficient even for a whole year), and as
            for water he found that there. And he went and
            dwelt there in a place which was like a cleft in the
            rocks, with the intention of seeing no man and of being
            seen by none, and he had his abode there for very
            many years; in the roof of his house there was a small
            opening, and through this he used to receive [bread]
            twice yearly, for the mountain wherein he dwelt was
            [remote] from inhabited land. Such people as came
            to him<anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#21"/>, whom he could not be induced to
            admit into his presence remained outside, perhaps for one
            or two days, and when they strained their ears that they
            might hear something, they would hear a noise like that
            of a mighty multitude of people, and confused sounds,
            and some sounds were like the voices of men shouting
            loudly, and some were great cries of lamentation, and
            some were those of men of slaughter and of a mighty
            tumult. And among all these was a voice which said,
           <quote>Depart thou from us! Why hast thou come to our
            country and to [cause] our death? Hast thou never
            heard that which thy Lord spake concerning us,</quote> saying,
            <quote>Evil spirits dwell in the desert, and in waste places,
            and in the lands wherein there is no water? Behold,
            henceforward thou shalt know that this is our habitation;
            depart thou, and give place unto us once more.</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            And when these words were heard those who were
            outside [<persName>Anthony</persName>'s dwelling] thought that men had entered 
            therein through the roof of [his house and that
            they were quarrelling with him; but when they had gone
            round about the house they found a small opening (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-1"/>
            <pb n="25"/>in the wall, and having looked through it they saw
            the blessed man alone. Then they understood that
            those voices were those of the devils who used to
            wage war against him, and mighty dread came upon
            them, and they began to cry out to the blessed man
            <persName>Anthony</persName>. Now the just man was more ready to
            hearken unto their words than unto the tumult of the
            devils, and to hold converse with them, and he would
            draw nigh to the side of the door, and say unto them,
            <quote>Come ye nigh unto me, and be not perturbed;</quote> and
            having conversed with them graciously, and filled their
            hearts, he would dismiss them in peace, and admonish
            them, saying, <quote>Be ye afraid neither of sounds (or,
            voices) nor of phantoms of this kind, for in this wise
            the devils are wont to act towards those who are
            timid; but seal ye yourselves with the Seal of the
            Cross, and return ye unto your homes in confidence
            and forgive those who make you laughingstocks.</quote>
            Thus they were dismissed in peace. And as for <persName>Anthony</persName> 
            himself he had dwelt in strife with the devils for
            a long time past, and was very courageous, and the
            strength which was in him was added to in proportion
            as <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#22"/>he saw that his enemies were vanquished.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now when the report of the kind of strife in which
            he lived reached his friends and acquaintances, they
            set out to go to him, for they thought that they would
            certainly find him dead;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-1"/> and, having arrived at the
            place where they wished to be, they came to the side
            of his house, and inclined their ears at the door that
            peradventure a sound or breathing might be heard
            inside. And they heard a sound like the voice of one
            who played a harp and said, <quote>Let God arise, and let
            all His enemies be scattered, and let all those who
            hate Him flee before Him; let them be destroyed
            even as smoke is made to disappear, and as wax
            melteth before the fire let the wicked perish before
            <pb n="26"/>God.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n26-1"/> And again, <quote>All the nations compassed me
            round about, and in the Name of the Lord I destroyed
            them.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n26-2"/> And the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> lived in this habitation 
            about twenty years.
         </p>
         <p>
            And it came to pass that in the process of time
            his fame reached all the monks who were in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>,
            and all the other folk therein who did not lead the
            life of the ascetic and recluse, and men of distinction,
            and monks in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> began to come unto him in large
            numbers; the <persName>Egyptian</persName> monks came that they might
            copy the manner of his life and deeds, and the laity
            came that he might pray over them, and might heal
            certain of them of their sicknesses. One day, when a
            multitude of people had come there in a body [to see
            him], and they had besought him repeatedly [to speak
            to them], and he had answered them never a word,
            they lifted the door out of its socket, and threw themselves 
            down on their faces before him, and made supplication 
            unto him and pacified him, and then each
            man among them stood up, and made known his
            request unto him. And having gone forth [to them],
            even like a man who gocth forth from the depths
            of the earth, they saw that his appearance was like
            unto that of an angel of light, and they marvelled why
            it was that his body had not been weakened by all
            his confinement, and why it was that his understanding
            had not become feeble, and why, on the contrary, his
            appearance, and his bodily stature, and his countenance
            were then as they had known them always to have
            been in the times which were past. Now when he
            saw <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#23"/>a large concourse of people he was not
            disturbed, and when they brought their petitions unto
            him he was not moved to impatient anger, but he
            remained in a placid and thoughtful state, for the Living 
            Word was unto him a guide. Among those who
            <pb n="27"/>came unto him there were many who were indeed
            very sorely afflicted, and our Lord healed them by
            the hand of the blessed man; and moreover, God
            gave him such a measure of grace in his speech
            that every man was wholly gratified thereat, for those
            who were in affliction and distress were encouraged
            to endure thereby, those who were occupied with contention 
            were quieted thereby, those who were afflicted
            sorely became longsuffering the haughty were made
            humble thereby, and the arrogant were brought low
            thereby, in order that every man might learn the
            doctrine of righteousness. For he used to say, <quote>That we
            should possess anything besides <persName>Christ</persName> is unnecessary,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27-1"/>
            and we should not esteem anything of value besides
            the love of <persName>Christ</persName>, neither possessions, nor kinsfolk,
            not even our soul itself. For if God did not spare
            His Son, but delivered Him up on account of our sins,
            how much the more is it right for us, having tasted
            and known Divine grace, to give our souls, not on
            His behalf, for such a thing is not required from us,
            but on behalf of our own lives.</quote> By these words he
            used to persuade many to withdraw themselves from
            this world and from the worry thereof, and to take
            refuge in a habitation of monks.
         </p>
         <p>
            And he began to increase from that time with <persName>Christ</persName>
            in simple-mindedness, and in love towards strangers,
            and in longsuffering; now these things not only go
            with us, but they also go before us, and they make
            ready for us a place in the country of the humble and
            meek, and no man should lack them, especially when
            he knoweth the will of his Lord, and that he is bound
            to prepare himself according to His will. Would any
            servant dare to stand before his master's face and say
            unto him, "Yesterday I toiled, but to-day I have done
            nothing at all?" Or, have we not heard what our
            <pb n="28"/>Lord said in the Gospel, "When a servant hath toiled
            nobly, and hath laboured in the work which is outside,
            as soon as he hath gone inside he shall weave a
            place for his hands <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#24"/>and shall minister unto
            his Lord, and then happiness shall be his?" Now,
            since we have heard these things from the Divine
            Books, what reason can we have for being without
            the fear of God? Was it not for this that <persName>Ezekiel</persName>
            the Prophet was made a watchman? Did not <persName>Judas</persName>, ,
            because of the one night wherein he wrought wickedness,
            lose the labour of all his days?
         </p>
         <p>
            Let us continue to be strenuous then, O children
            of our profession, and let it not become wearisome
            unto us, for our Lord hath been made a Guide unto
            us and unto every man who hath a desire for the
            virtues. And that it may not be tedious unto us the
            blessed <persName>Paul</persName> became an example unto us aforetime,
            and said, <quote>I die daily.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-1"/> Now if we were to think that
            we had to die daily we should never sin at all, and
            this is the explanation of the word which was spoken.
            If when it is morning we were to imagine that we
            should never arrive at the evening, and if also when
            it is evening we thought that we should never arrive
            at the morning: by this thought also the nature of
            our life would teach us that it is not a matter for
            confidence. If therefore we prepare our mind in this
            manner, and if we live with this thought therein, we
            should never be overcome by sin, and the lust of time
            would not reign over us, and we should not keep
            anger against a fellow creature of flesh, and we should
            not love the possessions which pass away, and we
            should forgive every man who offended us. And the
            lust for women would die in the heart, for how could
            it be ministered unto? For at all times every thing
            which is greater than its fellow overcometh its fellow,
            and the fear of God exalteth itself above everything.
         </p>
         <pb n="29"/>
         <p>
            Now therefore, O my beloved, let us be zealous
            in carrying out the work whereunto we have once
            bound ourselves, and let us travel to the end on the
            road whereon we have begun to journey, and let no
            man among us look behind him, lest we be like unto
            the wife of Lot.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29-1"/> It is not easy for him that shall
            turn behind him, after he hath received the doctrine
            of righteousness, to enter into the kingdom of heaven;
            he that turneth back, whatsoever be the way in which
            he turn, will repent of what he hath done, and he will
            turn to the elements of this world, even as <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#25"/>
            a dog to his vomit. Be ye therefore not afraid as if
            ye were carrying a heavy burden, for the burden of
            our Lord is easy and light unto those who desire it;
            if therefore we have the desire everything is easy
            unto us. The children of this world travel over the
            seas and make journeys across difficult countries in
            order that they may learn profane wisdom, in the
            doctrine of which the means of righteousness is not
            employed, and in the praise of which there is no profit of
            life; but we are not wanted either to set out on a journey
            or to travel on the sea for the sake of the kingdom of
            heaven, for our Lord declared aforetime, saying, <quote>The
            kingdom of heaven is within you.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29-2"/> So therefore, O my
            beloved, life is in our own hands to gain, for it is within
            us, and it is ministered unto by us. For the soul by
            its nature possesseth the perception of the understanding, 
            and therefore our soul hath knowledge of what
            our life is; it is prepared by the nature of its creation,
            and is ready for everything which it wisheth. Therefore 
            also <persName>Joshua</persName>, the son of <persName>Nun</persName>, commanded the people,
            saying, <quote>Prepare your hearts before the God of <placeName>Israel</placeName>;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29-3"/>
            and <persName>John</persName> also said, <quote>Prepare your ways.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29-4"/> Now when
            <pb n="30"/>the Book decreeth the preparation of the soul, it wisheth
            that the rectitude of the nature of its first creation
            shall be in it, but when it goeth forth from its limit
            it is condemned by the Book like the Evil One. Therefore 
            the matter is not a difficult one unto us. For, if
            we remain in that wherein we were created from the
            beginning, life is in us and with us; and our mind
            also condemneth us when it thinketh evil and hath
            envy of the thoughts, and bringeth forth a deed of injury 
            in an unseemly manner. Everything, therefore, is
            given into our own power to do, and there is no
            master set over us to command us what we shall do;
            moreover, there is no who can restrain us
            either from thinking or doing fair things; whether we
            live or whether we die belongeth unto ourselves. For
            if we desire to hold ourselves excused<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-1"/> from thoughts
            of the wicked and of deposit[s]<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-2"/> let us take heed diligently 
            and guard <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#26"/>for our Lord the liberty,
            which hath been given unto us without blemish, as
            something which we have received from the beginning,
            and let us be faithful children unto the Lord. Therefore 
            take ye heed, O my beloved sons, that ye keep
            not silence like those who have been brought low
            through sin, or by wrath or by lust; for it is written
            that the anger of a man perfecteth not the righteousness
            of God, and besides, lust conceiveth and bringeth forth
            sin, and when sin hath been performed completely<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-3"/> it
            bringeth forth death.
         </p>
         <p>
            In this wise, O my beloved, let us lead the life of
            watchfulness and strenuousness, even as it is written,
            <quote>Keep thine heart with all diligence,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30-4"/> for we have
            cunning and crafty enemies, and it is against these
            that our strife must be, even as the <persName>Apostle</persName> said, <quote>Our
            <pb n="31"/>contending is not against flesh and blood, but against
            principalities, and powers, and against those who are
            masters of the world of darkness which is beneath
            the heavens.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31-1"/> Their contending against us is very
            frequent, and there is no respite to their attacks upon
            us. Now even between the devils there is a distinction,
            and concerning their nature and concerning [this] difference 
            it would be a labour to narrate; but we will here
            reveal and describe very briefly those things which
            are necessary to be learnt concerning their contending
            against us, and their temptings, and their blandishments
            (or, flatteries), and, in short, the whole system of their
            cunning.
         </p>
         <p>
            Before this, however, it is proper for us to learn
            that the beings which are called devils were not created
            that they might be devils, for there is nothing evil in
            the works of God, and even they were created beautiful 
            beings; but when they turned aside from the
            mind of righteousness, or from the heavenly understanding, 
            they were removed to a distance from the
            place wherein they lived. And seeing that they were
            cast away by the exalted Will they drew nigh and
            mingled themselves among created things (or, creation),
            and they made the heathen to go astray wholly according 
            to their desire; and against us, because they have
            envy of us, they multiply their contendings that, peradventure, 
            they may be able to divert us from the
            way of the truth of the kingdom of heaven, and that
            we may not attain unto the country wherefrom they
            were swept out <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#27"/>and fell. Therefore the
            labour of prayer and of abundant supplication is necessary 
            for us, that through Divine Providence, and through
            the gift which we have received from the Holy Spirit,
            we may be able to know what distinction existeth
            between the evil spirits, and what each one of them
            hath been commanded to [seek] after, and by what
            <pb n="32"/>manner of means the destruction of every one of them
            is to be brought about. For their cunning is very
            great, and they spread abroad the root of their net
            in everything. Therefore the blessed <persName>Apostle</persName> and the
            rest of the righteous men who, like him, had experience
            of and had tried the Tempter in everything, and it is
            for this very reason that they have declared it, said,
            <quote>The artifices of the Evil One shall not overcome us.</quote>
            And I will now narrate something of what I have
            endured from them, and a little of the vast knowledge
            which I have of them, and, like the beloved Prophets,
            I will tell what I understand about them.
         </p>
         <p>
            The whole race of devils is beyond measure an
            envious one, and it is altogether jealous of all mankind,
            and particularly of the monks, for they cannot bear
            to see heavenly deeds wrought and heavenly lives led
            upon the earth, and they, therefore, make hidden pits
            and snares for us, as it is written, <quote>They have laid
            their nets over my paths;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n32-1"/> now [the words] <quote>their
            nets</quote> mean thoughts of iniquity. Let us, however,
            be not afraid of their commotion, and let us not be
            made lax by reason of their blandishments (or, flatteries);
            but let us be constant in fasting and in prayer, and
            straightway they shall be vanquished and disappear.
            Now when they depart let us not be confident and
            say, <quote>Behold, they are put to shame, and we are freed
            from them,</quote> for this species can never be put to
            shame, and it knoweth not how to blush; for whilst
            their temptations are being brought to nought on this
            side, they make an attack upon us on the other; and
            when they have examined and tried by what means
            the understanding may be flattered or made to be
            terrified, they multiply excuses (or, reasons) to it such
            as the following. The devils are in the habit of leading 
            men astray with some such reason as this:–"Behold, 
            we will inform you concerning the things which
            <pb n="33"/>are about to be," and then they shew them phantoms
            which reach up to the heavens, and mansions<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33-1"/> which
            are exceedingly strong, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#28"/>so that by means
            of these similitudes they may lead astray those whom
            they are not able to injure in their minds.
         </p>
         <p>
            It is quite unnecessary that we who are believers
            should be terrified either by the motions of the various
            species of devils, or by the various similitudes (which
            they assume), and we should not be afraid of their
            voices which are angry and threatening at one time,
            and which are flattering at another. For the Evil One
            is a liar, and there is no truth either in his words or
            his deeds. But although mankind once gave him power
            and sin lifted up its horn, our Lord hath now broken
            the goad (or, sting) thereof, and hath humbled it and
            brought it down beneath our feet; and it hath been
            made a thing for the Gentiles to trample upon and a
            laughingstock to the nations. And this is a proof that
            the matter is thus, and righteousness testifieth that it
            hath been performed in creation, for behold, he who,
            in his error, is exalted in his heart, and who boasteth
            that he can dry up the sea and can parcel out the
            dry land, hath not the power to destroy the heavenly
            mind which is in the monks, and he is unable to divert
            such a small and unimportant creature as myself from
            speaking about him. Now the devils are cunning, but
            they can only lead astray those upon whom they find
            an opportunity for exercising their wiles; they appear
            in all kinds of forms and similitudes, and it happeneth
            that the Evil One even demandeth for himself the
            form of righteousness, as it is written, <quote><persName>Satan</persName> even
            taketh upon himself the form of an angel of light.</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            There is a time when we see no man and yet the
            sound of the working of the devils is heard by us,
            and it is like the singing of a song in a loud voice;
            and there are time[s] when the words of the Scriptures
            <pb n="34"/>are heard by us, just as if a living man were repeating 
            them, and they are exactly like the words which
            we should hear if a man were reading the Book. And
            it also happeneth that they rouse us up to the night
            prayer, and incite us to stand up; and they make apparent 
            unto us also the similitudes of monks and the
            form[s] of those who mourn (i. e., the anchorites); and
            they draw nigh unto us as if they had come from a
            long way off, and they begin to utter words like unto
            these, that they may make lax the understanding of
            those who are little of soul:–<quote>It is now a law unto
            all creation that we love desolation,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-1"/> but we were unable<anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#29"/>, 
            by reason of God, to enter into our
            houses when we came unto them, and to do fair
            things.</quote> And when they are unable to work their
            will by means of a scheme of this kind, they depart
            from this kind of deceit unto another, [and say], <quote>How
            now is it possible for thee to live? For thou hast
            sinned and committed iniquity in many things. Thinkest 
            thou that the spirit hath not revealed unto me
            what hath been done by thee, or that I know not
            that thou hast done such and such a thing?</quote> If, therefore, 
            a simple brother hear these things, and feel
            within himself that he hath done even as the Evil
            One [hath said], and he be not acquainted with his
            craftiness, his mind shall be troubled straightway, and
            he shall fall into despair and turn backwards.
         </p>
         <p>
            It is then, O my beloved, unnecessary for us to be
            terrified at these things, and we have need to fear
            only when the devils multiply the speaking of the
            things which are true, and then we must rebuke them
            severely; for even in the days of our Redeemer when
            they spake<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34-2"/> [unto Him] the things which were true
            <pb n="35"/>He rebuked them and made them to hold their peace
            and to speak not, lest they should mingle their wickedness
            with the truth in the words which they were speaking. 
            Let us then take heed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35-1"/> that we incline not our
            hearing to their words, even though they be words of
            truth which they utter; for it would be a disgrace
            unto us that those who have rebelled against God
            should become [our] teachers. And let us, O my
            brethren, arm ourselves with the armour of righteousness, 
            and let us put on the helmet of redemption, and
            in the time of contending let us shoot out from a
            believing mind spiritual arrows as from a bow which
            is stretched (or, bent). For they are nothing at all,
            and even if they were their strength hath in it nothing
            which would enable it to resist the might of the Cross.
            Whatsoever they do they do like thieves and robbers,
            and not after the manner of fighting<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35-2"/> men, for they
            have not the strength to stand up and to contend for
            any length of time; and they shout, and wrangle, and
            make tumultuous noises and commotions that, peradventure, 
            by means of the sheer fright which they themselves 
            inspire they may be able to lead away captive
            weak minds and to make them do their will. If they
            had the power to perform <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#30"/>anything, or to
            do any harm whatsoever, so much tumult, and outcry,
            and trouble would be unnecessary, and if one of them
            only were to come he could perform [by himself] that
            which he had been deputed to do. For when the
            angel of truth was sent by the Lord of creation against
            the camp of the <persName>Assyrians</persName> he had no need of many
            companions, and he came not with tumult and terror,
            but with quietness and firmness he made use of the
            power which had been given to him, and destroyed
            one hundred and fourscore and five thousand of the
            <pb n="36"/><persName>Assyrians</persName>; but the assembly of the evil ones, because
            it possesseth not the power of performing its own will,
            maketh use of means which are full of terror.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now if any man shall say, <quote>Supposing now the
            devils to have no power in them, by what agency
            did they bring upon <persName>Job</persName> all the calamity which is
            written in the Book?</quote> let him understand that he must
            think in this wise, that is to say, that the Evil One
            hath no power to do harm, and that God only gave
            it into his hands to tempt him; for if this were not
            thus He would not have stripped him of everything,
            and He would have had compassion upon his soul, for
            mercy is not found with him. In this wise must a
            man think. Moreover, the Evil One appeareth to
            have been particularly feeble, inasmuch as the just
            man vanquished him in the contest which he waged
            with a man; yet this is not a matter for wonder, my
            beloved, for <persName>Job</persName> the just was not given over into the
            hands of the Evil One. And know ye that unless God
            had so wished he would neither have had power over
            <persName>Job</persName> himself, nor over his herds and his flocks, nor
            over the miserable wealth of those who were spectators
            of him–if a man may say so. And that the matter
            is thus be ye persuaded from the blessed Gospel, for
            when our Lord restrained and pursued the devils in
            one place they besought him to permit them to enter
            into a herd of swine which was nigh unto them. If
            now the devils had not power over the swine, how
            much [less] can they have power over man <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#31"/>
            who was made in the image of God? So therefore
            in proportion as it is necessary for us to increase our
            fear of God it is meet for us to add to the contempt
            which we should have for the congregation of the evil
            ones. Now in what way can we increase our fear of
            God, or in what way are we able to add to our contempt 
            for the evil ones? The means by which both
            these things are to be performed are similar in each
            case. Whensoever we make our life and deeds better
            <pb n="37"/>than they were before, we increase the pleasure which
            we give to God, and we also multiply the contempt
            which we have for the evil ones; for the devils are
            far more afraid of the fasting of the monks, and of
            their prayers, and of their chastity, and of their abstinence, 
            and of their meekness, and of their gentleness,
            than they are of their exploits, and they are afraid
            most of all of their righteousness which is in <persName>Christ</persName>;
            and all these [virtues] pierce them on every side after
            the manner of arrows, and for this reason they do all
            they can, and they become mad and foam at the mouth,
            that if they can help it they may not arrive at this
            condition of disgrace.
         </p>
         <p>
            Therefore do not ye give unto them an opportunity
            in any matter whatsoever, neither when they come
            against us in the guise of enemies in wars, nor when
            under the form of friends they attempt to flatter us;
            for they are wont to draw nigh unto us in the guise
            of friends and to reveal matters unto us. At one time
            they will come unto us and inform us beforehand concerning 
            the coming of the brethren, and at another
            we hear (from them) also rumours and reports [of things
            which are] remote; when therefore it happeneth that
            they tell us of something which is going to happen,
            and it cometh to pass, let us not be disturbed. For
            it is not a great thing, seeing that they themselves
            are spirits in their persons, that they should see and
            perceive the brethren who are coming to us, and should
            tell us beforehand of their coming, and should [make
            known] a matter which hath happened in a certain
            place, and that they should be as it were those who
            revealed it unto us. Now these things a runner who
            is swift in his course could do, and also a horseman
            who rideth rapidly. Therefore, let us not be led away
            after their deeds through such things, and let us neither
            marvel at them nor think that they are matters of
            importance, for that they are not things <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#32"/>
            which have not been done already hath been made known
            <pb n="38"/>aforetime; but to reveal secret things and to make
            known what is to be performed aforetime are things
            which are in the hands of God only.
         </p>
         <p>
            Know ye, however, O my beloved, that they have
            made known to many who were afar off the fortune
            of this our present congregation, and all matters which
            were in dispute; and of what I have said the following
            [words] will afford a proof and an explanation. It hath
            happened by chance that a man hath set out from
            <placeName>India</placeName>, or from some remote country, to come unto us,
            and when as yet we did not see him or know anything 
            about him, straightway we have had sight of
            him and have heard where he was prepared to go,
            for immediately [the devils] seized upon the word[s]
            quickly and brought it unto us, saying, <quote>Behold, such
            and such a man from such and such a place is coming 
            unto you.</quote> It hath happened, moreover, that the
            man who was coming was a king, or that some obstacle 
            hath prevented him from coming, whomsoever
            he was, or that having travelled a certain distance,
            which was not little, he returned to his own country,
            but nevertheless the shameful and reprehensible craftiness 
            of the devils had found it out.
         </p>
         <p>
            And thus it is also in the case of the waters of
            the river <placeName>Giḥôn (Nile)</placeName> which is in our country, for
            they inform us beforehand whensoever they are going
            to rise. And whensoever they see the clouds and the
            abundant rain which [falleth] in <placeName>India</placeName>, (now this river <placeName>Nile</placeName>
            cometh from that country) they know and see that by
            reason of the storm which hath taken place in <placeName>India</placeName>,
            the river will be full from one bank to the other, and
            that the final rise of the waters of the <placeName>Nile</placeName> cometh they
            declare beforehand, and thus they lead astray the souls
            of various people who lack understanding. Now the
            inhabitants of <placeName>India</placeName> also if they had the power to
            travel as the devils have would come and announce
            the rise of the waters of the <placeName>Nile</placeName> to the people who
            are in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>.
         </p>
         <pb n="39"/>
         <p>
            And the matter is like that of the watchman when
            he goeth up to some high place in the sight of the
            whole camp and is able to see him that is coming
            before he arriveth; but he who cometh is also able to
            afford exact information concerning what is coming
            and what are the contents of his despatch, and what
            is the condition of the nation from whom he cometh.
            In like manner do the devils see or hear and give
            information [concerning what they see and hear beforehand]. 
            Now if that which God meditateth concerning
            the waters of the river<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n39-1"/> ....... <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#33"/>for He
            hath the power ...., their cunning handiwork is reprehensible 
            unto us who are wise, but unto those who
            lack understanding their error is sweet. By such means
            of error as these hath paganism made its way throughout 
            creation, but the Lord of created things came and
            rebuked him that did these things, and humbled his
            spirit; and behold, the earth is tilled by the law of
            righteousness, and by the sword of the Spirit; and
            behold, the thorns, and the briars, and all the weeds
            of the seed of the Evil One have been rooted out
            therefrom. Such are the means which are made use
            of by their error, and with such forms as these do they
            lead astray creation. And supposing there be among
            you, O my children, any man who shall say, "Behold,
            do not the devils declare many things which they
            have not [before] heard, and do not they see many
            things which they have not before seen?" even if
            this be so, O my beloved, let not your minds be
            disturbed thereby; but enter ye into the counsel of
            your mind, and get understanding concerning the things
            of [this] world, and from these ye will obtain the power
            of [preserving your minds] free from storm[s].
         </p>
         <p>
            And before all things know that the physicians, by
            means of the experience which they have gotten of
            their handicraft, are able to know of a certainty before
            <pb n="40"/>a man falleth sick whether he will live or die, and how
            long the sickness will last, and when it will be at an
            end. And it happeneth that, even when a man himself 
            hath no idea that he is about to enter into
            afflictions, the physicians from their constant practice
            and from the experience which they have acquired,
            are able to inform [him] concerning the sicknesses
            which are about to come upon him, even when the
            first symptoms thereof have not declared themselves.
            Now the power of foretelling things is even greater
            with those who steer ships than with the physicians,
            for they have experience of the heavens (or, sky) and
            of the wind which is therein, and they are able to
            declare several days beforehand on what day the
            heavens (or, sky) will change, and at what periods
            the wind will become strong, and these things they
            can do by their knowledge and by their experience.
            And know ye also that the ability of the devils is not
            superior to that of helmsmen and physicians, for they
            also by their experience of matters are able to declare
            what they have never before heard, and to describe
            what they have never before seen<anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#34"/>. Unto
            you then these devils and the supplication which concerneth 
            them are superfluities; let those who are without 
            them seek these things, but seek ye not freedom
            therefrom, and let it be unto you an object to finish
            your work.
         </p>
         <p>
            For who [hath commanded us] that we should be
            strenuous in this matter, and should know it? Who
            among the men of olden time received praise because
            they had knowledge of events before they happened?
            And who [among them] was ever blamed because
            he had no knowledge of events which were afar
            off or were about to take place [immediately]? Each
            one of us will, however, be judged if he performeth
            not the work of righteousness, and not because he
            knoweth or doth not know. Therefore let us excuse
            ourselves from this supplication and let us pray, not
            <pb n="41"/>that we may know secret things, but that we may
            please the Divine Majesty, and that power may be
            given unto us to stand against the darts of the Evil
            One; but if we also desire to know hidden things, this
            too is in our own hands, and we must purify our heart
            as a habitation for the Holy Spirit, and behold, He
            will abide and rest in us, and by the rays of light
            which proceed from Him our eye will be able to see
            hidden things from remote distances. Did not <persName>Elisha</persName>,
            who was a man like unto ourselves,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41-1"/> through the purity
            of his heart see that which his eyes had never seen?
         </p>
         <p>
            Ye must then make a distinction between the things
            of the Holy Spirit, and the things of the congregation
            of the Evil One. And perhaps ye will say, <quote>How are
            we to make the distinction?</quote> First of all, pray and
            make supplication unto the Revealer of secret things
            that He will make you to possess [the power] of
            distinguishing between these matters; and for the rest
            I myself am bound to impart unto you gladly, as my
            sons, whatsoever I have learned from a long experience.
            The visions and revelations of the Holy Spirit are not
            of a terrifying or tumultuous character, for they take
            place under conditions of rest and tranquillity, and in
            like manner also with gentle pleasure and quiet satisfaction 
            doth the soul feel the rise of the Holy Ghost
            therein, for it is not wont to put terror into people
            or to produce trembling where it maketh itself to be
            seen. Look ye now into the Scriptures and they will
            inform you in what manner the revelation of the Spirit
            taketh place, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#35"/>and they will shew you that
            it taketh place in restfulness, and gladness, and peace;
            these are the similitudes which are in the revelation
            of the Spirit, and whensoever it is brought about it is
            done in this manner. And if, after the manner of men,
            a man be straightway terrified or greatly moved through
            the love of the thing itself, or through the beauty of
            <pb n="42"/>the revelation, and through the quietness and pleasure
            which are caused thereby, in due season the fear or
            terror will come to an end, and comfort and gladness
            will come to him in its place, even as <persName>Gabriel</persName> wrought
            for <persName>Zachariah</persName>, and according to what the other angels
            did for the blessed women at the grave of our Lord,
            and the angel who appeared unto the shepherds and
            proclaimed to them the good news of the birth of our
            Redeemer. And ye will find many other instances
            which are like unto these in the Scriptures if ye seek
            for them. Now if the soul be terrified or be afraid
            by reason of those visions it doth not follow that such
            fright is caused by the Evil One, for it may, peradventure, 
            arise in it because the soul thinketh itself unworthy 
            of the heavenly revelation which hath been
            vouchsafed unto it. This then is the manner of the
            revelation of the knowledge of the truth.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now fright of the Evil One cometh about in this
            wise. First of all the soul is disturbed and terrified,
            and it heareth the sounds of a great tumult, and of the
            playing of musical instruments, and of singing, which
            are like unto those made at a feast of drunken men
            and in the caves of robbers, and because of these
            sounds which it heareth the timid soul is greatly moved,
            and for this reason it becometh afraid; and moreover,
            the other souls which are brave are terrified because
            they have heard strange sounds, for all their affairs
            in every possible way belong to tribulation and misery.
            And there is a time when they ask for the similitudes
            of the persons of the children of men in very truth,
            and although [they do] thus, it is well known that it
            is merely a phantom and the form of a man only
            [which they obtain]. For however much an <persName>Indian</persName>
            were to rub himself he could never make himself
            resemble a Greek, and similarly with <persName>Satan</persName>, however
            many forms of the children of men he might steal for
            himself in order to enable him to declare unto those
            who beheld him that the truth was with him, and to
            <pb n="43"/>lead into error <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#36"/>the children of the truth,
            and however much the phantom might resemble the
            reality, that it could be compared with it is impossible.
            There is therefore no room for the devils to lead us
            into error by any one of these things, and whatsoever
            they do, they do to their own disgrace.
         </p>
         <p>
            Understand ye also the following matter, and learn
            briefly concerning it, that is to say, in the revelation
            of the Spirit, and in the tumult caused by devils [in
            the soul] fear is vouchsafed. In respect of the devils,
            however, they can certainly stir up in us a tumult, and
            put terror therein, but they cannot turn them away and
            make an end of them; now whilst the Holy Spirit is
            revealing itself to a man, the soul is greatly moved
            by the majesty thereof, but the terror which it hath
            of Him cometh to an end speedily, and perfect happiness 
            maketh its abode in him. Thus are the wiles
            and crafts of the Evil One, but, even according to the
            things which I have already said, let us not be moved
            by the fear which he causeth, and let us not be terrified 
            at his visions, and let us not turn unto him and
            make ourselves subject to him so that he may say
            unto us, <quote>Fall ye down and worship me.</quote> By his wiles
            and crafts he hath led the heathen into error, and they
            imagine that he is God, but the fearers of our Lord
            have prevented us, and they have gathered us into His
            habitation, and [thus there is not given unto him an
            opportunity of leading us into captivity. For the Evil
            One is exceedingly bold, and he is without shame, and
            he even dared to approach our Lord in his madness
            and depravity, that is to say, the body which He had
            put on; and our Lord looked upon him and scorned
            him, and rebuked him, and said, <quote>Get thee behind me,
            <persName>Satan</persName>: for it is written, Thou shalt worship the Lord
            thy God, and Him only shalt thou serve.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43-1"/> Through
            the consolation of these things especially the Evil One
            <pb n="44"/>should be held in contempt in our sight; for the word
            which was spoken by our Lord to <persName>Satan</persName> was spoken
            on our behalf and on account of us, that in the same
            manner we ourselves might also rebuke the devils, and
            that as the Evil One was destroyed before the word
            of our Lord, so he might also perish and come to an
            end before our words, for in this he cannot multiply
            boasting.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now when <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#37"/>our word hath power over
            the devils, and the fiends [run] terrified from before
            us, let no man marvel when he rebuketh the demons
            and they become subject unto him, and let him not
            hold in contempt another man by whose hands a similar
            thing cannot be wrought, but let him examine first of
            all and understand the lives and works of various men,
            and from this [scrutiny] let him know with whom abideth 
            Divine Grace, and where the righteousness of God
            resteth; for they will be unto us a very much better
            mirror than those who cast out devils, and in them
            the wicked will be able to see their blemishes and [so]
            become rebuked, and in them good men will be able
            to look carefully at their career and become strengthened.
            Whether a man becometh a prosperous toiler
            or an abject coward belongeth unto himself, but for a
            man to stretch out his hand against the devils and
            for them to yield place belongeth not unto him but
            unto heavenly Grace. For when the Disciples returned
            with joy unto their Lord from [preaching the] Gospel
            which they had been sent out to preach, they rejoiced
            in that even the devils were obedient unto their words.
            Now therefore let him that hath discernment look and
            hearken unto this answer which was given unto them:–
            <quote>Rejoice ye not because the devils also have been
            made subject unto you, but rejoice because your names
            have been written down in heaven.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44-1"/> Now for names
            to be written down in the Book of Life is a testimony
            <pb n="45"/>to conduct which is pleasing<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#45n-1"/> [to God] and an upright
            mind for those who are worthy of this thing; but power
            over devils is, manifestly, [a mark of] the grace of our
            Redeemer. And that [ye may know that] this is so,
            observe what <persName>Christ</persName> answered those who took refuge
            in this thing when the spirits were going forth before
            Him and they said unto Him, <quote>In Thy Name we have
            cast out devils, and have performed many signs and
            wonders.</quote> And He said unto them, <quote>Verily, verily,
            I say unto you I know you not.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n45-2"/> Therefore let us
            pray, as I have already said, that there may be given
            unto us the grace to seek after the [power to] distinguish
            between spirits, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#38"/>according to the word of the
            Book which saith, <quote>Be not ye led astray by the spirits
            which err.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n45-3"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            [THE FOLLOWING IS] BY THE HOLY WRITER MÂR <!-- I am not sure how to mark this up. -->
            <persName>ATHANASIUS</persName>. Now I merit praise in that whilst repeating 
            the triumphs of the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> I desire to
            keep silence concerning many things, being at the same
            time very careful not to speak anything on mine own
            authority only; it is sufficient for me to record the things
            which actually took place. Let not any man imagine
            that we declare these matters as a pastime, but let
            him be sure that we narrate them as things which
            took place in very truth, and that we do so knowing
            from actual experience that they are true, and that we
            are only placing on record the wonderful acts of the
            blessed man that they may form a small memorial of
            him. Let the wise man know the purity of our intention 
            and that we do not narrate the things which
            have been said by us in this history without a good
            object; and we shall be made strong by the measure
            of your love. For I am convinced that it would be
            <pb n="46"/>neither useful nor beneficial if matters of this kind were
            spoken of in a boastful manner, because our Adversary
            is very crafty, and it might happen that he could cause
            us to stumble even in a thing which concerneth the
            truth; therefore, whilst recording the narrative of the
            histories of the wiles and arts of the Evil One, it is
            meet that we should make you to be watchful against
            his subtlety.
         </p>
         <p>
            THE BLESSED AND HOLY MAN <persName>ANTHONY</persName><!-- I am not sure how to mark this up. --> [saith]:–How
            often then did they ascribe blessings in a loud voice,
            and whilst the voice of blessing was reaching my ears,
            the words of cursing were sent forth by them. For
            how many times did they inform me beforehand concerning 
            the flood of the <placeName>Nile</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46-1"/> that is to say, of the
            river <placeName>Gîḥón</placeName>, and how many times did I say unto them,
            <quote>And as for you what have ye?</quote> And I used to say
            unto them, <quote>I have no need to learn these things from
            you,</quote> but they would come again to me after this in
            the guise of thieves, and they would surround me, and
            would stand up and utter threats against me, having
            at the same time their weapons upon them. And
            again, on another occasion they were suddenly found
            filling my house with serpents of various kinds, and
            with reptiles in large numbers, and with these there
            were also horses which neighed; then straightway I
            made myself ready and I stood up and I lifted up my
            voice in Psalms, and said, <quote>Some [put their trust in
            chariots, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#39"/>and some in horses, but we will
            be strong in the Name of the Lord our God,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46-2"/> and
            immediately they came to an end and disappeared from
            before me. On another occasion they came to me by
            night, and they were holding torches of fire and were
            saying, <quote>We have come now to burn thee [alive], O <persName>Anthony</persName>,</quote> 
            and as they were saying these things unto me
            I closed my eyes so that I might shew them that I
            <pb n="47"/>had placed their light in the portion of darkness; and
            straightway I put on the armour of prayer against
            them, and whilst I was praying the light of the sinful 
            ones was extinguished, and it was no more.
         </p>
         <p>
            And again, after a few months they came in the
            guise of the singers of the Psalms, and they began to
            speak to me [with words] from the Scriptures: but I,
            like a deaf man, did not hearken unto them. On
            another occasion they shook down upon me the habitation 
            wherein I was living, but I laughed at them by
            reason of my confidence which [was placed] in our
            Lord, and my mind was in no way whatsoever disturbed 
            by them. And after this they came unto me
            with whistlings and they were beating their hands
            together and dancing with joy;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47-1"/> but when they saw
            that notwithstanding all their clamour I did not cease
            to pray, and that I held not my peace from the singing 
            of Psalms, like unto men who have been defeated
            and overcome they turned their songs of joy into
            lamentations, and they began to wail and to beat
            their breasts in grief, and at the same time I gave
            thanks unto my good Lord for all these things, and
            because He had broken, and destroyed, and brought
            low, and humbled, their audacious arrogance and mad
            folly.
         </p>
         <p>
            And again, on another occasion, there appeared
            (unto me) a devil of an exceedingly haughty and insolent 
            appearance, and he stood up before me with
            the tumultuous noise of many people, and he dared to
            say unto me <quote>I, even I, am the power of God,</quote> and
            <quote>I, even I, am the Lord of the worlds.</quote> And he said
            unto me <quote>What dost thou wish me to give thee? Ask
            and thou shalt receive.</quote> Then I blew a puff of wind
            at him, and I rebuked him in the Name of <persName>Christ</persName>, and
            I made ready to smite him, and when, as I thought,
            I did smite him, at that very moment all his strength
            <pb n="48"/>and all his host [of fiends] at the [mention of] the
            Name of <persName>Christ</persName> came to an end. And on another
            occasion, when I was fasting, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#40"/>the crafty one
            appeared unto me in the form of a brother monk
            carrying bread, and he began to speak unto me words
            of counsel, saying, <quote>Rise up, and stay thy heart with
            bread and water, and rest a little from thine excessive
            labours, for thou art a man, and howsoever greatly
            thou mayest be exalted thou art clothed with a mortal
            body, and [thou shouldst] fear sicknessess and tribulations.</quote> 
            Then I regarded his words, and I held my
            peace and refrained from giving [him] an answer. And
            I bowed myself down in quietness and I began to
            make supplication in prayer, and I said, <quote>O Lord, make
            Thou an end of him even as Thou hast been wont
            to do him away at all times;</quote> and as I concluded my
            words he came to an end and vanished like dust, and
            went forth from the door like smoke.
         </p>
         <p>
            And again, how very many times in the desert
            hath he shewn before me things like phantoms which
            resembled gold in order that I might bow myself down
            before him and touch him even with my finger! I,
            however, never, ceased from singing the songs of the
            Holy Spirit. And how very many times when I was
            receiving enjoyment in the Holy Spirit did he disturb
            me in anger, and he even dared so far as to strike
            me! Not that I myself am of any account whatsoever,
            but that it may be seen that the power of our Lord
            is mighty, and that it cannot be vanquished even in
            the feeble ones who believe in Him. And <persName>Satan</persName> laid
            upon me hard stripes (or, cruel blows), and in proportion 
            as he multiplied them I kept crying out with
            a loud voice, saying, <quote>There is nothing which shall
            separate me from the love of God;</quote> and after these
            words [had been said] <persName>Satan</persName> and the members of his
            host fell one upon the other, and each of them vented
            his wrath upon his fellow. Now it was God, Who
            aforetime reduced <persName>Satan</persName> to subjection, and God alone,
            <pb n="49"/>Who performed all these things which I have related;
            and [the Book] saith, "I saw <persName>Satan</persName> like lightning fall
            from heaven."<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49-1"/>: And I, O my sons, remember the
            word[s] of the <persName>Apostle</persName>, who said, <quote>I have spoken these
            things for your behalf, both for myself and for Apollos
            that ye may learn of us;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49-2"/> in this wise ye also must
            learn of me <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#41"/>these things which ye have
            heard, and ye shall not be wearied [in running] your
            course and ye shall not fear the appearances (or, visions)
            of <persName>Satan</persName> and of all his hosts. And even though I, like
            a simple man, have made use of these histories, it is for
            you to hold them to be true; for it is meet that we should
            bring forward in this place whatsoever we remember,
            lest under one pretext or another, or by some means
            or other, [<persName>Satan</persName>] draw nigh unto you, and that ye may
            find yourselves ready [to fight against all his schemes.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now on one occasion <persName>Satan</persName> approached the house
            one night and knocked at the door, and I went out
            to see who was knocking, and I lifted up mine eyes
            and saw the form of an exceedingly tall, and strong
            man; and having asked him, <quote>Who art thou?</quote> he
            answered and said unto me, <quote>I am <persName>Satan</persName>.</quote> And after
            this I said unto him, <quote>What seekest thou?</quote> and he
            answered and said unto me, <quote>Why do the monks, and
            the anchorites, and the other <persName>Christians</persName> revile me,
            and why do they at all times heap curses upon me?</quote>
            And having clasped my head firmly<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49-3"/> [in wonder] at
            his mad folly, I said unto him, <quote>Wherefore dost thou
            give them trouble?</quote> Then he answered and said
            unto me, <quote>It is not I who trouble them, but it is they
            who trouble themselves. For there happened unto me
            on a certain occasion that which did happen to me,
            and had I not cried out to them that I was the
            Enemy, his slaughterers would have come to an end
            <pb n="50"/>for ever.
            I have, therefore, no place [to dwell in],
            and not one glittering sword, and not even people
            who are really subject unto me, for those who are
            in service to me hold me wholly in contempt; and
            moreover, I have to keep them in fetters, for they
            do not cleave to me because they esteem it right to
            do so, and they are ever ready to escape from me in
            every place. The <persName>Christians</persName> have filled the whole
            world, and behold, even the desert is filled full with
            [their] monasteries and habitations. Let them then
            take good heed to themselves when they heap abuse
            upon me.</quote> Then, wondering at the grace of our
            Lord, I said unto him, <quote>How doth it happen that whilst
            thou hast been a liar on every other occasion at this
            present the truth is spoken by thee? And how is it
            that thou speakest the truth now when thou art wont
            to utter lies? <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#42"/>It is indeed true that when
            <persName>Christ</persName> came into [this] world thou wast brought down
            to the lowest depths, and that the root of thine error
            was plucked up from the earth.</quote> And when <persName>Satan</persName>
            heard the Name of <persName>Christ</persName> his form vanished and his
            words came to an end. Since, therefore, <persName>Satan</persName> himself
            confessed that there was nothing in his power, we are
            compelled wholly to despise him and his host. Such
            then are the crafts and wiles which are found with the
            Enemy and with the greedy dogs which form his host.
            And having learned the feebleness and helplessness
            thereof it is meet that we should make ourselves ready
            to [march] against them as over a road which our
            Lord hath trodden for us.
         </p>
         <p>
            Let then these phantoms be a help unto us so that
            our minds may not be frightened by his cunning, and
            fear may not abide in us by reason of his impudence;
            and let not anxious thought be wrought in us, lest the
            Evil One gain greater strength, and let us not be
            afraid when he hurleth his darts at us lest this thing
            be an occasion unto him for boasting. And let us not
            be like stricken men, but let us be prepared at all
            <pb n="51"/>times [to act] as men who have vanquished the enemy;
            and let this thought be with us at all times, namely,
            that God, Who hath revealed and exposed the <quote>powers
            and dominions</quote>, is with us at all times. For [otherwise]
            when the evil ones draw nigh unto us, having made
            ready to come against us in the hope that they may
            gain some advantage over us, or may discover some
            thoughts of fear in us, for they prepare phantoms
            [which appear] unto us in the event that they may
            find that we are terrified and afraid, straightway, like
            thieves who have discovered a place which is without
            guardians,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-1"/> they will enter into us and will lead us
            captives of their will, and our miserable souls will be
            found to be in an agitated state, not by reason of the
            punishment of the Adversary, but through our own
            sluggishness.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51-2"/> If, however, the evil ones find us in the
            love of <persName>Christ</persName>, and meditating continually on the hope
            [of that] which is to come, and thinking thoughts concerning 
            the commandments of our Lord, and [believing]
            that the kingdom and dominion are His, and that the
            Evil One hath neither opportunity nor power to resist
            the might of the Cross, if, I say, the Evil One shall
            find any believing man in this state of mind when he
            draweth nigh unto him, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#43"/>at that very moment
            he will remove himself from him to a distance.
         </p>
         <p>
            It was in such a frame of mind that he found <persName>Job</persName>
            who was prepared [to resist him], and the Evil One
            feared, and was ashamed, and he departed from him
            as from a man of war; on the other hand, he led
            captive to his will wholly <persName>Judah</persName> whom he found to be
            entirely destitute of such matters. Let us learn then
            fully from such examples and from such narratives, that
            if we wish to do so it is very easy for us to hold in
            contempt the Evil One. Let us meditate at all times
            on our Lord, and let our souls rejoice in His Hope,
            <pb n="52"/>and behold, we shall find that the Evil One will vanish
            from before us like the darkness, and we shall also
            discover that those who came to persecute us will turn
            [their backs] upon us like men who are chased out of
            the battle, for, as I have already told you, they are
            cowards. For the decree of doom (or, judgment) is at
            all times before them, and they are ever expecting the
            punishment which is prepared for them, and the fear
            of the Cross is cast upon them in proportion to their
            impudent audacity. Let then these and all the other
            things [which I have said] be unto you the means of
            understanding the insolent cunning of the Evil One,
            and of recognizing the similitudes of the forms of his
            appearances. If it happen therefore unto any of you
            that the appearance of one of these forms presenteth
            itself, be ye not forthwith terrified, but look upon it
            with great courage as it really is, and ask it, <quote>Who
            art thou? And whence comest thou?</quote> And if it be
            a true revelation of the Holy Spirit, straightway the
            mind will feel that it is so, and will have confidence,
            and courage (or, consolation) will grow in you and
            fear will diminish; but if it be an appearance of
            the error of the Evil One, the thing will be confounded, 
            and there will be no opportunity for it to
            be bold, and the form of the appearance will not
            tarry, and the question [which ye ask] will make
            manifest the courage of the confidence of refuge in
            our Lord.
         </p>
         <p>
            On one occasion a manifestation revealed itself unto
            <persName>Joshua</persName>, the son of <persName>Nun</persName>, and he asked that which had
            appeared unto him who he was, and took his stand
            upon the question; and similarly <persName>Daniel</persName> also saw one
            of the watchers and rejoiced at the sight, and was
            afraid at the measure of the honour of him that had
            come, but he was wholly comforted by the grace
            <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#44"/>of the confidence which he had in his truth.
            And in like manner a revelation (or, manifestation) of
            the truth came to each and every one of the [saints
            <pb n="53"/>of] olden time, and none of the stratagems of the
            phantoms of the Wicked One ever led them astray.
         </p>
         <p>
            And as the blessed man <persName>Anthony</persName> was saying these
            things, and every man was hearkening unto him with
            gladness, unto every man who listened unto him was
            given help of one kind or another according to his
            need; the man who was strong found his strenuousness
            to be increased, and the man who was weak found
            that he received encouragement, and the proud man
            found that his arrogance was overthrown and swept
            away, and every man was persuaded to reach forward
            confidently towards the hope which is to come. And
            all the people with one accord ascribed blessing unto
            the righteous man <persName>Anthony</persName> because such a degree of
            strength had been given unto him, and because such
            great wisdom had made its abode in him, and because
            that in the fierce strife and warfare which he waged
            against devils he was able to distinguish and discern
            the difference between good and evil appearances, and
            the manifestations (or, revelations) of our Lord from
            those which appertained unto devils. And in the days
            of the blessed man the habitations of the monks were
            accepted as tabernacles of praises, and Psalms, and
            hymns, and spiritual songs were heard therein; and
            love and righteousness rejoiced therein, and therein
            was found the rest of prayer coupled with fasting.
            And the monks toiled in the labour of their hands that
            they might not be a burden upon any man, and of
            [the proceeds of] the sweat of their faces the poor
            and the needy were relieved. And the monastery [of
            <persName>Anthony</persName>] became at that time a wonder unto the inhabitants 
            of the country, for behold, the silver, and
            the gold, and the riches of this world which were so
            highly esteemed in their sight, were despised and
            accounted as dross by such men as the monks thereof;
            and those at whose wastefulness, and drunkenness, and
            lasciviousness the monks marvelled, returned [to their
            homes] in wonder as [if they had seen] an angel and
            <pb n="54"/>not a human being. No sounds of dissension or contention 
            were heard there, and no voice of the violent
            man(?) or of his gaoler sounded therein; <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#45"/>
            well might a man describe that monastery in the words
            of the parable which was uttered in olden time, and
            say, <quote>How fair are thy habitations, O <persName>Jacob</persName>, and thy
            tabernacles, O <placeName>Israel</placeName>,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54-1"/> for the country was as if
            the desert had been roofed over, and it was like
            a paradise which was by the rivers, and tabernacles
            which the Lord had stablished, and like cedars by the
            side of the stream.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now therefore the blessed man, according to his
            wont, withdrew himself and departed to his habitation
            (or, cell) and to the place which was convenient for
            him to dwell in, and there like a mighty man he
            triumphed in the apparel of war; at all seasons he was
            mindful of the mansions which were in the heavens,
            and ...... He despised the world and held it in contempt,
            and his mind longed greatly for the kingdom
            of God, for already, even according to the word of
            the <persName>Apostle</persName>, he wished to be with his Lord. And
            moreover, he was greatly troubled when the time drew
            nigh in which it was proper for him to eat and drink
            with the sons of his habitation, for he was shamefaced,
            and he would fain depart from their midst, and he
            did not like any man to see him eating or drinking;
            nevertheless, although he felt thus at the appointed
            season he would eat (with them). Now on the greater
            number of days the love which he bore towards the
            brethren would in this way draw him to their company,
            for he did not desire to grieve them in any way
            whatsoever, and he was as careful for them as if they
            had been himself; for he was mindful of the word of
            the Book which saith, <quote>Ye are members,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54-2"/> each of the
            <pb n="55"/>other, and if one member be glorified the whole body
            is glorified.</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            And this he used to say and teach unto them:–It
            is right that we should at all times follow after the
            food of the soul, for the soul worketh together with
            our spirit in the striving which is against the Adversary; 
            but it is meet for the body to be in subjection
            and tribulation, for it very speedily becometh unduly
            exalted by the persuasion and flattery of the Evil One.
            And it is therefore right that the soul should be more
            prepared and more exalted than the body, that the
            body may not prevail (or, be strong) over it, and
            bring it low by the lusts [thereof]. And our Lord
            also gave this indication <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#46"/>to the blessed
            <persName>Apostles</persName>, and commanded them, saying, <quote>Be not careful 
            as to what ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink,
            for such things do the peoples of the earth seek after,
            and your Father knoweth whatsoever things ye have
            need of; but seek ye the kingdom of God and His
            glory, and the things which are superior unto these
            shall be added unto you.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-1"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            Now after these things some short time a storm
            and a persecution arose<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55-2"/> in the Church, during the years
            [of the reign] of <persName>Maximinus</persName>, the wicked Emperor, and
            [the soldiers began to seize and to take into <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>
            a great company of the blessed confessors; and the
            report of these things reached the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>.
            And straightway he left his habitation and place of
            abode, and he made haste at the sound of the strife,
            and he said to himself, <quote>I will go and draw nigh
            :[thereto]. so that if Divine Grace call me it shall find
            me prepared, and if it thinketh otherwise concerning
            my unworthy self, I shall at all events be a spectator
            of the strife;</quote> now he desired exceedingly to enter
            <pb n="56"/>[the race], and to be accounted worthy of the athlete's
            crown. So he travelled on his way and drew nigh
            and arrived at the city, and he went in through the
            gate, and enquired where the athletes had been made
            to assemble, and where they had been gathered together, 
            and asked concerning the report of the strife.
            And when he had heard and had learned where the
            place was, and in what manner of restraint they were
            fettered, he made his way thither; and as soon as he
            saw those who had been called by Divine Grace [unto
            death] at this time, he planned<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n56-1"/> with all diligence and
            by every means in his power that he might be a companion 
            unto every one of them in the contest wherein
            they were to stand. And he prepared<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n56-2"/> and made
            himself ready to be with every man, and he became
            a prisoner in the prison with those who were shut up
            therein, and he ministered unto them and relieved their
            wants; and he passed his time continually in close companionship 
            with the rest of the prisoners who were to
            be exiled, and those who were to be sent out from the
            country to the mines<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n56-3"/> and to the islands, and he
            ministered unto them with great pains and care. And
            he was found to be ready to accompany all such as
            were brought and were going in to their doom, both
            in their going in and coming out; as they went in he
            gave them encouragement and admonition, and as they
            came out <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#47"/>he ascribed blessings unto them
            and sang hymns of praise. And it was his custom
            [to do this day by day, and his acts were so well
            known and so famous in all the city that at length
            [the report thereof] came to the cars of the governor.
            Now when the wicked governor learned concerning
            <pb n="57"/>him, and the people had informed him concerning <persName>Anthony</persName>'s 
            disposition and work, he marvelled at [the
            bravery of] his mind, and because he was neither
            moved by all the tortures and tribulations which were
            falling upon his companions, nor was afraid; and he
            commanded that he should no longer be found in the
            city, and that the other monks who were with should not
            come therein because they also were doing the same work.
         </p>
         <p>
            And on another day certain athletes were summoned
            to the contest, and when the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> knew
            of the command and threat (or, prohibition) of the
            judge, he washed and made white the apparel with
            which he was clothed (now his tunic was without
            shoulder coverings and was like the tunics with which
            the <persName>Egyptians</persName> cover themselves), and having arrayed
            himself in his clothing, he went and stood up inside
            the hall of judgment, opposite to the wicked judge;
            and when the men who had heard the commands of
            the king concerning <persName>Anthony</persName> and his companions lifted
            up their eyes and saw him, they prevented him that
            day from appearing before the judge, for they marvelled 
            at him, and at his boldness concerning himself,
            and his courage in the face of death. Now all this
            threatening was very sad to him, and [in spite of] his
            contempt for the Enemy, the door which would enable
            him to testify was not opened; but God preserved him
            for the strengthening of those who testified, and for the
            benefit of those who were about to do so, and for the
            increase of the monasteries of the monks, and for the
            praise of the whole Church. And he continued to do
            this work until God was pleased to put an end to this
            persecution of the Church (now in those days the
            blessed Peter, Bishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, bore his testimony)
            (i. e., was martyred); and after these things the blessed
            <persName>Anthony</persName> departed to his monastery and habitation, and
            he bore testimony continually, and, as it is written, he
            died daily, and after the persecution <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#48"/>he was
            always adding a little more to the toil of his daily life.
         </p>
         <pb n="58"/>
         <p>
            Now he wore his apparel with the hair inside,
            and the skin outside, and to the day of his death he
            never touched his body with water, for he wished to
            keep it meagre, and he never dipped his feet in water
            without the sternest necessity; and no man ever saw
            him naked or exposed, except when he died, and his
            body was carried in honour by his disciples. He once
            decided that for a short time he would remain in silent
            contemplation, and that he would neither go outside
            his dwelling nor be seen by any man, and it came to
            pass that during the days wherein [he was thus occupied 
            a certain Roman nobleman whose name was
            <persName>Marţinînôs</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n58-1"/> came to visit him, and he drew nigh and
            besought him to come forth and to pray with him,
            and to lay his hand upon his daughter, who was torn
            by a devil. And when the nobleman had waited a
            very long time, and had besought the blessed man
            incessantly to open his door, though he would not be
            persuaded to do so, <persName>Anthony</persName> looked [out of the window]
            and saw him, and said unto him, <quote>Oman, why dost
            thou weary me? I am a man like unto thyself, but
            if thou dost believe in the <persName>Christ</persName> Whom I serve, depart
            in peace, and according as thou believest pray, and
            it shall be [unto thee] even as thou wishest.</quote> Then
            straightway that man had full and complete confidence
            in the word which he had heard, and went back by
            the way he had come, taking his daughter with him,
            and she was delivered from the power of the subjugation 
            of the Evil One. And God, Who did say,
            <quote>Ask ye and receive</quote>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n58-2"/> performed very many things
            like unto this by the hands of <persName>Anthony</persName>; now many
            people who were smitten with diseases of several kinds
            thronged to him, and came and sat down by the side
            of his cell, and each of them obtained relief from their
            afflictions.
         </p>
         <pb n="59"/>
         <p>
            Now when he saw that much people were gathered
            together to him, and that the trouble which men and
            women caused him increased, he became afraid either
            lest he should be unduly exalted in his mind by reason
            of the things which God had wrought by his hand, or
            lest others should esteem him <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#49"/>beyond what
            was right and more than he deserved, and he determined 
            to go away from that place and to enter the
            <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName>. Then he took a little bread and went down
            and sat by the side of the river, and waited until he
            should see a boat going to that district to which he
            was ready to go. And as he was pondering these
            things in his mind, suddenly a voice from heaven was
            heard by him, and it called him and said unto him,
            <quote><persName>Anthony</persName>, whither goest thou? Why art thou departing 
            from this place?</quote> Now he was not afraid of the
            voice which came to him, but like a man who was
            accustomed to do so he spake with it, and answered
            and said, <quote>Because, O my Lord, the people will not
            permit me [to enjoy] a little silent contemplation; it
            is for this reason that I am wishing to go up to the
            <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName>, and especially do I desire it because the
            people are seeking at my hands that which is wholly
            beyond my powers.</quote> Then again the voice came to
            him, saying, <quote>If thou goest up it will not be to the
            <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName> only, and even if thou goest into the <placeName>Thebaïd</placeName>
            as thou art thinking [of doing] thou wilt have to
            endure toil greater than that which thou [performest]
            here; if, however, thou wishest to enjoy silent contemplation 
            and to be at rest, get thee gone into the
            innermost desert.</quote> And <persName>Anthony</persName> the blessed answered 
            and said, <quote>O my Lord, who will shew me [the way
            to] that difficult place? For neither do I myself know
            it, nor am I acquainted with or have knowledge of
            men who do.</quote> Now whilst he was standing up there
            passed by certain <persName>Arabs</persName> who had made ready and set
            out on their way to go to that region, and the blessed
            man drew nigh unto them, and entreated them to let
            <pb n="60"/>him go with them, and they received him gladly because 
            it was manifest that it was the commandment
            of God which was to be performed in this matter.
            And having travelled with them for three days and
            three nights, he arrived at a certain high mountain,
            and he found in the lower parts thereof water which
            was clear, and cool, and sweet, and a few palm trees,
            for the land which was by the side of the mountain
            was a flat plain; and the place was <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#50"/>pleasing
            to the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, and he loved it well, and he
            loved it especially because God had been his Governor
            and had led him to that spot. Therefore <persName>Anthony</persName>
            encamped there and dwelt in that place, and he was
            exalted there like a king in the courts [of his palace].<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n60-1"/>
            Now when those <persName>Arabs</persName> who had brought him to that
            place saw [this], they wondered and marvelled, and
            they left with him a little bread which was found with
            them; and from that time forward whensoever they
            were journeying into <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and returning therefrom
            those <persName>Arabs</persName>, by reason of the wonderful things which
            they saw in the man, always passed by the place where
            he was, and also brought him bread. Now there were
            found in that region a few small birds [which came]
            from the palm trees.
         </p>
         <p>
            And it came to pass that after a time it was heard
            by the brethren where he was, and like beloved sons
            they remembered their righteous father, and they made
            enquiries and found out where the place was,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n60-2"/> and they
            laboured strenuously and sent to him everything that
            could be of use to him. Now when the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> 
            saw that the brethren had begun to take trouble
            for him, he besought those who had begun to go to
            him to bring him a little wheat and a hoe, and when
            they had brought them to him, he went about the
            land at the foot of the mountain, and found a little
            <pb n="61"/>place which was suitable for cultivating and watering;
            thus he was able to provide himself with as much
            bread as he needed, and he rejoiced greatly because
            he had found the means which would prevent him
            from troubling any man, and because he would be a
            burden to himself only. And having seen that the
            brethren were thronging to him, and that they would
            not be prevented from coming to him, he tilled a
            portion of that ground and made it into a vegetable
            garden for the benefit of those who came to him. Now
            when he first began to sow wheat in that place the
            wild animals used to come there in large numbers for
            the sake of the water, and they damaged the crop,
            but one day when they were among the corn according 
            to their custom, he went quietly <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#51"/>and
            seized one of them, and he said unto them all with a
            laugh, <quote>Why do ye do harm to me seeing that I do no
            harm to you? Get ye gone therefore in the Name of the
            Lord, and come ye never again nigh unto this place;</quote>
            and from that hour this was a command from heaven
            to them, and they never again did harm to that place.
         </p>
         <p>
            And the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> was alone in that desert,
            for the place wherein he had his habitation was waste
            and desolate; and his mind therefore dwelt the more
            upon exalted things, and it was content therewith. Now
            the brethren who used to go to visit him besought and
            entreated him to allow them to bring him there month
            by month a few garden herbs, and olives, and oil; and
            although he contended with them about it they overcame 
            him with their entreaty, and compelled him [to
            receive them], and they began to pay him visits, one
            at a time, according to their entreaty to him. And
            the blessed man was exceedingly old, and he was far
            advanced in years<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n61-1"/> And in that desert also he endured
            strife, not with flesh and blood, but with devils and
            with impure spirits, and we have learned this also from
            <pb n="62"/>those who were going to visit him continually. They
            used to hear also there the sound of tumult and of
            outcry, and to see flashing spears, and at night time
            they would see the whole mountain filled with fiery
            phantoms, and those men were greatly terrified; but
            the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> was trained in stratagems(?) of war
            like a man of war, and he was prepared, and he stood
            up and rebuked the Evil One, who straightway ceased
            according to [his] wont, and he encouraged the brethren
            who were with him not to be terrified or to tremble
            at [the sight of] such visions as these. For, said he to
            them, <quote>they are only empty phantoms which perish as
            if they had never existed at the Name of the Cross;</quote>
            and wonder and admiration laid hold upon every man
            at the greatness and at the manner of the righteousness
            which was found in the blessed man.
         </p>
         <p>
            He was not <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#52"/>terrified at the devils, he
            was not wearied by the desert, and his soul had no
            fear of the wild beasts which were therein; but <persName>Satan</persName>
            suffered torture from all these things. And one day
            he came to the blessed man who was singing the
            Psalms of <persName>David</persName>, and he gnashed his teeth upon him
            loudly; but the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> ceased not [to sing],
            and he was comforted and helped by the grace of our
            Lord. One night whilst he was standing up and was
            watching in prayer, <persName>Satan</persName> gathered together all the
            wild beasts of the desert, and brought them against
            him, and they were so many in number that he can
            hardly have left one beast in its den; and as they
            compassed him about on every side, and with threatening 
            looks were ready [to leap upon him], he looked
            at them boldly and said unto them, <quote>If ye have received
            power over me [from the Lord] draw nigh, and delay
            not, for I am ready for you; but if ye have made
            ready and come at [the command of] <persName>Satan</persName>, get ye
            back to your places and tarry not, for I am a servant
            of <persName>Jesus</persName> the Conqueror.</quote> And when the blessed man
            had spoken these words, <persName>Satan</persName> was straightway driven
            <pb n="63"/>away by the mention of the Name of <persName>Christ</persName> like a
            sparrow before a hawk.
         </p>
         <p>
            And on another day, when he was weaving palm
            leaves, for such was his occupation, and he used to
            toil thereat so that he might not be a burden upon
            any man, and that he might [make baskets] to give as
            gifts to the people who were continually coming to visit
            him, suddenly he threw up his hand above the door,
            and took hold of a rope of palm leaves to bring it
            outside, and he leaped and stood up to see; and looking 
            out from the door he saw an animal which had
            [the following] form: from its head to its sides it was
            like a man, and its legs and feet were those of an ass.
            When the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> saw it he only made the
            sign of the Cross over himself, and said, <quote>How can
            anyone imagine that the Evil One is crafty? And
            how can any one be agitated [by him] more than once
            or twice? Is it not within the scope of his cunning
            to know that these things are accounted by me merely
            empty phantasms? And now, if there be anything
            whatsoever in the power of him that sent thee<anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#53"/>,
            come hither and perform that which thou wast sent to
            do; but if <persName>Christ</persName>, Who shall make an end of thee, and
            in Whom I have my hope, liveth, and if He be true,
            let the destruction of thyself and of him that sent thee
            take place immediately.</quote> Thereupon, at the word
            <persName>Christ</persName>, there fell upon the creature quaking and trembling,
            and he took to flight, and [as] he was going forth in
            haste and was running along terrified he fell down and
            burst asunder at no great distance from [<persName>Anthony</persName>'s]
            abode. Now the devils did all these things in order
            that they might drive the blessed man from the desert.
         </p>
         <p>
            And it came to pass after a time that the brethren
            [who were] monks appeared before him and besought
            him to come down and visit them in their monastery
            for a long period, and having multiplied their entreaties
            he granted their request; and he rose up and travelled
            with them in the desert to the borders of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>. Now
            <pb n="64"/>there was with them a camel which was laden with
            bread, and water, [and] provisions for the way, for no
            water whatsoever was to be found in the whole of
            that desert. And having travelled for one or two days,
            the water finished and came to an end, for the men
            with him were not a few, and in those days the heat
            was very fierce, and the people were overcome by
            thirst; and they were troubled the more because they
            had wandered about the whole of that district that they
            might find water, and they threw themselves down on
            the ground, being in trouble and in great danger, and
            because they were in despair about themselves they
            turned the camel adrift to wander about in the desert.
            Now when the blessed old man saw the people in such
            great distress, he sighed heavily, and having departed
            from them a short distance, he bowed his knees upon
            the ground and spreading out his hands towards heaven,
            he cried out to God, and said, <quote>Consider, O Lord, at
            this time also the prayer of Thy servant;</quote> and before
            the words of his prayer were ended, water sprang
            up from that place whereon he had prayed, and he
            brought all the people and made them to come [there],
            and they prayed, and gave thanks unto God, and they
            drank and were relieved from their tribulations, and
            they also filled the water-skins with the water. <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#54"/>
            Then they went forth in quest of the camel, and they
            brought him back [to their camp]; now they found him
            quite near, because it happened that, through the Providence 
            (or, Dispensation) of God, whilst the animal
            was wandering about his cord was caught by a root and
            he was unable to move, and he stood still until they
            went and brought him [back]. And they gave the
            camel water to drink, and they loaded up his load
            upon him, and they set out on their road.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64-1"/>
         </p>
         <pb n="65"/>
         <p>
            Now when they had come to a district which was
            inhabited and had entered the villages, many people
            burst forth from the whole of that neighbourhood and
            came to the place where the blessed man was, for
            every man was waiting and longing for him, and the
            love of him was hot in their minds, and they drew
            nigh and made obeisance unto him as unto a righteous
            father. And the blessed man spread abroad the things
            which he had provided and was carrying [with him]
            when he came from the desert,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65-1"/> and he made them
            happy with the enjoyments of the Spirit; and at that
            time there was twofold joy in the monasteries of the
            monks, and they rejoiced in the triumphs of the blessed
            old man whom they saw renewing his youth like the
            eagle. Now the chief of all the commandments which
            he used to give unto all the monks was that they
            should freely confess, before everything, the true faith
            of <persName>Christ</persName>, and should love it with all their strength;
            that they should preserve themselves from evil thoughts,
            and from the lusts of the body; that they should flee
            from vain boasting; that they should pray continually,
            and should be prepared and ready [to sing] Psalms
            and [to recite] the Office before they went to sleep;
            that after sleep they should read and remember the
            words of the Scriptures, wherein was their life; that
            they should meditate upon the acts and lives of the
            <persName>Apostles</persName>, and should consider what they were before
            they approached <persName>Christ</persName>, and also what they were after
            they had drawn nigh to Him, and how in their former
            state they were despised and held in contempt by the
            world, and how in the latter state they suddenly waxed
            great, and were held in high honour, both in this world
            and in the kingdom of God; and that it was not their
            own strength which had made for them this exalted
            estate and honour, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#55"/>but their perfect righteous<pb n="66"/>ness 
            towards God. With these and such like [admonitions] 
            did he make zealous and strengthen their
            minds.
         </p>
         <p>
            And, moreover, he spake the following words:–
            <quote>Since we, the monks, are not held fast by anger in
            anything whatsoever, <persName>Satan</persName> filcheth us away through
            this very thing that we may rage one against the
            other; and it is therefore meet that we should at all
            times remember the word of our Lord which saith,
            'If thou bringest to the altar thine offering, and there
            'rememberest that thou art held by anger against thy
            brother, go thou and be reconciled with thy brother,
            and then offer up thine offering.'</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66-1"/> We should remember
            also the word of the <persName>Apostle</persName>, <quote>Let not the sun go
            down upon your wrath.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66-2"/> Now this command, <quote>Let
            not the sun go down upon your wrath,</quote> was not
            written merely [to tell us] that we were never to be
            angry, but [to warn us] against offences of every kind,
            and against keeping wrath one against the other; for
            it is very right and seemly that the sun should not go
            down by day and leave us in sin, and that the moon
            should not overtake us in the same by night, and
            should not find us in the service of the Wicked One, or
            thinking of him. Since therefore it is well for us [to
            be] thus, it is right that we should consider and examine
            into the word of the <persName>Apostle</persName> which admonished us, saying, 
            <quote>Try ye one another, examine ye one another.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66-3"/>
            Let us then each and every day meditate in such a
            way that every man among us may receive from his
            soul the computation of all his works and thoughts,
            both by day and by night; and let every man be an
            honest investigator of his own thoughts for himself,
            before shall come the righteous Avenger Who shall
            reward righteously and shall punish even according as
            <pb n="67"/>the Holy Gospel hath admonished us; for the wages
            of the mind are always the same. Those who have
            fought against sins He will encourage, and him that
            standeth in the truth He will admonish and urge to
            new exertions, lest he be filched away by boasting, and
            be despoiled by means of over-confidence, and lest he
            despise one man and love another, and justify his own
            soul. [Let us then do these things], even as the <persName>Apostle</persName>
            <persName>Paul</persName> said, <quote>until our Lord cometh,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n67-1"/> Who shall judge
            the things which are hidden.
         </p>
         <p>
            For it may happen that we ourselves do not know
            our own manner of life and works, but though we have
            lost this knowledge <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#56"/>it is manifest before God,
            Who knoweth the things which are hidden. Let us
            therefore appoint Him to be the Judge. Let us, at all
            times, take each the burden of the other, and let us
            suffer for each other even as our Lord suffered for us;
            but let us examine our souls unceasingly, and let us
            provide and fill our houses in this world with whatsoever 
            things we lack with the greatest care. And
            let this thing also be an admonition to us against sin,
            and let each man of us write down both his actions
            and his thoughts upon the tablets of his heart, as if
            he were obliged to read and lay them out in due order
            under the eye of every man. For when he pondereth
            and considereth [he will find] that it would be a shame
            and a disgrace that these things should come to light,
            and when he meditateth further [he will see] that, inasmuch 
            as the mere hearing of the same would cause
            him great ignominy, it is manifest that the doing of
            the same [would work] great destruction. And since
            it is difficult for sin to come to light, it is certain that
            falsehood clingeth and cleaveth thereto; for as when
            the natural eye seeth [what is happening] no act of
            shame is to be expected, so also if we were men who
            were obliged to tell each other our manner of life (or
            <pb n="68"/>conversation) and thoughts, no sin would ever be committed 
            by us because of the shame which would result
            therefrom. Let then the writings wherein are inscribed
            our shortcomings be things of which to be ashamed,
            for they take the place of the eyes of the spectators,
            and since we are as much ashamed of the writings as
            if they had been spectators, let us, like men of understanding, 
            cease from the doing of and from meditating
            upon the works which bring in their train reproach.
            Now therefore by such means as these, if our souls are
            a care unto us, let us bring our bodies into subjection,
            so that by our works we shall please God, and treat
            with contempt the Enemy by means of our strenuousness.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now it was with such matters as these that the
            blessed man <persName>Anthony</persName> used to rejoice the monks who
            went to visit him, and the others, that is to say, those
            who were smitten with sickness, and those who were
            evilly entreated by evil spirits he would comfort by
            his words, and would aid by his prayers. And our
            Lord at all times made him to be happy in his prayers,
            for when they were heard he was not unduly lifted
            up <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#57"/>in his heart, and when they were not
            hearkened to he murmured not, but in all of them he
            gave thanks to God. And moreover, he encouraged
            those who were smitten with sickness not to be disheartened 
            by reason of their tribulations, and he told
            them that they must know that neither he nor any
            other man had power to grant relief to them, and that
            it was God alone Who could do so, and that He would
            do so for whomsoever He pleased whensoever He
            pleased. And these and such like words became a
            relief and an aid for those who were smitten with
            sicknesses, and he gladly lightened the weight of their
            trials by more than the words which were offered unto
            them; but those who were made whole were told before 
            everything else that they must not return their
            thanks and gratitude to the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, but
            <pb n="69"/>that they must ascribe praise wholly unto God [for
            their healings].
         </p>
         <p>
            Now there once went to the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> in
            the inner desert a certain nobleman who was an officer
            in the palace, and whose name was <persName>Parnîtón</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n69-1"/> and he
            had an evil spirit; he was always gnawing his tongue,
            and the light of his eyes was well nigh destroyed.
            And this man went to the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> and entreated 
            him to pray over him, and having done so he answered 
            and said to that man, <quote>Depart, and thou shalt
            be healed,</quote> but <persName>Parnîţón</persName> entreated him that he might
            remain with him for some days. And the blessed man
            was saying unto him continually, <quote>Thou canst not be
            healed here. Go away from this place, and when thou
            arrivest in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> thou wilt see suddenly the wonderful
            sign which God hath wrought upon thee.</quote> And having
            confidence in [these words] the man went forth, and
            before he saw <placeName>Egypt</placeName> there came unto him deliverance
            straightway, and he became healed, according to the
            word of the blessed man which was revealed unto him
            in the Spirit by our Redeemer.
         </p>
         <p>
            And there was a certain virgin of <placeName>Bûşâr</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n69-2"/> who suffered
            from a severe and terrible disease, for the water (or,
            tears) which flowed from the pupils of her eyes, and
            the matter which fell from her nostrils, before it fell
            upon the ground became worms, and her <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#58"/>
            whole body was in a state of putrefaction; and because
            of the progress of the disease her eyes had lost the
            power of natural sight and were useless. Now when
            the kinsfolk of this young woman heard that certain
            brethren [who were] monks were preparing to go to
            the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, because they believed wholly in
            the man who had healed a woman of a flow of blood
            <pb n="70"/>[which had lasted] twelve years, they entreated them
            to allow them to go with them also and to follow in
            their company; and as the brethren received their
            petition and permitted them to go in their company
            they arrived [in due course] at the place [where the
            blessed man was]. And the kinsfolk of the maiden
            remained with their daughter a short distance on this
            side of the mountain, at the place where dwelt the
            man of God, <persName>Paphnutius</persName> the confessor and anchorite.
            And when the brethren had gone in and had greeted
            the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, and whilst they were meditating
            about relating to him concerning the maiden and her
            kinsfolk, he began to speak before they did about her
            sickness and afflictions, and said how it happened that
            she came to be in their company. Then making the
            conversation of the blessed man the pretext for their
            words they besought and entreated him to allow the
            maiden to come into his presence, but he would not
            be persuaded to do so, and he said unto them, <quote>Get
            ye back to the place where the maiden is, and if she
            be not already dead, ye will find that she hath been
            wholly healed, for this hath not happened either
            through me or through the gift which my poor and
            contemptible person possesseth, but it is a gift from
            our Redeemer, who performeth grace and mercy in
            every place for those who cry unto Him in affliction.
            Get ye out then quickly, for the merciful God hath
            hearkened unto the prayer of the maiden, and hath
            regarded the toil and labour of her kinsfolk; and
            behold, His lovingkindness hath made known and
            revealed unto me in this hour that relief from her
            affliction hath come unto the maiden. Thus this
            wonderful thing hath taken place.</quote> And the brethren
            went forth and found the kinsfolk of the maiden
            rejoicing, and their daughter was freed from <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#59"/>
            and was completely healed from her affliction.
         </p>
         <p>
            And at the same time there went forth from <placeName>Egypt</placeName>
            two brethren to visit the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, and when
            <pb n="71"/>they were near to arrive at the place where he was
            it fell out that the water failed, and they were so
            completely brought low for want thereof that, by reason
            of his great tribulation, one of them departed from
            this world, and his companion was well nigh departing
            likewise. Then the blessed man called suddenly unto
            two of those brethren who happened to be with
            him, and said to them, <quote>Take ye a little water in a
            vessel and get ye down quickly on the road to <placeName>Egypt</placeName>,
            for two brethren set out together to come to us, but
            when they had left behind them the greater part of
            the mountain road they lacked water; one of them
            hath already fainted and died, and the other is nigh
            unto death, [and will die], if ye do not speedily overtake 
            him. For thus hath it appeared to me when
            I was praying.</quote> And the brethren having made
            haste arrived at the place and found [a dead man]
            according to what had been said to them, and they
            took up the body of him that was dead and carried
            it away, and they fed him, in whom the spirit was still
            found to be, with bread and water, and took him and
            brought him with care to the old man. Now the
            blessed man was distant from them a journey of two
            days. And if any man ask why and wherefore the
            vision did not appear unto the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> before
            the man died he will ask that which is unseemly, for
            it belonged not to him to know what God was meditating 
            concerning every man; this thing belongeth unto
            God only Who, whensoever He pleaseth, maketh a revelation 
            unto him that feareth Him.
         </p>
         <p>
            And the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> possessed this wonderful
            attribute. When he was dwelling in the mountain his
            mind was alert and watchful to observe and to see,
            by the operation of the Holy Spirit which dwelt in
            him, that which was afar off as if it were near. For.
            on another occasion when he was in the mountain, he
            lifted up his eyes to heaven and suddenly saw a man
            being taken up therein; and wonderment having fallen
            <pb n="72"/>upon him <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#60"/>he magnified [God] and ascribed
            blessings unto him that had been accounted worthy of
            this [honour], and he besought the Lord that he might
            know who the man was who had attained unto such
            exalted greatness. And suddenly a voice from heaven
            was heard, saying, <quote>This is the soul of the blessed
            man <persName>Ammon</persName> who used to dwell in the country of <placeName>Nitria</placeName>.</quote>
            Now <persName>Ammon</persName> was a mighty man and a valiant fighter
            [in the ascetic life], and he had been a monk from his
            early manhood even unto his old age, and the end of
            his life was greater than the beginning thereof; and
            the distance of the country of <placeName>Nitria</placeName> from the mountain
            wherein dwelt the blessed man <persName>Anthony</persName> was a journey
            of thirteen days. And when those who were found
            with the old man <persName>Anthony</persName> saw him marvelling in this
            manner concerning the blessed <persName>Ammon</persName>, they entreated
            him that they might learn when his departure from
            the world took place, and he informed them that
            it had happened when the revelation had appeared
            unto him.
         </p>
         <p>
            And there was also another famous man with whom
            many were acquainted, for he used to come very
            frequently to the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, and many glorious
            deeds and signs and wonders were wrought by his
            hands unto our Lord. Now on a certain occasion
            one reason or another made it necessary for the blessed
            <persName>Ammon</persName> to cross the river, the name of which was
            Dâbhâ<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n72-1"/> and he had with him the righteous man, [who
            was called] <persName>Theodore</persName>; and this blessed man also was
            mighty in the ascetic life. And when they had come
            nigh unto the river, and were standing on the bank
            they agreed that each should go away a short distance
            from the other so that they might not see each other's
            nakedness as they were crossing the river. Now when
            the righteous man <persName>Theodore</persName> had removed himself
            <pb n="73"/>from him, the blessed man <persName>Ammon</persName> began to have
            shame even of himself, and whilst he was in this state
            of mind suddenly Divine Grace seized him, and set
            him up upon the [other] side of the river; and when
            the righteous man <persName>Theodore</persName> had crossed the river, he
            drew nigh unto the blessed <persName>Ammon</persName>, and examined him
            attentively, [and found] that his feet had not been
            dipped in the water, and that not a drop of water
            had touched either his body or his garments. Then
            <persName>Theodore</persName> began to entreat <persName>Ammon</persName> to inform him how
            <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#61"/>his passage over the river had been effected,
            and when he saw that he was making many excuses
            about it and was debating the matter he became certain
            in his mind that it was Divine Grace which had taken
            him across the river. And he persisted strongly in
            questioning <persName>Ammon</persName>, and took hold of his feet, and
            said unto him, <quote>Yes, or no? I will not leave thee until
            thou hast shewn me</quote> (this thing). Now when the old
            man <persName>Ammon</persName> saw the persistence of the righteous man
            <persName>Theodore</persName>, and [remembered] especially the word which
            had gone forth to him, he entreated him to make the
            matter known to no man until his departure from this
            world had been effected, and then he revealed to him
            that he had indeed been carried across the river, and
            that he had never walked upon the water thereof at
            all. And this thing our Lord Himself did by His
            own power, and He made the great <persName>Apostle Peter</persName> to
            do so, and it was done [by <persName>Ammon</persName>] also by the command 
            of our Lord; and [it was only] after the old
            man <persName>Ammon</persName> was dead that this matter was spoken
            of by the righteous man <persName>Theodore</persName>, according to the
            agreement which he had made with <persName>Ammon</persName>.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now the brethren, who had heard from the blessed
            <persName>Anthony</persName> the story of the departure of the old man
            <persName>Ammon</persName> from the world, bore in mind the day and the
            hour wherein it took place, and three days later, when
            certain brethren came from the country of <placeName>Nitria</placeName>, they
            enquired of them concerning the death of the blessed
            <pb n="74"/><persName>Ammon</persName>, and they learned that the days of the old
            man had come to an end at the very moment and at
            the very hour when the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> had spoken
            to them, and when he himself saw <persName>Ammon</persName> being taken
            up into heaven. Then the brethren did indeed marvel
            among themselves concerning the purity of the soul
            of the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, and how he had seen performed 
            clearly and openly before him that which had
            taken place at a distance of a journey of thirteen days,
            that is to say, the ascension of the soul of the blessed
            <persName>Ammon</persName> into heaven.
         </p>
         <p>
            And moreover, there came unto him <persName>Archelaus
            Kósós</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n74-1"/> and he found him in the outer mountain praying 
            by himself, and he made entreaty unto him on
            behalf of the nun <persName>Pùlakrațiâ (Polycratia)</persName>, who was from
            the city of Laodicea, and was faithful and devoted
            to the ascetic life; now she was much afflicted by pains
            in her stomach and in her right side, and, in short,
            her whole body was in a state of suffering. And
            when the blessed man had prayed for her, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#62"/>
            <persName>Archelaus</persName> wrote down the day and the hour in which
            the prayer had been made, and after this the blessed
            man dismissed him, and he returned to his own country;
            and when he had gone to the province of Laodicea
            he found <persName>Pûlaậrațià (Polycratia)</persName> the nun in perfect
            health. Then he asked at what time she had found
            deliverance from her sufferings, and by what means
            it had been brought about, and they related to him
            that the mercy of God had been poured out upon her
            at a certain time suddenly, and that she had felt relief
            and found herself made whole and free from the violent
            pains of her disease. And immediately that the words
            of their narrative concerning her illness had come to
            an end, <persName>Archelaus</persName> brought forth the paper whereon
            were written the day and hour wherein the prayer
            <pb n="75"/>had been made on behalf of the believing woman
            <persName>Pûlaậrațîâ (Polycratia)</persName>, and the words of their narrative
            agreed with those which were written on his paper
            as if they had been written down [at the same time]
            with a pen.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n75-1"/> Then wonder laid hold upon every man,
            and they all admitted openly that the time at which
            the prayer was made by the blessed man was precisely
            that at which relief had come to her.
         </p>
         <p>
            And multitudes of things similar to those which
            have already been described were performed by his
            hands; and also when the brethren used to set out to
            come from <placeName>Egypt</placeName> to him he knew it beforehand and
            was able to declare it to those who happened to be
            with him, and it was revealed unto him sometimes
            even months and days beforehand that they were
            coming to him, and the reason for their journey. For
            some used to come to him merely to see him, and
            others [came] that they might be with him for a
            few days, and others came to him because of their
            diseases and afflictions of various kinds; and no man
            found that long road exhausting or fell into despair
            thereon, because the relief which each man obtained
            from the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> was greater than the toil
            which he had endured thereon. And when a man saw
            these triumphs, and felt anxious to narrate them, the
            blessed man used to entreat him not to marvel <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#63"/>
            at these deeds, but to wonder at the Divine Grace
            of God which considered unworthy and fecble men
            worthy of such great [care].
         </p>
         <p>
            And on one occasion the brethren entreated him
            to visit their monasteries, and when they had come to
            a certain place they besought him to embark in a boat
            and to cross over the river; and when he had gone
            up into the boat a foul and fetid smell smote him
            suddenly. And when the brethren heard of this, they
            <pb n="76"/>answered and said unto him, <quote>Master, this smell ariseth
            from the fish and the salted meat with which the boat
            is loaded,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-1"/> but he would not be persuaded that it
            was so, and he said, <quote>This smell ariseth not from these
            things.</quote> Now whilst he was ending his words a young
            man, in whom was an evil spirit, was found in the
            boat, and as soon as he saw the blessed man he shrank
            away from him straightway; but when the devil abused
            him, he cried out and uttered threats against the blessed
            man from among the people. Then the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> 
            turned himself round, and rebuked him, and
            silenced him, and immediately the young man felt the
            deliverance from him; and every man was persuaded
            that the smell was that of the devil whereat they had
            wondered.
         </p>
         <p>
            And again there came to him a certain well-known
            man who was very sorely tried by an unclean spirit,
            and he was so distressed through him that his mind
            was carried away, and he was unable to understand
            any question which was asked of him; and in his whole
            body there was not a spot which was not lacerated
            by his bites, and those who had brought him took him
            to the blessed man <persName>Anthony</persName> and besought him to pray
            for him. Then the old man <persName>Anthony</persName> looked upon him,
            and his mercy having revealed itself, he took him by
            the hand, and made him stand up, and he knelt down
            on his knees before him, and he watched with him
            the whole night. And at the time of dawn the
            young man approached the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> from behind
            his back, and smote him, and those who had brought
            him began to rebuke him; but the blessed man answered
            and said unto them, <quote>Let no man be wroth against
            him; this act is not of him, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#64"/>but of the
            evil one who is in him, for he hath been commanded
            to depart from that which God hath created, and to
            <pb n="77"/>return to his place, and he is, in consequence, incensed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-1"/>
            with him, and hath done this thing. Glorify ye then
            God, because of this thing which hath taken place,
            for it hath given unto you a sign whereby ye may be
            sure that God hath wrought for him deliverance.</quote>
            And when the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> had said these things
            straightway the young man was made whole, and he
            knew himself,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-2"/> and remembered where he was, and
            through whom deliverance had come unto him, and
            then he began to salute the blessed man, and to confess 
            God with many loud protestations. Now believing
            men have related very many [wonderful] things like
            unto this, but in comparison to the other deeds which
            were wrought by the blessed man these are not very
            important.
         </p>
         <p>
            On one occasion he stood up to pray at the ninth
            hour, and he perceived that his mind was exalted, and,
            what was still more wonderful, that whilst he was on
            the earth his mind was transformed, and he did not
            feel that he was upon the earth. For he saw that his
            soul was not being lifted up by the power of his mind,
            but was being governed by the angels; and when he
            himself was raised up, he saw other beings who came
            and tood opposite to him, and they prevented him
            from passing on. And they said, <quote>Let us see of what
            kind are his deeds, and if we cannot by any means
            make him to be taken (or, held) by us.</quote> Then those
            who were guiding him turned round and rebuked them,
            and said unto them, <quote>Our Lord by His grace blotted
            out his shortcomings and his sins before he became
            a disciple, but ye are embodied in his triumphs and
            in his works and deeds [which took place] after he
            had become a disciple;</quote> and thereupon his soul was
            immediately exalted to the place unto which it attained.
            And after this his mind took up its abode in him, and
            <pb n="78"/>he felt and perceived that which had happened to him;
            and he magnified and gave thanks to (or, confessed) God
            by reason of everything which had taken place, and
            [he remained] in prayer the whole night which followed
            that day, and he tasted no food of any kind whatsoever 
            therein.
         </p>
         <p>
            And a man must also marvel at the severity
            <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#65"/>of our contest, and at the great labour by
            which he passeth to this air; and he must remember
            and say, <quote>This is the word of the <persName>Apostle</persName> who spake,
            saying, 'Your contending is against the ruler who
            holdeth the power of this world.'</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-1"/> For this reason
            the <persName>Apostle</persName> himself commanded, saying, <quote>Put on the
            armour of God in order that ye may be able to stand
            against him in the evil day,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-2"/> so that the Enemy
            may have no occasion in any way to say about us
            that we have been sorely put to shame. And, my
            beloved, in connexion with the history of the blessed
            man let us remember the matter of the <persName>Apostle</persName>, who
            said, <quote>Whether in the body or out of the body, I
            know not; God knoweth.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-3"/> Now the blessed <persName>Paul</persName> was
            snatched up into the third heaven, and heard words
            which may not be uttered, and came down (again); but
            the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> was lifted up unto the place to
            which he was lifted up, and he received a pledge of
            the confidence of his labour, and he returned and took
            up his abode with himself. And the [sign of] grace
            was also found with him. Whensoever he had in his
            mind any matter the truth of which he could not comprehend 
            with his thoughts, he would make supplication
            in his prayer, and it would be revealed unto him, and
            in all these things he was taught by God, even as it
            is written.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-4"/>
         </p>
         <pb n="79"/>
         <p>
            And after these things he had a disputation with
            certain men who came to him about the ordering and
            disposition of the soul, and the place to which it went
            after its departure [from the body]. Then, on another
            day, he heard a voice from heaven, which said, <quote><persName>Anthony</persName>, 
            get thee forth, and thou shalt see.</quote> And,
            moreover, this thing had also been wrought for him:
            he was able to distinguish between heavenly voices
            and the voices of enemies. And he lifted up his eyes
            and saw the form of a man which was immeasurably
            abominable; his head reached up into the heavens, and
            round about him, on all sides, were numbers of beings,
            some of which were flying about with their wings, and
            were soaring up above him; and he put forth his hands
            that he might lay hold<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n79-1"/> of some [of them], but he was
            not able to do so. Now those winged beings who
            were flying about were those who had preserved (or,
            guarded) their faith <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#66"/>and their works; but the
            others he could lay hold of because they were those
            who had not received the faith, and who were remote
            from works. Then the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> saw that the
            form of the man was gnashing his teeth with bitterness
            at those who were being lifted up into life, for [that]
            son of perdition would have been content that every
            man should perish with him. And straightway a voice
            came unto the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, and said, <quote>Know thou
            that which hath been made;</quote> and then he understood
            that this was the passage (or, bridge) of souls, and
            that he who was standing in the midst was <persName>Satan</persName>, the
            enemy of righteousness. Such was the vision which
            came unto him, and it roused him up and incited him
            exceedingly to triumph in his old age.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now these things were not related by his will, but
            the brethren who saw him when he was sighing during
            his prayer to God perceived that something had been
            seen by him, and they clung to him and pressed him
            <pb n="80"/>with entreaties to inform them what had happened.
            And having examined his mind, and seen that it was
            free from boasting, he decided within himself that the
            report of such things as these would certainly admonish
            the youthful monks to stand up like mighty warriors
            in the war which the Enemy maketh against us, and
            not to be caught by him in any way, so that he might
            not be able to lift up his heel against us; and having
            thus decided he revealed and made known unto them
            the whole matter even as it appeared unto them. For
            he was exceedingly longsuffering in respect of the things
            which were fitting, and he was thoroughly meek in
            spirit, and in all these things he preserved scrupulously
            the Canons of the Church, and made answer unto
            every man according to his grade and rank. Unto
            Bishops and Elders he paid honour like a man who
            was in duty bound so to do, and he was not ashamed
            to bow his head before them at the time of the Blessing; 
            but deacons he received with joy and with affection,
            and although, like a father, he made them to hear
            words of righteousness and admonition, during the time
            of prayer he would set them in front by reason of the
            authority which had once been given unto them by
            God. He meditated continually upon righteousness,
            <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#67"/>and he did not seek only to make another
            hear the Word, but he himself rejoiced to hear it, and
            he was never ashamed to do so, even though he was
            an old man and a famous one; but on several occasions
            he asked questions of those who were with him at all
            times, and entreated that he might hear that which
            was suitable to his life and deeds, and he would confess
            that he had been benefited whensoever a subject of
            this kind was debated among them.
         </p>
         <p>
            And the countenance of the blessed man was clothed
            with the splendour of praise, and wonder thereat laid
            hold upon every man. Whensoever it happened that
            he was with many people, and it fell out that a man
            came there who had never seen the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>,
            <pb n="81"/>his eyes would glance quickly over all the people, and
            he would gaze intently upon them all, and would [at
            once] distinguish the newcomer, who, by reason of
            the splendour of grace which dwelt in the blessed
            man, would, as if drawn by cords, leave the other
            people and boldly make his way direct to him. Now
            this did not arise because the stature of the blessed
            <persName>Anthony</persName> was greater than that of any other man, or
            because his external appearance was more beautiful
            than that of any other man, but by reason of those
            spiritual triumphs which were within [him], even as it
            is written, <quote>A good heart maketh beautiful the body;
            and an evil heart maketh gloomy the countenance.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n81-1"/>
            And, moreover, <persName>Jacob</persName> discerned by the appearance of
            the countenance of Laban that he was meditating fraud
            concerning him, for he said<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n81-2"/> unto his wives, <quote>I see that
            the face of your father is not towards me as it was
            yesterday and formerly;</quote> and in the same manner
            <persName>Samuel</persName> recognized <persName>David</persName>, for his eyes were beautiful<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n81-3"/>
            and his features were joyous. And thus was it also
            in the case of the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, and by such
            indications he was known by those who saw him;
            when he was troubled [they saw that] his visage was
            disturbed, and when he was angry that his thoughts
            were ruffled.
         </p>
         <p>
            And, moreover, he was immeasurably firm in the
            faith, and he held fast thereunto with honour and discretion 
            (or, discernment); he did not conduct himself
            in the matter of faith like a man who made himself a
            stranger unto the children of men, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#68"/>or like
            one who dwelt in the desert, either in common with
            other monks, or by himself; and he would not receive
            the people who used to go to him without question
            and also enquiry. For he never joined himself to the
            <pb n="82"/>Meletian heretics<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n82-1"/> who were in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, for from the
            very beginning he was well acquainted with their dissensions 
            (or, schisms), and their restlessness, and he
            never took count at all of the other heresies, and he
            even exhorted every man to withdraw himself from them,
            for he used to say, <quote>Neither in the discussion of them nor
            in their result is there any advantage.</quote> Similarly the
            Arian heretics were so detestable and contemptible in
            his sight that he withdrew himself altogether from
            having any dealings with them, and he also exhorted
            other people to keep themselves far from their words
            and their doctrines. And it happened on one occasion
            that some of these Arians went to him, but when he
            had enquired at their hands, and he had asked them
            questions and learned that they belonged to the dough
            of the leaven of <persName>Arius</persName>, the unbeliever, he drove them
            forth from his presence like the other wild beasts and
            vipers. And he said unto them, <quote>Ye are more bitter
            and more evil than the beasts of prey and deadly
            serpents.</quote> Now on one occasion the Arians spread a
            report and made a scandal which they cast upon the
            world, and they went about, saying, <quote><persName>Anthony</persName> hath
            agreed to our faith and hath accepted it,</quote> and when
            this report came to his ears, astonishment laid hold
            upon him, and he marvelled greatly at the falsehood
            of the Arians, and how easily error came to them
            through the impudence of their minds.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now when the bishops and the other brethren saw
            that the wickedness of the Arians was prevailing, and
            that they had spread this report through the whole
            city, they entreated the blessed man to exert himself
            a little in order that those liars might be put to great
            shame; and he was persuaded by them to go down to
            the city of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and to proclaim openly there
            that the Arians were <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#69"/>blasphemers, so that
            <pb n="83"/>their iniquity might come back upon their own
            heads. And having gone down [to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>] a vast
            multitude of people thronged there at the report [of
            the coming of] the blessed man, and when all the
            people were gathered together [to him] he admonished
            and exhorted them in a loud voice to beware of the
            error of the Arians, and he said, <quote>This [i. e., Arianism]
            is the essence of all heresies, and it is the work of
            the Christs of falsehood; get ye away then from them
            afar off that ye become not corrupted by them. God
            forbid that the Son of God should be proclaimed to
            be a thing<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n83-1"/> which hath been made, or that He should
            be named as something which came from nothing.
            For He is of the substance of the Father, and He is
            His Child, and it is therefore great wickedness for a
            man to say that there was ever a time when He was
            not; for the Word existed at all times with God.
            Therefore flee ye from association with them, lest ye
            have a portion in their blasphemy, for light hath
            no connexion with darkness, and ye must have no
            connexion whatsoever with them, and ye must have no
            likeness to or association with them, for ye are in the
            righteousness of your faith believing <persName>Christians</persName>, and
            those who say that the Son of the Living God is a
            created thing are in no wise different from the heathen.
            Believe me, O my beloved, that the very creatures
            are far more to be desired than those who worship
            the creatures in preference to their Creator, and who
            confound and compare the creatures with the Lord
            and Creator of the universe.</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Thereupon all the people held the Arians to be
            like other heretics, and they were esteemed in their
            sight wholly as blasphemers and unbelievers, and all
            men were confirmed in the correct view concerning
            the faith. Then [the people of] the city, both the
            <pb n="84"/><persName>Christians</persName> and the Armâye,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n84-1"/> and also those who were
            called <quote>priests,</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n84-2"/> ran into the church to see the <quote>man
            of God,</quote> for by this name and title was he called;
            and in that city also our Lord wrought by the hand
            of the blessed man many signs and wonders, and so
            many of those whose <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#70"/>minds had been injured
            through error obtained through him the means of healing 
            that more people became <persName>Christians</persName> on that day
            than in the whole year [previously]. And large numbers
            of the heathen entreated to be allowed to see the
            blessed man, and to draw nigh unto the cloak of the
            righteous man; to this wonderful pass did the measure
            of the power of the blessed man come. Now when
            the brethren saw that a great uproar had arisen,
            and that the people were troubling him by thronging
            about him, they made a way through them and surrounded 
            him, for they thought that he would be
            choked by the throng; but the blessed man answered
            and said unto them quietly, and with a smile, <quote>Let the
            people perform their desire. For what think ye? Is it
            not as easy for me to bear with this crowd of believers
            as the throng of devils which are in the desert?</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            And when he had made an end of all these things
            in <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> he went forth to depart into the wilderness, 
            and the whole city clave unto him; and when he
            had come to the side of the gate of the city, a certain
            woman came running with all her strength after the
            crowd, and cried out, <quote>Wait a little for me, O man of
            God. My daughter is grievously vexed by a devil
            and tormented, and I beseech thee to wait, and let
            healing be to my daughter; and moreover, let not
            my soul be carried out of [my body] through running
            overmuch.</quote> And when the voice was heard by the
            <pb n="85"/>ears of the old man, he paused and stood still until the
            woman drew nigh unto him and cast her daughter down
            by his feet. Then the blessed man looked up to heaven
            and cried out the Name of <persName>Christ</persName> over the devil, and
            straightway the damsel stood up, and turned towards
            her mother, being freed from the subjection of the Evil
            One; and every man gave thanks unto God, and the
            mother of the damsel also glorified him that had wrought
            deliverance for her. And immediately after the blessed
            man had performed this work he turned [again] to his
            journey, for he rejoiced exceedingly at his going to the
            desert, and he was even like unto <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#71"/>the man
            who rejoiceth at going [again], after a long absence, to
            his own house, and the house of his kinsfolk. Now the
            blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> was a wise man, and he was one who
            was full of understanding, and it was a very great
            wonder in the sight of men how such knowledge and
            understanding could dwell in a man who had not learned
            to read or to write.
         </p>
         <p>
            On one occasion there came unto him two philosophers
            to try him (now he was living on the outer mountain),
            and so soon as he perceived them afar off he knew
            and discerned what they were by their garb. And
            having gone forth to meet them, he said unto them by
            means of his interpreters, <quote>Why have ye given yourselves 
            all this trouble to come and see a man of low
            estate?</quote> and they answered him [in these] word[s],
            <quote>Thou art not a man of low estate, but a wise man.</quote>
            Then, after he had understood (or, tasted) their words,
            he began to say unto them, <quote>If ye had come to a man
            of low estate ye would have given yourselves all this
            trouble in vain, but if your words are true, and if ye
            indeed believe that I am a wise man, become ye even
            as I am, for it is meet that we should at all times be
            zealous to obtain the things which are fair. Had it
            happened that I had come unto you I should have
            been compelled to become like unto you; and now
            that ye have come unto me, become ye <persName>Christians</persName>
            <pb n="86"/>like myself.</quote> And when these philosophers heard these
            words, and saw in what a state of subjection the devils
            stood before him, they marvelled exceedingly and turned
            away on their heels in silence.
         </p>
         <p>
            After these there also came unto him others who
            were like unto them to the outer mountain; now they
            came prepared to make a mock of him as if he had
            been a fool, for they had heard that he possessed no
            learning. And when they had pressed their talk upon
            him after this manner, the old man said unto them, <quote>I
            will ask you a question, and ye shall return me an
            answer. Which is the older, learning or the mind?
            And which is the source (or, cause) of the other? Is
            learning the source of the mind, or the mind of learning?</quote> 
            Then the philosophers said unto him, <quote>The
            mind is the prince of learning, for it hath <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#72"/>
            discovered learning.</quote> And he said unto them, <quote>Doth
            not then the man whose mind is enlightened and bright
            surpass greatly [him that hath only] learning? For by
            the first word [which he uttereth] do men test a man,
            and they understand whether he possesseth a wise
            and understanding mind [or not];</quote> then they also
            marvelled at what they had seen and heard, and they
            likewise went back to their own country.
         </p>
         <p>
            For he was a man whose intelligence was profound,
            and he was wise and exceedingly understanding, and
            he was not in any way like unto a man who had been
            brought up in the desert from his youth. And when
            he became old and waxed aged he was simple in his
            speech, and austere and stern(?) in his mind, but still
            he was perfect and complete in everything, and every
            [good] quality was found in him in the state which
            was most fitting. Now his speech, even as we have
            already said, was so exceedingly savoury and so well
            seasoned with heavenly salt, that none of his hearers
            could be angry at his words, and no man could be
            envious of the acts of his daily life, for he was ready
            and prepared to hear and answer every kind of opinion.
         </p>
         <pb n="87"/>
         <p>
            Now on another occasion it happened that certain
            men, who were wise according to the world and who
            were received gladly among the <persName>Greeks</persName>, went to him,
            and began to ask him questions concerning the faith
            which is in our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, wishing to confound
            him in a discussion concerning the matter of the Cross
            and of the preaching of our Lord, and having seen
            that they were ready to scoff and to mock, he bore
            with them a little, and then, having observed them, he
            roared greatly in his heart concerning the error which
            dwelt in them. Then he spake unto them by means
            of an interpreter, who was exceedingly skilled in translating 
            words from the <persName>Egyptian</persName> into the Greek language,
            and he said unto them first of all, <quote>Which is the easier?
            For a man to confess the Cross, or to believe that
            adultery, and fornication, and impure acts with men
            are committed by those who are called 'gods.' For
            the [doctrine] which is spoken and believed by us is
            a mark and a likeness of the men by whom <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#73"/>
            death is held in contempt, and the world is considered
            to be of no account, but the religion which ye preach
            is a service of impurity, and the desire of foul lusts.
            Which thing then is more beneficial for us to believe?
            That [<persName>Christ</persName>] is the Son of God, and that that which
            He was in His Godhead was in no way changed, although 
            through His care for the redemption of the
            children of men He took upon Himself the body of
            our human nature, and with His Godhead was mingled
            therewith, so that by means of His union with our
            human nature He might mingle it with His Godhead,
            or that we should liken God unto beasts and cattle,
            and that in consequence thereof man should make
            himself like unto the similitudes of beasts and of the
            creeping things of the earth and should worship them?
            Now, our belief proclaimeth that the coming of <persName>Christ</persName>
            took place for the redemption of the children of men,
            and that it should not be unto us a cause for fornication, 
            and falsehood, and injustice (or, avarice), and
            <pb n="88"/>gluttony, and drunkenness, and lasciviousness, and the
            rest of the luxurious practices which exist in the world.
            And we exhort and admonish [men to avoid] all these
            things, for a penalty hath been decreed for every man
            who shall dare to transgress in respect of one of these
            things. Now ye, through the fable of error labour
            in the work of abomination, but we, because we have
            trust in the power and lovingkindness (or, mercy) of
            God, believe that the preaching of the Cross is easiest
            for us [to follow]. And ye, without any discernment,
            ascribe all kinds of hateful practices to your gods, so
            that ye without any further thought may do everything 
            [ye please].</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>And moreover, as concerning the soul ye say that
            it is an image of the mind (or, understanding), and
            when ye have meditated well upon this subject ye go
            back and say that it will be dissolved; and therefore,
            because of this opinion which cometh from [your] study,
            ye lay it down that the mind itself will be divided
            (or, broken up) and changed. For, of necessity, the
            image must in its form and similitude be exactly like
            that of which it is the copy<anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#74"/>; and ye should
            know that when ye think in this manner about the
            mind that ye also blaspheme the Father thereof.</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>And in respect of the Cross, which is it better for
            us to say? That it endureth patiently the anger of
            the attack of the madness of our human nature, and
            that it neither departeth by death, nor doth the terrible
            death which striketh fear into the mighty man come
            unto it, or [shall we ascribe to it] the error, and the
            allegories, and the cunning plans, and the vain stories,
            and the incitements [to sin], and the flight, and the
            mockery, and the shame, which are written down in
            your fables, wherein your gods took refuge when strife
            and death came upon each one of them? For such
            things are the wisdom of your wisdom. And wherefore 
            do ye make a mockery of the Cross only and
            hold not in wonder the Resurrection? For those who
            <pb n="89"/>have written [the account of] <persName>Christ</persName>'s crucifixion have
            also proclaimed His Resurrection. And why, when ye
            make mention of the Cross, do ye not also recount
            the miracles, and the Resurrection from the dead, and
            all the other things also, that is to say, [the restoration
            of] the sight of the blind, and the cleansing of the
            lepers, and the healing of the paralytics, and the walking upon the
            the waters? For from these ye would be
            able to have understanding of <persName>Christ</persName>, and ye would
            learn that He was not only a man but God also.
            Indeed, ye appear to me to act wholly unjustly. For
            ye do not judge matters rightly, and the Scriptures
            are not read in a proper manner by you; and since
            certain things are accepted and believed in by you,
            whilst others, which are akin to them, are not, where
            is your fair dealing in this matter?</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>Narrate ye now unto us your scriptures, and explain
            ye unto us what is therein. What are the animals
            which are worshipped, and what are the reptiles unto
            which are given the names of gods, except subjects
            for mockery and disgrace? But if a man void of
            understanding cometh to you ye liken each one of
            them [unto gods] in the speech of rational beings, and
            ye expound the unlikely things [which are declared
            concerning them] so that the foolish may think <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#75"/>
            that they are true. Ye give names to the earth, and
            to the heavens, and the sun, and the moon, and the
            air, and the sea, and the fire, and the waters, and to
            other created things, and ye call them gods, that ye
            may lead man astray thereby from the One God Who
            is the Creator of the universe. The quest of the God
            of truth is not among you, and ye are found worshipping 
            the things which have been created rather than
            Him Who created them. For, if ye gave the names
            of gods to such similitudes because created things
            were so exceedingly beautiful, it would have been
            sufficient for you to be able to admire them, without
            holding them in such absolute and singular honour in
            <pb n="90"/>your minds. And because of this opinion of error
            which dwelleth in your mind it is not difficult for you
            either to divert to the house which He hath fashioned
            and adorned the honour which is due to the Master-handicraftsman, 
            or to hold lightly the king, and to
            ascribe the glory which is His due to His household
            which ministereth unto him. What then have ye to
            urge against these [words], O wise men? [Speak,] so
            that we may know if there be in the Cross anything
            which meriteth mockery.</quote> And when the blessed man
            had spoken unto them in this fashion the things which
            they could not endure to hear from him, they began
            to look to the right hand and to the left.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now when the blessed man knew that they were
            silently seeking to make objections to his words, he
            spake unto them again through an interpreter, saying,
            <quote>The work (. e., proof) of these my words is also their
            testimony; but because ye yourselves take refuge in
            words of guile and falsehood, and because ye employ
            them with the greatest skill, ye desire that we, like
            yourselves, shall also journey on without the truth of
            investigation. Shew ye me now briefly the work [or,
            proof] of [your] words. First of all, How can the
            knowledge of God be truly comprehended? Which
            is the older: the faith which is in works, and this is
            true knowledge ..........<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n90-1"/></quote> The old man saith
            unto them, "Ye have well said, for faith is the sign of
            the <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#76"/>love which is made perfect in the soul.
            For discussion cometh from words which are strung
            together, and therefore the faith which is in works,
            and which is closely united to them, is not sought after,
            because the quest of words is superfluous; for the
            matters which we comprehend by faith ye try by every
            means to represent by comparisons and similitudes,
            and howsoever much ye weary yourselves ye will
            never be able to narrate the things the truth of
            <pb n="91"/>which we have comprehended. It is, therefore, well
            known and evident that our faith which is in works
            is far more excellent than your wisdom [which consisteth 
            of] a discussion of words, and that your
            wisdom cannot by any means be [rightly] compared
            therewith.
         </p>
         <p>
            For we <persName>Christians</persName> have not acquired the mystery
            of life through the wisdom of strange words, but by
            the power of faith which hath been given unto us by
            God, the Lord of all; and that the[se] word(s) are true
            accept the proof from the following. Behold, we are
            not learned in books, yet we believe in God, and we
            possess understanding concerning His creation, and
            concerning the mercy of the Providence of His grace,
            and we have confidence through the faith of <persName>Jesus</persName>
            <persName>Christ</persName> that our faith is sure, [whilst] ye have only
            words which are full of contentions; in your case the
            phantom of the adornment of your idols gradually
            cometh to an end, but in ours our faith increaseth and
            becometh more abundant day by day everywhere. In
            your case, in spite of the abundance of your discussions
            and wisdom, ye have no power to turn even one
            Christian to paganism, but in ours by the faith of
            <persName>Christ</persName> which we preach, we despise your doctrine
            and there is in your well-ordered, carefully arranged,
            and polished words no power which can do away the
            teaching of <persName>Christ</persName>. And, moreover, we by means of
            the Cross which ye hold in contempt chase away and
            put to flight those devils which ye worship as gods,
            and wheresoever the name of the Cross is mentioned
            all the crafts and wiles of error come to an end. If
            it be divination, it is destroyed, and if it be sorcery
            it is made an end of; and that such hath been done
            in very truth ye must admit when ye are asked by
            us <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#77"/><quote>Where is divination? Where are the
            magicians who were in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>? Where are the
            phantoms of the error of the sorcerers? When were
            these things which appertain unto you destroyed
            <pb n="92"/>except when the Cross of <persName>Christ</persName> was mentioned?</quote>
            Is then this Cross worthy to be despised? Judge ye
            this matter in your souls, and consider it also and
            marvel thereat. It is a matter of wonder that your
            doctrine hath never before been a subject for persecution,
            and that it hath only become so at this time when
            <persName>Christian kings</persName> [live] in honour and majesty in every
            place.
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>In proportion as persecution cometh your doctrine
            hideth itself, but ours, against which storms innumerable 
            have arrayed themselves, becometh stronger
            and stronger. Your doctrine, notwithstanding that
            it is praised and magnified, becometh despised and
            rejected, whilst ours although held in contempt is great
            in its acts and glorious in its operation, and being
            harassed [spreadeth] from one end of the earth even
            unto the other without men taking care about it. For
            when did the knowledge of God come down into the
            world, and chastity flourish, and virginity shed its
            light abroad, and death become held in contempt, if it
            be not after the Cross of victory came and triumphed
            throughout all the earth? And of this fact no man
            can have any doubt, when he considereth the blessed
            martyrs by whom death was despised because of the
            victory of the Cross. And behold, do we not see that
            the Church rejoiceth in innumerable congregations of
            virgins, both men and women, who preserve their
            bodies in all holiness? These are the true likenesses
            which make known and shew forth the faith of <persName>Christ</persName>,
            which is a living confidence and a knowledge in faith
            unto those who put their trust therein. Now if ye
            have been in doubt [concerning these things] up to
            this present, it is because your mind (or, opinion)
            hath been fettered with words of binding and loosing,
            the end of which ye will never be able to find; for
            we do not, like you, go astray through the blandishment 
            of the words of alien wisdom, but, according to
            what our Teacher spake, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#78"/>we give a proof of
            <pb n="93"/>our faith, and we readily make manifest in the clearest
            possible manner the truth of our opinion unto every
            one who wisheth [to see it].</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            And behold, there were in that place certain men
            who were suffering from injuries to their bodies, and
            the blessed man commanded them, and they came forth
            and stood in the midst; then he answered and said
            unto those wise men, <quote>Draw nigh now and, by whatsoever 
            means ye wish and will, whether by the wisdom
            of your renowned idols, or by your sorceries and
            enchantments, give the word, and let these afflicted
            souls have relief from their sufferings. But if ye are
            not able so to do, stand aside and cease your hostile
            attacks upon us, and ye shall straightway see the
            power of the Cross of <persName>Christ</persName>.</quote> Then he made the
            sign of the Cross over them three times, and the
            people were healed immediately and stood up; and
            when those philosophers saw [this] they praised him
            greatly, and they marvelled in very deed at the understanding 
            of the man, and at the visible sign which
            had been wrought by his hand. And the blessed man
            said unto them, <quote>Why marvel ye at this thing? It is
            not we who have done this, but <persName>Christ</persName> Who is wont
            to do such like things by the hands of those who fear
            Him. Therefore do you also believe even as do we,
            and become like us, and see that we possess none of
            the handicraft of devils, but only the faith which is
            made perfect by means of the love of <persName>Christ</persName>, our
            Lord <persName>Jesus</persName>. If ye possess this also ye have no
            need of the quest of much discussion, for the deed
            itself will convince you that it is not by words but
            by manifest works that our doctrine increaseth and
            giveth the faith of our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>.</quote> Such were
            the words which the blessed man spake unto those
            philosophers, who tarried to hear [them]and who put
            to the test and then received the proof of all the
            [mental] adornment of the old man; and thus having
            received his grace, they applauded his words and his
            <pb n="94"/>acts, and having saluted him with great honour they
            returned to their own country.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now the fame of the blessed man reached <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#79"/>
            even unto the king and the princes, and the Emperor
            <persName>Constantine</persName> and his sons <persName>Ķüsnâțis (Constantius)</persName> and
            <persName>Ķûstos (Constans)</persName> heard concerning his works and
            triumphs, and they began to write epistles unto him as
            unto a father and to entreat him to pray for them,
            and they longed greatly to become the recipients of
            letters from him. Now he did not write letters quickly,
            and he did not consider too highly or boast about
            those which he received, but he continued to preserve
            the humility and sweetness of disposition which he
            possessed before he received the imperial epistles, and
            after he had, received them he remained unchanged.
            Whensoever he received the imperial letters he would
            call and gather together the monks who happened to
            be with him, and say unto them, <persName>Ye marvel, perhaps,
            that the kings and the princes should write epistles
            unto us, but what [need] is there for wonder, seeing
            that it is only one man writing letters to another;
            but what ye should wonder at is how God wrote the
            Law for the children of men, and how He hath spoken
            unto us through His only Son.</persName> He preferred, however, 
            not to receive epistles which were sent unto him
            by the king and the princes, for he said, <quote>It is not in
            my power to write epistles like theirs;</quote> but inasmuch
            as the king and the princes were <persName>Christians</persName> he did
            not consider it seemly that their epistles should be
            held lightly, lest they might become offended and be
            displeased, and he permitted them to be read before
            every one who happened to be with him.
            Now the manner in which he wrote his epistles
            [in answer] was as follows:–In the first place he
            magnified [those to whom they were addressed], and
            returned thanks because they were worshippers of
            <persName>Christ</persName>, and he gave them advice and united thereto
            the counsels which were suitable, and which would
            <pb n="95"/>benefit them both in this world and in that which is
            to come. And he told them that the wearisome labours
            which were visible should not be accounted overmuch
            by them, and exhorted them to remember the judgment
            which is to come, and that it is <persName>Christ</persName> Who is the true
            <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#80"/>and everlasting king. And he advised them
            to let lovingkindness be found in them, and to be
            careful for that which is right, and to have considerate
            regard for the poor. Kings used to receive him and
            rejoice in him greatly, and he was greatly esteemed
            by every man, and regarded as a righteous father.
         </p>
         <p>
            Whensoever certain matters had to be done, and
            certain things had to be talked about he was in the
            habit of going back to the inner mountain, and as
            something which was gratifying unto him he would
            work his triumphs there. On many occasions when
            he was sitting with those who went to him, or was
            walking about, he would hold his peace for a long
            time, and would keep wholly to himself according to
            that which is written in [the book of] <persName>Daniel</persName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95-1"/> and after
            a season he would utter in its order the word which
            would bind him to the brethren. Now those who saw
            him (act) in this manner use to know that some vision
            had appeared unto him, and indeed on several occasions 
            when he was in the mountain he saw things which
            were being wrought in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>; and <persName>Serapion</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95-2"/> the Bishop
            related that during the whole of the time which he
            remained with him he had seen the blessed man for
            several days at a time labouring seriously with visions
            in this manner.
         </p>
         <p>
            One day whilst he was sitting down at work on
            the palm leaves he fell into a state of profound stupefaction, 
            and remained for an exceedingly long time
            <pb n="96"/>therein seeing a vision of revelation, and he groaned
            frequently, and after a season he turned round to those
            who happened to be with him, and groaned again;
            and he trembled greatly, and began to pray, and he
            bent his knees and [then] stood up with his eyes full
            of tears. Now those who saw the old man thus troubled
            were beginners in the monastic life, and they were greatly
            moved and were afraid with a great fear; and after a
            season they began to entreat him to tell him what was
            the vision which he had seen, and which had troubled him
            in this fashion. Then when they had pressed him he sighed
            the more, and said unto them<anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#81"/>, <quote>It would be
            much better for me to die than for that which hath
            appeared unto me to happen.</quote> And being urged by their
            entreaty, he spake sadly and excitedly, saying, <quote>Great
            wrath is coming upon the Church, which is about to
            be delivered over to men who are in no wise different
            from the wild animals. I have seen an altar surrounded 
            by mules which without mercy kicked all
            the people, both great and small, for they were as
            excited as a drove of horses which have been turned
            loose without bridles. When I sighed concerning these
            things, even ye heard the sound of my sighs, and I
            heard a voice which said, 'My altar shall be defiled.'</quote>
            Such were the things which the old man saw. Two
            years later<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n96-1"/> the trouble with the Arians took place,
            and the spoliation of the churches by the hands of the
            pagans in the sight of all the people of the city who
            were gathered together, and they caused the performance 
            of the holy service to be set aside and abrogated.
            Now these pagans went forth into the streets of
            the city, and they thronged them and brought
            forth people from their shops, and compelled them to
            assemble with them, and before their eyes they performed 
            the service of the Church and [administered]
            the Holy Mysteries. It was then that we understood
            <pb n="97"/>[what] the kickings of the mules [meant], that is to
            say [the vision] which had appeared unto the blessed
            man, and the whole work which was wrought with
            such iniquity and wickedness by the hands of the Arians
            in the Church.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now when the blessed man saw this vision, and
            perceived that it was very grievous to the brethren,
            he consoled them, and said, <quote>My beloved sons, be not
            afficted, for as God is angry now even so will He
            become pacified again, and after no [great] interval
            between these trials and injuries rest and peace shall
            come upon the Church of God. And ye shall see
            those who have been persecuted for righteousness'
            sake return to their places, and the Evil One, together
            with those who work his will, shall turn on his heels,
            and the horn of the righteous men who hold the
            true faith shall be exalted, and shall openly proclaim
            <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#82"/>the truth in the ears of a persecuted but
            believing nation. Hearken ye then unto these things
            from me, and take heed that ye keep yourselves from
            fornication in respect of the faith, and from intercourse
            with people who are polluted therewith; for the time
            of these things shall be short, and there shall be
            redemption for the people of God, and the righteous
            man shall live by faith.</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Such were the things which were spoken by the
            blessed man, and it is not a great matter that such
            things were uttered and seen by the man who was
            crucified unto the world, and to whom the world was
            crucified. For our Lord made the promise unto believers, 
            saying, <quote>If ye have in you faith like a grain
            of mustard seed ye shall say unto this mountain,
            'Depart'; and it shall depart, and there is nothing
            which shall be too hard for you;</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n97-1"/> and again He said,
            <quote>Whatsoever ye shall ask of My Father in My Name
            shall be given unto you.</quote> And He commanded His
            <pb n="98"/>disciples, saying, <quote>Go ye forth, and preach, and heal
            the sick, and cast out devils; freely ye have received,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n98-1"/>
            freely give.</quote> Now the blessed man did not perform
            healings by his own power after the manner of a
            master, but only with prayer and with the mention of
            the Name of <persName>Christ</persName>, so that it might be manifest unto
            every man that it was not he who was the doer of
            these things, but that God wrought them by his hands.
            Thus the old man was triumphant in all such matters,
            for his strength was renewed from day to day even
            as is the youth of the eagle, by the fervour of his
            mind, and he had pleasure in the constant works which
            our Lord <persName>Jesus</persName> wrought for him.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now he was afflicted and suffered much by reason
            of the people who were continually coming to him,
            and he enjoyed no respite from them, and he was
            therefore compelled to withdraw to the outer mountain;
            and moreover, the judges and the governors of the
            country entreated him to come back to a place of
            habitation because it was difficult for them to come
            near him on account of the numerous people who
            clung to him, and because of the fatigue of the journey
            which [they had to endure] in going to him. And
            this matter was exceedingly hard to the blessed man,
            and he excused himself <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#83"/>from such like things.
            Now when the judges and the governors saw that he
            refused to do what they wanted, they dealt craftily
            with him in this matter, for they sent to him the
            <persName>Greeks</persName> and the other people who had been arrested
            for evil dealing and wickednesses of various kinds, and
            they entreated and besought him with much supplication
            to come back to the habitations of men so that he
            might work deliverance from prison for them; and by
            such means and excuses the judges were able to see
            him continually, and the toil which he suffered on such
            journeys was not in vain, for his coming was beneficial
            <pb n="99"/>to everyone. Now the judges heard from him that
            which helped them to rule [righteously], and they
            learned to know they themselves were men, and were
            even as those who were subject unto them, and that
            they must not behave towards them angrily, but judge
            them righteously, for, <quote>With what judgment ye judge
            [ye shall be judged</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n99-1"/>]. But although the blessed man
            rejoiced in the works of the fear of God which he
            wrought, he was more pleased with his habitation in
            the desert than with any other thing. And after he
            had been led by force by those men who had made
            supplication unto him, and had entreated him to come to
            the outer mountain, so soon as he had performed for
            them his kind offices and had spoken unto the governor
            words which were suitable to his majesty and dominion,
            he would hasten back to his place. And when the
            governor did homage to him, and begged him to
            remain with him for a day or two, the old man entreated
            him courteously [to be allowed to depart], saying, <quote>This
            thing is impossible, for as fish die if a man lift
            them out of the water, so, if we monks prolong our
            stay with men, do our minds become perverted and
            troubled; therefore it is meet that as fish [pass] their
            lives beneath the waters we also should let our lives
            and works be buried in the wilderness.</quote> Now when
            the governor heard these and other things like unto
            them<anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#84"/>, he marvelled and said, <quote>Verily [this
            is] a true servant of God. He speaketh not that
            which cometh from himself, but that which is given
            unto him from heaven. How could this simple man
            possess such rich knowledge unless he was beloved
            by God?</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Now a certain duke whose name was <persName>Bâlak</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n99-2"/> persecuted 
            the Church sorely at the instigation of the
            <pb n="100"/>Arians, and his wickedness increased to such an extent
            that he would beat the nuns, and strip the monks
            naked and flog them. And when the blessed old man
            heard of the wickedness of this man, he wrote a letter
            and sent it to him, and in it was thus written, <quote>Behold,
            I see that wrath is coming upon thee; desist therefore,
            and accept rebuke, and persecute not the believers,
            that peradventure the angel of wrath may be restrained,
            for behold, he hath set out to come.</quote> When <persName>Balak</persName>
            received the letter, he looked thereat and laughed, and
            he spat thereon and took it up and threw it away;
            and in his hatred he cursed the bringer of the letter,
            and said unto him, <quote>Get thee back and tell these things
            unto him that sent thee.</quote> And he said unto him,
            <quote>Inasmuch as thou hast exceedingly great regard for
            the churches and for those who are persecuted, behold
            I will speedily execute judgment upon thee also;</quote> but
            after these words he went no further than five days
            before wrath overtook him. For he set out to journey
            to the first stopping place [on the road from] <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>
            which is called <persName>Khróaðs</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n100-1"/> and as the duke <persName>Bâlaş</persName> and
            <persName>Nestor</persName>, the prefect of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, were riding together–
            now they were riding two of <quote>Bâlaķ</quote>'s horses which were
            the gentlest of all his horses–before they arrived at
            the place (of destination), the horses began to play together 
            according to their wont, and suddenly the gentler
            of the two horses, that is to say the animal whereon
            <persName>Nestor</persName> the prefect rode, seized the thigh of <quote>Bâlaķ</quote> with
            his mouth and dragged him from his horse and fell
            upon him and rent him like a dog. And they took
            <persName>Bâlak</persName> and brought him in to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#85"/>
            and after three days he died; and thus the word of
            the blessed man actually came to pass, and wonder
            laid hold upon every man.
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>And these were the things which he was wont to
            <pb n="101"/>say to the judges of [this] world, and he would give
            them counsel in a loving manner, that they should not
            be puffed up in their minds, and that they should not
            magnify themselves over the people, for there was no
            governor at that time who would not gladly hearken unto
            him, and they repented of their [evil] deeds, and ascribed 
            blessing unto those who despised the world and
            became aliens thereto. And moreover, he had such
            great care for those who were treated unjustly, and
            were plundered of their possessions, that he himself
            would bear all their (troubles); and his words were so
            grateful and pleasant unto all those who drew nigh
            unto him that many of the dwellers in villages and in
            towns, and pagans (or, rustics) and men who served
            in the army would forsake their riches and their
            occupations and would go and enrol themselves in the
            order of the monks. Now he was unto <placeName>Egypt</placeName> like a
            good physician who had been given unto the people
            thereof from God. For who ever came unto him being
            afflicted that did not go away rejoicing? Or who ever
            came unto him in sorrow because of the sufferings
            which had come upon him that did not come back
            wholly encouraged? And who ever came unto him
            full of rage and wrath that was not enriched with
            graciousness and longsuffering? And what poor man
            ever came unto him broken by poverty who did not
            [afterwards] by reason of his words and the sight of
            him despise all riches? And what monk ever came to
            him sorrowful in mind who did not depart full of
            strength like a mighty man of war? And what young
            man ever came unto him with lusts burning in him,
            and saw that the old man had conquered in the strife,
            who did not go away with his lusts quenched and dead
            within him? And what youth who was afraid of the
            war which had come upon him ever came unto him,
            and seeing his triumphant old age did not [henceforward] 
            contend <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#86"/>in the forefront of the
            battle?</quote> And what man ever came unto him troubled
            <pb n="102"/>in mind who did not go away with it composed and
            in a state of reason?
         </p>
         <p>
            And there was found in him the gracious gift of
            being able to distinguish and understand the wiliness
            of the devils, and the various ways whereby each one
            of them caused injury [to man]; and he comprehended
            not only those things which were wrought by the
            Evil One, but also the various causes whereby men
            were troubled and perturbed, and he could inform them
            concerning the craft and cunning of the deceitful one.
            And every man hearkened unto these things and learned 
            them, and he went away bearing armour and a
            shield against the profound wiles of the Evil One.
            And moreover, how many were the virgins who saw
            the blessed man afar off and left the men to whom
            they were betrothed, and betrothed themselves to <persName>Christ</persName>!
            And many people used to come to him from outside
            <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and unto all the questions he would return
            suitable answers; and he was so great, and was so
            much beloved by every man, that after he had departed
            from this world, and had left all men orphans, the
            memory of him never died among the people, and
            every man gave himself courage by the repetition of
            his triumphs and of his words.
         </p>
         <p>
            CONCERNING HIS DEATH. It is meet that we should
            call to remembrance his death, and should relate how
            it took place, and in what manner he finished his life,
            for I know that ye will be exceedingly pleased therewith; 
            now he was accustomed to go out and visit
            the memorial stones of the brethren in the outer mountain. 
            Now the matter of his death also was not hidden
            from him, and he went forth [to visit them] even when
            he knew that his departure was nigh. And after he had
            spoken to the brethren according to his wont, he said unto
            them, <quote>This act which ye have just performed is the end
            of all acts; and I marvel at this world. Let each look
            [for himself] alone; for it is the time for me to die.</quote>
            Now he was then about one hundred and five years old.
         </p>
         <pb n="103"/>
         <p>
            And when the brethren heard [these things] they
            wept bitter tears, and each of them began to embrace
            and to kiss him<anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#87"/>, and the old man, like unto
            a man from a strange country who is about to depart
            thereto, with great gladness besought them to be quiet,
            and exhorted them, saying, <quote>Be not ye in despair by
            reason of your tribulations, and be not lax in your
            lives and works, but even as men who are dying
            daily prepare ye for life, and as I have already said,
            be watchful ever. Keep ye your souls from thoughts
            of iniquity, and strive ye for good gifts, and guard
            ye yourselves against associating yourselves with the
            <persName>Meletinians</persName>, who are heretics, for ye know the cause
            of their schisms, and how cunning and bitter they
            are. And flee ye with all your might also from the
            doctrine of the Arians, for their wickedness is clearly
            manifest, and take good heed to avoid them, and be
            not like unto them for ever, neither if they be mighty
            in their help, nor if they be many in bearing burdens,
            for however often error raiseth up her nest(?) it shall
            never be able to contend against the truth. Be ye
            therefore free from all intercourse with them, and thus
            shall ye be able to take good heed to the true doctrine 
            of our fathers, and to the preaching of the truth
            of our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, which ye have received
            from the Scriptures.</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Now when the brethren heard concerning the matter
            of his departure, they entreated him that he would
            remain with them in order that his course might be
            ended there, but he would not accede to their request
            for many reasons which he had made known in his
            silence, but for the following reason especially. The
            <persName>Egyptians</persName> were in the habit of taking the dead bodies
            of righteous men, and especially those of the blessed
            martyrs, and of embalming them and placing them not
            in graves, but on biers in their houses, for they thought
            that by so doing they were doing them honour. And
            the blessed old man had on very many occasions be<pb n="104"/>sought 
            the Bishops to preach to the people and to
            command <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#88"/>them to cease from this habit.
            And he himself used to entreat and exhort the multitudes 
            who came to him, saying, "This work is neither
            seemly nor right. Moreover, the burial places of the
            early Fathers, and of the Prophets, and of the <persName>Apostles</persName>
            are known unto this day, and even the grave of our
            Lord Who rose on the third day." And by these
            words he shewed forth that it was a transgression of
            a command for a man not to hide [in the ground] the
            bodies of those who were dead, even though they were
            righteous men. Therefore many hearkened and were
            persuaded not to do so, and they laid their dead in
            the ground, and buried them therein, and they thanked
            God because they had accepted [his] entreaty, which
            was seemly. And it was through fear of this thing
            that he would not grant the entreaty of the brethren
            and remain with them, but departed to his own
            place.
         </p>
         <p>
            And after a few months he became sick, and he
            cried out to the brethren who were with him (now
            these were only two in number, and they had been
            with him from the time when his old age [began],
            which was nearly fifteen years before, and they had
            ministered unto him with the greatest care), and said
            unto them, even as it is written, "Behold, I go the
            way of my fathers, for I have felt within myself for
            some days [past] that I have been called by my Lord.
            Observe ye now how carefully ye can maintain this
            contest, and take good heed that ye lose not the
            longsuffering which ye have acquired, and that, like
            men who are just beginning [the strife], ye increase
            it more and more and add to it day by day. Ye are
            well acquainted with the baneful devils and their
            craftiness, and ye know well this fact that if ye please
            they shall be accounted as nothing by you. Be ye
            therefore not terrified by them, but always take refuge
            in <persName>Christ</persName>. And remember ye everything which ye
            <pb n="105"/>have heard from me during all this time [which ye
            have been with me], that ye have no intercourse
            whatsoever with the Arians, the heretics, for ye know
            how filthy they are in my sight because of their
            blasphemy <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#89"/>of our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>. Take
            ye also heed then diligently at all times that ye cleave
            to the Spirit of <persName>Christ</persName> and agree therewith, and be
            ye, moreover, friends and associates of just men that
            they may receive you into their everlasting habitations
            as friends and men of whom they have good knowledge. 
            Therefore meditate ye upon these things and
            keep them in your minds. And if your minds are
            [set] upon me, and ye remember me as a father, permit 
            no man to take my body and carry it into <placeName>Egypt</placeName>,
            lest, according to the custom which they have, they
            embalm me and lay me up in their houses, for it was
            [to avoid] this that I came into this desert. And ye
            know that I have continually made exhortation concerning 
            this thing and begged that it should not be
            done, and ye well know how much I have blamed
            those who observed this custom. Dig a grave then,
            and bury me therein, and hide my body under the
            earth, and let these my words be observed carefully
            by you, and tell ye no man where ye lay me; [and
            there I shall be] until the Resurrection of the dead,
            when I shall receive [again] this body without corruption.
         </p>
         <p>
            And divide ye my garments [into lots], and give
            one leather tunic to Bishop <persName>Athanasius</persName>, and the covering 
            of this my bed which he gave unto me when it
            was new; but now it hath become old. And to Bishop
            <persName>Serapion</persName> do ye give the other leather coat, and this
            covering of my bed which is made of hair ye yourselves 
            shall keep; now therefore, my children, abide in
            peace, for, behold, <persName>Anthony</persName> bringeth his journey to an
            end, and he goeth whither Divine Grace shall bring
            him."
         </p>
         <p>
            And when he had spoken these words, he straight<pb n="106"/>away 
            stretched out his legs, whereupon the brethren
            began to cry out [to him], and to kiss him; now his
            face was full of joy unspeakable at the meeting of those
            who had come for him, and it resembled that of a
            man when he seeth a friend whom it rejoiceth him to
            meet. So the blessed man held his peace and died,
            and was gathered to his fathers. <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#90"/>Then the
            brethren, according to the command which they had
            received from him, wrapped him round in the garment
            which he wore, and they carried him out, and dug a
            hole in the ground and buried his body in the earth,
            and no man knoweth where they buried him except
            those two brethren who laid him in the earth. Now
            whosoever received any one of the clothes of the
            blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> regarded it as most valuable
            possession, for whensoever a man looked thereat he
            imagined that he was looking at the blessed man<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n106-1"/> in
            it, and whensoever any man put on one of his garments
            he felt as if he were arrayed in the commandments
            and promises of the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>.
         </p>
         <p>
            Here end the history of the life of the blessed
            old man in the body, and the previous narrative thereto
            which [dealt with] the beginning of his deeds and
            labours; and if these appear to be too small in comparison 
            to [the number of] the triumphs of the blessed
            man, still from these ye will be able to imagine how
            great was this man of God, who, from his earliest
            youth to his old age, never desisted from his career in
            the fear of God. Old age did not reduce his vigour
            and compel him to gratify the body, and he was not
            urged by the sickness of his body even to touch water
            with his feet; and whilst he was thus keeping his body
            in restraint God preserved him unharmed. For, in spite
            of his great old age his eye waxed not dim, and not
            one of his teeth dropped out, and both his feet and
            his hands were in a sound and healthy state; and not<pb n="107"/>withstanding
            that he kept his body low [in respect of
            food], his appearance was more glorious than that of
            all those who fed themselves luxuriously on dainty
            meats, and who wore fine clothes, and who made use
            of baths. And moreover he possessed strength which
            was out of all proportion to his aged body.
         </p>
         <p>
            Now inasmuch as the fame of the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>
            hath gone into every place, and every man holdeth
            him in wonder, <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#91"/>and worshippeth him, it is
            a sure and certain sign of the truth of his acts and
            deeds and of his perfect love towards God. For he
            did not become known unto all the world by means
            of [his] discourse, or by the wisdom of words, or by
            means of crafty plans and schemes, but by radiant
            righteousness towards God, for it was God Who performed 
            this work, and he who hath a doubtful mind
            about this shall be held in contempt. Otherwise how
            is it possible that a man who lived in seclusion and
            who dwelt alone in the desert should become known
            and proclaimed abroad in Spain,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n107-1"/> and in Âlânîâ, and
            in Rome, and in Africa and other countries unless
            God, Whom <persName>Anthony</persName> confessed from the earliest
            times, had revealed him [to them]? For although these
            men of God live in secret places and do not desire
            to be seen and known, yet our Lord [maketh them]
            to shine like lamps upon all men. Thus also let those
            who hear [me], and who are mighty men before God,
            and who love His commandments, be persuaded to
            keep (their) steps, not that they may be praised but
            that they may be justified. Let all the brethren
            then who are monks read these things so that they
            may know how it is meet for them to live their lives,
            and let this little book be unto every man like the
            testament of a righteous father who had divided his
            <pb n="108"/>riches and possessions among his beloved sons in our
            Lord; for when we gather together and reveal unto
            the believers those means whereby he gained possession
            of and collected all this wealth, we deliver up riches
            and give them unto prosperous and beloved sons, even
            as doth the man who gathereth up wealth [for his
            family].
         </p>
         <p>
            Let every man know then and have confidence
            that our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> our Redeemer honoureth
            those who honour Him, and who serve Him unto the
            end, and that He doth not only invite them to the
            kingdom of heaven <anchor type="sourceText" corresp="#92"/>and lead them into it,
            but in this world also, even though they live in seclusion
            and hide themselves, He revealeth them, and proclaimeth
            abroad [their names] for their own glory, and for the
            benefit of our humanity. And if it be seemly, do not
            excuse yourselves from reading these things even in
            the sight of (or, before) the heathen, for peradventure
            even by hearing the same they may become convinced
            that our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> is not only God and the
            Son of God, but also that for those who serve Him
            in purity of heart, and who believe in Him in truth,
            those devils who are imagined to be gods take to
            flight at the name of <persName>Christ</persName>. Now that they are not
            gods the matter itself maketh known, for behold, they
            are held in contempt, and they are trodden down like
            the furrows of a field, and they are expelled as thieves
            and destroyers by the believers everywhere. 
         </p>
         <p>
            Here endeth, by the help of our Lord, the history 
            of the triumphs of the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>,
            the athlete, and perfect man, who triumphed in 
            the contest and received the crown of victory.
            By his propserous trafficking he made double his
            merchandize through our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, who
            helped him and made him to triumph, the Lord [of
            righteous men], and the conqueror.
         </p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n4-1">Literally, "by the bringer of a letter".</note>
            <note xml:id="n4-2">Literally, "what was his order before this".</note>
            <note xml:id="n5-1">Literally, "by measure".</note>
            <note xml:id="n5-2">I. e., overwhelmed and flooded his mind.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7-1">Genesis XXV. 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7-2">Or, "the amusement of youth".</note>
            <note xml:id="n8-1">St. Matthew XIX. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8-2">See St. Matthew VI. 25, 31, 34; St. Mark XII. II; St. Luke XII. II, 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9-1">I. e., he wished to emulate his beautiful works.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-1">I. e., the old man mentioned above.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-2">Read mor.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-3">2 Thessalonians III. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-4">1 Thessalonians V. 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11-1">St. Luke II. 52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11-2">The text is defective here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-1">I. e., make progress.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-2">Reading</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-1">Read</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-2">Isaiah LXV. 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-1">Hosea IV. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-1">Read</note>
            <note xml:id="n17-1">2 Corinthians XII. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17-2">Philippians III. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17-3">i Kings XVII. I.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18-1">The "Watchers" were one of the nine orders of angels.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18-2">I. e., in the cemetery which belonged to the village.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18-3">Read sed iam? "now and then".</note>
            <note xml:id="n18-4">Literally "where".</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-1">Literally, "without tempests."</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-1">Or, plate.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23-1">The text is probably corrupt here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-1">The text has besoins "basilisk"; read islam (?)</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-1">Read</note>
            <note xml:id="n26-1">Psalm LXVIII. I, 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n26-2">Psalm CXVIII. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n27-1">I. e., if we possess Christ it is unnecessary to possess anything else, and compared with His love nothing is of value.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-1">I Corinthians XV. 31.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29-1">Genesis XIX. 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29-2">St. Luke XVII. 21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29-3">Joshua XXIV. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29-4">St. Luke III. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-1">Or, to withdraw ourselves.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-2">I. e., usurers and pledges.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-3">I. e., been actually committed.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30-4">Proverbs IV. 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31-1">Ephesians VI. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n32-1">Compare Psalm LVII. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33-1">Reading</note>
            <note xml:id="n34-1">I. e., the belief that we love desolation (or, destruction) is so firmly implanted in men's minds that it has become a fundamental conception in them.</note>
            <note xml:id="n34-2">Read</note>
            <note xml:id="n35-1">The text reads zob? Jás, but is probably corrupt.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35-2">I. e., like freebooters and not like soldiers who have been trained in a regular army.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39-1">The text is corrupt here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41-1">This appears to be the meaning of the sentence.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43-1">St. Luke IV. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n44-1">St. Luke X. 20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n45-1">Or, "testimony to a beautiful life, and character, and works."</note>
            <note xml:id="n45-2">St. Luke XIII. 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n45-3">Compare i Timothy, chap. IV.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-1">Or, "the overflow of the Nile."</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-2">Psalm XX. 7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-1">Read abaso.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-1">St. Luke X. 18.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-2">Compare i Corinthians III. 6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-3">Literally, "And having multiplied and held my head."</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-1">I. e., find an opportunity when we are not on guard.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-2">Read</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-1">Numbers XXIV. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n54-2">Romans XII. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-1">St. Matthew VI. 31 ff.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55-2">The persecution began A.D. 235: see Eusebius, Hist. Eccles. VI. 28; Rufinus, Hist., VI. 19.</note>
            <note xml:id="n56-1">Read </note>
            <note xml:id="n56-2">Read ܐܸܬܼܓܲܝܲܒ </note>
            <note xml:id="n56-3">Probably the mines to the west of Aswân, and those of the Wâdi ‘Alâki, which lie about 80 miles east of Dakkeh in Nubia.</note>
            <note xml:id="n58-1">I. e., Martinianus. See Rosweyde, as Vitae Patrum, p. 48.</note>
            <note xml:id="n58-2">St. Matthew VII. 7; St. Luke XI. 9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-1">Or, "in the open spaces", (i. e., squares, of his city).</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-2">Literally, "and they stood upon the place."</note>
            <note xml:id="n61-1">Literally, "and had entered into many days."</note>
            <note xml:id="n64-1">"Ut camelus errans per eremum, dum funiculum trahit, in quodam lapide eiusdem alligatione funiculi teneretur." Rosweyde, Vitae Patrum, p. 49.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-1">The text is faulty here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-1">St. Matthew V. 23, 24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-2">Ephesians IV. 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-3">2 Corinthians XIII. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n67-1">Compare i Timothy VI. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n69-1">Fronto autem quidam, vir ex Palaestinis; Rosweyde, Vitae Patrum, p. 50. col. 2 (Cap. XXIX). </note>
            <note xml:id="n69-2">I. e., Busiris, bjos= Pa-Asar । ਪਹੈ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n72-1">Flumen nomine Lycum subitis aquis inundatum transvadere; see Rosweyde, Vitae Patrum, p. 51, col. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n74-1">=Count; Rosweyde (p. 51) has "Archelaus quoque Comes."</note>
            <note xml:id="n75-1">Percontatus diem sanitatis, reperit tempus medelae cum annotatione congruere. Rosweyde, p. 51, col. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-1">Asserebant cuncti, piscium salvorum et tarichorum in navi positorum hunc esse putorem. Rosweyde, p. 52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-1">Read A.</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-2">I. e., came to himself.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-1">Ephesians VI. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-2">Ephesians VI. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-3">2 Corinthians XII. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-4">St. John VI. 45; Isaiah LIV. 13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n79-1">Read</note>
            <note xml:id="n81-1">Proverbs XVII. 22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n81-2">Genesis XXXI. 5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n81-3">I Samuel XVI. 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n82-1">I. e., the followers of Meletius, Bishop of Lycopolis; he was deposed for his irregular behaviour A. D. 306.</note>
            <note xml:id="n83-1">Literally, "a creation."</note>
            <note xml:id="n84-1">The "Armâyê" are usually Syrians, but here the Armâyê appear to be the mixed multitudes of the city of Alexandria and its suburbs who were not Christians.</note>
            <note xml:id="n84-2">I. e., heathen priests.</note>
            <note xml:id="n90-1">A portion of the text is wanting here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-1">Daniel viii. 26(?).</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-2">Bishop of Thmuis, the site of which city is marked by the Arab village Tamai al-Amdid; he was surnamed 'Scholasticus', and died about A.D. 360.</note>
            <note xml:id="n96-1">I. e., about A.D. 343.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-1">St. Matthew XVII. 20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-1">St. Matthew X. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-1">St. Matthew VII. 2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-2">Praeterea cum Balacius, qui sub Nestorio prefecto Alexandriae dux Aegypti fuit; Rosweyde, Vitae Patrum, p. 58, col. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-1">Ad primam mansionem Alexandriae, quae appelatur Chaereum. Rosweyde, Vitae Patrum, p. 58, col. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n106-1">Read</note>
            <note xml:id="n107-1">Africae, Hispaniae, Galliae, Italiae, Illyrico, ipsi etiam, quae urbium caput est, Romae, ut in exordio promiserat, demonstravit. Rosweyde, Vitae Patrum, p. 60, col. 2.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
