<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Mar <persName>Paulus</persName></title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_2">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_2 </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 2: The History of Mar <persName>Paulus (Paule)</persName> the Prince of Monks and Anchorite</head>
         <p>Concerning Abbâ <persName>Paulus</persName> there were questions among the monks and anchorites who were
            living in the land of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and they asked who were the first monks who lived in the
            desert. And some of them remembered the saints of olden time, and said, <quote>It hath been
            proved that the first to dwell in the desert were Saint <persName>Elijah</persName> the Prophet, and <persName>John</persName> the
            Baptist, and it is manifest that <persName>Elijah</persName> was immeasurably superior in ascetic excellence
            to the [other] monks, and, moreover, <persName>John</persName> was proclaimed in the womb to be a prophet
            before he was born.</quote> Now there were many who contradicted this opinion and who asserted
            with firmness that Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> was the first and the prince of them all, and also of the
            order [of monks]; but if we wish to learn the whole truth we shall discover that it was
            not Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> who was the first [monk] that dwelt in the desert, but the blessed man
            Mâr <persName>Paulus</persName>. For I myself have seen the disciples of Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> who buried him, and they
            it was who related unto us the history of the man <persName>Paulus</persName> the anchorite, the Theban, who
            was indeed the first [monk to live] in the desert; therefore we believe that it was not
            the blessed man [<persName>Anthony</persName>] who was the first to do this, as some men say, but <persName>Paulus</persName>, and
            for this reason I wish to narrate briefly the history of <persName>Paulus</persName> the anchorite, and how
            he began and how he ended his [career] in the days of Decius and Valerianus the
            persecutors, and [how] Cornelius made an end of the strife of his testimony for the sake
            of the Name of our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> in <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
         <p>Now this blessed man <persName>Paulus</persName> dwelt with his sister, who was the wife of a certain man;
            and their parents died and left <pb n="197"/>them great riches when the blessed man <persName>Paulus</persName> was
            sixteen years of age. And he had been educated in the learning of the Greeks and the
            <persName>Egyptians</persName>, and he was meek of soul, and he loved God thoroughly. And when the
            persecution of the Christians waxed strong, he remained continually in one place, and he
            took care of himself at all seasons (or continually). Now the avarice which constraineth
            the race of the children of men to commit evil deeds did not cease from him, for his
            sister’s husband, instead of hiding him, endeavoured most strenuously to give him up [to
            the persecutors], and he neither had pity upon the tears of his wife nor did he fear the
            judgement of God; and he desisted not from this iniquitous conduct, but continued in his
            envy and sought always to give him up because he was a Christian. And the wise young
            man, having comprehended his guile and knowing that he was lying in wait for him, took
            to flight secretly, and he went to a certain high mountain which he found to be not what
            he desired, and he changed his place [of abode] on account of the violence (or
            necessity) of the persecution; but as he was living there, little by little he found out
            in the mountain a rock, wherein was a large cave, which was shut in with a stone, and
            having lifted up the stone he found within great repose, and he looked inside with great
            desire. And he discovered that the cave was clean, and that the dust of the ground also
            was fair, and he loved the place and dwelt there, and he gave thanks unto God Who had
            given it unto him for a dwelling-place; and he lived in that mountain all the days of
            his life, and his food and his raiment were made of the palm trees which were in the
            mountain. Now in order that no man may say, <quote>How is this possible?</quote> I take God and His
            holy angels to witness that we have seen many monks [living] in this fashion, and that
            they have brought their lives to an end in this way, and have not been afraid of
            <persName>Satan</persName>.</p>
         <p>I must not, however, neglect the history of the blessed man <persName>Paulus</persName>. This holy man lived
            a heavenly life upon the earth in love to our Lord for one hundred and thirteen years;
            and Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName>, who was ninety years old at the time, was living in another desert. And
            Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> on one occasion told me the following: <quote>I once thought within myself that
            there was no man living beyond me in the desert, and on the night wherein I pondered
            upon these things in my mind, it was revealed unto me from God [by one] who said unto
            me, <quote>Beyond thee [in the desert] there is a man who is more excellent than thou art, and
            it is meet that thou shouldst [go and] see him with all diligence, and with great joy.</quote>
            </quote> And when the morning had come, the blessed old man Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> took the palm branch
            whereon he leaned his weight, and he began <pb n="198"/>to walk in the desert as his mind directed,
            because he did not know the way; and when it was noon, although the heat of the sun was
            fierce and burning, the blessed old man did not turn aside from the way, but he said, <quote>I
            believe that God will not withdraw [His] hands from me, but will shew me His servant
            concerning whom He hath sent me a revelation.</quote></p>
         <p>And as he was thinking thus about him he suddenly saw a man who possessed two natures,
            one half of him being that of a man, and the other half being that of a horse; now the
            poets call this being a <quote>centaur.</quote> Then the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> called unto him and said,
            <quote>I, a man of God, say unto thee, <quote>Where dost thou dwell here?</quote> </quote> And the creature
            returned him an answer in a barbarous language with words of impurity, and his mouth was
            full of fear; so the old man went on his journey seeking out the way. And as <persName>Anthony</persName> was
            marvelling [at this thing] the animal passed in front of him as if [it were going] to a
            broad field, and [<persName>Anthony</persName> knew that] it was <persName>Satan</persName> who had taken the form of the creature
            in order that he might terrify the blessed man, and he wondered at the similitude of the
            form which he had seen in the animal. And having passed on a little way further he saw
            another animal, which was smaller in stature than the first one, and he was standing on
            a rock, and he had horns upon his head and on his forehead; and when the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>
            saw him he put on the helmet of faith and [took the] shield of righteousness, and he
            asked him, <quote>Who art thou whom I see here?</quote> And the creature answered and said unto him,
            <quote>I am a mortal man and one of these who are in the desert, whom the heathen call
            <quote>satyrs,</quote> and whom because of their error concerning them they worship as a god</quote>; and
            the beast having spoken these words the old man <persName>Anthony</persName> went on his way, and his tears
            were flowing and they ran down upon the ground, but he rejoiced because of the glory of
            <persName>Christ</persName>, and because of the destruction of <persName>Satan</persName>, and he wondered within himself how he
            had been able to understand the words of the animal. Then he smote the ground with his
            staff and said, <quote>Woe be to <persName>Alexandria</persName>! Woe be to the city of the heathen, wherein are
            gathered together all the devils of all creation!</quote></p>
         <p>And <persName>Anthony</persName> went on his journey thinking anxiously [how] he could attain to the end
            thereof, and he wished to find the servant of God; and whilst he was meditating what he
            should do and where he should go, he observed on the flat surface of the desert the
            footprints of an animal which had passed over the spot that very day. Then he meditated
            within himself, saying, <quote>It is impossible for our Lord to forsake me</quote>; and he journeyed
            on his way during the night with his prayers in his <pb n="199"/>mouth continually. And when the
            morning had come he saw a huge hyena, running with all its might up to the top of a
            mountain, and he followed in its footsteps, and having ascended the mountain he came
            nigh unto a cave, and saw the hyena going into it; and he looked into the cave and saw
            perfect love, that is to say, Mâr <persName>Paule</persName>, the old man. Then he cast away from him all
            fear and doubtful thoughts, and looking into the cave he saw that there was much light
            therein, and he approached the door of the cave, and knocked thereat with a small stone,
            but as soon as the blessed man <persName>Paule</persName> heard the sound of the knocking he rolled the stone
            [down] quickly and closed the entrance of the cave. Then <persName>Anthony</persName> fell upon his face
            before the door of the cave and besought him to let him come in, and said, <quote>I am alone</quote>;
            [and the blessed man <persName>Paule</persName> answered and said, <quote>Why hast thou come?</quote>] And <persName>Anthony</persName> said,
            <quote>I know that I am not worthy to see thee, but since thou receivest wild beasts why dost
            thou hold the children of men in abhorrence? I have sought and have found [thee], and I
            knocked with confidence; open thou then the door unto me. And if this may not be I shall
            die here, and when thou seest my dead body do thou bury it.</quote> And when with these words
            <persName>Anthony</persName> had taken up his position there the blessed man <persName>Paule</persName> answered from within and
            said unto him, <quote>No man who is angry cometh [in here], and no man entreateth [for
            admission] and maketh accusations</quote>; then he spake unto him words of gladness, and he
            opened unto him the door, and they met and embraced each other and kissed each other
            with holy kisses, and each man told his fellow his name.</p>
         <p>Then after these things the blessed man <persName>Paule</persName> made Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> sit by his side, and he
            said unto him, <quote>Why didst thou cast upon thyself all this tribulation, and the great
            labour of seeking to see an old man whose body is altogether withered and emaciated?
            After a short time thou wilt see that I have become dust; but love overcometh all
            things. Tell me now what is the present condition of the race of the children of men,
            and whether they are still building houses in the ancient cities, and whether there are
            still kings in the world, and whether the governors of the world are still in subjection
            to the error of devils.</quote> And having said these things unto <persName>Anthony</persName> the two of them
            looked and they saw a raven sitting on the branch of a tree, and straightway it stood up
            with great quietness upon the branch, and it had in its beak a whole loaf of bread which
            it came and laid down between them, whilst both men were looking on; and when the bird
            had departed they both marvelled. And the blessed <persName>Paule</persName> said unto Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName>, <quote>Truly
            our Lord is merciful <pb n="200"/>and pitiful in that He sendeth us a meal [in this way]. For behold,
            for fully sixty years I have been in the habit of receiving from this bird half a loaf
            of bread [daily], but at thy coming, behold, our Lord hath sent unto us a double portion
            of food because we are His servants.</quote> Then having given thanks unto God, both men sat
            down at the table, and they disputed with each other who should first break the bread,
            and whilst they were thus disputing the night came on; thereupon the two men took the
            bread and spread out their hands, and brake the loaf in the Name of our Lord, and ate
            it, and having eaten they stood up the whole night in prayer.</p>
         <p>Now when the morning had come <persName>Paule</persName> said unto <persName>Anthony</persName>, <quote>Thou must know, O my brother
            <persName>Anthony</persName>, that I have been living in the desert for a long time past, and that it was our
            Lord Himself who revealed unto me what manner of man thou art; but, because the time of
            my rest hath come, and because that which I have been seeking, that is to say, that I
            should depart and be with our Lord, is about to overtake me [I could not go to see
            thee]. And now that my time hath come to an end, and, as I believe, a crown of
            righteousness hath been laid up for me, thou hast been sent by our Lord that thou mayest
            bury my body in the ground.</quote> Now whilst the blessed man <persName>Paule</persName> was saying these things
            Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> was weeping with many tears and heaving sighs, and he made supplication unto
            him, and said, <quote>O my beloved one, leave thou me not here, but take me with thee whither
            thou goest.</quote> And the blessed <persName>Paule</persName> answered and said unto him, <quote>It is not meet that thou
            shouldst seek thine own [advantage], but that of thy neighbours, and therefore, O my
            beloved, I beseech thee, if it be not a thing which is too hard for thee, to go quickly
            to thy monastery, and to bring hither to me the cloak which Mâr <persName>Athanasius</persName> the Bishop
            gave thee.</quote> Now he did not speak thus because he had need of any apparel, but because he
            wished to depart from his body whilst Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> was absent.</p>
         <p>And when <persName>Anthony</persName> heard concerning the Bishop and concerning his cloak, he marvelled
            within himself, and having looked upon the blessed <persName>Paule</persName> in our Lord <persName>Jesus</persName>, and bowed
            down before him, he prayed and set forth to go on his journey, and he approached and
            kissed him on his eyes and on his hands, and he made haste and went forth to depart to
            his monastery. And having made the journey and arrived at this monastery, his two
            disciples, who had been seeking him for a long time, met him, and they said unto him, <quote>O
            father, where hast thou been these days?</quote> And he answered and said unto them, <quote>Woe be
            unto me! woe be unto me a <pb n="201"/>sinner! For the name of <quote>Christian</quote> which I bear is only a
            borrowed thing. This day have I seen <persName>Elijah</persName> and <persName>John</persName> in the desert, for verily I have
            seen <persName>Paule</persName> in Paradise, and he was holding converse with them</quote>; and Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> smote
            with his hand upon his breast, and he took the cloak and went from his disciples, who
            besought him to reveal unto them the whole matter. And he said unto them, <quote>There is a
            time to be silent, and a time to speak</quote>; so he departed and went forth on his way
            without taking any provision whatsoever with him. And he made haste to come to the place
            where the blessed man <persName>Paule</persName> was, for he desired earnestly to see him [again], and he was
            afraid lest whilst he was yet afar off <persName>Paule</persName> might deliver himself up unto our Lord. And
            he journeyed on his way the first day, but on the second day, at the time of the ninth
            hour, he saw along the road, in the air, a company of angels, and a multitude of the
            Prophets and of <persName>the Apostles</persName>, and Abbâ <persName>Paule</persName>, who was shining with light like the sun,
            was in their midst, and he went up with them into heaven. And immediately he saw them he
            fell upon his face on the ground, and he sighed and wept, and cried out, and said, <quote>O
            fearer of God, why hast thou left me thus? And why didst thou not receive my salutation
            together with all [the toil of] this journey which I have made as swiftly as a
            bird?</quote></p>
         <p>And Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> went on his way and arrived at the cave, and he saw Abbâ <persName>Paule</persName> kneeling
            upon his knees, with his face gazing into heaven and his hands spread out; and seeing
            him thus Mâr <persName>Anthony</persName> thought within himself, and said, <quote>Perhaps he is alive</quote>; and he
            prayed fervently, and the blessed <persName>Paule</persName> also stood up and prayed with him. And when some
            time had elapsed, and he heard neither the sound[s] nor the sighs which are customary in
            prayer, he knew that it was only the body of Abbâ <persName>Paule</persName> which prayed; and he bowed down
            before God, in Whom everything liveth, and he placed the body in the middle of the
            cloak, and wrapped it in it, and he took it upon his shoulders; and though he sang
            Psalms, according to the custom of the monks, the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName> was greatly grieved
            because he had not remembered to bring with him a spade or some other instrument
            wherewith to dig a grave for the body. Then he meditated within himself and said, <quote>What
            shall I do? If I go to my monastery and bring a spade I cannot possibly return here in
            less than four days</quote>; and he said, <quote>O <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, let me also die with Thy beloved
            servant <persName>Paule</persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>Now as he was saying these things, behold, two lions came running along together, and
            when he saw them his whole body smoked with fear; and when he had lifted up his mind to
            God and had looked at them again, they appeared to be doves fly<pb n="202"/>ing through the air. And
            the lions drew nigh and stood near the body of the blessed <persName>Paule</persName>, and they wagged their
            tails at the blessed <persName>Anthony</persName>, and they crouched down before him in perfect tameness, and
            they rubbed their teeth together and purred so loudly that the blessed man knew that
            they wished to be blessed, and to be helped, and that they desired [to know] concerning
            the departure of the blessed <persName>Paule</persName>. And after they had acted thus, the lions began to
            dig [a grave], and they threw up the earth with their paws, and they made the hole in
            the ground deep enough, and wide enough, and long enough, according to the measure of
            the body; and they lowered their ears and their tails, and bowed down their heads before
            Abbâ <persName>Anthony</persName>, and they licked his hands and his feet, and he knew that they wished to be
            blessed. Then he gave thanks for the glory of God because that even the wild and savage
            beasts knew how to [help] the good and chosen men of God, and he spake thus:—<quote>O Lord
            God, without Whose command not one leaf falleth to the ground, and against Whose Will
            not one bird droppeth into the snare, do Thou bless all of us.</quote> And he brought his hand
            nigh unto the lions, and commanded them to depart; and when the two lions had gone away
            <persName>Anthony</persName> took the body and buried it in the customary way. Then, after one day, he took
            the tunic of Abbâ <persName>Paule</persName>, which was made of palm leaves sewn together, like a true
            inheritance and a thing which brought privilege, and departed to his monastery. And when
            he had arrived there he related unto the monks the whole matter in due order; and on the
            feast of unleavened bread and at Pentecost Saint <persName>Anthony</persName> used to put on the tunic of the
            blessed and holy man <persName>Paule</persName>, and he would pray with it upon him.</p>
         <p>And I, <persName>Hieronymus</persName> the sinner, entreat all those who read this book to pray for me. [In
            the text here comes the following note by some editor of <persName>Palladius</persName>:]</p>
         <p>Concerning these histories of <persName>Paule</persName>, and of the company of Mark (?), and of <persName>Macarius</persName>,
            there are some who say that they were compiled by <persName>Hieronymus</persName> because his name occurs at
            the end of them.</p>
         <p>Here endeth the History of Mar <persName>Paule</persName>, the holy Man, the Firstborn of all the Desert
            Monks</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
