<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Alexandrian</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_3">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_3 </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 3: The Triumph of a young Man who was an Alexandrian</head>
         <p>There was a certain young man in Alexandria, who, immediately the law of nature began to
            work in him, and to make him to possess the knowledge which distinguisheth good from
            evil, endeavoured by every means in his power to make himself wholly a stranger unto
            things which are evil, and to cleave unto those which are good. And having been trained
            for a long time, and having made himself proficient in the things which befit monks,
            even though he still lived and went about in the city, he at a certain time thought
            within himself, and said, <quote>Since there is no good reason whatsoever which compelleth me
            forcibly to remain in the city any longer it is not right that I should do so,</quote> and he
            was at all times reminding himself of the word which was spoken by our Lord to the rich
            man, <quote>If thou wishest to be perfect, go and sell all that thou hast and give [it] to the
            poor, and take thy cross and come after Me</quote> (St. Matthew 19:21). And the young man said,
            <quote>The word of our Lord is true, but it is impossible for a man to acquire that perfection
            of which He spake whilst he is living among men.</quote></p>
         <p>When then he had made himself ready to perform in very deed this great thought, he began
            to journey along the road which leadeth to one of the deserts of Alexandria, where large
            numbers of monks used to dwell, and he offered up prayer unto God that He would prepare
            a way for him, and would direct him unto a man who would be able to help him [to attain]
            his object, and would lead him to the end which he desired. And he decided within
            himself, and said, <quote>This shall be unto me a sign that the Lord hath prepared His way
            before me:—The door whereat I shall knock, and wherefrom shall go forth one who liveth
            there, and shall receive me in peace, and shall urge me to go in to him, and shall
            receive me in the love which monks have for strangers, that shall be the place, and that
            shall be the man whom the Lord hath prepared for the fulfilment of my thoughts
            concerning spiritual excellence.</quote> And he said, <quote>Unto the man who hath been prepared by
            the Lord it is meet for me to be in subjection as unto Christ, and I must hearken unto
            his command willingly and unhesitatingly as unto that of Christ.</quote> Now as he was praying
            with these words, and with others which were like unto them, and was thinking deeply, he
            arrived in the desert into which he had set his face to go. And having gone in among the
            monasteries, he found himself by the dispensation of God before the door of a habitation
            wherein a certain old man dwelt; and when, according to his expectation, he had drawn
            nigh, and had knocked at the door which was in front of him, there came forth therefrom
            straightway the old man who dwelt inside, and opened the door to him; and when he saw
            the young man who was standing there he saluted him gladly, when as yet he had asked him
            nothing whatsoever, and entreated him urgently to come inside. And this actually took
            place.</p>
         <p>Now after he had gone in and had, according to custom, prayed, and sat down, the young
            man compared the things which had taken place with those which he had written down in
            his mind, and he waited for a right issue to all [the rest]. Then, being full of
            gladness, the old man urged him repeatedly to partake of food, but the young man
            answered and said unto him, <quote>My lord, I beseech thy holiness to permit me first of all
            to speak openly, and to make known to thy fatherly nature the reason of my coming, and
            if through the working of God thou wilt make thyself the perfecter of my desire, and of
            my thoughts, whatsoever thy holiness and thy meekness shall command me [to do] I will
            perform strenuously.</quote> Now when the old man had heard these things, he answered and said
            unto him, <quote>Thou hast full power to say everything which thou wishest, joyfully and
            fearlessly, as unto thy father who, according to his power, in great love, is ready to
            fulfil thy desire by the help of God.</quote> Then, after these words, which the old man spake
            in simplicity (now none of the thoughts of the young man had entered into his mind), the
            young man made clearly manifest before the old man the matters which he had marked out
            and decided upon in his mind from the beginning of his actions in the city even until
            that very hour.</p>
         <p>And when the old man had heard all these things he was greatly moved and disturbed,
            because he remembered his own former acts and life, and because he was held in contempt
            by his conscience by reason of the conditions and circumstances under which he was then
            living, and because that by reason of these he was unable to promise to fulfil the works
            of which he had [then] no knowledge whatsoever, [and he was afraid] and excused himself
            from the task. And when he considered his own feebleness, and the greatness of the
            matter concerned, and the strenuousness and readiness of the young man, and the many
            other reasons which he called to mind, he was ashamed to reveal to the young man the
            true reason for his refusal, yet nevertheless, because of it, he said that he was unable
            to act [for him]; but the young man dismissed his objections and made an end of them,
            and he shewed [him] that they all were insufficient to drive him away from the old man,
            and to do away the fervent desire and aim which were in his mind. Then the old man felt
            compelled to make plainly manifest before him the true reason for his refusal and to
            shew him that it was not a mere matter of a report of words, but one which could be seen
            by the actual sight of the eyes. And wishing to fulfil his intention [of shewing] that
            the true reason was not a mere excuse, or one which was fabricated like those which he
            had previously given, and that it was indeed a true one, and one which would proclaim
            concerning itself openly, he took the young man by the hand, and led him into a certain
            chamber wherein dwelt the wife of that old man with her two children, and he said unto
            him, <quote>God hath sent thee hither for my shame, and for the condemnation of mine old age.
            Behold, this is my wife whom Satan and not God hath given unto me, and behold, these are
            the children of shame whom I have had by her, and they are the fruits of a contemptible
            and damnable union.</quote></p>
         <p>Now when the young man saw and heard these things, because the foundation of his
            building was laid upon the rock of truth, he was neither moved nor disturbed, and he was
            not offended with the old man, and he did not hold him in any contempt whatsoever. And
            after these things the young man answered and said unto the old man, <quote>My lord, I entreat
            thy holiness to confirm that which I am about to say unto thee. Let me have with thee,
            even as with a real father, a wholly perfect understanding, such as it is right for
            children to have with their fathers and with their brethren, which shall be free, by the
            help of God, from all stumbling-blocks; and let me have the same understanding with this
            woman, as with a real mother, and with thy children as with beloved brethren.</quote> Thus the
            old man was overcome by means of all these words by a gracious defeat, and though he
            wished by the urging of his own mind to give the young man permission to live with him
            as a disciple, and to fulfil his desire according to the bent of his mind, he was driven
            thereto far more by the power of the excellence of the young man himself. And when these
            things had taken place they gave thanks to God, and then they occupied themselves, each
            one with the service and work which were requisite for their habitation, day by day with
            the help of God, and the young man excelled in works towards the old man, according to
            his promise, in humility, and in great obedience, and the spiritual excellence of his
            mind was greatly revealed.</p>
         <p>One day the old man said unto the young man, <quote>My son, knowest thou that thou and I are
            building this house with weariness and abundant toil, and that we have not sufficient
            reeds [to make] the roof, and that the winter hath drawn nigh? Now, in order that our
            labour may not be in vain, behold, I see that there are reeds in the habitation of the
            monk who is our neighbour, and since he is not there that we may borrow from him, and
            supply our need, do thou go down and take up from there a bundle, and bring [it hither],
            so that we may finish the roof, and may rejoice through his forethought.</quote> And when the
            brother heard this, he made ready quickly to fulfil the command of the old man, and
            having gone down and brought that which was necessary for them, they completed their
            work. Then the old man said unto that brother, <quote>Tell me truly, O brother, what didst
            thou think in thy mind about that which I said unto thee, that is to say, that thou
            shouldst go down, and shouldst bring reeds as it were by theft, and without the
            knowledge and during the absence of their owner?</quote> And that brother said [unto him], <quote>As
            I have already told thee, everything that thou shalt say unto me I shall receive as if
            it came from the mouth of Christ, and shall perform it in faith unhesitatingly. I said
            within myself, <quote>Christ said unto me, Thou shalt not steal, but now it is He Who hath
            just said unto me, Steal; I have nothing to do with the matter, and it is Christ unto
            Whom I must render obedience.</quote> </quote> And when the old man had heard these words he marvelled
            at the wisdom and at the integrity of his obedience; and wishing to make him to rejoice
            in his hope, he said unto him, <quote>My son, thou must know that I had made up my mind that
            we must tell the owner of the reeds [what I had done], and must give him whatever price
            he might require, [when] I sent thee down to bring up that which belonged to him, and I
            did not do so with the abominable intention of stealing [from him].</quote></p>
         <p>And after a certain time, during which the two men had lived together a correct life
            which was full of peace and profit, the old man thought within himself, saying, <quote>It is a
            great iniquity on my part, and it meriteth a severe penalty, that I who have grown old
            in sins, and who am still in the mire of fornication, should dwell with this brother who
            is perfect in spiritual excellence; for it is not seemly that darkness should live with
            light. But I will leave this abode in his hands, and I will take away this
            stumbling-block which Satan hath set in my way, and these fruits of shame which have
            come to me from her, and I will go to the world and unto those whom I resemble, whose
            works are like unto mine own.</quote></p>
         <p>And when he had meditated with these and suchlike thoughts, and had made them known unto
            the woman who dwelt with him, he sent to the village which was nigh unto them, and
            brought from thence an animal to take away that which he needed from the monastery, so
            that he might lead away his wife and his children, and he might go and live in one of
            the villages round about them. And when the animal had come, and the old man had loaded
            him with whatsoever they needed, and he, and his wife, and his children began to go
            forth, he said unto that brother, <quote>My son, we are not able to dwell in a monastery
            because our sins are many, and because we are not worthy so to do; for it is great
            wickedness for us to dwell under the cloak of falsehood among monks, whilst our deeds
            are more evil than those of the folk who are in the world. But do thou remain in this
            dwelling, O my son, and the God Whom thou hast loved, and Whom thou hast made plans to
            please in everything, shall be unto thee a father, and a fellow monk; and do thou pray
            on my behalf that the Lord may visit me.</quote> And when that brother had heard these words,
            he answered and said unto the old man with love and great humility, <quote>O my father, I have
            made a covenant with the Lord that I will not be separated from thee except by death,
            and inasmuch as my dwelling with thee hath been unto me source of great benefit, there
            is nothing which can remove me and take me away from thee; but wheresoever thou goest I
            will go; and wheresoever thou dwellest I will dwell with thee.</quote></p>
         <p>Then after all these things the old man came to himself, and he sighed greatly, saying,
            <quote>Verily, this is a matter which can only have come from God, the Merciful, Who desireth
            not the death of a sinner, but that he may turn to Him and live, and He it is Who hath
            remembered my former works, and hath not left me to perish utterly, but hath sent this
            young man unto me that He might again turn me unto Him.</quote> Then the old man found himself
            able by means of words, which were full of strong entreaty, to persuade the woman to
            take her daughter with her, and to go and dwell in one of the abodes of women which
            existed in the villages round about them. And this actually came to pass. And after the
            old man had remained there with his son, and with that excellent disciple, he began to
            remember his former life, and to renew the habits thereof, and he excelled greatly in
            the cultivation of all kinds of spiritual excellences, and he gave thanks unto God
            unceasingly, that by means of the young man He had held him worthy of the end of peace.
            And he was always saying, <quote>Truly obedience for the sake of God not only greatly helpeth
            those who possess it, but it greatly gratifieth God also, and it is found by others to
            be the cause of life, and it tormenteth Satan sorely; on the other hand, disobedience
            worketh that which is contrary to all these things.</quote> So after a long time that old man
            died in peace, being worthy of the great measure [of reward] of his fathers, and he
            departed from the world, and left behind him as upright heirs of his spiritual
            excellences and of his monastery his spiritual son, and the son who was his according to
            the body and the spirit; may our Lord through their prayers make us worthy of their
            spiritual excellence and their inheritance! Amen and Amen.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
