<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of a Disciple</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_5">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_5 </ref>. This
               Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 5: The Triumph of the Disciple of another Old Man who dwelt alone in a
            Cell</head>
         <p>One of the aged men said: I have heard from certain holy men that there have been youths
            who have led and guided old men to life, and they told me the following story: There was
            a certain old man who used to plait mats of palm leaves by day and sell them in the
            village [in the night], and get drunk on the money which he received for the same. At
            length there came a certain brother who took up his abode with him, and he also worked
            at the plaiting of mats by day, and the old man took his work also and sold it, and got
            drunk with the money which he received for the work of both, and he would bring home at
            eventide a little bread for that brother; and though the old man did thus for a period
            of three years the brother said nothing to him about it. And after these things the
            brother said within himself, <quote>Behold, I am naked, and I only eat my bread by forcing
            myself to do so; I will therefore arise and depart from this place.</quote> But again he
            thought within himself, saying, <quote>Whither have I to go? I will stay here a little longer,
            for I can live unto God just as well as if I were in a monastery where many monks are.</quote>
            And straightway the angel of the Lord appeared and said unto him, <quote>Depart thou not unto
            any [other] place, for to-morrow we are coming unto thee.</quote> Then that brother made
            supplication unto the old man and entreated him, saying, <quote>I beseech thee, O my father,
            not to go forth this day to any place whatsoever, for the angels are coming to receive
            my soul.</quote> When now the hour had arrived for the old man to go out and sell [the work]
            according to his wont, he said unto the brother, <quote>My son, they will not come to-day, for
            they have delayed too long</quote>; but the brother said, <quote>Yea, my father, indeed they will
            come</quote>; and whilst he was talking to the old man he died. And when the old man saw what
            had happened he wept and sighed deeply, and said, <quote>Woe is me! Woe is me, O my son! I
            have lived in faith for many years, but thou hast gained life for thyself through a
            short period of patient endurance!</quote> and from that day forward the old man led a life of
            sobriety and became a chosen monk.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
