<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Abba Pior</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_11">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_11 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 11: Of Abba <persName>Pior</persName></head>
         <p>And there was an Egyptian youth whose name was <persName>Pîôr</persName>, and he was a holy man; and when he
            departed from the house of his parents he made a covenant with God with the zeal of
            excellence that he would never see again any of his kinsfolk. And after fifty years had
            passed, the sister of this blessed man, who was very old and grey, heard that he was
            alive, and she greatly desired to see him; now she was unable to come to him to the
            desert, and she besought the Bishop, who was in that country, to write to the fathers
            who lived in the desert [telling] them to urge him, and to send him to see his sister.
            Then when the blessed man saw the pressure which came from them to make him go, he took
            with him certain of the brethren, and set out to go on the journey, and [having arrived]
            he sent and informed his sister’s household, saying, <quote>Behold, <persName>Pîôr</persName> thy brother hath
            come, and he standeth outside.</quote> Now when his sister heard his voice, she went forth in
            great haste, and when <persName>Pîôr</persName> heard the sound of the door, and knew that the aged woman his
            sister was coming forth to see him, he shut his eyes tightly, and said, <quote>So and so, I am
            thy brother; look at me as far as thou canst do so</quote>; and having seen him she was
            relieved (or gratified) in her mind, and gave thanks unto God, but she was unable to
            persuade him to enter into her house. And he made a prayer by the side of the door with
            his eyes closed tightly, and departed to the desert.</p>
         <p>And he also wrought the following wonderful thing: In the place where he lived he dug a
            hole in the ground, and found water which was bitter [in taste], but until the day
            wherein he died he endured the bitter taste of the water, in order that he might make
            known that which he suffered patiently for the sake of God. Now after his death many of
            the monks wished <pb n="218"/>to abide in that place, but they were not able to do so, even for one
            year, chiefly because of the terrible nature of the country and the barrenness
            thereof.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
