<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Abba Moses, the Libyan</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_12">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_12 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 12: Of <persName>Abba Moses the Lybian</persName>.</head>
         <p>There was also another old man whose name was <persName>Moses</persName>, who came from the country of the
            <persName>Libyans</persName>; he was exceedingly meek and compassionate, and through this was held to be
            worthy of the gift of healing. And this old man himself related unto us the following
            story, and said: When I was a young man and dwelt in the monastery, we dug out a large
            cistern which was twenty cubits wide, and eighty men were digging it out, and we set
            seventy men to build [walls round it]; and they dug down according to their knowledge,
            and they passed the place where they expected [to find water], and went down even one
            cubit more, but they did not find water, and being greatly distressed at this we wished
            to abandon the well and go away. But when Abbâ <persName>Pîôr</persName> came from the desert at the season
            of noon, now he was an old man and was covered in his head-cloak, he saluted us, and
            said unto us, <quote>Why hath your spirit lessened, O ye of little faith? For I observe that
            your spirit hath diminished since yesterday because ye have not found water.</quote> Then he
            went down by a ladder to the bottom of the well, and made a prayer with the men, and
            having prayed he took up an iron tool and drove it into the earth three times, saying,
            <quote>O Lord God of the holy Fathers, make not the weariness [of these men] to be in vain,
            but send them water in abundance</quote>; and straightway the waters sprang up in such quantity
            that they all were wetted, and having prayed a second time he went forth and departed.
            And when they urged him to remain with them and eat he would not be persuaded to do so,
            but said unto them, <quote>The matter concerning which I was sent hath come to pass, and to
            eat I was not sent.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
