<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of a Wandering Monk</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_13">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_13 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 13: Of <persName>a certain distinguished Wandering Monk</persName></head>
         <p>The copyist adds the note: <quote>We have found [the story of] this wandering monk and recluse
            following [that of] the recluse <persName>John of <placeName>Lycus</placeName></persName>.</quote></p>
         <p>There was a certain distinguished wandering monk who (as have heard from the famous
            monks who dwelt by the side of the country of <placeName>Antinoë</placeName>) lived a life of great sanctity in
            the mountains, and many folks were helped by him both by word and deed. And the Enemy
            had envy of him, even as he hath of every [good] man, and he cast into his mind thoughts
            which appeared to be humble, saying, <quote>It <pb n="219"/>is not seemly for thee to be ministered unto
            and treated with honour by others, for thou shouldst minister unto thyself. Go therefore
            to the city and sell thy plaited baskets thyself, and buy whatsoever thou hast need of,
            and lay no burden upon any man.</quote> Now the crafty one counselled him in this wise because
            he was envious of the assistance which he obtained from the silent contemplation and
            constant [prayer], and because he kept God in his mind, and he was laying nets for him,
            and was trying to snare him by every means in his power. And the monk, being convinced
            as it were by [a counsellor of] good, for he was not greatly skilled [in the knowledge]
            of the cunning and of the abundant wickedness of him that was lurking in ambush, went
            down from the mountain, and the brethren marvelled, because he was a wandering monk, who
            was well known and famous; and thus in a short time, through want of care and also
            through converse with women, he was caught in the toils and fell.</p>
         <p>And he came to <placeName>the river [Nile]</placeName> in a desolate place (now there was with him the Enemy
            who had cast him down and who rejoiced because of his fall, and because many folk would
            be made to offend through hearing thereof); and because he had greatly grieved the
            Spirit of God, and the Angels, and the holy Fathers of the same class as himself, having
            become unlike any of those who in the cities and everywhere else had overcome [<persName>Satan</persName>];
            and because he had forgotten that great might was nigh unto him [that fighteth] against
            the Enemy, and who truly hath his hope in the Lord, because, I say, he forgot that this
            help existed, he fell into error, and knew not how he was to be healed, and wished to
            throw himself into the river flood and die. And moreover, although his body was brought
            exceedingly low, through the suffering of his soul, it would have been in vain had not
            at length the mercy of God helped him not to die (which would have afforded perfect joy
            to the Enemy), [and it urged him] to depart again with weeping and bitter suffering of
            heart, and, as was meet, to make supplication to the compassion of God. And thus, having
            returned to his place and blocked up the window of his cell, he wept, as was right,
            after the manner of one who weepeth in a suitable manner over a dead person, and he
            reduced his body to emaciation by means of his fasting, and vigil, and grief, for the
            expectation of his repentance had not as yet come to him.</p>
         <p>And on several occasions, when the brethren came to comfort him, and knocked at his
            door, because he had no excuse to make he would say, <quote>Pray ye for me, O my brethren, for
            I have made a covenant to live a life of silent contemplation all my days, having
            everything of which I have need.</quote> Then <pb n="220"/>they would go away having no hope whatsoever for
            him; now he was a monk who was very precious in their sight. And from Pentecost, when
            the brethren were in the habit of relaxing their severe rules of life, and when they ate
            freely—now because of his fall that monk did not act thus—onwards, throughout the whole
            year until the feast of unleavened bread, he prayed with tears, and he vexed sorely the
            life of his flesh, and was crucified with <persName>Christ</persName>. But on the eve of the [day of] the
            Resurrection, at the rejoicing of the holy First Day of the week, he took a new lamp,
            and trimmed it ready for lighting, and he set it in a new vessel likewise, and covered
            it over, and being unable to stand up in prayer, he said, <quote>O Thou Merciful One, Who
            desirest that the <persName>Barbarians</persName> and all the people who are without God should have
            knowledge of Thee, and should turn to Thee, and Who alone art the true Physician of
            souls, have mercy upon me, for I know that I have made Thee wroth not a little. I have
            obeyed the Enemy even to my death and, behold, I am a dead man. O Thou Who didst teach
            the children of men who were not merciful to shew mercy to each other, O have mercy upon
            me! For unto Thee nothing is impossible, even though I be brought down as as low as the
            dust in <placeName>Sheol</placeName>. But Thou art the Lord of Thy hosts, and Thou art He Who is good unto
            those whom Thou hast fashioned, and Thou art He who shall raise up the dead bodies [of
            those who] have no being, and Who shall make them to have being in the Day of
            Resurrection; answer Thou me because my heart and my body are sick, for I am overcome by
            the fear of Thee and am ready to perish, and I cannot live any longer. And, because as
            yet I have no confidence in [my] repentance, a twofold destruction have I in my despair.
            Show compassion upon me, O Merciful One, and kindle this lamp by Thy light, so that I by
            means thereof may receive the encouragement of Thy mercy, and may pass the remainder of
            my life which Thou wilt bestow upon me in the way which shall please Thee, and may never
            again as long as I live be unmindful of the fear of Thy Commandments.</quote></p>
         <p>And he said these things with tears on his face, and he rose up to see if the lamp had
            been lighted, and he uncovered it, and saw that there was no light in it. Then he fell
            upon his face as he had done before, and he besought the Lord frequently, saying, <quote>O
            Lord, Thou knowest that the strife hath taken place and that it is ended, and Thou wilt
            not require especially that I should be disgraced by crying out with the wicked, and
            that I should suffer torture for ever. Have mercy then upon me, and I will confess Thy
            goodness; I have been <pb n="221"/>ashamed before the righteous angels, and if it were not that it
            would cause scandal, I would make my confession to the children of men. Therefore have
            compassion upon me, for from this time forward I will teach others that their hearts
            must not be outside Thy fear, even for a moment; and now I make supplication unto Thy
            goodness, O make me to live, and I entreat Thee [so to do], for I am about to die.</quote> And
            the monk prayed in this manner three times, and then he was heard by God, for when he
            went back the fourth time [to see if the lamp had been lighted] he found it burning
            brightly; and he was strengthened with hope, and rejoiced, and wept abundantly, and he
            marvelled at Divine Grace, and he made prayer to the Lord about this also, saying, <quote>Thou
            didst shew compassion upon the life of this world of him that is unworthy, and
            especially by the great and new sign [which Thou hast given]; yea, Lord, Thou dost
            always shew Thy compassion upon the miserable soul, and dost spare it.</quote> And the monk
            continued [to give] simple thanks [until] the day dawned, and he rejoiced in the Lord,
            and forgot the food of the body; and he tended the light of the lamp every day, and
            poured oil therein, and he trimmed it from above, and kept it covered so that it should
            not be extinguished. And thus that man became like one who had risen in the resurrection
            of the righteous, and like the chaste man, and like the humble man in the Spirit of God
            [who obeyeth] readily, and [who giveth] gladly unto the Lord gratitude and thanks. And
            when he was about to yield up unto the Lord the soul which had been graciously given to
            him, he related the story gladly unto the brethren who happened to be there, that it
            might cause them fear, and he said, <quote>Let that lamp be placed in [my] grave in
            commemoration of [my] repentance.</quote> And we, who heard concerning the grace of God, have
            written down these things in order that men may be watchful in the Lord.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
