<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Malchus</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_15">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_15 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 15: The History of <persName>Malchus</persName> the Solitary Monk</head>
         <p>About three miles from <placeName>Antioch</placeName> in <placeName>Syria</placeName> there is a certain village which is called
            <placeName>Mârônîâ</placeName>, and in this village was an old monk whose name was <persName>Malchus</persName>, and he was a
            wonderful and a holy man. Now at that time I had travelled far away from the house of my
            fathers, and I went to <persName>Evagrius</persName> the priest, where I heard concerning the holy man
            <persName>Malchus</persName>, and I desired greatly to see him and to be blessed by him; so I went to him,
            and he received me gladly, and began to tell me about the habits of life and the works
            of the monks, and how it is right to fear the Lord, and having rejoiced greatly in the
            pious words of his doctrine, I besought him to confirm me especially in such things.
            Then he said unto me, <quote>My son, I will relate unto you concerning the temptations which,
            in proportion to my presumption and thoughtlessness, have come upon me, in order that
            they may help you, and also concerning the compassionate grace of the Lord God Who took
            me out of and redeemed me from them, and Who permitted them to come upon me for the
            correction of many who should learn of me, and should not become disobedient to the
            exhortation of their spiritual fathers, because disobedience is the cause of death.</quote></p>
         <p>Then having said these things he began to narrate to me his history, and he said:—I was
            born in the village which is called <placeName>Nisibis</placeName>, and I was the only child of my parents,
            who, because I was the only child they ever expected to have, were proud of me; and when
            I had arrived at manhood’s estate they were anxious to marry me to a wife, but when I
            spake against their [wish], saying, <quote>It is right for me to become a monk and to serve
            the Lord,</quote> and they heard of it, they were exceedingly wroth with me. Now my father
            urged me to marry and threatened me with penalties if I did not, and my mother was
            always inciting and counselling me to do so. And seeing that their minds were most
            firmly set upon this, which would become unto me an impediment to my confession of the
            faith before God, I forsook them, and treated with contempt all the riches of this
            world, and took with me only a very small sum of money, which was just sufficient for
            the expenses of my journey; now I wished to go to the monasteries of <persName>the East</persName>. And
            because at that time the Greeks had determined to make war upon the Persians, I changed
            my intention, and made up my mind to go to the west; and whilst I was pondering this
            matter I learned that between <placeName>Keneshrîn</placeName> and <placeName>Aleppo</placeName> there was a monastery which was
            situated in a peaceful spot, so I gave up my former intention, and went thither, and <pb n="226"/>I
            asked them [to receive me], and I remained with them, and I wrestled with all their
            ascetic habits and rules of chastity according to their godly ways of life, and I made
            good progress therein in the Lord.</p>
         <p>And having remained in that monastery for a certain number of years, and having lived
            blamelessly the life of spiritual excellence, all the brethren rejoiced at the growth of
            my asceticism; but because the <persName>Calumniator</persName>, that jealous and envious being, could not
            endure [this], he cast into my mind thoughts [which were apparently] correct ones,
            saying, <quote>Since thy father is dead, return to thy house, and comfort thy mother so long
            as she is alive, and after her death sell thy possessions, and give some of the price
            thereof to the poor; and the remainder keep, and with it build a monastery, and thou
            thyself shalt become a father and governor of monks.</quote> And to tell the truth to thee, my
            son, the <persName>Calumniator</persName> cast within me the passion of avarice, saying, <quote>Keep some of the
            money for thine old age.</quote> And when the war which was caused by these thoughts had been
            [waged] against me daily for some time, I felt obliged to reveal this sickness of my
            soul to the spiritual father, who, when the holy father had heard thereof, said unto me,
            <quote>My son, hearken not to thy feelings, for this is a snare of <persName>Satan</persName> who, by means of this
            cunning device, hath put many monks backward in their course, even as a dog goeth back
            to his vomit, and hath cast them down and hath made them lose their inheritance, and
            who, though continually setting before them the hope of that which is good, hath
            nevertheless brought them down into <placeName>Sheol</placeName>. For having raised <persName>Adam</persName> to a height of error
            which resembled this, he brought him down to the bottom of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>; and our Lord
            commandeth him that hath laid his hand upon the plough not to turn back.</quote></p>
         <p>Now when by means of such testimonies which he brought from the Holy Scriptures he was
            not able to persuade me [to stay], he thereupon fell down before me and wished to swear
            by the Lord that I would not forsake him. And whilst that merciful and pious father was
            saying these things for my deliverance, the Enemy was placing in my heart the words,
            <quote>The father acteth not thus because he would shew compassion on thee, but he wisheth
            that the whole community of the brethren may be glorified [by thy staying here]</quote>; and by
            saying words of this kind to me, that evil adviser made me to gain a victory of
            wickedness, and he made me to come forth out of the monastery. And still clinging unto
            me, as unto one who was lost, the father said unto me, <quote>My son, I see that thou art
            consumed by love of money; the sheep which goeth forth from his flock without his
            shepherd straightway becometh a prey unto wolves</quote>; and when he had spoken these words
            unto me I left him.</p>
         <pb n="227"/>
         <p>Then I went from <placeName>Aleppo</placeName> to <placeName>Edessa</placeName> by the king’s highway, and being afraid of the
            soldiers (i.e., bands of marauding robbers), who had already taken up their abode in the
            countries round about, I remained in <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, hoping to find company for the journey, for
            so great as this was my watchful fear. And when we had gathered together a company of
            men and women, [whose] names were seventy in number, and had therefore set out on the
            road, suddenly a band of Arab soldiers swooped down upon us, and carried us all away;
            then I called to mind the exhortation of the holy father, and I said to myself, <quote>O my
            soul, such are the great riches which I went forth to inherit! O wretched man that I am,
            such are the promises of the Enemy, the deceiver and destroyer of souls! Inherit [thy
            wealth] then, O wretched one, and make thyself happy therewith.</quote> And as I was saying
            these things to myself, one of the Arabs took me and a certain woman, and set the two of
            us on one camel, and having travelled a short distance in the desert, because we were
            afraid lest we should fall from the camel, we were compelled to hold tightly to each
            other; and not only did this shame come upon mine unconvinceable mind, but I was also
            obliged to eat with her. And the Arab gave us milk and camel’s flesh, and he carried us
            to his tent, and he commanded me to do homage to his wife and to bow down before her,
            and he said, <quote>This is thy mistress.</quote> Now through these things I, the chaste man and
            monk, was becoming acquainted with the form of the nakedness of these people, according
            to the reward which my passion of avarice merited; and the Arab ordered me to gird
            myself about with woollen garments and to shepherd the sheep and this [occupation]
            became unto me a source of consolation for the tribulations which surrounded me, because
            after a few days I was released from the evil faces of my masters and companions. But
            this alone did not bring me consolation, for I remembered that <persName>Abel</persName>, and the Patriarch
            <persName>Jacob</persName> and his sons, and the holy man <persName>Moses</persName>, and king <persName>David</persName> were shepherds of sheep, and
            I rejoiced in the desert, and I pastured the sheep, and prayed, and sang the Psalms
            which I learned in the monastery. And I used to eat cheese made of goats’ milk, and I
            drank milk, and I gave praise to God, that I had obtained such a [light] penalty for my
            disobedience; and remembering that <persName>the Apostle</persName> said, <quote>Servants, be submissive to your
            masters, not only to the good, but also to the wicked</quote> (Colossians 3:22; Ephesians 6:5),
            I took care of my master’s sheep with the utmost diligence. Now in all these things I
            kept in mind always the envy of the <persName>Calumniator</persName>, which hateth that which is good.</p>
         <p>And when my master saw that I was acting rightly towards him, he wished to reward me
            well therefore, and he wanted to <pb n="228"/>marry me to that woman who had been taken captive with
            me; and when I spake against his proposal, saying, <quote>I am a monk, and I cannot do this,
            besides this woman hath a husband who was taken captive with us, and who hath passed
            into other ownership,</quote> his wrath went up, and he drew his sword, and he set his gaze
            upon me, and would have killed me, had it not been that I ran and took hold of his
            wife’s hand. And having married me to the woman, he brought me into a cave with her.
            When, therefore, I knew that this was indeed the captor of my soul, I cried aloud, and
            wept, and said, <quote>Woe unto me the sinner! What hath happened unto me? For having grown
            old in the life of virginity, a terrible evil now cometh upon me, and I must, forsooth,
            become the husband of a wife! Where now is my mother? And where are the possessions and
            riches of my fathers? For because I was not persuaded to [perform] the obedience of the
            servants of God, and because I separated myself [therefrom], and because I forsook the
            Lord I must endure things of this kind! Now what wilt thou do, O my wretched soul? For
            if thou dost conquer by patient endurance, by the Grace of God thou wilt be held worthy
            of help, but if thou art lax severe punishment is laid up for thee. Fight then mightily
            against sin, and turn the sword against thyself, that there may be kept for thee the
            testimony of chastity; hold in contempt the fire of time, that thou mayest flee from the
            fire of eternity, and conquer thou sin in the desert, that thou mayest be a persecuted
            and chosen witness.</quote></p>
         <p>Then I took the sword in my hands, and saluted that woman, saying, <quote>Mayest thou remain
            in peace, O wretched woman, and acquire for thyself rather a martyr than a husband, for
            because I would not marry a wife I fled from and forsook my parents.</quote> Now when the woman
            saw the sword which was shining in the darkness, she fell down before my feet and said
            unto me, <quote>I will make thee swear by <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, the Lord of praise, that thou wilt not
            kill thyself for my sake; and if thou wishest to do this turn the sword against me. Why
            shouldst thou wish to kill thyself so that thou mayest not take me to wife? Knowest thou
            that I am far more anxious than thou art to preserve my chastity unto <persName>Christ</persName>, and must
            guard it not only against thee, but also against my lawful husband, for even if he were
            to come I would keep myself chaste. This is what this captivity wherein I am teacheth
            me, for this affliction should teach us to take refuge in the Lord. Take me then to
            thyself as a companion of thy chastity, and let us love each other in spiritual love, so
            that when our masters see us they may think that our intercourse is carnal. Now God, Who
            knoweth hearts, recognizeth spiritual brotherhood, and we can easily persuade these
            people when they see <pb n="229"/>us together in this wise that we love each other.</quote> Then whilst
            marvelling at the understanding of the woman, I received her good advice gladly in
            <persName>Christ</persName>, and henceforward I loved her as a spiritual helpmeet, and as a pure and chaste
            helper. I never saw her body naked, and I never approached her couch, for I was afraid
            lest, having been victorious in the time of war, I might receive a severe wound through
            the arrows of the Enemy in the time of peace. In this wise then our masters left us for
            a long time, and they were not afraid that we were preparing to run away from them, for
            it happened on several occasions, sometimes for a whole month together, that I was alone
            [with the woman] in the desert. And my master used to come, and when he saw that I was
            taking good care of his sheep, he would go back [to his place] rejoicing.</p>
         <p>And it came to pass one day when, according to my custom, I was sitting in the desert,
            that I began to meditate upon the peaceful life of the brethren who were in the
            monastery, and I saw also the face of our holy father as if it had been an image; and I
            thought of his perfect and abundant love for me, and how anxious he was in every way
            that I should not be separated from him, and how I would not be persuaded [to stay with
            him] by the Divine revelation, and how he bore witness beforehand concerning the things
            which would happen to me—Whilst, then, I say, I was pondering upon these things in my
            mind, and was greatly afflicted thereby, I saw an ants’ nest, and I saw multitudes of
            these insects working with the greatest diligence and care in their various ways, and I
            saw how they were all making their way into the nest through a narrow entrance, without
            impeding each other. Some of them were bringing seeds for their winter food; and others
            were bringing loads which were larger than their bodies; and others were carrying on
            their backs those which had been wounded; and others were expelling from the nest those
            which had settled themselves inside, and they were cutting them up into small pieces,
            lest being drenched in the winter they should have to return to the grass, and should
            die of hunger and be destroyed; and others were carrying dust, so that when the winter
            rains fell with violence they might be able to block up the entrance to their nest
            firmly. Now this sight was in my opinion worthy to wonder at, because everything which
            these small creatures did was done in perfect order, and I spent the whole of the day in
            watching them, and so enjoyed some relaxation from my afflictions, and I said, <quote>Well did
            <persName>Solomon</persName> counsel us to be like these creatures, for he [wished to] stir up our lazy and
            sluggish understandings in this wise [to perform] with a ready mind the things which
            befit our redemption.</quote></p>
         <pb n="230"/>
         <p>Whilst then, I say, I was pondering upon these things in my mind, and was greatly
            afflicted thereby, I began to have sorrow concerning myself, because my lazy and
            sluggish mind lacked the great sense of order and arrangement which the ants possessed,
            and also the faculty of not being disturbed by thoughts of laziness, which the brethren
            possessed in common with the ants, and also because the <persName>Calumniator</persName> had hunted me down
            like a child, and had set me in captivity, and had hurled me into such [great]
            temptations. And I thought of those who were offering their souls with all their hearts
            to <persName>Christ</persName>, and who were being guided on their way in all the monasteries by submission
            and spiritual grace, through the righteous redemption of our Redeemer, and who were
            anxious to preserve their souls blameless, and who were labouring diligently and without
            any hindrance and with all their strength to do their work, and to minister unto one
            another; and who were not saying about any possession which was theirs, <quote>It is mine,</quote>
            and who had everything in common; and who carried out perfectly the manner of life,
            which is described in the Acts of the Apostles (Acts 4:32), according to which no man
            said about any possession that it was his, and everything was in common; and who, though
            possessing nothing, yet possessed everything; and who enjoyed sufficiently that which
            they had for their [daily] needs, with all fear or with all praise, and glorified Him
            Who richly provided them with everything.</p>
         <p>And having made my heart sad and low with such thoughts for many days, I went to that
            woman, who seeing how greatly my countenance was changed, entreated to be allowed to
            learn the cause thereof; and having confessed to her that it was because I had
            remembered the regular life of the brethren, and that I wished to escape and return to
            the monastery out of which the Enemy had made me to come, she advised me and besought me
            to take her [with me] and to place her also in a nunnery. And having together decided
            upon this plan, we wept and entreated our Lord to help us to carry out what we had
            determined and to deliver us from that wicked people. Now therefore, having firm hope in
            God’s assistance, we took thought for our return, and I slew two large goats which I had
            with me, and made their skins into water bottles; and having loaded their flesh upon our
            shoulders, I took the woman, and we departed. And we travelled the whole night long, and
            came to an exceedingly great and wide river, and I blew up the water bottles, and I gave
            one to the woman and kept the other myself, and we laid hold upon them with our hands,
            and sitting astride of the skins we paddled with our feet, and crossed over the river.
            Then, seeing that we should <pb n="231"/>have to cross a desert wherein there was no water, we drank
            abundantly of the water of the river, and rose up from that place and went on our way
            quickly; and we were turning round continually [to look] behind us because of our
            horrible expectation that there would be men pursuing us, and that even if we could
            escape from them we should fall [into the hands of] wicked men like unto them.</p>
         <p>Now because of our fear lest this should happen, and because of the heat of the sun, we
            were obliged to travel by night, and urged by this great fear, and also by our great
            anxiety, we were looking behind us ceaselessly. And after [travelling for] five days, we
            turned round suddenly, and saw our master and one of his companions, riding upon camels,
            and holding drawn swords in their hands, and pursuing after us; and by reason of our
            fear the sun appeared to us to become dark. And whilst we were in this terrible state of
            fright, and did not know where to escape, through the Providence of <persName>Christ</persName>, the Hope of
            the hopeless, and the Help of the helpless, we peered about in that place and found a
            frightful cave in the ground, wherein had gathered all the numerous kinds of snakes
            which are found in the desert, serpents, and asps, and vipers, and scorpions, which had
            gone therein because of the burning heat of the sun. Into this cave we tottered, and we
            hid ourselves in a corner, on the left hand side thereof, and we said, <quote>If our Lord help
            us this cave shall be unto us a house of deliverance; but if He leave us to the sinners
            it will be our grave.</quote></p>
         <p>Now when our master and his companion following in our footprints had pursued us to the
            cave, they alighted from their camels, and stood by the mouth thereof, and when we saw
            our master, such great fear laid hold upon us that we were unable to move our tongue to
            utter a word; for owing to the greatness of our fear we were already [as] dead men,
            before the sword-stroke fell upon us. And when our master stood outside the cave and
            called to us, we were unable to speak to him because of our fear. And he took hold of
            the camels, and commanded his companion to go in and bring us out, whilst he stood
            [outside] waiting for us with his sword drawn, so that he might by means thereof quell
            his brutal madness. Now when the young man had gone into the cave for a distance of five
            paces he stood [still], and because he had come in from the outside, his eyes had become
            dazzled by the light of the sun, and he could not see. Now we being quite near him could
            see him standing [there], but because he was unable to see us he began to terrify us
            with [his] voice, saying, <quote>Come out, O ye wicked slaves who deserve death, wherefore do
            ye delay? Behold, your master is outside expecting you.</quote> And as he <pb n="232"/>was saying these
            words, we saw a lioness rise up on the right hand side of the cave, and she sprang upon
            him, and whilst he was yet speaking, she seized him by the throat and strangled him
            forthwith, and then dragged him in and laid him on her lair, for she had a male cub; and
            when we saw our enemy lying [there] before our eyes, we glorified God with great joy.
            Now his master, not knowing what had happened, and thinking that the young man had been
            overcome by us, and being unable to contain himself for rage, ran forward, holding his
            drawn sword in his hand, and, standing at the mouth of the cave, cried out in his wrath
            to the young man, saying, <quote>Quick, quick, bring forth these [slaves] to me that they may
            die an evil death.</quote> And whilst he was speaking, the lioness sprang upon him suddenly,
            and ripped him up, and threw him headlong on the ground.</p>
         <p>And we marvelled at all these unspeakable and inexplicable wonders of the Lord, and we
            gave thanks to Him, and we rejoiced in the glory of Him Who in this tribulation had
            risen up, and by Whose command the wild beast had destroyed our enemies. Now when the
            lioness turned back and passed from one side to the other of the cave where we were, we
            thought that she would destroy us, but, because of the wonderful thing which had been
            wrought, we [continued] to praise the Lord, and we said, <quote>Since the Lord hath delivered
            us from those wicked men He can, if He willeth, hand us over to the lions; but
            nevertheless let us praise Him and give thanks unto Him.</quote> Now whilst we were thus
            thinking in our minds, the lioness took up the cub in her mouth, and departed from the
            cave, and left the place to us; but after she had gone, because of the state of fear in
            which we were, we remained the whole of that day in the cave.</p>
         <p>And in the morning we went forth and found the camels that were still laden with
            provisions which our master had brought for himself and his slave; and we ate and drank
            therefrom, and for all these things we gave thanks unto the Lord, Who had delivered us
            from our enemies. And we rode upon the camels, and having crossed that desert in ten
            days, we arrived at a Greek camp, and we drew nigh to the Tribune who was in command of
            it, and related unto him everything which had happened unto us; then he sent us on to
            <persName>Sabinus</persName>, who was at that time Duke of <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>, and he likewise learned all our
            affairs and took the camels and gave us their price, and he dismissed us to depart to
            our country in peace. Now before our return it happened that my spiritual father fell
            asleep. And the woman who had been [my] helper, and who had given [me] excellent advice,
            and had counselled good actions, I placed in <pb n="233"/>an abode of virgins, and I returned to my
            own monastery and to my spiritual brethren, where at the beginning the Lord directed me.
            And I related unto that blessed brotherhood the story of all the things which had
            happened to me, and I confessed that it was because I had not hearkened unto the
            admonition of that holy father that the Lord left me so that all these trials might come
            upon me; and He did this for the correction of many.</p>
         <p>Now therefore, O my son, all these trials, which came upon me because of my
            disobedience, and which I have narrated before thee, are [intended] for the edification
            and the protection of thy soul; get thou possession of them, because, by the help of
            God, patient endurance and implicit obedience will deliver a man from all temptations.
            Obedience to the commandments of God is everlasting life, and the patient endurance
            which is perfect produceth everlasting life in us; for <quote>he who endureth unto the end
            shall live</quote> (St. Matthew 10:22). These things did the old man <persName>Mark [Malchus]</persName> himself
            relate unto me whilst I was a young man, and on account of the law of brotherly love I
            have written them down because they befit the chaste life of holy old men, and tend to
            [their] edification and admonition; do ye then relate them unto those who are young, so
            that they may learn that those who have drawn nigh to the venerable estate of pure
            chastity, and who have preserved the same for <persName>Christ</persName>’s sake even unto the end, and who
            are protected by His power, shall overcome all the temptations of the Enemy. And neither
            captivity, nor the sword, nor any temptation, shall be able to overthrow those who have
            preserved in all purity and holiness the temple of <persName>Christ</persName> without spot and blemish, even
            unto death, and they shall become holy temples, and the Spirit of God shall dwell in
            them, and notwithstanding all the words of the <persName>Calumniator</persName>, He shall bestow victory upon
            them, for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
