<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of an Old Man who went Naked</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_17">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_17 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Chapter 17: Of a certain Old Man who went naked</head>
            <p>And they used to speak of a certain solitary monk who went out unto the desert carrying
               his apparel on his shoulder, and having gone a journey of three days, he climbed a rock,
               and saw below him an old man who was grazing like the beasts, and he came down secretly
               and gave chase to him. And the old man was naked, and his soul had diminished to such a
               degree that he could not bear the smell of men, and he was able to remove himself from
               them and to make his escape by flight. And having taken to flight that brother pursued
               him, and he cried out to him and said, <quote>I am following after thee; for God’s sake wait
               for me.</quote> Then the old man answered and said unto him, <quote>And I, for God’s sake also, am
               fleeing from thee</quote>; and finally, casting away from him the garment which was on his
               shoulder, he pursued him with all his might. Now as soon as the old man saw that he had
               cast away his garments he waited for him, and when the brother came up with him the old
               man said,. <quote>As thou didst cast away from thee the things of the world I waited for
               thee.</quote> Then that brother entreated him, saying, <quote>Speak to me a word [of advice] that I
               may be redeemed thereby</quote>; and the old man said unto him, <quote>Flee from the children of men,
               and keep silence, and thou shalt live.</quote></p>
         </div>
         <div><!-- Something is off here between the numbering in the table of contents and the numbering in the text. I will need to sort this out later. -->
            <head>Chapter 18: Of a certain Naked Old Man who fed with the Beasts</head>
            <p>And a certain brother came to the monks who lived in that spot wherein there were twelve
               wells of water, and seventy palm trees, where Moses and the people [of Israel] encamped
               when they went forth from Egypt, and that brother told them the following story,
               saying:—I once had it in my mind to go into the inner desert and see if there was any
               man living therein, and I went a journey of four days and four nights, and found a
               certain cave; and having approached it I looked inside it and saw a man sitting therein,
               and I knocked at the door according to the custom of the monks, so that he might come
               out to me, and I might salute him, but he never moved, for he was dead. Now I did not
               hesitate or draw back, but I went in and laid my hand upon his shoulders, and he
               crumbled into dust and became nothing at all; and in wonderment I came out of that place
               and journeyed on again in the desert.</p>
            <p>And I saw another cave by the side of which were traces of men, and I plucked up
               courage, and drew nigh to it, and though I knocked no man answered me; then I went
               inside and found no man, and I rose up [and came] outside, and said within myself, <quote>The
               holy man will soon come here.</quote> Now when it was the season of evening, I saw a number of
               beasts, which are called <quote>buffaloes,</quote> and the servant of God was in their midst, naked;
               and his hair had been made into a covering for his shame. And when he saw me he stood up
               in prayer, for he thought that I was a spirit, and he was greatly vexed by an evil
               spirit, as he subsequently told me; and I understood this matter, and said unto him, <quote>I
               am a man, O holy one. Look at my footprints, and touch me, for I am flesh and blood.</quote>
               And after he had prayed, and I had answered <quote>Amen,</quote> he looked at me and took heart, and
               brought me into his cave, and asked me, <quote>Why didst thou come here?</quote> Then I said unto
               him, <quote>That I might be blessed by the servants of God have I come into this desert, and
               He hath not deprived me of my desire</quote>; and I also asked him, <quote>How didst thou come here?
               and how dost thou live?</quote> And he began to speak unto me thus:—I was once in a monastery,
               where my work was [to weave] linen, and the thought came to me that I would leave it and
               dwell by myself, and [my mind said], <quote>Thou wilt be able to live in seclusion, and to
               entertain strangers with the results of thy labour, and thy wages will be more than
               enough for thee</quote>; and I agreed with my thoughts, and I carried them into effect. So I
               built me an habitation, and took up my abode therein, and men used to come to me and
               carry away my work. Now whilst I was doing thus, and was giving my work for the benefit
               of strangers and the poor, Satan, the Enemy, with his wonted envy cast his arrows at me,
               and instead of the reward of my labours wherewith I expected to be rewarded, he
               flattered me by causing a certain virgin to come to me, with the excuse that she wished
               to buy the labour of my hands, and I gave her that which she wanted. And he stirred her
               up, moreover, and with one excuse or the other she was always coming to me; and when she
               had been accustomed to come, and had acquired freedom of speech with me, she began to
               come near me, and she would take hold of my hands, and laugh, and she was so bold as to
               eat with me; and subsequently we conceived and brought forth iniquity. And having lived
               with her in this fallen condition for six months I thought in my mind that whether it
               was to-day, or to-morrow, or at some future time, however far off that time might be, I
               should be delivered over to everlasting torment. The man who taketh out [of her house]
               the wife of another man, and seduceth her, is delivered over to the punishment of the
               Law; how much greater then will be the punishment of the man who hath seduced a woman
               who hath been betrothed to Christ? Then straightway I determined to come to this desert,
               and leaving everything I had behind me I went forth secretly, and I came and found this
               cave, and this fountain, and this palm which is in front of it, which produceth twelve
               clusters of dates each year, and thus yieldeth each month that which is sufficient for
               me for the whole month. Now after some time the hair of my body grew long, and my
               clothes wore out, and my hair covered my bodily shame; I have now been here for thirty
               years, and the air (or climate) always supplieth me in moderation with what is
               necessary.</p>
            <p>And I questioned him further, saying, <quote>Was thy mind disturbed about anything during the
               first years of thy life here?</quote> And he said unto me, <quote>I was greatly afflicted at first,
               and I used to throw myself upon the ground by reason of pain in my liver, and I could
               not stand up to say my prayers, but was obliged to make my supplications unto God lying
               on the ground. Now whilst I was in this tribulation I saw a man who came, and stood by
               my side, and said unto me, <quote>What is thy pain?</quote> And at these words I gained a little
               strength, and I said unto him, <quote>My liver troubleth me and causeth me pain</quote>; and he said
               to me, <quote>Shew me where the place is.</quote> And having shewn him, he spread out his fingers and
               his hands, and slit up my body as with a sword and he took my liver and shewed me the
               sore on it; then he removed the pain, and having made the place whole again, he said
               unto me, <quote>Behold, thou art healed. Serve thou Christ, thy Lord, as is meet for Him</quote>; and
               I have been healed since that, and have lived here without any pain. Then I entreated
               him to permit me to live in the first cave, wherein I had seen the dead monk, and he
               said unto me, <quote>Thou art not able to endure the attack of the devils</quote>; and knowing that
               what he had said unto me was right, I entreated him to pray for me and to dismiss me.</quote> I
               have narrated this story unto you, O my brethren, so that we may be zealous in the
               spiritual life and its works of excellence, and may attain to everlasting life; may our
               Lord in His grace and goodness make us worthy to receive it!</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
