<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Two Young Men with Macarius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_21">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_21 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 21: Of <persName>the two Young Men who were with <persName>Macarius</persName></persName></head>
         <p>Abbâ <persName>Bytinius</persName> said:—The disciple of <persName>Macarius</persName> once told me the following story, and
            said:—Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> once said to me whilst I was living in <placeName>Scete</placeName>:—Two young men, who are
            strangers, have gone down there, and one of them hath a few hairs as a beard, and the
            other hath the beginning of a beard. And these young men came and said unto me, <quote>Where
            is the cell of Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName>?</quote> And I said unto them, <quote>What seek ye with him?</quote> And they
            said, <quote>We have heard of his life and deeds, and we have come to see him.</quote> And I said
            unto them, <quote>I am he</quote>; and they offered me repentance, and said unto me, <quote>We wish to
            abide here.</quote> Now, seeing that they were proud because of [their] riches, I said unto
            them, <quote>Ye will not be able to dwell here</quote>; and the elder of them said unto me, <quote>If we
            are unable to dwell here, we will go to another place.</quote> Then I said to myself, <quote>Why
            should I be an occasion of stumbling to them, for the labour itself will make them
            flee?</quote> And I said unto them, <quote>Come, make ye a cell for yourselves if ye can</quote>; and they
            replied to me, <quote>Only shew us how to do it, and we will do it.</quote> So I gave them an axe,
            and a tool for digging up the ground, and a sack of bread and salt, and I shewed them a
            rock wherefrom they might [hew] stone, and I said to them, <quote>Hew your stone from here,
            and then bring wood from the forest and roof over [the <pb n="240"/>place], and then take up your
            abode.</quote> Now I thought that they would straightway take to flight, but they said unto me,
            <quote>What is your work here?</quote> And I said unto them, <quote>The weaving of palm leaves,</quote> and I
            plucked some leaves from the palms in the grove, and shewed them how to begin to work to
            plait baskets, and I said unto them, <quote>Give them to the guardians, and they will give you
            bread.</quote> And from that hour I left them, and everything which I had said unto them they
            performed with great persistence and diligence, and they remained there for three years
            and never came to me; and I continued to debate in my thoughts, saying, <quote>What kind of
            work is theirs that they never come in to me to ask me for anything? The people that are
            afar off come to me, but these who are close by do not come to me, and they have gone
            nowhere else, except to the church to receive the Offering when they have leisure.</quote></p>
         <p>Then I prayed to God and fasted for a whole week that He might shew me their work, and
            straightway I rose up and went to them that I might see how they were; and when I had
            knocked, they opened the door to me, and they saluted me, and then held their peace; and
            I prayed, and sat down. Then the elder of the men motioned to the younger, who went
            outside, and sat down, and he plaited ropes, and said nothing; and at the season of the
            ninth hour he knocked at the door, and the younger man came and made a sign to him, and
            he went forth and cooked a little food. And he made another sign to him, and he prepared
            a table with three bread cakes upon it, and then stood by in silence. Then I said,
            <quote>Arise, let us eat</quote>; and they drew nigh and we ate, and one of them brought an
            earthenware pitcher of water, and we drank. And when the evening had come, they spake to
            me, and said, <quote>Art thou going away?</quote> and I said, <quote>No, I am going to pass the night
            here.</quote> Then they laid down a palm-leaf mat for me on one side [of their cell], and they
            threw themselves down upon the bare earth on the other side of the cell by themselves.
            And when I had prayed to God to inform me concerning their toil, the roof was opened,
            and the place became as light as it was in the day time, but they did not see that
            light. Then, thinking that I was asleep, the elder man smote the younger, and they rose
            up, and girded up their loins, and spread out their hands to heaven; and I saw them, but
            they did not know that I could see them. And I saw the devils hovering about over the
            young man like flies, and some of them wished to settle on his eyes, and some on his
            mouth, and behold, the angel of the Lord was going round him, and was driving away from
            him the devils with a sword of fire; now the devils did not dare to <pb n="241"/>approach the elder
            man. And about the time of morning the two men threw themselves on the ground and I made
            myself to appear like one who had just woke up from sleep, and they likewise feigned to
            have only then become awake. And the elder man spake unto me these words only: <quote>Dost
            thou wish us to recite twelve Psalms only?</quote> And I said unto him, <quote>Yes,</quote> and the younger
            man recited five Psalms out of [each of the] six <foreign>Pethgâmâ</foreign>, and one <foreign>Hûlâlâ</foreign>; and at every
            <foreign>Pethgâmâ</foreign> a lamp of fire came forth from his mouth, and went up into heaven; and
            similarly, when the elder man stood up and recited the Psalms there went forth from his
            mouth as it were a rope of fire, which ascended into heaven. Now I could only recite the
            Psalms little by little. And I came forth and said unto them, <quote>Pray ye for me</quote>; but they
            excused themselves, and were silent. And I learned that the elder man was perfect, but
            that the Enemy still waged war against the younger man. And after a few days the elder
            man died, and three days later the other man died also; and whensoever the fathers came
            to Abbâ <persName>Macarius</persName> he used to take them to the cell of those brethren, and say unto them,
            <quote>Behold ye the martyrium of these little strangers.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
