<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Acts of Bessarion</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_23">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_23 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 23: Of the wonderful things which Abba Bessarion wrought</head>
         <p>Abbâ Shâôl (or Dulas), the disciple of Abbâ Bessarion, used to say:—We came once to the
            bank of a lake and I was athirst, and I said unto Abbâ Bessarion, <quote>I am thirsty.</quote> And
            the old man prayed, and said unto me, <quote>Take water from the lake, and drink,</quote> and I went,
            and drank, and I found the water to be sweet; and I drew therefrom and filled all the
            water vessels which I had with me, for I thought that peradventure I should be thirsty
            again when I continued my journey. Then the old man seeing me do this, said, <quote>Why
            fillest thou [these vessels with] water?</quote> And I said unto him, <quote>Forgive me, father, but
            I did so lest, peradventure, as we continue our journey, I may become thirsty again</quote>;
            and he said to me, <quote>May God forgive thee, for here, and there, and everywhere, God
            directeth us.</quote></p>
         <p>And on another occasion he was travelling along a road, and he came to the river
            Chrysoroan, and there was nothing wherewith it might be crossed, and he stretched out
            his hands, and prayed, and crossed over to the other side. Now I was astonished, and I
            offered unto him repentance, and said, <quote>Father, when thou wast passing over the river
            how far up thy legs didst thou feel the water?</quote> And he said unto me, <quote>As far as my
            ankles I felt the water, but all the rest of it was solid beneath my feet.</quote></p>
         <p>And on another occasion we were journeying to a certain great sage, and the sun was nigh
            to set, and the old man prayed, and said, <quote>I beseech Thee, O Lord, to let the sun abide
            in his place until I come to Thy servant</quote>; and it was so.</p>
         <p>And on another occasion I came to him in his cell that I might speak with him, and I
            found him standing up in prayer, with his hands stretched out to heaven, and he remained
            standing up in this position for four days and four nights; and afterwards he called me,
            and said unto me, <quote>Come, my son,</quote> and we went forth and set out on the road. And being
            athirst I said unto him, <quote>My Father, I am athirst.</quote> Then he removed himself from me
            about the distance of a stone’s throw, and prayed and came to me, and he brought with
            him his garment filled with water from the air, and I drank, and we travelled on our
            road until we came to Lycus, to Abbâ John. And after each had saluted the other, he
            prayed, and sat down, and he discoursed concerning the vision which he had seen, and
            Abbâ Bessarion said, <quote>A decree of judgement hath gone forth from the Lord, that all the
            temples of the idols be blotted out</quote>; and this actually came to pass, for at that time
            they were all uprooted.</p>
         <p>And there was in Egypt a certain man who had a son that was a paralytic, and he took him
            on his shoulders, and brought him to Abbâ Bessarion and left him by the door of his cell
            weeping, and he departed and went to a place some distance off. Now the old man heard
            the sound of the weeping of the young man, and he looked out, and seeing him, said unto
            him, <quote>Who art thou that art here?</quote> And the young man said, <quote>My father brought me here
            and then went away, and I weep.</quote> Then the old man said unto him, <quote>Rise up, hasten after
            him, and overtake him</quote>; and straightway the young man was made whole, and he went to his
            father, who took him and departed.</p>
         <p>And on another occasion there came to the church a man who had a devil, and prayer was
            made on his behalf in the church, but the devil did not go forth, for he was difficult
            [to cast out]; and the clergy said, <quote>What shall we do about this devil, for no man can
            cast him out except Abbâ Bessarion? Let us entreat him concerning the man, and even
            though he cometh not to the church, let us act thus. Behold, the old man cometh to the
            church early in the morning before everyone else. Let us make the sick man to occupy the
            seat wherein the old man sitteth usually, and when he cometh in, let us stand up in
            prayer, and say unto him, <quote>O father, make to rise up this man also</quote> </quote>; and they did so.
            And when the old man came [into the church] in the morning, they rose up in prayer, and
            said unto him, <quote>Father, make to rise up that brother</quote>; and Abbâ Bessarion went and
            struck him with his fist, and said, <quote>Rise up and get thee forth</quote>; and straightway that
            devil went forth from the man, and he was made whole immediately.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
