<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Man with Nine Virtues</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_24">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_24 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 24: The History of <persName>a Holy Man who [possessed] Nine Virtues</persName></head>
         <p>The fathers used to say concerning a certain brother who lived in a large monastery
            that, having contended mightily, and having been helped by God, he had made himself
            master of nine virtues, and that he was exceedingly desirous of making them ten, but
            that in spite of many contendings he was unable [to do so]. Then the Enemy, according to
            his custom, cast his arrows at him, and both by day and by night he vexed him and
            troubled him in order that he might depart from the monastery wherein he was, and he
            advised him, saying, <quote>In another monastery thou wilt be able to complete the ten
            [virtues].</quote> Now the brother, not understanding the cunning of the Evil One, was led by
            his thoughts, which seemed to incite him to [further] spiritual excellence, and he
            departed and went to another monastery with the expectation that he would find that
            which he sought. And having been received into the monastery to which he had gone, after
            a very short time, through the contending of the <persName>Calumniator</persName>, he lost one virtue. And
            once again the <persName>Calumniator</persName> cast into his mind the thought that he would depart from that
            monastery, although he remembered his promise, and said, <quote>Thou hast not only not found
            that which thou didst seek, but thou hast also lost that which thou hadst.</quote> Then the
            brother, being sad and sorry about that which had happened unto him, departed and went
            to another monastery, with the expectation that he would be able to acquire the virtue
            which he had lost, and also that he would be able to add another thereto. And whilst the
            brother was working and contending to acquire that virtue <pb n="245"/>which he had lost and that
            which he had coveted, the <persName>Calumniator</persName>, through his wicked craftiness, made him lose
            another, and he did the same thing to him on several occasions; and he made him to go
            out from one monastery, and brought him into another so often that the brother at length
            lost four virtues.</p>
         <p>And the brother wandered about hither and thither in a state of great agitation, and
            coming to a certain monastery he rested himself, and leaned against the door thereof, in
            dejection of spirit, and he cried over himself, and wept because of what had happened
            unto him. Then, having rested a little, he determined to go into that monastery in order
            to be received into it. And he told himself of all the things which had happened unto
            him, and all the trials which had attacked him in the monasteries wherein he had been;
            and he passed judgement upon his soul and said, <quote>Art thou able to bear all the [trials]
            which are in this monastery?</quote> And his soul made answer, saying, <quote>I place my trust in the
            mercy of our Lord that He will give strength to my weakness, and that I shall endure
            [them].</quote> Then, having decided these things in his thoughts, the brother wrote them all
            down on a piece of paper, and placed them in his girdle, and he strengthened his
            thoughts to go into the monastery that he might be received therein.</p>
         <p>Now after he had been received, and had lived in the monastery for a short time, he
            began to have freedom of speech with the brethren, and with the archimandrite, and
            temptations also began to assail him; then he took out the written paper which was
            placed in his girdle, and read it, and felt relieved, and this he continued to do
            whensoever temptation assailed him. And the brethren marvelled because he was not
            perturbed when they were, for on several occasions, when the brethren of that monastery
            were in a state of excitement, he had not permitted himself to be agitated with them in
            the smallest degree, and they wished to know the reason of this. And one day when the
            monks were agitated and disturbed by a quarrel which was so serious that the matter
            nearly came to murder, that brother took the paper, and looked at it, and as he was
            reading it one of the brethren watched him. And when the tumult was over, and the
            brethren saw that he was not agitated, they marvelled, and said, <quote>What is the meaning of
            this thing? And why is not that brother as excited as we are?</quote> Then the brother who had
            watched the monk [read his paper] revealed to them the matter, saying, <quote>He hath
            something in his girdle, and on account of it he remaineth undisturbed</quote>; and the
            brethren enquired into the matter, and they found that it was even as the brother had
            said.</p>
         <p>Then they approached the archimandrite, and said unto him, <pb n="246"/><quote>If thou dost not expel this
            brother, we will not remain here, and we will go forth, because he is a sorcerer, and
            behold, his sorceries are in his girdle</quote>; and the archimandrite promised to expel him.
            Now the archimandrite delayed the expulsion of that brother, and one night, whilst he
            was asleep, the archimandrite went to him and took the paper from his girdle, and he
            read it and rejoiced with a great joy; and having read the paper he put it [back] into
            the girdle of the brother, who knew not what had been done, and no other man knew. And
            after a short time the brethren, through the agency of <persName>Satan</persName>, were greatly disturbed by
            a very serious quarrel, and that brother was in no wise agitated; and when they saw that
            he was not disturbed at all and that he was wholly tranquil, they rose up against the
            archimandrite, saying, <quote>If thou dost not expel this brother we will all depart
            forthwith.</quote> Then the archimandrite called the brother and said unto him, <quote>What is this
            that thy brethren are saying against thee? They are bringing an accusation against
            thee.</quote> And the brother expressed regret, saying, <quote>Yes, father, all [their words] are
            true; but permit me to repent.</quote> And the archimandrite said unto him, <quote>But they say that
            thou art a sorcerer</quote>; and the brother said, <quote>Yes, I am even as they say, but I beseech
            thy piety, O father, that thou wilt allow me to repent here.</quote> Then the archimandrite
            said unto him, <quote>But they say that thy sorceries are in thy girdle.</quote> And the brother,
            being unwilling that his spiritual excellence should be revealed, fell upon his face
            before the archimandrite and took hold of his feet, and made supplication to him, and
            wept with groans and sighs, saying, <quote>Expose me not, O father, but forgive me for this
            once only, and I will repent with all my soul.</quote> Then the archimandrite, who knew that
            great advantage would accrue to the whole brotherhood, would not be persuaded by him,
            but he commanded that his girdle should be loosened, and he himself took it and brought
            out therefrom the paper; and he then ordered that all the brethren should be gathered
            together, and that the paper should be read in a prominent place, so that all of them
            might hear. And after the paper had been read the brethren repented, and fell upon their
            faces before that brother, and they entreated him, saying, <quote>Forgive us, father, for we
            have sinned against thee.</quote> Thus that brother benefited the whole brotherhood, and they
            regarded him as a father.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
