<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Two Brothers</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_27">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_27 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 27: Of <persName>Two Brothers who dwelt in <placeName>a Persian Monastery</placeName></persName></head>
         <p>A certain history, which is full of pain and profit, O my beloved, came to me by chance,
            that is to say, through conversation and speech with the brethren, and I have thought
            much about it, and have determined that it is right for me to narrate it, and to set it
            down in writing, so that many from the reading of the same may acquire spiritual profit,
            and may watch against enmity, and may not have bitter hatred of one another for any
            reason whatsoever, and that each [of us] may be at peace with the other, and so that
            each [of us] may forgive the other any cause for murmuring or anger, and may remember
            the words of our Lord, and God, and Redeemer, <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>.</p>
         <p>There were two brethren who dwelt in one abode in <placeName>a certain Persian monastery</placeName>, and it
            happened that one of them had cause for dispute with the other, and they separated, each
            from the other, the one leaving the monastery altogether, and the other remaining in the
            abode wherein they had lived hitherto. And it came to pass that he who remained behind
            was seized, and bound, and shut up in prison, for [giving] testimony concerning our
            Lord, and he was brought before the judge, and was questioned by him once, twice, and a
            third time, and he bore severe stripes and did not deny <persName>Christ</persName>, and he was again fast
            bound in the prison house. Now when his companion heard [this] he repented in his soul,
            and he thought, <quote>It is right that I should go and be reconciled with my brother, for
            perhaps through this testimony which he persisteth in giving, he may depart from the
            world and go away, each of us keeping wrath against the other, and through this we both
            shall suffer no small loss, and probably I more than he.</quote> And when the brother had
            meditated thus, he came to the prison and enquired for his companion who was imprisoned
            there, and he went into his presence and fell down at his feet, and besought and
            entreated <pb n="253"/>him to be reconciled to him; but the brother who was in fetters would not be
            persuaded to do this, and continued in his wrathful condition, and when the brother saw
            this he left him and departed in sorrow.</p>
         <p>And on the following day the judge commanded and they brought in before him the man who
            was bound and in prison, and he asked him if he would be persuaded to deny his God and
            to worship the sun, and he would not agree to do either; and the judge gave orders that
            he was to be laid out and beaten, and to be smitten with rods, and when they had laid
            him out, and the strokes were being laid on by two [men] at a time, he denied <persName>Christ</persName>.
            Now when the judge saw this, he commanded the men to stop beating him, and he called him
            to him, and asked him, saying, <quote>What aileth thee? I caused thee to bear severe stripes
            on three previous occasions, and thou wast neither overcome nor didst play the coward’s
            part, and yet now, whilst they are coming near thee, thou dost deny [thy God].</quote> And the
            brother said, <quote>I have acted thus because I have sinned and treated with contempt the
            commandments of the Lord my God, Who commanded us to forgive each his offences. I had
            once a brother in our Lord, and we lived together in one monastery, and it happened that
            some cause for anger rose up between us, and we separated from each other in enmity.
            Yesterday he came to me in prison, and fell down before me and begged for peace from me,
            and I would not consent to be reconciled unto him, and therefore the goodness of God was
            cut off from me, and He did not help me this day as He hath always done before, and I
            denied [Him]. During the stripes which I received formerly I used to see Him spread out
            about a hand’s breadth above me, and He did not permit me to suffer, but to-day He
            forsook me, and at a small amount of pain I was terrified and I denied [Him].</quote> Now when
            the judge had heard these things from him, he commanded that his fetters should be
            loosed from off him, and that he should be dismissed; and the brother, feeling disgrace
            and shame at the fall which had come upon him, went forth from the presence of the
            judge, and directed his way straight to his companion, and he fell down on his face at
            his feet, and wept and cried out bitterly, and entreated for mercy and peace; and when
            his companion looked upon him, he also suffered great grief, and he received him, and
            they were reconciled, and he prayed for him, and though the thing was bitter to him,
            they separated one from the other.</p>
         <p>Then the brother who had denied his God straightway returned to the door of the judge,
            and he began to cry out and to curse the king, so that they might again bring him before
            the judge for examination; but the judge did not wish to say <pb n="254"/>anything to him. And when
            the brother saw this, he departed from thence, and through penitence and grief for what
            had happened to him, and also through the pain and anguish of his soul, he threw
            himself, body and soul, into a fire temple; and he began to cast dust and everything
            else which came to his hands on the fire; and he cursed the king mightily, saying, <quote>God
            will receive those who have been tripped up and have fallen, if they repent and turn
            unto Him.</quote> And he departed from thence also, and he wandered about and went hither and
            thither, and he threw stones at every magian or pagan whom he met, and he never ceased
            from reviling the king; and he never ceased or kept silent concerning the compassion of
            our Lord, which is laid out for those who repent, and he cried out, saying, <quote>Verily,
            there is no god except our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, although I, through my sins, and my
            negligence of His mercy, have denied Him.</quote> Now when the judge heard these things, he
            feared lest he would suffer a penalty and be condemned to death as one who had heard the
            king reviled, and had been neglectful; and straightway he sent forth a decree concerning
            him, and ordered that his head should be cut off quickly with the sword. And when they
            had seized the monk, and had taken him outside the city, he cried out with a loud voice,
            and said, <quote>Blessed art Thou, O our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, for ten thousand times ten
            thousand sins are too few for Thy mercy to forgive in one hour</quote>; and having said this
            they made him kneel down, and he was smitten by the sword and received mercy. Glory be
            to the Power Who maketh strong His saints to do His Will, and may we have mercy shewn
            unto us through their prayers, for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
