<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Stephana</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_29">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_29 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 29: Of <persName>Stephana</persName>, a Man who fell into filthy Wantonness</head>
         <p>There was a certain man in <placeName>Scete</placeName> whose name was <persName>Steph창n창</persName>, who had dwelt in the desert
            for twenty-nine years; his apparel was made of palm leaves, and he lived in such a
            strict state of self-denial, and persisted to such a degree in ascetic abstinence that
            he never had the least inclination for the meats which are usually desired, and which
            are pleasant to the taste; and he greatly condemned those who, because of sickness,
            either ate cooked food or drank cream. Now the gift of healing had been given to him to
            such a degree that he could cast out devils by a word. And it came to pass that on one
            occasion a man in whom was an unclean spirit came to <placeName>Scete</placeName>, and he wished to be healed,
            and when the monk saw that he was vexed sorely by the devil he made a prayer and healed
            him. But at length this monk was rejected by Divine Providence because of his
            immeasurable arrogance and haughtiness, for he imagined himself to be more excellent in
            his life and works than the other fathers; first of all he separated himself from the
            brotherhood, and then he went and became archimandrite in one of <placeName>the Alexandrian
            monasteries</placeName>, <quote>For,</quote> he said in his pride, <quote>am I to be in subjection to <persName>Macarius</persName>? And are
            not my life and works better than his?</quote> And this man arrived at such a state of madness
            that he went to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and gave himself up to gluttony, and drunkenness, and to the
            eating of more flesh than rational beings are wont to eat, and finally he fell and
            settled down into the pit of the lust for women; and he was always going about in the
            houses of harlots, and in the taverns of ill-fame, and he hung closely to the whores,
            and gratified his lusts in a filthy manner without shame, and he became a laughing-stock
            to all who knew him. But the spirit went forth to those who knew him, saying, <quote>The law
            was not made for the perfect,</quote> and he himself said, <quote>I do not act [thus] because of
            passion and fornication, neither do I do anything which is abominable, for it is not a
            sin to go with women, for male and female were created by God.</quote></p>
         <p>And it fell out that one day I and the blessed man <persName>Evagrius</persName> went to <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> on some
            business which called us thither. And we had with us four brethren; and as we were
            passing through the city market that monk met us accidentally, and he was talking with a
            harlot about his filthy lust; and when the blessed <persName>Evagrius</persName> saw him, he wept, and fell
            down at his feet and made obeisance unto him, but the man did not incline his head in
            the smallest degree, and with infinite arrogance and <pb n="260"/>haughtiness he made answer to him,
            saying, <quote>What do hypocrites and deceivers seek here?</quote> Then the blessed <persName>Evagrius</persName>
            entreated him to go with us to the place where we were lodging, but he did not by any
            means wish to go; and when, with the greatest difficulty, he had been persuaded to go
            with us, so soon as we had entered in and prayed, the blessed <persName>Evagrius</persName> fell upon his
            neck and kissed him, and with tears said unto him, <quote>Verily, O my beloved, from all that
            divine service of angels thou hast been brought down to this depth of wickedness; and
            thou hast turned thyself from converse with God to converse with harlots; and instead of
            the life and service of angels thou hast chosen the life of devils! But I beseech and
            entreat thee not to cut off the hope of thy redemption, but arise, and come with us to
            the desert, for by my hands God the Merciful is able to restore thee to thy former
            grade.</quote> Now his understanding had been so blinded by <persName>Satan</persName> that he did not know how to
            listen to what was said unto him, nor did he know what he answered. And he said unto
            <persName>Evagrius</persName>, <quote>Up to the present I have certainly been wandering about, but now I have found
            the path of truth,</quote> and he began to make a mock of the fathers, and to say, <quote>Ye
            certainly wander about [i.e., err], and ye dwell in the desert under a false character,
            for the sake of men, and not for the sake of God, and ye are to the spectators as idols
            whom men decorate, and to whom they pay worship</quote>; and thus, being full of the pride and
            boasting of <persName>Satan</persName>, he spurned the fathers and went forth and departed, and the blessed
            <persName>Evagrius</persName> and the brethren wept and groaned over him greatly.</p>
         <p>Then that man carried off a certain virgin, who was an orphan and a nun living by
            herself, with a foul design to his monastery, and though he did this with the excuse
            that he was going to help her by means of alms of which she was in need, it was in
            reality that he might fulfil his wanton desire. And having lived with her in this
            degraded state for about two years, at length there came to him thieves by night, who
            first tied him with cords, and then smote him with hard and cruel blows, until he
            brought out whatsoever he had in his dwelling and laid it before them; and last of all
            they shut him up with the woman with whom he used to work out his wantonness in a house
            wherein there was straw, and, both of them being bound with cords, the thieves set fire
            to the house, and thus the two were consumed, and they died a bitter death. And in them
            was fulfilled that which was spoken by the teacher of the Gentiles, who said, <quote>Because
            they did not decide within themselves to know God, God delivered them over to the
            knowledge of vanity, that they might disgrace their bodies <pb n="261"/>therewith, and they received
            the reward which befitted their error in their own persons (Romans 1:28); that is to
            say, the burning of the fire which is here is a pledge of that fire which tormenteth all
            the wicked.</quote> Now the things which happened to <persName>Steph창n창</persName> took place because he separated
            himself from the brotherhood, and because he was [unduly] exalted in his mind, and
            because he imagined that he was perfect.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
