<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Deacon</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_31">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_31 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 31: Of a certain Famous Deacon who dwelt in a Coenobium in Egypt</head>
         <p>A certain brother asked an old man and said unto him, <quote>If it should happen that a man
            fell into temptation, by the permission of God, for the benefit of his soul, what is it
            right for those to do who are made to stumble by the same temptation?</quote> The old man
            answered and said unto him, <quote>If he repent in very truth, and with all his heart, and
            make confession unto God in his repentance, [saying,] <quote>I have been rightly humbled,</quote> and
            shall say unto God, <quote>It is good for me that I have been humbled, so that I might learn
            Thy commandments,</quote> God is able to heal the consciences of those who have already
            offended Him.</quote> And the old man spake and narrated the following:</p>
         <p>There was a certain deacon in a coenobium in Egypt, and a rich man, who had been driven
            out and had departed from the presence of a governor who had dominion over him, came
            with his household to that coenobium; and the deacon stumbled and fell into adultery
            with the wife of one of those who were with him, and he became a laughing-stock unto
            every man. And he went to a certain man who was his friend, and revealed unto him the
            matter, and he said unto him, <quote>Let no man know where I am</quote>; for he hid himself in a
            secret part of the cell of him that loved him, and he said unto him, <quote>Here bury thou me
            during my lifetime</quote>; and having gone down into the darkness of that hidden place he
            repented unto God in very truth. And after a certain time, the river, which was nigh
            unto the place in the region wherein the deacon had hidden himself, did not rise
            according to its wont, and the people of the country having prayed and made supplication
            it was revealed unto one of the saints that, <quote>Unless that deacon who is hidden among us
            come forth, the waters will not rise.</quote> So they went and brought him out from the place
            where he was hidden, and when he had come, and had made a prayer, straightway the river
            rose, and those who had been formerly offended by him were now edified the more, and
            they profited through him greatly and glorified God.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
