<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Bishop</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_32">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_32 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 32: Of <persName>a certain excellent Bishop who fell into Fornication</persName>, and <persName>the People
            having walked upon him he was forgiven</persName>.</head>
         <p>There was a certain bishop in one of the cities, who through the working of the
            <persName>Calumniator</persName> fell into fornication; and one day when the congregation was in the church,
            although no one knew of the Bishop’s sin, he voluntarily confessed it before all the
            assembly, and said, <quote>I have fallen into fornication.</quote> Then he took off the vestments
            which were on him, and laid them upon the altar, and said, <quote>I cannot, henceforward, be
            your Bishop.</quote> And all the people cried out with tears, saying, <quote>Let this sin be upon us;
            only remain thou in thine episcopate.</quote> And he answered and said unto them, <quote>If ye wish
            me to remain in my episcopate, do ye that which I shall say unto you</quote>; and he commanded,
            and all the doors of the church were shut with the exception of one, and he threw
            himself down upon his face, and said, <quote>The man who goeth out from the church without
            walking upon me shall have no portion with God</quote>; and they did according to his word, and
            when the last man had gone out, a voice was heard which said, <quote>Because of his great
            humility I have forgiven him his sin.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
