<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Abba Poemen's Neighbour</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_33">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_33 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 33: Of <persName>a certain Brother who was a Neighbour of Abba <persName>Poemen</persName></persName></head>
         <p>When Abb창 <persName>Poemen</persName> came into the countries of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> to dwell there, it happened that he
            took up his abode by the side of a brother who had a wife, and though the old man knew
            of this he did not rebuke him. And when the time had come for the woman to bring forth,
            and this was known to the old man, he cried out to a younger brother, and said unto him,
            <quote>Arise, take this jar of wine and carry [it] to our neighbour, for he will have need
            thereof this day.</quote> Now the matter was not known to that brother, but he did as the old
            man commanded him. And the brother [who had a wife] groaned and repented in his mind,
            and after a few days he dismissed the woman, and gave her whatsoever he happened to <pb n="265"/>have
            by him; then he came to Abb창 <persName>Poemen</persName>, and said unto him, <quote>Behold from this day onwards I
            repent, O father, but I entreat thee to pray to God on my behalf so that He may receive
            my repentance.</quote> And Abb창 Poeman said unto him, <quote>If thou repentest with all thy heart, I
            believe that God will bestow forgiveness upon thee; and do not despair of thy
            redemption.</quote> And the brother went and built for himself a place of retreat, and he made
            therein an entrance through which he used to come to visit the old man; and he would go
            to Abb창 <persName>Poemen</persName> thereby, and the old man would reveal unto him the way of God, and thus
            he profited spiritually. And the brother laboured in fasting, and in prayer, and he wept
            and sighed, and grieved sorely for his sin; and [at length] it was revealed unto the old
            man on behalf of the brother that God had accepted his repentance.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
