<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of a Brother who denied Christ</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_34">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_34 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 34: Of a certain Brother who denied [Christ] because of the Daughter of a
            Heathen Priest</head>
         <p>Once a certain brother was engaged in a war against fornication, and he happened to pass
            through a village in Egypt where he saw the daughter of a heathen priest, and he loved
            her, and he said to her father, <quote>Give her to me to wife.</quote> And the priest answered and
            said unto him, <quote>I cannot give her to thee before learning from the god [his will in the
            matter]</quote>; and he went to his devil, and said unto him, <quote>Behold, a certain monk wisheth
            to take my daughter to wife; shall I give her to him or not?</quote> And the devil made him
            answer, saying, <quote>Seek out and enquire if he will deny his God, and his baptism, and the
            vows which he made before entering the monastic life.</quote> And having gone to the brother
            the priest told him that he would accept him [as his daughter’s husband] if he would
            deny both these things (sic), and the priest also said unto him, <quote>Wilt thou deny the
            baptism wherewith thou wast baptized?</quote> And the brother answered and said, <quote>Yea, I will</quote>;
            and straightway he saw the Spirit of God go forth from his mouth in the form of a dove,
            and ascend into heaven. Then the priest went to the devil and told him what the brother
            had said, <quote>Behold, he hath promised to deny all three things</quote>; and the devil answered
            and said unto him, <quote>Thou shalt not give [him] thy daughter, for his God hath not
            departed from him, for He is still helping him, and will accept him if he repenteth.</quote>
            And the priest came and said to that brother, <quote>I cannot give her to thee, for thy God is
            with thee, and He will not leave thee, but will help thee.</quote> Now when the brother heard
            this he said within himself, <quote>So God keepeth such great grace as this for thee, and will
            still help thee!</quote></p>
         <p>Then that brother, having come back to his senses, made strong his mind, and fortified
            his will, and went forth to a certain old man in the desert, and related the matter unto
            him. And the old man answered and said unto him, <quote>Sit thou down here with me in [this]
            cave, and fast for three weeks, only eating once every two days, and I will make
            supplication on thy behalf unto God.</quote> And the old man laboured with the brother, and he
            made entreaty and supplication unto God, saying, <quote>I beseech Thee, O Lord God, to grant
            me the soul of this brother, and to accept his repentance.</quote> And when the first week was
            fulfilled, the old man came to the brother, and asked him, saying, <quote>Hast thou seen
            anything?</quote> and the brother answered and said, <quote>Yes, I have seen a dove flying about in
            the heights of heaven, and standing before my head,</quote> and the old man said unto him,
            <quote>Take heed to thyself, and pray unto God with groans and sighs</quote>; and the following week
            he came again to the brother, and asked him the same question, saying, <quote>Hast thou seen
            anything?</quote> And the brother made answer, saying, <quote>I saw a dove which came and drew near
            to my head,</quote> and the old man admonished him, saying, <quote>Rouse up and pray unto God with
            abundant supplication.</quote> And when the third week was fulfilled the old man came to the
            brother and said unto him, <quote>What hast thou seen?</quote> And he answered and said unto him, <quote>I
            saw a dove which came and stood upon my head, and I stretched out my hand and took hold
            of it, but it fled away and entered into my mouth.</quote> Then the old man gave thanks unto
            God, and said unto the brother, <quote>God hath accepted thy repentance; henceforward watch
            thyself and take heed to thyself.</quote> And the brother answered and said, <quote>Behold, from this
            day onwards I shall live with thee, O father, even to the day of my death.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
