<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of an Old Man in Scete</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_35">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_35 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 35: Of <persName>A Certain Old Man In <placeName>Scete</placeName></persName></head>
         <p>There was a certain old man in <placeName>Scete</placeName> who, having become very sick indeed, was ministered
            to by the brethren, and he thought in his mind that they were tired of him, and he said,
            <quote>I will go to <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, so that the brethren may not have to labour on my account.</quote> And
            Abbâ <persName>Moses</persName> said unto him, <quote>Thou shalt not go, for if thou goest, thou wilt fall into
            fornication</quote>; and the old man was grieved and said, <quote>My body hath long been dead, and
            sayest thou these things unto me?</quote> So he went up to <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and men heard about him, and
            they brought many offerings unto him, and a certain believing virgin came in faith to
            minister unto him. And after a time, when the old man had been healed, the <pb n="267"/>young woman
            lay with him, and she conceived, and folk asked her, saying, <quote>Whence hadst thou that
            which thou hast conceived?</quote> And she said unto them, <quote>From the old man,</quote> and they
            believed her not. Now when the old man heard that they would not believe her, he said,
            <quote>Yea, I have done this thing; but protect ye for me the child which shall be born.</quote> And
            when the child had been born and was weaned, there was a congregation in <placeName>Scete</placeName>, and the
            old man went down carrying the child on his shoulder, and he went into the church before
            all the people; and when they saw him they all wept. Then the old man said unto the
            brethren, <quote>Observe ye, O my brethren, this is the child of disobedience; take heed,
            then, unto yourselves, for I have committed this act in my old age, and pray ye for me</quote>;
            and the old man went to his cell, and dismissed the things wherewith he hath lived, and
            returned to his former deeds, and after a time he arrived [once more] at his old measure
            of ascetic excellence.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
