<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Serapion and the Harlot</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_36">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_36 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 36: Of the Harlot whom Serapion converted</head>
         <p>Abb창 Serapion once came and passed through a certain village in Egypt, and he saw a
            harlot standing in his cell, and the old man said unto her, <quote>Remain here until the
            evening, for I wish to come with thee, and to pass this night with thee</quote>; and the harlot
            said, <quote>It is well, O father.</quote> Then she made ready, and prepared her bed, and she awaited
            the old man with that which he required. Now when it was evening, Abb창 Serapion came,
            but he brought nothing with him, and he went into her cell, and said unto her, <quote>Is thy
            bed ready?</quote> And she said unto him, <quote>Yea, father</quote>; and they shut themselves in. Then the
            old man answered and said unto her, <quote>Wait a little, because I must perform a certain
            thing which is a law unto us.</quote> And he began to recite the Book of the Psalms of David
            from the beginning, and with every Psalm he offered up a prayer on her behalf, and he
            made supplication before God that she might repent and live, and God hearkened unto him.
            And the harlot stood up in fear by the side of the old man and prayed also, and when
            Abb창 Serapion had finished all the Psalms she fell down upon the ground, and he began to
            repeat many verses from the [books of the] Apostles. When he had finished his service,
            God having opened the heart of that woman, she knew that Abb창 Serapion had not come unto
            her for the purposes of sin, but that he might redeem her, and she fell on her face
            before him, and said unto him, <quote>Perform an act of grace for me, O father, and take me to
            any place whatsoever wherein I can please God.</quote> And he took her to an abode of nuns and
            placed her therein and he said to the mistress of the convent, <quote>Take this sister, O
            mother, and lay not upon her the rules and the yoke like the [other] sisters, but
            whatsoever she requireth that give her; and in proportion as she findeth rest let her
            submit to be led.</quote> And when the woman had dwelt in the nunnery for a few days, she said,
            <quote>I am a sinful woman, and I wish to eat only in the evening</quote>; and after a few days more
            she said, <quote>Many sins lie to my charge, and I therefore beg that I may eat once every
            four days,</quote> and she did so; and after a few days more she besought the mistress of the
            nunnery, saying, <quote>Do an act of grace for me. Since I have made God exceedingly angry,
            take me into a cell and wall it up, and through a small opening therein give me a little
            bread and work for my hands [to do].</quote> And the abbess of the nunnery hearkened unto her,
            and did thus, and in this wise that woman pleased God all the days of her life.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
