<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of a Harlot</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_37">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_37 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 37: Of <persName>the Harlot whom a Subdeacon drove out of the Church</persName></head>
         <p>A certain old man said: There was a harlot who was so beautiful and so rich that all
            princes flocked unto her. One day she went into the church and desired to pass inside
            the gates, but a subdeacon who was standing at the door would not allow her to do so,
            and he said, <quote>Thou art not allowed to enter into the house of God, because thou art an
            unclean woman.</quote> Now whilst they were striving together, <persName>the Bishop</persName> heard the sound of
            the noise, and he went out to see [what was the matter]. And the harlot said unto him,
            <quote>He would not permit me to go into the church,</quote> and <persName>the Bishop</persName> said to her, <quote>Thou art
            not permitted [to do so] because thou art unclean.</quote> Then having repented within herself,
            she said, <quote>I will never play the whore again.</quote> And <persName>the Bishop</persName> said unto her, <quote>If thou
            wilt strip thyself of all thy possessions, I shall know of a certainty that thou dost
            repent</quote>; then she brought her possessions, and the Bishop took them, and divided them in
            the fear of God among the needy. And the woman went into the church, and wept and said,
            <quote>If it hath happened to me thus in this world, what would have happened to me in the
            next?</quote> And she repented, and became a chosen vessel.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
