<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Apollo in Scete</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_38">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_38 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 38: Of <persName>Abba Apollo who was in <placeName>Scete</placeName></persName></head>
         <p>They say concerning Abbâ <persName>Apollo</persName>, who lived in <placeName>Scete</placeName>, that he was originally a rude and
            brutish herdsman, and that he [once] saw in the fields a woman who was with child, and
            that, through the operation of the devil, he said, <quote>I wish to know the condition of the
            child which is in the womb of this woman,</quote> and that he ripped her open and saw the child
            in her belly; then straightway he repented, and he purged his heart, and having repented
            he went to <placeName>Scete</placeName>, and revealed unto the fathers what he had done. And when he heard them
            singing the Psalms, and saying, <quote>The days of our years are threescore years and ten, and
            with difficulty [we come] to fourscore years</quote> (Psalm 90:10), he said to the old men, <quote>I
            am forty years old this day, and I have never yet made a prayer; and now, if I live for
            forty years more, I will never rest, nor cease, nor refrain from praying to God
            continually that He may forgive me my sins.</quote> And from that time onwards he did even as
            he had said, for he never toiled with the work of his hands, but he was always
            supplicating God, and saying, <quote>I, O my Lord, like a man, have sinned, and do Thou, like
            God, forgive me</quote>; and he prayed this prayer both by night and by day instead of reciting
            Psalms. And a certain brother who used to dwell with him once heard him say in his
            prayer, now as he spake he wept, and groaned from the bottom of his heart, and sighed in
            grief of heart, <quote>O my Lord, I have vexed Thee, have pity upon me, and forgive me so that
            I may enjoy a little rest.</quote> Then a voice came to him, which said, <quote>Thy sins have been
            forgiven thee, and also the murder of the woman; but the murder of the child is not yet
            forgiven thee.</quote> And one of the old men said, <quote>The murder of the child also was forgiven
            to him, but God left him to work because this would prove beneficial to his soul.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
