<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of Abba Macarius</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_40">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_40 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 40: Of Abba Macarius who was accused of committing fornication</head>
         <p>Abba Macarius used to tell a story about himself, and to say that when he was a boy he
            dwelt in a certain cell in Egypt, and that the people came and made him the priest in
            the village, and that as he did not wish to receive [the office of priest] he fled to
            another place, and took up his abode in a cell which was not very far from the
            habitations of man. And a certain young man who feared God used to come and take away
            the work of the hands of the blessed man, and to minister unto him. And it came to pass
            that, as a result of temptation, a certain virgin in the village fell into iniquity (?),
            and conceived a child, and the folk said unto her, <quote>By whom art thou with child?</quote> And
            she said, <quote>By that monk who liveth in the desert</quote>; and they went out, and brought him
            into their village, and smote him sorely, and they hung round his neck black pots, and
            the ears (handles) of empty pans, and they made him to go round about through the
            markets of their village, and they mocked at him and buffeted him, and said, <quote>This is
            the monk who hath seduced our daughter! Let him be hanged! Let him be hanged!</quote> And they
            beat him [nearly] to death.</p>
         <p>Then came one of the old men of the village and said [unto them], <quote>How long will ye go
            on beating this monk who is a stranger?</quote> and the man who ministered unto him came after
            him, and he was ashamed and pained because of his disgrace; and the people fastened
            their gaze upon him, and said, <quote>Behold the monk concerning whom thou didst bear witness
            and say that he was a <quote>holy man.</quote> </quote> <quote>Consider what he hath done,</quote> said the parents of
            the young woman, <quote>and unless he giveth us a surety who will provide for her food we will
            not release him.</quote> Then he said unto the man who ministered unto him, <quote>Give a pledge on
            my behalf, saying, <quote>I will provide for that</quote> </quote>; and he gave a pledge for him, and then
            the monk went to his cell and gave him all the palm-leaf mats thereof, and said to him,
            <quote>Sell these and give [the money] to my wife that she may eat.</quote> For Macarius said in his
            mind, <quote>Behold, thou hast found for thyself a wife, and it is necessary for thee to work
            little or much that thou mayest feed her</quote>; so he worked by night and by day, and sent
            [the proceeds of his toil] to her.</p>
         <p>And it came to pass that, when the time for the woman to bring forth her child arrived,
            she suffered very severely for many days, and [although] she was in great tribulation
            she did not give birth to the child; and when her parents saw this they said unto her,
            <quote>What is this which hath happened unto thee?</quote> Then the woman, by reason of her pains and
            sufferings, said, <quote>This has happened because I told a lie and falsely accused a monk who
            never touched me</quote>; now it was such and such a youth who had done this thing to her. And
            when the man who ministered unto Macarius learned this, he came to him with gladness,
            and he rejoiced and said unto him, <quote>The virgin was not able to bring forth until she
            confessed and said, <quote>The monk never touched me, and what I have said about him is a
            falsehood,</quote> and behold, all the village is preparing to come to thee with repentance so
            that thou mayest forgive them.</quote> And Macarius, in order that he might not be troubled by
            them, rose up straightway, and fled, and departed to the place wherein he had his abode
            at that time, and this is the reason why he came to Scete; and he said, <quote>I hate the love
            of praise of young men who toil, and who have no reward, because they expect the
            adulation of the children of men.</quote> Then another well-known old man said unto him, <quote>And
            it is not greatly acceptable unto me, but it is better that they should work for praise
            rather than they should despise [it], for it always constraineth those who love praise
            to lead lives of abstinence, and to keep vigil, and to live in nakedness for the sake of
            vainglory, and to bear afflictions for the sake of praise.</quote> Then after these things the
            Grace of God came to them and spake, saying, <quote>Wherefore do ye not toil for My sake? And
            why do ye toil for the sake of children of men?</quote> And they were convinced that they must
            not expect the praise of men but that of God, and when the brethren heard [this] they
            said, <quote>Verily the matter is indeed thus.</quote></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
