<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">The History of the Melchisedekian</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Paradise</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Paradise (1907) by Palladius of Galatia, translated by Ernest Alfred Wallis
               Budge</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 10/27/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_41">
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Paradise/Volume_1/Book_2/Chapter_41 </ref>.
               This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Chapter 41: Of <persName>a certain Old Man</persName> who in his simplicity said that <persName>Melchisedek</persName> was the
            Son of God</head>
         <p>And Abbâ <persName>Daniel</persName> told a story of another old man who used to live in the lower countries
            of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, and who said in his simplicity that <persName>Melchisedek</persName> was the Son of God. Now, when
            this became known unto the blessed man <persName>Theophilus</persName>, the Archbishop of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, he sent
            a message that [the monks] should bring the old man to him, and when he saw him, he
            perceived that he was a seer of visions, and that everything which he had asked God for
            He gave him, and that he spake these words in his simplicity. And the Archbishop dealt
            with him wisely in the following manner, saying, <quote>Father, entreat thou God [for me],
            because my thoughts tell me that <persName>Melchisedek</persName> was the Son of God.</quote> And he said to him
            likewise, <quote>It cannot be thus, for the high priest of God was a man. And now, because I
            had doubts in my mind concerning this, I sent for thee that thou mightest make
            supplication unto God that He may reveal to thee the matter.</quote> Then, because the old man
            had confidence in his labours, he spake unto him boldly, saying, <quote>Wait three days, and I
            will enquire of God, and then I shall be able to inform thee who <persName>Melchisedek</persName> was.</quote> So
            the old man departed, and came [again] after three days, and said unto the blessed
            Archbishop <persName>Theophilus</persName>, <quote><persName>Melchisedek</persName> was a man</quote>; and the Archbishop said unto him, <quote>How
            knowest thou, father?</quote> And the old man said, <quote>God showed me all the Patriarchs, one by
            one, and they passed before me one after the other, from Adam to <persName>Melchisedek</persName>, and an
            angel said to me, <quote>This is <persName>Melchisedek</persName></quote>; know then that of a truth the matter is as it
            hath appeared unto me.</quote> And the old man departed, and he himself proclaimed that
            <persName>Melchisedek</persName> was a man, and the blessed <persName>Theophilus</persName> rejoiced greatly.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
