<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/799">Abraham the Recluse</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/799.xml -->
         <head>Next the Seventh History’ of the Old Man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1555">Abraham</persName> the Layman, the Recluse,</head>
         <p>
            We wish next to place on record the history of the old man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1555">Abraham</persName> also,
            <pb n="119"/><pb n="119"/>who was called the consecrated<note></note>, and had reached old age being about
            sixty years old. This man one day, when the gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έυαγγέλιον</foreign>) was
            being read, heard that our Lord said, <quote>Whoever shall leave wife or
               children etc. for my sake and for the sake of my preaching shall receive
               thirty fold and sixtyfold and an hundredfold in this age, and in the future age
               shall inherit eternal life</quote>'; and again <quote>Whoever doth not take up his cross
                  and follow me is not worthy of me</quote>. When this old man heard these words,
            sorrow entered into his mind, and he thought within himself, and said:
            <quote>Wherefore am I for my part alive and called a Christian, if I do not do
               now that God's will? If it is pleasing to God that I should leave wife and children, even
               my days have been completed and the sentence has reached me that
               I shall leave them against my will, why do I not that which God wishes?
               What have I gained either from children or from wife, or from the whole
               world, except that I have consumed my life in it in vanity, and idly wasted
               my moments, and passed my days evilly?, and lo! I have come to the gate
               of the grave. Who will shelter me there in that judgment? or who will rescue
               <pb n="120"/><pb n="120"/>me from my sins? But now even for this little remainder of my life that
               remains to me I will go and repent of my sins, and then I will die, having
               hope in that parable of the labourers which our Lord spake, that, even after
               the day had declined and one hour only was left for those who came,
               they were thought worthy to receive the pay with the first'. So I too also
               hope that God will not shut the door of his mercy in the face of my
               repentance</quote>. And thereafter the old man would think, <quote>What shall I do?
                  If I go to a monastery, I cannot work; and they will say, <quote>This old man
                     has come upon us in order to get a present out of us</quote></quote>. Then the old
            man left everything, and went to a certain monastery and said to them,
            weeping: <quote>Rise make the prayer for me, and give me the tonsure, and
               take the hair of my secular life from me, since I desire to repent for a short
               time for my sins before I die</quote>. But the blessed men did not frustrate
            his wish and stand in his way, when they heard the announcement of repentance 
            from him, but they encouraged him and they say to him: <quote>You
               are doing right, our father, if you are turning in repentance toward God;
               since he is merciful and will receive you</quote>. After they had held much
            conversation with him, because they supposed that he intended to live with
            <pb n="121"/><pb n="121"/>them, they said to him: <quote>After you are tonsured, where do you intend to
               live?</quote> But he said to them: <quote>Rise give me the blessing and take my hair,
                  and where God wishes I will live</quote>. They say to him: <quote>We seek to learn
                     whether you intend to remain with us or elsewhere; and then, if you remain
                     with us, we will ourselves give you the tonsure, and, if elsewhere, why will
                     you be tonsured away from the place where you are going to live?</quote> The
            old man said to them: <quote>I came to you that you might make the prayer for
               me and give me the blessing and the tonsure, not that you might argue with
               me. If you are willing, well; and, if not, pray for me.</quote> The blessed men,
            when they saw the old man's own intention and purpose, made the prayer
            and gave him the tonsure, and he rose and left the place, and he directed his
            steps to a certain oratory at the boundary of his village, which had been
            formerly built and roofed and in which a man had lived; and he went in and
            repaired it and closed its doors, and took up his abode in it, after requesting
            a man to bring him his little food every first day of the week. And so he
            would stand and recite a service and pray constantly and weep, while
            everyone was struck with astonishment at him, and some mockers would
            <pb n="122"/><pb n="122"/>say, <quote>Come let us go and be blessed by <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1555">Abraham</persName> the consecrated recluse</quote>,
            and others, uttering words that came from the evil one, would say, <quote>If he
               had shut up his wife with him, he would be doing rightly</quote>. But the old
            man despised everything and set one object only before his eyes, since he
            would ask repentance for his sins and healing from the merciful Physician,
            not ceasing from prayer and recitation of service, either by night or by day.
            And his service was as follows: <quote>Glory to the Father and to the Son and to
               the Holy Spirit Halleluyah!</quote>; and again as follows: <quote>and from eternity to
                  eternity Amen and Amen! Halleluyah!</quote> And thus he spent the hours of the
            night and of the day in these words of praise with prayer and supplication
            and thanksgiving, while he gave orders that none of his kin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) should
            appear in his presence; and before the first day of the week he did not speak
            to anyone, but wept continuously for his sins; and so men used to go by
            stealth, and listen to the sound of his sobs, and they were astonished at him.
            And the old man persevered in his repentance for eight years. And in the
            eighth year, when he was near his end, there used to be hail in these villages
            <pb n="123"/><pb n="123"/>every year<note></note> and they were smitten, and their crops also were utterly ruined.
            And, when the time arrived and that terrible cloud had come up according to
            its custom, on the first day of the week, when some persons were present at
            his lodging, they began to weep, because the cloud was terrible and very
            trick, and something like fire was blazing and roaring within it, and it came
            and settled over the boundaries of that village, after the fire had burnt up
            all those round it. But the old man looked out from the window and saw it;
            and he turned his eyes toward heaven, and said: <quote>My Lord, if thou hast
               been pleased with the sinner's repentance, and thy mercy has declared of me
               that I shall not perish, let not this cloud come within the boundaries of this
               village</quote>. Then that cloud took in the middle of it as it were the likeness
            of serene air (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άήρ</foreign>) inside all that darkness; and, while it all divided this
            way and that, and passed by the boundaries of that village, the signal of light
            remained until that cloud had passed. And so through the power of the
            old man's prayers that village was delivered and escape from that terrible
            rod of chastisement, which injured not one leaf within its boundaries; and,
            <pb n="124"/><pb n="124"/>outside all its boundaries all round, not even the leaves remained upon the
            trees<note></note>. Then the boundaries of that village exulted, while they themselves
            made proclamation concerning the power of the prayers of the blessed
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1555">Abraham</persName>, everyone being astonished and giving thanks to God. And the
            old man also rejoiced, and he gives thanks to God who had shown him that
            he accepted his repentance. And, at the end of the eighth year, he departed
            from the world in the good ending of repentance.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the old man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1555">Abraham</persName> the layman, the recluse, is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
