<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/801">Mare of Beth Urtaye</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/801.xml -->
         <head>Next the Ninth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1866">Mare</persName> of Beth Urtaye</head>
         <p>
            This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1866">Mare</persName> was a clergyman (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κληριχός</foreign>) in the church of a certain
            large village in the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Anzetene</placeName> called the village of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2794">Hula</placeName> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ύλη</foreign>?).
            This man then, when he was a member of the clergy (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κληριχός</foreign>), used to behave
            with great and measureless arrogance, and he was haughty and a good
            speaker and teacher, and very well-informed on every subject. And, grace
            having at a certain time arisen in his mind, suddenly he began to form the
            plan of taking upon him the yoke of monasticism; and he disposed of ands
            distributed all that he had among the needy; and he withdrew to a certain
            mountainous spot about three miles from the village; and he bound himself
            never to taste bread or wine or oil, or cheese or fish, or anything whatever
            except pulse and herbs and water; and thus he exercised himself
            severely.<pb n="136"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            Then <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan </persName> again, who wishes to restrain men from good actions, did
            not neglect to stir up against the blessed man the trial of persecution; and so
            the assaults of persecutions often attacked him, and he was arrested and
            imprisoned and ill-treated, and he did not give way and allow his rule (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κανών</foreign>)
            to be relaxed, while the adversaries kept him in prison a week and two
            weeks and as much as a month; and he determined in his mind that even
            the very food that he was in the habit of eating he would not taste at all
            as long as he was under their power. And so they by <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3651">Satan </persName>’s machination
            would leave him until his life was approaching dissolution, saying, <quote>This
               man defeats us</quote>. But the valiant man was so determined in his soul that
            down to the end he tasted nothing that came from the renegades. And thus
            they were continually defeated in him and left him, not being able to weaken
            his fortitude in God. While he was occupied with such severe asceticism,
            and moreover with persecution, he built an admirable, substantial, large
            monastery, with many excellent details of construction; since he was also a
            craftsman with intellectual skill in all crafts. And he built and finished it,
            and twelve years were completed by him in such labours. Then he departed
            from the body, bearing good testimony, nothing whatever having been found<pb n="137"/>
            to weaken him, or to make him remit what he had originally undertaken,
            not sicknesses nor persecutions, nor any other distresses.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1866">Mare</persName> is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
