<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/805">Thomas, Stephen, and Zota</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/805.xml -->
         <head>Next the Thirteenth History, of Certain Saints and Servants of
            God, Thomas and Stephen and Zwṭʾ the Notaries (vocap.OS) and <foreign>syncelli</foreign>
            of the Holy Mare' Metropolitan of the City of Amida</head>
         <p>
            After the decease of the believing king Anastasius who is among the saints,
            when Justin? was set over the kingdom, he was making a beginning of
            divisions and contentions in the church of God by introducing the impious
            synod of Chalcedon; and from that time forward by order of the same
            schismatic king everyone who did not assent to the reception and introduction
            of the synod lived under persecution and expulsion, and certain members
            of the church were accordingly banished to various places of exile (égopías).
            The beginning of these things occurred in the year eight hundred and thirty
            of Alexander'; and from this time forward were clearly seen in every
            man's case the love that was in him and the foundation of his heart and the<pb n="188"/>
            firmness of his will, those who had' the love of God, and those again who
            had' the love of the world and desire for positions of power and inclination
            toward the renegades. These things therefore quickly reached Mesopotamia,
            and overtook the holy Mare bishop of Amida; and he took upon himself to
            suffer persecution and expulsion with Christ, rather than to depart from Christ
            and occupy the temple and the throne of temporal honour? This saint
            therefore, with Sergius and Stephen and Thomas his notaries (vorápios) and
            <foreign>syncelli</foreign>, weresent to a hard and distant place of exile (topía) at Petra; and
            they accepted it and departed and went; and they were there in great distress
            exceeding their power of endurance, until their lives were near disappearing.
            By reason of this distress therefore the holy Mare was constrained to send
            the virtuous zealous Stephen his deacon and notary (vo táctos) to the royal
            city, in the hope that he might perhaps by the intercession of anyone whom<pb n="189"/>
            God might put in his way be able to have that place altered for them. But,
            when he went up, the good God, who, as the divine apostle also says,
            <quote>is faithful and just, who will not permit you to be tried more than ye are
               able to be tried</quote>' directed the virtuous Stephen to Theodora who came
            from the brothel (ropvēžov), who was at that time a patrician, but eventually
            became queen also with King Justinian”. She therefore, when she learned of
            that distress, as if by divine instigation, because she saw that saint's distress,
            made her mercy manifest, and made entreaty to Justinian her husband, who
            was master of the soldiers (otpatnéons) and also a patrician and the king's
            nephew', that he would inform his uncle, and he might order relief to be
            given to these distressed men, making this entreaty even with tears. And,
            through the grace which cares for every man's life, it was done and an order
            went out to them to come to Alexandria. And Stephen the deacon took this
            order, and brought it down, both to them and to the holy Isidore another
            bishop, of Kenneshrin', who also was exiled there with them; and according<pb n="190"/>ly 
            a great relief and deliverance was effected for these blessed men, because
            at that time this city became a habitation of men driven by persecution
            from all quarters, and a place of reception for men expelled from every place;
            and from that time the blessed men were quietly settled in the same city.
            But, after a short time, some cause called them to be in need of a utensil
            (sxevźprov) such as they make out of the leaves of the date-palm for household
            use; and, as it were by the dispensation of God, an old man was found selling
            them who lived in a certain desert in the region of Libya belonging to a
            village called Mendis', which lies twenty-four miles above Alexandria, and
            this old man had also had also come into this desert from Palestine under
            persecution, with other blessed men as well as virtuous blessed women also
            who were living in quietude in that place, in a certain tower which had been
            set up for defence against barbarians?. Since therefore this man came from
            the territory (ope) of Amida, and the blessed men who accompanied the
            holy bishop Mare saw that he was an educated man and spoke their language,<pb n="191"/>
            they brought him, and received his <foreign>mzyqn</foreign>' from him, and conversed with
            him; and they inquired also further where he lived. And, when he had told
            them all his affairs, the blessed Stephen and Thomas the deacons conceived
            the desire of going out to that place; and he conducted them, and they went
            out with him; and they saw the blessed men driven out by persecution who
            were with him and the blessed women, and the quietude of the place also
            attracted them. And they also told them about a certain large pit that lay
            near the place in the desert at a distance of two miles, in which someone
            had once lived”; and they went and saw it. And from that time the blessed
            Thomas, with whom the chief part of the story and the course of the
            narrative are concerned, formed the plan of going down and living in that
            pit; a luxurious and dainty man, who from his childhood had been brought
            up like a king's son, who was also a descendant (yévos) of Ishakuni Bar Brʿy',
            who was a patrician; who was mighty and great and eminent above all who
            were in the East; and the blessed Thomas moreover possessed an estate
            (ousia) and male and female slaves, and great riches; and he was so luxurious<pb n="192"/>
            and dainty that he used to clean his face and his hands with water more than
            ten times a day. This saint then, who lived under these conditions, now in
            opposition to these things formed the resolution of acquiring ascetic habits.
            But, when his object became known, that he wished to do these things, then
            everyone who heard it would as it were laugh at his purpose, saying, <quote>All
               that delicacy and luxury wants to dwell in the waste uninhabited desert</quote>.
            And, though the blessed Stephen had the intention of doing spiritual service,
            yet, because he was feeble and sickly of body, he refrained from doing
            these things, saying, <quote>For ourselves this is too great a thing to live in the
               desert on account of our feebleness; but, my brother, let us look after our
               soul, and gain a desert by our manner of life and our heart, and always
               entreat the Lord to cause his grace to shine upon us</quote>. When they had
            returned to the city, the blessed Thomas provided for the concerns of his
            cell, doing everything in secret, and he gave his key (xheid) to the bishop's
            cellarer (xendapítns), and for some reason was blessed by the saint without his
            knowing of it'; and he departed and returned to the place, and went straight<pb n="193"/>
            to that pit, bravely applying himself thenceforward to asceticism and vigil
            and protracted recitation of services. But he used to go down into that pit
            and come up again, that he might not put force upon his body all at once and
            faint and be overcome, while the blessed men who were the occasion of his
            going out to that place supplied his necessary requirements. And so in
            that pit he laid great and grievious labours upon himself, and was without
            ceasing continuously occupied in weeping and sorrow and mourning for
            his sins, and these blessed men (since these also were very perfect in their
            manner of life) used to relate to me', <quote>Whenever we see the blessed Thomas,
               we find him beating his face, and saying, <quote>Woe to me, my brethren, since I
                  have consumed my days in vanity. Woe to me, since my moments have
                  melted away in evil deeds. Woe to me since my life has been squandered
                  in works of darkness. The world has deceived me. The demons have
                  mocked me. My mind has been lost in the vanity of the affairs of this lying
                  world. Pray for me, my brethren, that the merciful God may receive me in
                  repentance, and not turn his face away from my hatefulness. Pray for me
                  that the door of mercy at which I am knocking may be opened to me, and I<pb n="194"/>
                  may find the life of my wretched soul which was lost. All the carefulness of
                  life I for my part expended on these corruptible concerns of this body of
                  dust; and life has passed away and death has come near, and corruption is
                  at hand, and judgment has overtaken me. And what shall I do, my brethren?
                  Woe to me woe to me, the erring one. Where, pray, was my darkened
                  mind, that it did not think of these things till to-day?</quote>. As often as he saw us</quote>
            (these blessed men used to say to me), <quote>by reason of the sound of his sobs
               and his weeping and mourning for his soul he would make us also weep</quote>.
            When he had been in that pit six years, because attacks of bodily infirmity
            and the influence of damp (voría) had greatly affected him, and he had become
            infirm by reason of the severity of the labours which he had laid upon
            himself, they with great force lifted him out of it. After a space of eight
            years the holy bishop Mare departed from the body in Alexandria', while
            his two sisters? also who were deaconesses were there in Alexandria, women
            who are themselves also in truth among the saints by reason of the greatness
            of their mode of life. And, after the decease of the blessed bishop Mare',<pb n="195"/>
            his sisters with the rest of the company (Guvodía.) that was with them prepared
            to carry his bones down to his own country; and they sent the blessed
            Stephen the deacon to Theodora, who had before interested herself in
            procuring their release from exile (copia), who also at the time had become
            queen'; and she thereupon issued an order that the blessed man should be
            carried down. And, when the order came, they thereupon continued
            constraining this blessed man who loved the wilderness to show his gratitude
            to his holy bishop, and consent to go down with them with his bones to his
            country. But the blessed man utterly refused to do this, saying, <quote>It cannot
               be</quote>. And, when they had made many attempts to induce him to consent
            to go down, and if he wished, return, saying to him, <quote>If you wish this,
               it would not be right for you to leave your estate (noir) and your affairs to
               chance, but you ought to go down and arrange matters as you wish between
               yourself and your sister, and come back</quote>, and, when they had urged him,
            he considered this to be the right course, since he came to this conclusion,
            that it was not in accordance with right that his affairs should remain<pb n="196"/>
            without provision; and he accepted and went down with them in silence,
            and with his head covered, and his tears always flowing. And, when they
            saw that he was constantly weeping night and day, then these holy women
            also who saw that his tears ran down upon his food, and on the road also
            while he was travelling again the same, and similarly also at his lodging-place, 
            being much astonished at his sorrow, would say to him: <quote>What is
               the matter with you, father, that you thus constantly weep?</quote> But the
            devout and holy man would say to them: <quote>I weep because I am sick;
               but pray for me</quote>. But they, as they used to relate, <quote>as if to jest a little
                  with him said to him: <quote>And what of it? Does a man who is sick thus
                     constantly weep?</quote></quote> But he said to us: <quote>A man who is seriously ill, if he
                        feels that his complaints are giving him pain, weeps even if he does not
                        wish it'</quote>. And so we would praise God, who had thought him worthy
            of such sorrow and weeping and humility, and had given him repentance
            that he might know his blemishes. But, when they had gone down and
            reached the city, and the magnates and their kinsmen and the whole city
            had come out to receive them, and the bones of the blessed bishop had<pb n="197"/>
            been laid in his martyrs' chapel which he had built, called that of Beth
            Shurla', they proceeded to enter the city; but the blessed Thomas directed
            his steps to a monastic convent on the north of the city which is called
            that of the house of Mar John, of which I also was an inmate for about
            19 years from the time of the departure of the holy Maro my spiritual
            father”, both when it was suffering persecution and when it was at peace'.
            To this monastery then this saint came; and he went in and prayed, and
            he asked for a lodging, and it was given him. And, when his sister, whose
            name was Cosmo, who also was a woman of virtuous habits of life, and
            the other persons of high position urged him to go into his house and that
            of his people, he did not yield to them, saying, <quote>Learn, my brethren,
               from the divine psalmist who says, <quote>One day in thine habitation is better
                  than a thousand</quote>'</quote>. And, when the blessed Stephen the deacon saw
            that he had taken up his lodging outside, because they loved one another,
            and also imitated one another in the matter of virtuous practices, he also<pb n="198"/>
            asked to lodge outside in the monastery. And thus they did, while both
            of them were detained, because they intended to return to the desert
            together. And they were delayed for two years; though, if their thoughts
            had not been completely set upon God, it would have been decided that they
            should remain for good.' The blessed men thenceforward together with Zwṭʾ
            the deacon, who also was a clergyman (xanp.zos) of the church under the same
            holy Mare', himself also devoted himself to death or life with the blessed
            men, who himself also astonished those who knew him by the manner of life
            which he finally adopted, while it would never have entered any one's mind
            that that man would ever place upon his nock the great yoke of monasticism.
            And the three of them thenceforth lived with one virtuous purpose, while to
            see to what humiliation the blessed Thomas had come from what splendour
            and greatness astonished and saddened everyone; and so many used to spurn
            and despise everything in him.
         </p>
         <p>
            This space of two years then he occupied in making an equal division
            between himself and his sister, saying, <quote>She is in the world, and needs her<pb n="199"/>
               share. I am not required to dispose of anything except my own</quote>. When
            they had completed everything, and he was thenceforth desirous of returning
            to the desert, being every day vexed and annoyed and distressed at his detention 
            from that country, I, inasmuch as I was close at hand and had been in
            constant intercourse with him because I had seen his manner of life, and had
            also gained freedom of speech (csoénoía) before him, would say to him as if
            jesting with him, <quote>Why, pray, are you vexed, father? Lo! are you not in
               a monastery? (for are you in the world?), lo! it lies before you to fast and to
               pray, and practise asceticism as much as you wish. Wherefore are you
               distressed? You had a cell in the desert, and lo! here too is a cell. Do in
               it as you wish</quote>. But the blessed man, while I on my part was sayi these
            things to him, kept his hand resting upon his cheek, and looked at me in
            astonishment; and at last he sighed and said to me: <quote>Can a slave then (öpce)
               serve two masters'? or again can a man be in intercourse with God and<pb n="200"/>
               with men and can one see any of one's relatives and bodily kin (yévos) and
               approach spiritual things? accept my statement, sir, that for me a foreign
               land is much better, and it preserves me from many impediments. Or know
               you not that hour after hour and moment after moment privily steal and
               snatch away part of our life like wolves and flee from us, so that, since, if
               all our lifetime we run after one moment of our life, we shall not overtake
               it, how, father, shall we not weep and lament for one day only that passes
               idly from us, without bearing the fruits of our praises and presenting them
               to God, and again that also our petitions and prayers and requests may
               on it be' depicted and made visible before God? Know you not that man's
               days and his years are themselves like volumes full of letters, and every day
               and hour on which a man does good or evil, or performs praise or prayer, that
               hour or day records them upon itself, and presents them before God, and, since
               God is omniscient, in order that the man may be judged or applauded according 
               to his conduct in life, and that everything that has been done by him<pb n="201"/>
               may be known to him, therefore his own moments approach in order and pass
               before God, each one of them carrying that which that man did in it, whether
               it be what is good or what is evil, and showing it to God. And, if again
               a day which has passed of our life is one of abstention from good deeds and
               from evil, the place in the life of the man whoever he be is in it similarly
               void and torpid and useless, and it stands up and accuses him, since that day
               carries the fruits of the saints, and the confession of the confessors, and the
               praises of those who give praise, and the prayers of those who pray, and
               the alms of the givers, and the forgiveness of those who forgive, and shows
               them to God, every man's own actions which he performed in it being depicted 
               on it. And now, O father, when these things are so, how shall we
               neglect one hour and not tremble to let it pass from us void without carrying
               the fruits of our repentance, and without the words of our praises being
               written upon it? How, our brother, shall we be caught by the deceit of
               this lying world, and not understand and consider that from this hour in
               which we now stand we were equally distant from the time of our birth
               down to the present day, and, since we began to speak, it has been quickly
               fleeing from us and departing, and, if we run after it for a thousand years,<pb n="202"/>
               we should not be able to overtake it again or to see it for ever and ever?
               And for this reason it is much better for me to go and sit in some corner
               (revtx), and weep for my life and for my empty moments and for my profitless
               years, and for my hours that have melted and passed from me empty
               and void, where neither acquaintances nor relatives will harass me; because
               in the moment when the sentence goes forth upon me no friends, or loved
               ones, or kin (yévos), or members of the family, will give me any pleasure</quote>,
            As for me, while I was listening to all these things from this saint, great
            marvel fell upon me that he so effectually controlled his thoughts and collected 
            his mind, directing it toward God, and did not allow even if it were
            one idle hour or moment of his life to be lost without praise and prayer and
            repentance, and thus shunned and dreaded and feared the waste of one hour
            only. Then I marvelling in my mind thought, <quote>Pray, what sounds and
               songs of lamentations will suffice to make lament for my own sell, and for
               the rest of those who are like me? since I have wasted some of my moments,
               that is even the whole of my life, in wantonness (Goprivía); and not only has<pb n="203"/>
               one hour not been treated by me as of any account, but not even a whole
               year of days also</quote>. And marvelling I went out from the presence of the
            blessed man, and used to repeat all these things to my brethren with trembling. 
            Now the blessed man's manner of life while he was in the monastery
            was as follows, fasting from one evening to the next, and scanty food; and
            indeed with the freedom of speech (mašoncíx) that I had acquired with him
            I used to say to him, <quote>In truth I wonder how you live</quote>; but he would answer 
            me, saying: <quote>What have I gained by feeding my body as if for
               sacrifice down to the present time? Or ought I not to know that food
               belongs to the creeping thing and the worms? Wherefore must I take fire
               and scorch my eyelids? When the body receives foods and is nourished
               and grows fat, the fire of passions and lusts is kindled in it, and it scorches
               and burns the eyes of the soul so that they do not see and restrain it from
               sinning. And now, instead of it hanging to the soul so that it is brought
               down and, wallows in the mire of the body's lusts, let the soul hang upon
               it, that the body may rise out of its mire and share in the soul's purity
               and lightness. Those who concern themselves with the nourishment of their
               bodies, thinking that it is a good thing, are weaving a rope of pigskin and<pb n="204"/>
               throwing it round their own necks, and giving the end of it to Satan to
               drag them to torment</quote>. But, while he was delighting us with such words,
            he would abstain even from the scanty quantity of food that he was in
            the habit of taking. But his recitation of service was one which lasted
            without ceasing from the first hour in the night' until morning, while during
            every <foreign>marmitha</foreign>? he would make thirty Egyptian genuflexions which are
            called prayers, until he accomplished five hundred during the night with
            the service of matins; and these I myself on many nights secretly counted
            without his discovering me; because I too also occupied a cell behind
            his cell, and there was only a partition between me and him, while we were
            some distance from the common chapel of the brotherhood, together with
            the virtuous men Stephen and Zwṭʾ, and we alone lived in cells. The first
            time that I heard the sound of his <foreign xml:lang="grc">petávolal</foreign>' behind my cell, since he used to<pb n="205"/>
            make three knocks in quick succession, the sound would come to me just as
            if three men were striking together upon a smith's anvil with hammers, the
            sounds following one another till morning, since his hands first struck
            the ground, and after them his knees, and lastly his head; and so he would
            suddenly sink down, until I thought that the sound was coming up from
            beneath me, while I even crossed myself and said, <quote>Perhaps Satan is
               mocking me, and is making me hear this sound in order to deceive me</quote>;
            and I would go outside by night, and would hear the sound; and I would
            come in again, and there was the same sound. And, because the blessed
            man showed great care and earnestness in charging and entreating everyone,
            <quote>Let not a man approach the door of my cell till the morning, because
               I am a very bad sleeper, and, if I am aware that any one is passing round
               the place where I am sleeping, it is quite impossible for me to sleep
               again, and I am tormented the whole night</quote><!-- missing in translation -->, on account of this charge
            therefore no one approached his cell, lest he should annoy him, since
            we thought that it was as he said; but he wished to act by stealth
            and not be discovered by stealth.
         </p>
         <p>
            I therefore, keeping the charge, and being for many nights annoyed by
            the sound, from the first hour of the night till morning, wondered greatly.
            But one day, not having suflicient resolution to endure that sound which
            had lasted many days and take no notice, I went outside and stood still,
            listening to the sound; and I softly approached the door, and found that it
            was he, who was pressed down under all this labour, panting as if he were
            running before a horse; and I was greatly amazed at this man's labour.
            But his bed was magnificently laid, and raised high by the number of its
            rugs, and he had wrapt himself in a little piece of hair-matting fitted to
            his stature as iſ under his feet (?), and on it he rested so far as he slept at
            all, while to us he presented the appearance of really sleeping on his bed.
            And from that time I like an idle man would often keep count of the industrious 
            man's prayers, both those of the night and those of the day. And
            thenceforward the virtuous men Stephen and Zwṭʾ' the deacons made it their
            endeavour to imitate him in everything, and they themselves also underwent
            great labours. When then they had thereafter made preparations to set<pb n="207"/>
            forth to the land of Egypt, and to live there as before, queen Theodora, who
            had been in intercourse with the blessed Stephen the deacon both before she
            became queen and after she had become queen, sent magistrians' after him
            and a letter, earnestly inviting him to come up to the capital in order to be
            with her in the palace (Traditiov), because of his eloquence and his conversation
            and his wisdom, and moreover because he also lived a pure life and after the
            manner of a solitary; and this further hastened them in making their departure. 
            Then they left the district of the East, and I also with them in intercourse 
            with them, as far as Antioch. And there Stephen thenceforth continued 
            to entreat Thomas, saying, <quote>My brethren, let us on no account. part
               from one another; but, in order that this woman's will may not be disappointed, 
               let us go up together to the royal city, and return and go down
               together by sea to the desert</quote>. But he, declining to do this, continued
            entreating him and saying: <quote>Pray for me, my brother, since Thomas will
               not see anyone from this kingdom here</quote>. And so with weeping and many<pb n="208"/>
            sobs they parted from one another, while the blessed Stephen was entreating 
            him and saying: <quote>Pray for me, my brother, that I may sobs be dismissed
               from that city and come down to you, and we may end our lives together
               in the convent of solitaries'</quote>. But the holy Thomas, shedding tears and
            sobbing, said to him: <quote>Beware, my brother, and take care of your soul;
               and day by day, as far as in you lies, entreat God in penitence for your sins.
               Let not your thoughts mock you and say to you, <quote>You shall go out to the
                  desert and pray to God</quote>; because you shall never see the desert again; but
               neither indeed shall we meet one another in the body any more; and you will
               live in the royal city till the end of your life. Accordingly pray for me</quote>.
            And they prayed, and they set out at the same time, while the blessed
            Thomas said, <quote>As, when we left our country, we enjoined upon our kinsmen
               (yévos) and everyone to suppose that they were thus following us to the
               grave, so, my brother, in this hour also do you think that you are following
               me to the grave and you</quote>. And, while we were all listening to these
            things, the tears of us all burst forth with sobs. And thus they for their<pb n="209"/>
            part separated, each of them to his own quarter; and I returned again to the
            convent, intending by making petition to obtain leave, and betake myself
            soon to the blessed Thomas. And after my return I was a petitioner for two
            years; and, on account of the great love that the blessed men bore towards
            me, scarcely with difficulty did they allow me to go'. On reaching the city
            of Alexandria we learned about the life of the blessed Thomas, and about his
            marvellous habits; and we went out to him to the desert called that of Mendis, 
            twelve miles above the habitation of the holy Mar Menas?. But, when
            we arrived and I saw the blessed man, I scarcely recognised him, while I
            looked at him and was in doubt if it was really he, since his whole body was
            black and burnt by the sun, and all his hair was scorched and standing on
            end, and he was clad in one old garment of rags, and one ugly little hood was
            bound round his face. And, when he saw me, he was astounded, and fell
            on his face; and he came up and gripped us; and we greeted one another,
            while I was still not sure that it was he, until at last I fixed my gaze on him;<pb n="210"/>
            and I was seized with astonishment to think to what all that luxury had come.
            And, while he was exuberant with joy and was asking me, <quote>What have
               you to say, father? what has brought you to the sinners?</quote>, I was looking
            at him in astonishment, saying to him, <quote>What has happened to you that
               your body is thus burnt, our father?</quote> But he after these things bent his
            looks downward and shed tears; and he said to me; <quote>Would, our brother,
               that my outward body might be burnt, and not my soul that is stained with
               the evil deeds that I have done from my childhood and down to the present
               time.</quote> After we had remained a short time, about three months, occasion
            called us on our side to return again to Syria; and so we received the blessing
            of the saint, together with all the rest of the saints in the whole of the desert
            in which he was living, together with that of the blessed Zwṭʾ the deacon;
            and we left them, and returned, promising them that we would return again
            to them. And thus we parted, we to our vain occupation, and they to their
            spiritual employment. And, when twenty six years' had been completed<pb n="211"/>
            by the holy Thomas in such great labours, in order that the conflict (ayców)
            against his distresses which he displayed by means of his endurance might
            be further increased, he fell for about eight months under the chastisement
            of an illness; and then the blessed man finished his conflict (życów); and he
            departed carrying the great and honoured burden of his triumphs; and we
            were not again granted the privilege of seeing his face in the body. But he
            left in his place after him the blessed Zwṭʾ the deacon; who also passed out
            of this disturbing and deceiving world in the same desert with great labours
            and noble triumphs in the third year after the passing of the blessed
            Thomas. And so, after we parted from them and down to the passing of
            each one of them, both they and we were day by day in hope that we should
            be coming back to them; and so our sins brought it about for us that we did
            not come to the place where they lived till a year after the death of both.
            But we, after we had gone down to Syria, went up again to the royal city;
            and we also found the blessed virtuous Stephen too'; who also did not fail
            to obtain the glory that is gained by great labours of asceticism and of
            abstinence; and who was moreover a great harbour (2.bp.hv) of rest for all the<pb n="212"/>
            afflicted who used to repair to him from all quarters, and a comforter of all
            the distressed, and a noble example to all men; so that even the king and
            queen themselves stood in awe of his venerable mode of life, and they executed 
            his orders in everything; and thus his cell had in consequence become
            a house of rest for strangers. And, while half a denarius (nuíosov) a day
            was allotted to his table, besides the cost (avancópata) of his bondservants in
            addition to other matters, so this was not large enough for the expenditure
            on the strangers and the needy who used to come to him; and not only so,
            but to the senators (Guyxan Fixo) themselves he was a great comfort and support;
            and he was very well-known all over the city, but especially in the palace
            (max=toy). And when the sentence of pestilence went forth upon the world
            from God', he also too was carried off in it by the command; and in his
            cell as the property of a man who might be supposed to have more than five
            hundred pounds' weight (zeytnvéprov) of gold” nothing whatever was found
            after his death except a <foreign>denarius</foreign> and a half. And, while men supposed that
            he had money and the coins had been taken by others, there was found a<pb n="213"/>
            tablet (TIT TÍZOV) inscribed in his hand as follows: <quote>Lest anyone suspect me
               or accuse anyone else in any matter, I write these things with my hand, that
               I am prepared to give account to God on the day of judgment that neither
               at a distance nor close at hand do I possess anything in the world except
               this <foreign>denarius</foreign> and a half; and let this go to the poor</quote>.
            And thus everyone was seized with astonishment, insomuch that some time afterwards everyone 
            used to speak of these things with wonder.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the saints Thomas and Stephen and Zwṭʾ, the <foreign>syncelli</foreign> and notaries
            (vo ráp:05) of the holy Mare metropolitan of the city of Amida, is ended.
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
