<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/807">Two Monks</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/807.xml -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            Great caution therefore is required of us, my brethren, to provide that
            we may escape from the craftiness of the evil one, and again, that we may
            fear the divine words (especially men who are highly reputed for modes of
            life or for knowledge), when they caution us and say: <quote>Let him that standeth
               take heed lest he fall</quote>?. For the sake then of cautioning those who are
            running on the road of virtue, I have determined to commit to record an
            act also that is well worthy to be an object of great commiseration which the
            <pb n="221"/><pb n="221"/>fiends did to two brothers who were in truth running with all their strength
            in the way of virtue, and whom the fiends made such a laughing-stock that
            the like was never heard among men of older or of recent times. These blessed 
            men therefore, that is one of them especially, who was called James<note></note>,
            – this man employed himself in a marvellous way in the same community
            in great practices of standing and of watching and of abstinence and great
            quietude; and he came from the convent called that of the Edessenes adjoining
            Amida itself?. And this brother was so laborious and humble and meek
            that these seven hundred men<note></note> were all amazed at his labours, and at his
            asceticism; so that I also was with him on the weekly duties“, and particularly 
            marvelled at his gentleness and his quietude, and further at the way
            in which he crucified his body by night and by day. This man then had
            many who for the purpose of imitating his modes of life used to attach
            themselves to him and keep themselves close to him. And, while he was of
            <pb n="222"/><pb n="222"/>this character, as God himself knows, possessed persons were found to come
            outside the gate, and wail before him, and say: <quote>James drives us out, and
               it is he who expels us</quote>. When he and many besides heard these things,
            they continued laughing at these demons, and saying: <quote>See these evil beings,
               how they deceive and mock</quote>. Then the great seniors who were there,
            inasmuch as they knew the craftiness of the demons, commanded that they
            should be driven from the place. But they contended the more and said,
            <quote>James bound us and brought us here; and we cannot depart before he
               releases us</quote>, while they had not seen James at all. Then they came in,
            and say to him: <quote>Release these fiend-possessed persons that they may go
               hence, since they are pestering us</quote>. But he crossed himself, and said:
            <quote>What is it that you say, my brethren, since I do not understand it?</quote> But
            they continued in the same way to press him to go out and make the sign
            over them, saying: <quote>Perhaps these souls will receive deliverance</quote>. While
            he on his side continued declining and repudiating this proposal, they on the
            other hand continued to press bim the more to do this, <quote>that they may only
               <pb n="223"/><pb n="223"/>depart hence</quote>. And, when under great pressure he went out, these persons
            saw him, and began to foam; and he came up and made the sign over them,
            and immediately these persons were healed from that hour, and they departed.
            And thenceforth a multitude used to repair thither foaming, men and women,
            and boys and girls, and all ages; and from that time he was under the necessity 
            (vbyxn) of going out. But he on his side would go out to a certain small
            martyrs' chapel outside the gate, and would fill it; and he would put them
            to silence and drive them out one by one; and the persons from whom they
            came out no longer suffered from them. And thus he would drive them out
            in countless numbers; and they would come outside and cause annoyance,
            and cry out. And, if it was not in his power to come out, he would send
            them an order to go and lie down in that martyrs' chapel till he came out.
            And thus they would go away foaming, and would lie down there; and, if
            he waited two days, none of them dared to stretch himself out or to remove
            from the place till he came out. But, when the numbers of those who used
            to come there and cause annoyance increased, there were agitations there
            against this blessed man, both on the part of the inmates of his monastery
            <pb n="224"/><pb n="224"/>and also on the part of others; and accordingly he wished to give up this
            business, and could not, on account of the multitude who used to come.
            And in consequence of such annoyances it became necessary (évbyxn) for
            him to withdraw from the community; and so he withdrew under the instigation 
            (I believe) of the demons themselves, in company with the other who
            was attached to him, and they set out, and went in the direction of Hamimtha<note></note>, 
            to a certain village called Beth Musika<note></note>; and they had a certain
            monastery that was there given to them, and they resided in it. And in a
            similar way again there also multitudes began to flock together to them;
            and then also the blessed James would again command them authoritatively,
            and by means of his word demons without number were expelled. Then the
            evil one, who by means of his crafty tricks finds methods of deceiving men,
            contrived a method of making a mockery of these blessed men. One
            night, when the possessed persons were assembled there, there was also a
            certain young woman there of whom he had taken possession, who was also
            of worldly appearance<note></note>. Her accordingly the demons took, and they clothed
            <pb n="225"/><pb n="225"/>her in awe-striking forms of phantasmal<note></note> rays; and they led her up and
            seated her on the bishops' throne (Opóvos), which is usually placed in the
            churches or in the chief martyrs' chapels on the dais (zatátpop.x) of the altar.
            Then they filled the whole martyrs' chapel again with phantasmal<note></note> forms,
            as if forsooth they were angels of God; and some of them flew away and
            entered the chapel? where the blessed men were sleeping; and there also as
            well they emitted rays with the appearance of light, according to the text
            <quote>maketh himself like an angel of light</quote>s. And they roused the blessed men
            and urged them to haste, hastily alarming them and saying, <quote>Take incense,
               incense, and haste to the martyrs' chapel; for the holy Mary the God-bearer
               has been sent to you, with a great host of angels; and she has sent us for
               you, come straightway</quote>. But the blessed men were terrified by the sight,
            not perceiving the craftiness of the evil one; and they hurriedly took incense
            and spices, and ran to the martyrs' chapel; and on entering they found the
            whole house full of phantasmal<note></note> forms, in the semblance forsooth of angels
            <pb n="226"/><pb n="226"/>of brilliant light, and the woman moreover sitting on the throne (Opóvos),
            and a semblance of light flashing from her; and their wits were yet more
            taken from them by reason of their agitation, and they fell on their faces.
            Then (it is said) she that was sitting commanded them<note></note> to approach and raise
            them up; and the fiends approached and took hold of their hands, and they
            say to them: <quote>Rise, for she has commanded you; and approach, and make
               obeisance to her</quote>. And they on their part rose smitten with fear and robbed
            of their wits by the sight; and they approached and made obeisance on their
            faces, as if they supposed that they saw a genuine sight. But that young
            woman, being unaware even herself of what had happened, spoke with them
            (that is, the fiend spoke in her), and said to them: <quote>Come, approach me,
               and fear not. I myself am Mary the Mother of Christ; and my Son sent me
               to you, because he saw your righteousness and your love toward him, and
               that you are perfect in your modes of life; and he commanded me to ordain
               you, and that you should receive the priesthood from me because of your
               virtuousness. But come approach and receive it</quote>. But they, inasmuch as
            they supposed that they had in truth been granted some heavenly privilege
            <pb n="227"/><pb n="227"/>beyond other men, approached, and bowed their heads; and she rose, and laid
            her hand upon the heads of both of them, and said to them: <quote>You have both
               received from me the presbyterate. You have been made presbyters, perform
               the functions of your priesthood</quote>. When the fiends had done this, a sound
            of great laughter was heard in the air (áhe), since the demons were saying,
            <quote>Those who used to drive us out have to-day become as they supposed
               great</quote>. And at the same cry that girl was stripped of the phantasms (paviaGías), 
            and it was found that it was a girl who was a Greek who was sitting
            on the throne (Osóvos), and it was she who had done these things. When
            these men saw what had happened to them and came to their senses, they
            continued beating on their faces and saying: <quote>Woe to us! what has happened
               to us? Anything like this deceit never happened to men before. What to
               do, we know not</quote>. But, when they brought that young woman down from
            the throne (Opóvos), she continued laughing at them at the instigation of the
            demon and saying: <quote>What has come to you? Why are you troubled?</quote> . But
            they on their side resolved to find means of subjecting their case to the cure
            of penitence; and they left that place, weeping and sobbing at what had
            <pb n="228"/><pb n="228"/>happened to them, and they went down to Marde to the holy John bishop of
            Thella<note></note>, who ended his life in the conflicts (àyców) of persecution for Christ's
            sake. And, when they informed him of the affair, even the blessed man
            also marvelled at the wily, crafty artfulness of the rebellious evil beings.
            But he received them, and laid upon them three years' penance, and then
            they were to be admitted to communion. And from that time again they
            led even more severe lives than before, with sorrow and tears, until they
            attained to their former standing, and were admitted to the communion
            that is obtained by absolution. These things which we have written we have
            not received through hearsay, but they are all matters which were enacted
            in our knowledge and in our presence and before our eyes”, and we have
            brought comparatively few of them to the record of writing on account of
            the length of the narrative, that a man who is granted any gift may be
            especially cautious against the craft of the adversary, who uses all artifices
            in plotting to deceive.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of two brothers from the selſsame community at the same time
            of persecution is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
