<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/810">A Monk who Left the Monastery</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/810.xml -->
         <head>Next the Eighteenth History, of a Certain Brother Who Left
            A Convent Without Being Released<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n260-1"/>, and Betook Himself to Another.</head>
         <p>
            If therefore I cover with silence a sentence that was pronounced in a
            terrible story which I saw<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n260-2"/>, which was enacted in the case of one of the
            blessed brothers, I do not think that I also shall be freed from the sentence
            of blame that proceeds from justice. When formerly the community of those
            who had been everywhere expelled on account of the faith were celebrated,
            and the spiritual community of the diocese of <placeName>Amida</placeName>, that of these greatbl
            convents, were gathered together in great numbers in the village of <placeName>Ḥzyn</placeName> in
            <placeName>Ṭyšfʾ</placeName>, as we have indeed recorded these matters in one of the histories<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n260-3"/>,
            and blessed men from everywhere desired to join that spiritual unity, and
            the blessed men did not keep their door shut, but received everyone, it
            happened that a certain <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1932">blessed man</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n260-4"/> came thither, who by his habit (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>)
            <pb n="261"/><pb n="261"/>was an anchorite, and this man desired to be received in one of the convents
            in obedience<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-1"/>, and remain. And on his tendering this request to one of the
            blessed archimandrites he examined him as to his monastic training, and if he
            were in any other obedience, or barred by any impediment. But that
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1932">blessed man</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-2"/> on seeing the thoroughness of that examination was afraid to
            confess that he had not been released, lest he should fail to obtain what he
            desired and not be received; and therefore he said that he had been released
            from his monastery, when he had not been released; but as if by the grace of
            God, which knew the sentence that threatened that wretched man, it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-3"/> caused
            him to state the name of his monastery without falsehood<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-4"/>. And thus he
            was received, and entered the convent in obedience. At that time a great
            pestilence broke out<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-5"/>; and, as commonly happened, many died there from
            that community, insomuch that eighty-four men from the convents themselves,
            besides guests, died there, and were laid in the grave. And after twenty
            days the lot reached the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1932">blessed man</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-2"/> who had been received; and he was.
            <pb n="262"/><pb n="262"/>suddenly smitten, and was struck dumb, while his soul was convulsed and
            snorts proceeded from his throat, and he was bereſt of his senses and was in
            torture, not being among the dead or among the living. And, whereas it was
            the custom, when the end was overtaking a man and he was in great pain,
            for five or ten to meet together, and set down incense and make propitiation
            for him for the other transgressions, and, if he were still in pain, they would
            bring the holy gospel (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εύαγγελιον</foreign>) and lay it upon him, and immediately he
            would be released either to life or to death, this poor man, in order that the
            text, <quote>The word of God is living and doeth all things, etc.</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-1"/>, might be
            understood by actual facts, gained no release when the blessed men met
            together and made petition and prayer and much incense and many forms of
            propitiation. And the Lord of the world<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-2"/> even came and relics of the saints,
            and there was no release, nor relaxation from that intense, terrible, painful
            convulsion for ten days, insomuch that a hundred and twenty men were thus
            ranged round him, and were standing and marvelling, and weeping and
            <pb n="263"/><pb n="263"/>distressing themselves at the agitation of that soul, and at that terrible and
            violent driving; and from distress and grief they sat thus round him two and
            three days, marvelling and weeping, and not eating or drinking, and despising
            all human life. But, when it had lasted ten days, Grace in accordance with its
            mercy effected deliverance, that is, the release of that agitated soul, when on
            the tenth day all the seniors had met together and had stationed themselves
            round him with the Lord of the world<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n263-1"/>, and prayers and petitions and copious
            tears, while all who were standing there cried with affliction and said:
            <quote>Lord, great is thy mercy. Sufficient is this torture for this man. Let thy
               mercy persuade thee on his behalf, God who carest for thy creation</quote>. The.
            chief of the seniors, while standing over him and weeping, was saying these
            words, while my wretchedness also was standing and forming part of that
            sorrowful gathering and hearing him say in the midst of his sobs: <quote>What to
               do to you, afflicted man, we know not, in order to ask you <quote>Is it because<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n263-2"/> you
                  are conscious in your soul of grievous delinquencies that you are dying and
                  departing from life, and only torture remains for you in the bodily life?</quote>, and
               <pb n="264"/><pb n="264"/>to say <quote>Is there an impediment upon you and is your soul bound by it?</quote>.
               Who will inform us of this, unless the abụndant mercy of your Creator have
               pity on you?</quote>. Then again, as if by divine instigation, the other senior
            who was standing at the other side of his bed said: <quote>I, sir, think that
               this agitation of this soul is an impediment proceeding from the word of
               God</quote>. And, when he had said this, like one who is suddenly struck by his
            neighbour and roughly dragged out of deep sleep, he was smitten with
            stupefaction and suddenly quivered and nodded his head once. And, everyone
            being astounded, the senior again repeated: <quote>Is there an impediment
               upon you, agitated one?</quote>, and Grace caused him again to nod his head once,
            while his eyes dried up and there was nothing to show even that they existed.
            Then the blessed men deliberated: <quote>Even if this man is already a dead
               man, yet the divine grace has let us know that his soul is impeded by the
               word of God; and what shall we do? If we were accepted as ourselves
               making the release in place of the man who laid the bond, we have done so
               many times. But come now let us fetch a man, and let us all stand sureties
               in him that, God willing, we will send a petition to his archimandrite to release
               <pb n="265"/><pb n="265"/>him. Perhaps the merciful God will accept us, and release him from this
               torture</quote>. And, when they had determined upon these things, a certain
            deacon whose name was Addai rose, and came and knelt before his bed, and
            said: <quote>If God be willing to grant me life till I go and make the release, I will
               under the security of all my fathers take this soul's impediment upon myself</quote>.
            And, as the words that came from the mouth of that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1932">blessed man</persName> ended,
            then the release and the departure of that soul from its body also took place;
            and there was a great and terrible and mighty cry, while everyone was amazed
            and praised God. And so the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1932">blessed man</persName> exerted himself and travelled
            rapidly, and fulfilled his promise; and on the tenth day that agitated man was
            buried, while all marvelled and wondered at the things that had happened.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of a certain brother who left a monastery without being
            released and betook himself to another is ended.
         </p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n260-1">BH <hi rend="singleQuote">his rule (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κανών</foreign>) having been relaxed</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n260-2">Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n260-3">Ch. 14; cf. ch. 35. The date is 522-526 (See Introd.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n260-4">BH <hi rend="singleQuote">brother</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-1">I.e. as an inmate, not as a guest.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-2">BH <hi rend="singleQuote">brother</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-3">Sic syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-4">The rule had been lightened since Severus' time, when a monk was free to leave his monastery at any time (<title>Sel. Letters</title>, p. 451).</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-5">This clearly cannot be the great plague of 542, but must be an earlier epidemic not otherwise known.</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-1">Hebr., IV, 12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-2">The scribes of BH (or the scribe of the archetype of B and H) appy. understood this to mean the gospel (see p. 263, n.); but the consecreated elements must surely be intended.</note>
            <note xml:id="n263-1">BH <hi rend="singleQuote">gospel</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n263-2">Ms. om.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
