<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/814">Addai and Abraham</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/814.xml -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            These blessed men Addai and Abraham therefore were brothers on the
            mother's side, and at first they remained under training in a convent for
            several years; and afterwards they formed the resolution of going out on
            pilgrimage. And, when they had been thus going about for several years,
            they began to deliberate between themselves, saying, <quote>Wherefore do we
               thus go aimlessly about, and not show labour for our Lord, and erect places
               for his praise?</quote> And so, as they were going about, they found a certain
            place that was a convenient site for a monastery, and they planted their cross
            there, and made a cabin; and they asked for iron tools, and began to dig out
            a site for a martyrs' chapel. And, when the people of the district saw and
            heard it, they repaired to them from all quarters, providing money and wood
            and everything that was useful. And in one year they erected an extensive
            convent in that place, and they also gained disciples; and when they saw it
            they rejoiced, and they say: <quote>Now it is better for us than roving and
               going about aimlessly</quote>. And, when they had trained some men and taught
            them the psalms, and shown them how to conduct affairs, they conceived the
            plan of leaving them there as it were to govern themselves and depar<pb n="300"/>ting, 
            and erecting another place. And thus they continued doing for twenty-five 
            years, during which they erected twelve monasteries; most of which
            I know, which they erected in the district, and the rest, because they were
            some way off, I have not seen; but the men I saw at last in that in which
            the blessed Addai who was the elder died, and I was for some time in intercourse 
            with them, and they said, <quote>This is the twelfth monastery that we
               have erected, since we devoted ourselves to this object</quote>. And in each of
            them this is what they used to do. As soon as it was built, they would
            obtain everything that they could for it, and appoint an archimandrite in it,
            and then depart. But at last the blessed Addai fell asleep in the twelfth.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of Addai and Abraham the zealous brothers is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
