<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/815">Simeon the Solitary</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/815.xml -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            This blessed Simeon therefore used to occupy himself with great and
            marvellous practices in a convent adjoining the city of Amida, being distinguished 
            for quietude and humility and obedience, and love of all spiritual<pb n="301"/>
            labours, and especially the service of the saints, and great and abounding
            love towards all poor men and strangers. But, when he had completed
            twenty years in these heavenly practices, he desired to adopt the life of a
            solitary; and he set out and went to a certain mountain two miles from the
            city; and he passed the night at a certain spot. And there he prayed and
            traced the plan of some cabins for himself, and he began and built some huts
            there that were very marvellous, being supplied by many persons with all
            that he needed; and thereafter he used to carry out all the marvellous labours
            of his honoured course of life. But on account of the abundance of his
            charity and the love of strangers and poor men that burned in him he would
            not consent to make a court or gates for his huts, saying, <quote>Thus it will be
               open to Christ my Lord when he comes to me to enter my dwelling in the
               person of his bondmen simply and without impediment; that so he may grant
               me the blessing of his favour</quote>. And so much was this saint smitten with
            the love of God, and with the love of his brethren, that, when occasion called
            bim to leave his huts, he did not close the door and conceal any one of the
            articles of furniture in his cell, but also he used to do a thing that is particularly 
            great and splendid and marvellous to hear, when it happened that
            he was absent were it one day or two or three from his cell. Not only did<pb n="302"/>
            he not trouble himself to bring in any one article of furniture in his cell, but
            also on the day on which he left his cell he would first cook food, and would
            lay a table, and moisten bread and temper wine, and put it out, and a tablet
            inscribed and laid on the top of it as follows (which we have also often read),
            on which were these words: <quote>Welcome, our brothers, Christ's bondmen;
               come into your bondman's house confidently and refresh yourselves, and
               hesitate not. Since occasion has called me the sinner to go on necessary
               service, here is a present of what is required to satisfy need from the gift of
               our Benefactor set ready. For the sake of his true love, whether it is one or
               many whom Christ my Lord is preparing and sending to his bondman's house,
               shrink not from coming in and satisfying all your need, though I myself
               am absent in the body. If it be possible for him to wait till I come, I beg
               him to do so; if not, let him refresh himself out of our Lord's gift and bless
               the Giver, and leave us the blessing of his prayers, and thus go in peace;
               and, if he need anything else besides, lo! the whole cell is committed to
               Christ's hands, and at his hands let him satisfy all his need without restraint
               from everything that is in it. But let him leave this writing of ours in its
               place for the rest of our brethren who shall arrive in order to inform them<pb n="303"/>
               also</quote>. And so the fame of this saint's great charity was spoken of over
            the whole of the city and that district. But once two young men who were
            passing came, and they found the huts open, and no one was to be seen all
            round; and they went in and ate and drank, and the rest they put into their
            packs; and they loaded themselves, and started to go. And, when they had
            passed out of the door, their feet stuck there, and they stood still bearing
            their loads till the evening and standing erect; and they became incapable
            of moving, or of laying down their loads until the blessed man came. And
            on seeing them from a distance he understood what had happened; and they
            themselves cried with a loud voice and say, <quote>Sir, have mercy on us for we
               have sinned against you, and forgive us</quote>. But the blessed man immediately
            raised his eyes to heaven, and prayed, and said: <quote>Lord, deliver thy creatures, 
               and free them from the deceitful teaching of the enemy; and remove
               from them the teacher of evil who incited them to these things</quote>. And
            the same hour they were released, and fell on their faces before him. And
            he on his side said these words to them: <quote>Knew you not, my sons, that I
               had committed this cell to Christ my Lord, and him nothing escapes? or
               know you not that, wherever Christ's name is called, everyone who presumes<pb n="304"/>
               to stretch out his hand and lay it upon anything has to deal with God the
               Judge of all? And now, my sons, go and beware </quote>. And so he dismissed
            them'. And the fame of the saint's triumphs was spoken of everywhere.
            But afterwards the storm (ravu.ców) of persecution was stirred up against the
            same blessed man also together with all the rest of the church; and he
            bravely and heroically contended in the conflicts (šytóv), while all the convents 
            were overcome and defeated by the persecution, and driven from the
            whole district? And he himself held firm; and thus he persevered and
            maintained a heroic contest; and he used to go about the city itself at
            the very height of the persecution, and give absolution and baptize
            night and day, while he had previously determined this also, that nothing
            should enter his belly except from the labour of his hands; but he used
            to labour with his hands in proportion to his own needs, and those of
            the other strangers whom he was in the habit of receiving in secret and
            relieving out of his labour. And thus he contended several years while
            occupied in this labour; and he ended his life with this reputation, in the
            triumph of heroism, while contending until death on behalf of the truth.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the blessed Simeon the solitary is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
