<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/817">John of Hephaestopolis</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/817 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            Since the purpose of our work and the course of our history aims at
            showing and describing the circumstances of the perfect lives which the saints
            lived, therefore we say that in the order of our history we will insert spiritual
            pastors<note></note>, and will also in our work state the circumstances of their activity
            <pb n="527"/><pb n="325"/>in God's church, since they also were complete and perfect in both forms of
            beauty<note></note>; and for this reason, though we seem to be passing from one subject
            to another, we did not think it alien to the excellent purpose to describe and
            hand down to remembrance for the glory of God the life that was practised
            by these divine men also.
         </p>
         <p>
            This blessed man again, the great and divine John the bishop, was by
            his birth (yvos) a Syrian, that is a Palestinian, from tlhe city of Gaza, and he
            lived in a great convent called that of father Peter the Iberian, the doer of
            great and apostolic signs. This convent was expelled with the rest, and
            came into the territory of Alexandria; and there it lived in a place called
            Ennaton which means 'ninth<note></note>, viz. miles<note></note>; and there the saint dwelt with the
            rest of his convent, living a devout life and following great and divine practices.
            While the church was still at peace in Alexandria, and the blessed Theodosius
            was seated on his throne<note></note>, he heard of his manner of life and of his teaching,
            and sent and seized him and made him bishop in one of the cities of Egypt
            which is called Hephaestu. After a period of such-and-such a number of
            <pb n="528"/><pb n="326"/>years during which the blessed man had distinguished himself in his pastorate, 
            to which he had been called by the providence of God against his own
            will, preparations for persecutions were then stirred up against her whom
            one of the doctors names <quote>the Egyptian virgin</quote><note></note>, and severe fighting and
            much slaughter took place in it, as is common in that great city; and the blessed
            archbishop Theodosius with the rest of the eminent men of his jurisdiction
            were driven from their sees, and they were also invited to the royal city and
            went up thither through certain eminent men attached to the court, the
            adversaries thinking that by threats or blandishments they might perhaps
            bring them to communicate with them<note></note>. And, when they resisted strenuously
            and they were unable to overcome the constancy that was in their souls, a
            well-known<note></note> and cruel place of exile (opia) was then given to the holy
            archbishop himself and the whole of his company (cuvodía), the bishops with
            the most eminent clergy (xλñpos), about three hundred of them, in the interior
            of Thrace a day's journey (p.avcíwv) off, a certain fortress (xάoτρa) called
            Dercus, to which also we often used to go to visit the same saints, as well as
            the blessed man the perfect and great old man Zʿura the celebrated Syrian
            <pb n="529"/><pb n="327"/>from the country of Sophanene<note></note>, who also was confined with them; and
            thenceforth they were kept in custody there, though the Christ-loving
            Theodora, who was perhaps appointed queen by God to be a support for the
            persecuted against the cruelty of the times, showed great attention to them.
            as well as the other persecuted men everywhere, supplying them with
            provisions and liberal allowances (%vauarx).
         </p>
         <p>
            While these men were suffering distress there, and every where also the
            believers in all quarters were similarly suffering, they used to betake 
            themselves from all quarters to the royal city itself, firstly on account of the
            persecutions in all quarters, and secondly for the sake of ordination (etpotovía),
            as there was absolutely no man to extend a hand of ordination to any believer
            in the whole Roman territory as far as the Persian frontier; and accordingly
            many used to go to the same saints in Thrace, lamenting and representing
            their trouble; but even there they gained no hearing, as it was indeed in
            truth impossible for them to live if an ordination (ystpovovtx) were performed
            there, if the adversaries heard of it. But this holy John, when he heard
            these things, would shed bitter tears every day for the distress of Christ's
            <pb n="530"/><pb n="328"/>church, insomuch he that would often say in our presence: <quote>We for our
               part have been named pastors of God's church to no purpose, since we have
               suffered her lambs to be torn by wolves, and have come and sat down by
               ourselves, and have not consented to die for the sake of religion. What is
               the benefit that we ourselves are now doing to God's church? for lo! we are
               unwilling to cure or heal even those that come to us buffeted and bruised
               from a journey of sixty days</quote>. And these things he would say weeping, <quote>I
                  stand in awe of him who is the head'; otherwise, as Christ lives, nothing
                  would have prevented me from performing ordination (etpotovíx) in the great
                  church of the city if I had found opportunity, or in an open space (?) (xpos) in
                  the city in the sight of all men</quote><note></note>. When many were coming every day, and
            he continually heard the same things and could not contain himself, he was
            moved with zeal and his spirit was roused, and he said: <quote>Far be it from
               me in the Lord's name to hold aloof longer and pay no heed to the affliction
               of Christ's flock which was bought by his precious blood"; for, even if I die
               on its behalf, it is a boast to me</quote>. Then he concocted pretexts, and under
            pretexts of illnesses he went and begged the patriarch and the custodians for
            permission to go into the city to see physicians; and, because they heard
            <pb n="531"/><pb n="329"/>mention of illness, therefore they did not prevent him from going, and this
            matter also about the cause of his coming was made known to the queen; and
            by divine dispensation she also received him with great joy, and she gave
            orders that spacious quarters (µétatov) also should be given him in the great
            mansion called Anthemiu<note></note>, and an allowance (żváλwpx) also for him and his
            slave should be assigned to him there. And thenceforth the will and the
            zeal of the blessed man found expression; and from that time companies of
            those who were in distress, and had been for a long time beaten and buffeted
            and had none to relieve them, betook themselves to him, and he would dismiss
            them all and they would return to their own countries with joy, while he also
            anointed many altars that had been set up for a long time to be anointed and
            go to the countries, and himself also fixed an altar, and he was filled with
            great boldness (Tappncia) showing keen enthusiasm and confidence that contends
            with death. When he had stood up and become openly known, envy like
            Cain's was sown in the hearts of many who were inside and not outside; and
            they used to address mandates to him, saying, <quote>We are standing in a lion's
               mouth, and you are causing him to rend us all and cast us away in one hour</quote>.
            <pb n="532"/><pb n="330"/>But he said, <quote>As for the lion that is coming let no man stand before him;
               let him send him against me myself only; since it is I as you say that have
               provoked him, and God will do as he wishes. The mouths of lions are wont
               to be closed by command from on high'</quote> And so he did not cease from his
            zealousness. But afterwards they wrote to his patriarch also as well to
            inhibit him. But the saint, who saw his zeal, and on his own side also was
            not displeased by the saving and refreshing of the believers, passed over
            the sayings that were concocted against the same blessed man without notice,
            saying, <quote>He has gone away from my presence, and is in the city, and the
               queen also has received him; and she further knows that I have not ordered
               him to do such things.</quote> And so he took no account of the matter as one
            that knew it and did not know it. But the holy John would accept all who
            came from all quarters, that is on the testimony of those who presented them;
            and, though they were strangers, he did not immediately apply a hand of
            ordination without witnesses and persons to present. But, when those whose
            envy... saw it, and he also made them hostile to him, who were believers,
            members of his company (cuvodía), and some of them also even bishops, they
            <pb n="533"/><pb n="331"/>went and told the queen about him, having concocted a petition purporting
            to come from him that she would give him an order to leave the city for a
            short time. And she, inasmuch as she thought that he was perhaps in need
            of recreation, in order to gratify him, gave the order, and she also wrote,
            <quote>Go</quote>. But these men took the order, and formed a plan to catch the blessed
            man by terror by means of the order, in that they went and they say to him as
            if speaking in the person (ρóблov) of the queen, <quote>Do not linger another hour
               in this city or see my face; otherwise you will die. And the order has
               reached yourself (?), lest you die an evil death; since you have been accused
               to the king, and he ordered your death.</quote> But the intelligent man, inasmuch
            as he was in truth ready for death, determined <quote>If I depart, be it to death
               or to life, I will not depart before I go into the palace (αλátiov) and know
               the truth</quote>. Then he made these men think that he had been frightened
            and was packing his things to depart; and he went out and left them, and
            went down and came to the palace (rchácov) without these men heing avare
            of it; and he went in confidently before the queen with the great boldness
            (Tapincía) of the heavenly King, manifesting wrath also and threats against
            the king and queen on account of all the persecution of the believers. And,
            when the queen saw him, she was alarmed at his wrath, and says: <quote>Who
               <pb n="534"/><pb n="332"/>has injured you, sir? What is this affair?</quote>. And he said : <quote>Who has
                  injured and disturbed me or God's church except you and your husband?</quote>
            And she was astonished, and said : <quote>For what reason? Who has said
               anything to you?</quote> He says to her : <quote>You' ordered my death, and your 2
                  order came to me to leave the city hastily; and what more do you want to
                  learn?</quote> When she learned that it was not at his instigation that they had
            come and received the document from her, and that she herself had written
            in order to gratify him, she issued an order, and these enemies quickly came,
            while she said, <quote>Whom else was it your purpose to deceive except God and
               me and this saint?</quote> Then, when she threatened them with such things as
            their tricks deserved, the blessed man with great entreaty delivered them
            from death, and did not requite them according to their deeds. But on the
            matter of ordinations (xstpovovicc) she said to him : <quote>See that you remain within
               the palace (Tarov)”, lest trial in trutlh come upon you. Remain still and
               keep quiet like your companions and do not make priests in this city</quote>.
            He said to her, <quote>I will not do it; and, that you may know that I have no
               desire for this business, I was just about to request your majesty to order me
               to go out to a villa oustide for a secret retreat of thirty or forty days, as I now
               <pb n="535"/><pb n="333"/>also request, since I nam indeed ill</quote>. And she on her side gave him his will,
            and also dismissed him, since he was indeed really weak in bodily health,
            and, his body being greatly afflicted, he constantly suffered from diseases.
            But the blessed man was determined that, if anyone interfered with him in
            the way of preventing him from extending a hand of ordination to the believers
            within, he would go out and visit them himself in the district where they
            were, in the fervour of his enthusiasm; which also he did not delay to do,
            but under the appearance of having gone out to the villa he went on board a
            ship, and went out first to Lydia, and thence to Asia, in which there were
            in fact many convents of believers; and thus he visited in all districts and
            passed through them; and he came down as far as Tarsus in Cilicia, while
            he never spent a whole day in a place, but night and day devoted himself to
            travelling in all directions. And thereupon the report of him was heard over
            all that land; and, while the report of him was reaching the bishop of the
            district<note></note> or of the city, he himself did what he required and passed from it;
            since before he entered a district he would learn about the believers, and he
            would send a message two or three days beforehand that the men of every
            <pb n="536"/><pb n="334"/>place should assemble and be ready along his route<note></note> (?) at one day's journey
            (pavoíwv) from one another; and thus he visited as far as Tarsus, intending to
            go down over the whole of Syria. And there they learned about him; and
            there was great commotion, and much searching through the whole city on
            his account; and so he left his things there, and took his departure like a
            poor man, and was not caught. When he saw that the countries had been
            thrown into commotion, he thought <quote>Before search is made and the
               commotion reaches the king, I will return</quote>; and so he came back after two
            months, and he went straight to the villa, as if he had not gone anywhere.
            And he sent a letter to the queen, saying, <quote>Since I, my lady, have on account
               of ill health not been able to come in and make obeisance to you all this
               time, send me by letter what you wish to say</quote>. And she on her side
            consented, and sent him a present also there. And during the same days a
            letter from the patriarch of Antioch and all the rest of the bishops was
            brought in to the king which stated, <quote>One of the bishops who are there has
               come out, and has thrown the whole church into confusion, and has performed
               ordination (potovía) and given penances (xxvóvas) and absolution³, from the
               royal city as far as Syria</quote>. And, when a great search had been made, he
            <pb n="537"/><pb n="335"/>said: <quote>Perhaps it is so-and-so who lhas not been in the city all this time</quote>.
            Then by the grace of God no ordinary person, but the queen herself, came in
            to give evidence on behalf of the blessed man, saying: <quote>That man is sick
               and laid up in such-and-such a villa; for indeed it was by my order also
               that he went out thither; and only a few days ago he sent to me</quote>. And,
            when everyone testified that he was in his place, they dropped the matter.
            And so, vhile tlhese men wrote forcibly, they gained no hearing, and a
            message was sent to them to say, <quote>If you can, arrest him, for perhaps he
               is an impostor. No one lhas left this place</quote>. Again on another occasion,
            when this had been forgotten and had blown over, he succeeded in getting
            an order given him to go as far as the hot spring<note></note> on account of his diseases,
            and he was sent away; and he went out and passed over all the islands
            of the sea-coast<note></note> and those within the sea as far as Cyprus and visited the
            believers, and as far as Caesarea; and so he returned without anyone discovering 
            it. Again after this (on which same visitation we ourselves
            encountered him), he made a visitation and went down as far as Rhodes,
            and there we were privileged to see him. And, when he told us his intention,
            that he intended to pass through Asia a second time about six years after the
            <pb n="538"/><pb n="336"/>first, since we were ourselves going up from Alexandria to the royal city<note></note>,
            he returned with us. And so, when we had travelled a day's journey
            (pavoíwv), at every lodging-place, he would send envoys taken from the
            believers to go among them, and at every place we used to find from a
            hundred and fifty and from two hundred assembled waiting for him. And
            thus we passed through the cities and villages together; so that in the city
            of Tralles inside the church, while the clergy were performing the service,
            he made more than fifty priests. Since we were a large party, and there were
            distinguished gentlemen among us, we were given permission to occupy an
            upper space, in the upper catechumenia<note></note> of the church; and so they would come
            up there three and five at a time, while men stood at the doors and kept watch,
            and men who arranged these and sent them on, and this while I myself was
            carrying the oblation and the sacrament<note></note>, and he was standing and blessing
            and administering the oblation and dismissing them, and those below were
            performing the service; and I was amazed at the man's courage and fortitude.
            In the house of Mar John at Ephesus again the same, more than seventy men
            <pb n="539"/><pb n="337"/>were assembled; and<note></note>, they having been instructed to assemble<note></note> by night in
            the open space in the western court of the paved precinct (?) (λáziz) of the
            same house of Mar John, he there ordained them by night. And so from
            that place we again separated, he to Chios and thence to Alexandria and to
            Palestine, and we to the royal city, wondering at the grace of God which
            had stirred up this man to visit the believers, and had given him moreover
            [. . . . to] the whole church, while all the time that he had been away
            those who came to the city had been in distress and had been waiting for
            him as a good hope and a granter of their requests. And he also returned
            and came, and found many in distress and waiting for him; since, though
            there were many others in the city itself, there was no man whosoever to
            stretch out his hand to ordain by reason of his fear. These things, on account
            of the abundance of his zeal and the greatness of the goodness of God with
            the man, impelled us to stray into such a length of narrative, while we have
            repeated few of his actions, such as relate to the method in which he carried
            out his visitation, while on that which is indeed too great to tell, the subject
            of the rest of his brave character and his humility, we have kept silence, lest
            <pb n="540"/><pb n="338"/>we exceed the fixed limit. These things which tend to preserve the memory
            of these holy and zealous men mighty in conflicts (żyóv) on behalf of religion,
            the first John and further this second John, we have committed to the record
            of history, in the first place in order that the world may [reap benefit] from
            the description [of...]' their ascetic and virtuous life, and in the second
            in order to make known the graciousness of him who saved his church by his
            precious blood, how in this time of its distress also he set up these two
            pillars of light in it to comfort it; by whose holy prayers may schisms and
            strifes be done away from within it until the end, Amen! And may mercy
            light upon the sinner who wrote it through their prayers. Amen!<note></note>
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the blessed John bishop of the city of Hephaestu in Egypt is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
