<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/819">Susan</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/819 -->
         <head>Next the Twenty-Seventh History, of a Blessed Virgin of <persName>Christ</persName> Whose Name Was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName>.</head>
         <p>
            The strong power of <persName>Christ</persName> who is God therefore, which is wont to be
            glorified and displayed in human weakness in order that no flesh. may boast
            before him<note></note><note></note>, this strengthener of the weak is wont to display its operation
            not only through men of great size or mighty strength, but also in weak,
            feeble, powerless women, insomuch that it gives them such force and courage
            that they show mighty valour in fight not only 'with flesh and blood<note></note> (or
            <pb n="542"/><pb n="340"/>with insidious passions and the enticements of fleshly lusts and so on), <quote>but
               against principalities (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρχας</foreign>) and authorities, and against the rulers of the
               world of this darkness, and against evil spirits under heaven</quote><note></note>, so that
            against these they show mighty prowess and mock at them as a mighty
            man mocks at a party of babes and sucklings who make themselves ready
            and come to fight with him.
         </p>
         <p>
            For this also was declared to us through the most wise Paul in that he
            says: <quote>In <persName>Christ Jesus</persName> is no male nor female, nor bond nor free</quote><note></note>. So
            therefore this holy woman valiant in <persName>Christ</persName>, in that she astonished me by
            her appearance and speech and strength in God, did not seem to me to be
            in any way out of place in the series of histories of the saints, with whom
            she also is pressing to enter by the same narrow gate<note></note>, as she has indeed
            already entered.
         </p>
         <p>
            This blessed woman, as by inquiry we succeeded in learning accurately
            from her, was by her birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/285">Arzun</placeName><note></note> of the Persians. And,
            when this woman was a girl of eight, that is of high family (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>), from her
            <pb n="543"/><pb n="341"/>very beginning the light of her life rose in her mind, until men marvelled
            at her sorrow and modesty and devoutness; and her name given her by her
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3706">parents</persName>, as by way of prophecy, was <quote>blessing</quote><note></note>, who truly received a
            heavenly blessing. This virtuous woman formed the plan of going and
            worshipping in the holy places in which the salvation of our life was effected,
            and she continued asking her <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3706">parents</persName>' leave, and they would laugh at her
            childhood and say: <quote>You have not yet learned to interpret, and do you
               wish to go to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName>?</quote>, but she on her part was silent and kept it in her
            heart<note></note>. And in the same days she prayed and said: <quote>Lord, if thou wishest
               for the life of my wretched soul, make thy way straight before me' and
               provide an escort for me, and save my soul from the stain of the hateful
               mire of this world</quote>. Then the child, as she herself would repeat to us,
            when I pressed her much, placed her soul in the Lord's hands and fled.
            And after traversing three or four miles she found a large <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3658">party of women
               <pb n="544"/><pb n="342"/>and men</persName> travelling along the road to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName>; and, having joined them
            and made inquiries and learnt it, she rejoiced and would exult and praise
            God, and would say: <quote>Blessed am I, for the Lord has vished for my salvation, 
               and has answered me according to my petition. And far be it from me
               henceforth to return for the world or for kin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>), or for <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3706">parents</persName>, and die.
               But I am going to him that led me, and he himself will be to me father' and
               brother, and Lord and Saviour in both worlds</quote>. And thus she reachedmon
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName> with joy; and, when she had worshipped there, and her <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3660">companions</persName>
            desired to go back, they continued requesting her to return with them as
            being a countrywoman, saying, <quote>We will not leave you in this country</quote>.
            But she separated from them, and they did not see her again. And she
            made inquiries to find a monastery in which to live; and she learned that
            there was a large <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">women's monastery</placeName> betwen <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/674">Ascalon</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/87">Gaza</placeName>; and thither
            she directed her steps; and she made her wish know to the portress. And,
            since that <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">monastery</placeName> was severe (?)<note></note>, that old woman said to her: <quote>You,
               my daughter, cannot live here, since you are a girl, and you cannot bear
               <pb n="545"/><pb n="343"/>burdens and labours; and moreover also your own delicacy is unsuited for
               a monastery</quote>. But the devout woman because she was a stranger and in
            a strange country was distressed; and she remained sitting before the gate
            and weeping for seven days, while they tried to drive her away and she
            did not move. Then, after they had learned that she was a stranger, they
            received her; and she came in, while they looked down upon her tender
            years. And, when they learned from what country to what country she
            had come, they would say to her as if distressed over her, <quote>What profit
               was it to you, my daughter, to come out and ruin your soul in the mire.
               of sin in this way? Who is there whom, if he were to see that you are so
               young, and especially that you are alone, Satan would not set upon you
               even against his will, to ruin you before your day?</quote> But she, as the
            blessed women who were with her would relate that they had originally
            learned from her, would say:<quote> For our Lord's sake pray for me; since I
               hope in him to whom I have committed myself that he has not suffered me
               to be ruined, and will not suffer me</quote>. And so (she said) they gave thanks
            to God. But she from that time began to follow great modes of life, and
            austere practices of labours and abstinence and devoutness, though they
            <pb n="546"/><pb n="344"/>tried to prevent her and used to smite her on account of her childish age,
            that she might not apply herself to these things more than all the <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3662">sisters</persName>;
            and she on her side would increase them the more; so that she would go
            for two and three days at a time, and then eat lentils only, and she would
            keep a whole night's vigil standing in a corner (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γωνία</foreign>); and no single word
            from her mouth would be uttered to human beings all day unless it was
            demanded, while none of her <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3660">companions</persName> saw her face openly or the whole
            of the inside of her eye from the time that she entered that <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">monastery</placeName>, and
            no laughter came out of her mouth. When they saw the blessed woman's
            ways of life, that in proportion as they strove to prevent her on the ground
            of her tender years she on her side went on adding to this serious demeanour
            for a year and two years, then her that they had despised as a child they
            now regarded as a venerable woman; and she herself had also changed her
            name before entering the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">monastery</placeName>, lest any of her kin (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) should come
            and make inquiries and discover her; and she took the name of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName>. When
            she had been practising these habits for about ten years, a persecution was
            set on foot against their <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">monastery</placeName> to make them either submit<note></note> or quit.<note></note>
            <pb n="547"/><pb n="345"/>Since it was a large and celebrated convent, the majority of them were
            detained and conformed, and some were scattered this way and that. But
            the blessed woman was pressed by two alternatives, one of removing from
            the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/3049">monastery</placeName>, and the other of falling into the evil faith. Then she resolved 
            to leave, and go into the desert beyond <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, and live there.
            And she left at once, while a great division arose even among those who
            had submitted in that they said, <quote>Now that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName> has left, neither will we
               stay</quote>. But of the leading women who had not conformed five of them<note></note>
            attached themselves to her, while she was prepared to go alone; and these
            would say to her : <quote>It is impossible for us to be separated from you</quote>. But
            she, after she had been compelled, revealed her intention to them, saying:
            <quote>Do not come with me; since for my part, to put it shortly, if the Lord
               prosper me as he is wont to do, I am going to the desert</quote>. But they also
            as well stated their determination, <quote>We too will go with you to the desert</quote>.
            And, when they refused to give way, they embarked on a ship and crossed
            to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>. And the blessed woman heard a report of a place in the
            desert beyond <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2819">the house of Mar Menas</placeName>; and she directed her steps thither,
            <pb n="548"/><pb n="346"/>it being about two miles from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2820">a village named Mendis</placeName>; which finally became
            the abode of the blessed Syrians<note></note>, but took its beginning from the blessed
            woman. And there was there a tower that had been erected for protection
            against barbarians; and the other five also went in with virtuous zeal, and
            they took up their abode in it. And one of them went in and obtained
            material for work for them from that village; and thus they laboured with
            their hands for their necessities and supported themselves; and God took
            care of them, who saw their zeal and their trust in him. Now there was a
            cave outside that tower in the desert that had been dug in the earth underneath; 
            and once there had been a certain blessed man in it. And, having
            passed beyond human habitation, she was proceding further and going to
            and fro in the desert and praying; and on her walk she went and discovered 
            that cave; and immediately she threw herself inside it without her
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3660">companions</persName> or anyone else being aware of it; and she took no food or
            anything. And thenceforth like that which is written of Ishmael the son
            of Abraham, that he lived in the desert of Paran and was there instructed
            <pb n="549"/><pb n="347"/>in the bow<note></note>, so it would be fitting to say of this woman also that she lived
            in a cave in the desert, and was instructed in struggles and acts of valour
            against powerful demons, who show the power of their wickedness more
            especially in the desert. But her <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3660">companions</persName>, when a day and two days
            passed and she did not come, sat night and day in bitter distress and
            weeping, while they said, <quote>She in reliance upon whom we came hither
               has deserted us and departed</quote>. And, when again about ten days had
            passed, some persons from that village learned about it, and they came to
            the blessed women to learn the facts. And, when they saw the sorrow and
            the weeping of the blessed women, they thought, <quote>Has she perhaps gone
               down into the cave in the desert?</quote> And, inasmuch as they knew the place,
            they set out and went to that cave; and they looked in and saw the blessed
            woman lying on her face and crying aloud; and they spoke to her. And
            she, inasmuch as she supposed that they were the fiends, who had displayed 
            fearful and horrible shapes before her there, was not frightened out
            of crying in prayer. But they, when they saw that she did not answer them,
            left her; and they went and informed her <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3660">companions</persName>; and so they all ran
            to that cave; and they found the blessed woman in the same position,
            <pb n="550"/><pb n="348"/>kneeling and praying; and with difficulty, when they had spoken many
            words to her, was she brought to believe that it was they, since the day
            before also demons had clothed themselves in their shapes and come to her
            to dislodge her from that place. And they, while weeping, continued
            making this entreaty to her, saying: <quote>You know that it was in reliance
               upon you after our Lord that we came out to this desert; and now wherefore
               do you seek to destroy all our souls, and be yourself alone saved? and know
               you not that we without you cannot exist?</quote> But the valiant woman 
            addressed them weeping with her head bowed downwards : <quote>Leave me, my
               <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3662">sisters</persName>; and now I am with you always; but, since the Lord has prepared
               this place for me in which I have had the opportunity of being at peace, go
               and keep quiet; and every first day of the week one of you shall come and
               see me whether I am alive or dead</quote>. But they, in order that she might
            come with them, set upon her to lift her up and were unable to do so.
            Again after these things they demanded from her a sure promise, lest she
            should depart even from that place also and not let them know; and she
            gave them the promise. And again they continued begging her that they
            <pb n="551"/><pb n="349"/>might make a little dish of lentils and bring it her, inasmuch as it was now
            ten days that she had not tasted anything. But she on her side refused
            even to hear of it, saying: <quote>You seek to concern yourselves about my food,
               while I am lying flat on my face, and to make me eat the sweat of your
               faces, far be it from me! But for the support of my body it is enough
               that you bring me a jar of water on the first day of the week, and one cake
               (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παξαμάς</foreign>)' of bread a day</quote>. And thus they did for her for three years.
            But, after the fame of the blessed women had been heard everywhere, and
            moreover where they lived, many persons would come to them from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, 
            and from the villages of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2810">Libya</placeName>, and further afterwards a great old man,
            who also with his disciples, about ten of them, was a neighbour of their
            monastery in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/698">Palestine</placeName>, and, when they had been much persecuted, and
            driven from one place to another, when he learned where these blessed
            women were, and also about the quietude and pleasantness of that desert,
            set forth and directed his steps thither with his disciples, one of whom was
            brother of her who had been made head of the same blessed women, who
            <pb n="552"/><pb n="350"/>also was a man of marvellous modes of life, whose name was Samuel; and
            the name of the old man himself was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3234">Maro</persName>; and the old man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3234">Maro</persName> was by
            birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) an Amidene, while his disciple Samuel with his <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3662">sister</persName> came
            from the neighbourhood of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>. And, when they arrived, the blessed
            women on their side received comfort from their presence, and the men too
            rejoiced, and they gave thanks to the Lord that they were gratified with
            the quiet of the desert. And thereupon they began to plant a cell in that
            desert, and others moreover came thither, of some of whom a record has
            been set down by us in one of the preceding histories<note></note>. And that place
            was colonized, while the blessed women also were among them. Accordingly 
            they formed a plan of preparing a separate place for them, in order
            not to give occasion for evil speaking among persons outside; and on
            account of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName> they did not like to speak lest she should be
            offended<note></note>. But she was occupied with the same thought, <quote>Now that God
               has brought his bondmen to this place, neither is it possible for those of our
               female sex (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) to pass their lives among them (since the evil one's attack
               <pb n="553"/><pb n="351"/>upon saints is generally made through women even when they are
               absent, how much more therefore in their presence!), even if so be we'
               continue to run with caution after spiritual things. But now let us withdraw 
               into the desert beyond this</quote>. While the blessed men were ashamed
            on account of the saint's serious character, she herself addressed them in
            these words; and when they heard it they gave thanks to God; and they
            undertook to build and prepare for them a place in the vicinity of that village,
            while she herself intended to move farther up country; and they stood up
            and opposed her, saying: <quote>For you, mother, in a city, if you dwell in it,
               it is a desert to you'; but look at these souls who are hanging upon you'</quote>.
            Then she gave way to them; and they built an enclosed monastery for them
            and a tower inside it; and they took up their abode in it. But the blessed
            woman through strength proceeding from Grace received mighty power
            over fiends, since they would thenceforth set themselves in array against
            her night and day in the form (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τύπος</foreign>) of human beings, and they would come
            against her with all varieties of weapons; and she like a strong man who
            <pb n="554"/><pb n="352"/>despises the sickly men who threaten him would mock at them<note></note>. And the
            fame of her strength was heard everywhere, so that the fame of her perfection 
            instigated us also to see her as well as the holy men who were there,
            fifteen years after she had settled in the same desert. And, when we had
            been privileged to see her that I do not like to name a woman, I was amazed
            at the words of solemn feeling and of the wisdom of God that proceeded from
            her mouth during the space of more than twenty days that I was with these
            saints, going and coming, in order to hear her speech and her delightful
            conversation; and I was unable to see her head held erect, or a feature of
            her face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) except the tip of her nose only; so sorrowful was she and
            tearful. And she took upon herself to speak to us about this world how it
            is in the grasp of error, and how men see their fellows rotting and decaying
            and putrefying within graves, and the loathsome worm creeping about in
            the midst of their putrefying remains, and they who see these things are
            led astray by the vanities of this false world, and how again the thought
            of the rapidly-approaching terrible hour of the dissolution of this world does
            <pb n="555"/><pb n="353"/>not rise in men's hearts, and that they are about to stand before the terrible
            judgment-seat (<foreign xml:lang="grc">βήμα</foreign>) ol God, saying, <quote>It is a great absurdity that we hear
               of the pit of fire, and the abysses of flame, and the darkness, and the rest
               of the torments, and we do not lay it to heart and ask mercy while we have
               the opportunity as a means of escaping from these things</quote>. This divine
            woman would repeat in our presence many things yet more terrible than
            these, and we were brought into a state of great wonder at her speech.
            Then there was given to her also the gift of healing, so that every infirmity
            or disease upon which she stretched out her hand was healed. While we
            were there, a certain great and God-loving blessed man was living in a
            place in the desert that was not far from them; and the fiends used openly
            to set themselves in array against him; and he used to see their struggle
            with the blessed woman. and she his. But, since she was stronger than
            he, she both prevailed and had no fear whatever of the fiends, and she had
            become firm and immoveable like adamant, insomuch that the demons
            themselves used to cry to her, <quote>This is a woman, but she has become stone,
               and from flesh iron</quote>. These things the demons used to say to her. And,
            <pb n="556"/><pb n="354"/>inasmuch as she was so firm, that blessed man, whenever the visions pressed
            hard upon him, used to come to her as to a strong person; and while I was
            there, he came, stricken and smitten in his mind and perturbed. And
            when she saw him she understood; and she asked him <quote>Why are you
               distressed, father?</quote> But he continued saying: <quote>The fiends have been
                  mighty and have taken away my wits, since the whole week we have been
                  more than ordinarily involved in a struggle; and this night and day they
                  showed me terrible sights of fear, and my heart was shaken and my wits
                  were taken away and I was confounded; and from fear I fled; and I am
                  afraid to enter my cell on account of the sights that I saw. And now I will
                  leave that place</quote>. She on hearing it shook her head, saying: <quote>Come see
                     persons that are called men, and not only men but also <persName>Christ</persName>'s bondmen.
                     Is it right that you should be called <persName>Christ</persName>'s bondmen? You have in this
                     way reckoned <persName>Christ</persName> your Lord to be feeble, and by your own frailty have
                     made the mighty and invincible power of <persName>Christ</persName>, which cast down and
                     overthrew and brought to naught all the power of Satan, appear less than
                     that of the fiends, so that <persName>Christ</persName> now seems to be a runaway and one that
                     <pb n="557"/><pb n="355"/>can be overcome by the demons, and they are found to be strong and
                     vanquishers of the power of God. How are you a disciple of him who said:
                     <quote>Ye shall trample on all the power of the enemy</quote><note></note>?<!-- There seems to be an extra inverted comma in Brooks. -->
                     You have distressed me by causing the fiends to rejoice. If necessary,
                     were it not for other reasons, you should only last night have been hearing
                     the shapes and voices of the struggles of the demons which they showed
                     me, and have been marvelling' at them. And for my part I know that the
                     Lord's power surrounds my weakness like a wall of bronze, and there is
                     no other power that can resist it</quote>. While the weak woman was boldly
            saying these words in our presence, we looked at one another, while she
            did not see either of us. Then she said confidently to the blessed man:
            <quote>In the name of the Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> rise and return to your cell; and
               he as his custom is will make all the power of the evil one weak before
               you</quote>. But the blessed man, being struck with shame at the woman's
            words and trembling greatly from his shame, consented to go. And, when
            <pb n="558"/><pb n="356"/>we had risen up from before her and were speaking and expressing astonishment 
            at her spiritual strength and her courage, I said to him: <quote>How is
               it that this blessed woman's face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>) is not visible?</quote> He on his side
            said to me: <quote>One day while we were speaking I said to her <quote>For what
               reason do you hide your face from us?</quote> And she made oath to me, saying:
               <quote>He who by his grace laid his yoke upon me knows, our brother, that since
                  I took his yoke upon me, which is to day twenty-five years ago, I have not
                  seen a man's face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>), and do you desire me to see yours now?</quote>, and
               I on my side said to her: <quote>For our Lord's sake tell me the truth. Are
                  you for your part afraid lest you should yourself suffer harm from the sight
                  of a man, or lest he should suffer harm from the sight of you?</quote> And she
               said <quote>For both reasons</quote>.</quote> And thus in astonishment at the saint's habits
            of life and the endurance of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName> the virgin of <persName>Christ</persName> we departed from
            that place, praising God.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of a blessed virgin of <persName>Christ</persName> whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2092">Susan</persName><note></note> is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
