<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/820">Mary the Mourner</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/820 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            Therefore neither was the history of this holy Mary unworthy of admiration, 
            a woman who by nature only bore the form of females, but herself
            also too bore in herself the character and soul and will not only of ordinary
            men, but of mighty and valiant men.
         </p>
         <p>
            This blessed woman therefore also was the daughter of distinguished
            persons and a high family (yévos) in the world. Now there was a great old
            man of God who was living as a recluse in a village bordering on their village,
            a man far advanced in years; and to this saint the blessed woman's people
            used frequently to come, she being with them, when she was ten years
            old. And, when the damsel saw the serious character of the old man,
            solemn feeling was stirred in her mind, and she despised all the world with
            all that is in it, meditating in herself and saying: <quote>Lo! they are rich who
               <pb n="560"/><pb n="358"/>possess the world that passes not away for ever and ever, not we wretched
               persons among whom, as soon as a man has become rich and' proud and
               boastful, and believed himself to be lord of his own riches, death has come and
               cast him down into sheol, and others have taken away his toil in which he
               toiled from his childhood even to his death, and which has perhaps been
               amassed by sin, and the sin has remained with him, and the riches have
               become the property of others. Lo! then the things that are in this world
               are all deceit and vanity. For what reason do we not voluntarily leave a
               thing which we must in any case leave even if we do not desire it? and for
               what reason do we not become as this old man? Is not this a human being?
               Far be it from me henceforth to let the world deceive me, and refrain from
               following the course of life of this old man</quote>. And from that time the
            damsel's mind became inflamed, and she cut herself off completely from eating
            flesh and from drinking wine; and she began to fast and pray, and to run
            in the road of excellence. But her people, when they saw these things,
            used to reprove her, and to press her to continue eating flesh and drinking
            wine; and she would not obey, having cast her body, and all the enticements.
            of youth, and the adornment of childhood behind her, and begun to walk
            <pb n="561"/><pb n="359"/>soundly in the lofty road of anchoritism and asceticism. Since she had been
            betrothed by them to a certain rich man, they began as people of the world
            to be distressed and to think thoughts which were not theirs only but those
            of the hater of good things also as well, <quote>Let us rise and make a wedding-feast 
               for her, lest she run away and go to a monastery, and we lose the man
               who was to take her to wife</quote>. And, when they on their side had begun to
            prepare and make ready the things required for the wedding, the blessed
            woman became aware of it and said to them: <quote>Do not toil' to no purpose
               and lose your money; for my part I hope in him who invited the pure and holy
               and virgin to recline at his eternal wedding-feast that ceases not that I shall
               make no bodily partnership, nor corrupt the purity of my soul by fleshly
               conjunction with a mortal man</quote>. But, when this incited these people all
            the more, so that they met together (?)<note></note> in order to constrain her, she left
            them and went to a monastery; and she shaved her head and took the habit
            (pa). And from that time she took that holy old man as her model (Túños)
            in all things, in standing and abstinence and vigils and eating once in three
            days, while she also made for herself a hair-shirt and sandals (csvz), and
            <pb n="562"/><pb n="360"/>moreover from the first day on which she received the mark never again cut
            her hair, so that it became long and abundant, until it was wound round
            her four times up and down, so that at last (it is said) it became<note></note> a great
            weight. And she also distinguished herself in the conflict (ayov) of persecution
            for fifteen years, no longer passing night-vigils, but vigils lasting even a
            week, and ten days, and then she would taste something. And, when she
            had walked strongly and heroically in the road of righteousness for
            thirty years, she finished her course and received the crown<note></note> earned by her
            life, and fell asleep in peace.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the blessed Mary the anchorite<note></note> is ended.
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
