<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/824">A Monk</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/824 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            A certain blessed man had been settled for a considerable time as a solitary
            in a cell in the Ennaton of Alexandria' with two disciples; and, when we
            ourselves arrived at that place² and went in to him and received his blessing,
            three days after we had departed from his presence a brother from one of
            the well-known convents of the place came to him under the plea of desiring
            to live with him, even as I had myself made the acquaintance of that brother
            in his convent; and, when he had come in and passed about one week with
            him, Satan put it into his heart to take the contents of that solitary's cell
            and flee. And, having looked and learned everything, and devised in his
            mind a plan of action, he rose by night and collected everything that he
            could (since that blessed man had indeed no small number of saints³ and
            books), and he took them, a great load, and fled. And he went and found
            camel-drivers going into the desert above Libya that is called Cellia*; and
            he gave them a fee, leading them to think that he was carrying his own<pb n="587"/><pb n="385"/>
            belongings in order to go thither. And they took him, and he went into
            the desert with them; and he went in to a certain man there, and made
            search for a cell for himself in which to live and be a solitary. And, when
            he had passed one week there, his thoughts began to pass judgment upon
            him, and his heart to smite him, and he would say to himself, as he himself
            would inform us about everything, weeping: <quote><quote>In what way, O wretched
               man, did you wish to become a solitary? To Christ, pray, or to Satan?
               Lo! you have performed the service of Satan, and executed and fulfilled the
               will of a demon, and afflicted a soul fashioned in the divine likeness, and
               carried off the toil and sweat of that holy old man's labour; and he is
               sobbing and crying before God on your account at all times. And how
               have I hope of life and salvation?</quote> Then</quote>!-- This is really awkward. It seems like the previous quote within a quote should just be a quote and 'Then he said' should not be in quotations at all. --> (he would say) <quote>I passed one
                  week in penitence and horror and tears, weeping for myself, and meditating
                  upon these things and saying, <quote>What has befallen me? Who led me astray?
                     What shall I do? How shall I weep for myself? Alas for me! since my
                     companions are secretly stealing a kingdom, and I stole eternal torment for
                     myself. What will happen to me when I am about to go to God? What
                     defence (άñoλoyía) have I to give for this wickedness?</quote> And, while I on my<pb n="588"/><pb n="386"/>
                  side was weeping for myself, my hearers were wondering, and were desirous
                  of learning the cause of the lamentation and weeping on my part. Then
                  I revealed it to them, and they marvelled. And I said to them: <quote>What do
                     you advise me to do? because my meditation is inciting me to strangle
                     myself and perish out of this life, which deceived me and incited me to this
                     crime</quote>. And these saints advised me to return the stolen goods to their
                  owners, saying to me, <quote>If you listen to us and make restitution and humble
                     yourself and ask mercy for this your offence, God will be merciful to you
                     and men also will forgive you; and even they themselves will be merciful
                     to you and forgive you, and will also make petition for you</quote>. And, while
                  they pressed me, I on my part was restrained by my shamefacedness and
                  hindered from doing this, saying to them: <quote>My face is ashamed to do this.
                     With what face, or with what colour (xpopa), or with what brazen front can
                     this be carried out?</quote> But the blessed men went on saying to me, <quote>Which
                        is better for you, to endure reproach and transitory shame here, and repent
                        and live while you have opportunity, while you further relieve the souls to
                        which you have given sorrow and bitterness, or to be consumed in the<pb n="589"/><pb n="387"/>
                        eternal torment, where shame and reproach and torment are not finished
                        and brought to an end for ever and ever?</quote> When these words had been
                  spoken to me by many men, I rose and left all the utensils and the books
                  and the martyrs under seal, and I came in shame; and lo! I am settled
                  here till intercessors are found for me</quote>. All these things about himself
            that brother was relating by word of mouth in my presence with great
            humility and copious tears; since, while I was going round the districts to
            be blessed by the saints, I found him in a monastery called that of father
            Andrew', on the farther side where the holy Mar Menas is, which is
            called the desert of Mendia'; and, when I saw him, I was astonished in
            his presence, and I greeted him, having no knowledge of what had happened;
            and he on his side was bowed down, and was melancholy and wretched. And
            on my inquiring of him about his sorrow he sat down and accused himself
            and told the story of his crime at a length many times greater than what
            I have put in writing. And, when I heard it, I admired the man's penitence;
            and I comforted him by saying to him: <quote>You have done a great deed and
               one that deserves admiration, in that for the sake of your soul's healing
               you have despised shame, and have taken upon yourself that, be it igno<pb n="590"/><pb n="388"/>miny 
               or reproach, or chastisements and everything that comes here, you will
               submit to them, they being things that are transitory, in order to escape
               from the severe and terrible chastisement in hell which lasts for ever. And
               now fear not. You did well in that you did not carry out the work of
               Satan and his will to the uttermost, though he caused you a fall inasmuch 
               as you are a man</quote><!-- This close quotation is missing in Brooks but these requires it. -->. He on hearing these things was comforted; and
            he went on entreating us to return with him to the owner of the stolen
            property, in order to entreat him to receive his own in full and forgive the
            transgression. When we saw that it was a labour of profit to gain our
            brother', we did not refuse; and further also we were required to fulfil the
            precept given in the command, <quote>If thy brother shall force thee to go one
               mile, go with him two</quote>². And so we returned with him, and went in to
            that blessed man, having left him some distance away. And we found him
            agitated with great grief and much distress on account of the martyrs and on
            account of the books especially; and, when we began to speak before him,
            <quote>Indeed we can find your property for you</quote>, he was astonished, and began
            to make inquiries. Then we on our part asked him to perform a request
            for us, and all his belongings would be found complete; and he on his side<pb n="591"/><pb n="389"/>
            answered <quote>Everything that you command I for my part am ready to carry
               out even without that</quote>. Then we offered him repentance, having taken it
            upon ourself, and we said: <quote>Since Satan, father, caused us to fall like men,
               and we sinned against God and your holiness, receive your own, and forgive
               the crime, and remain without ill-feeling, in order that you may be a fulfiller
               of the command which said <quote>Forgive and it shall be forgiven unto you</quote>'</quote>.
            But the blessed man was much grieved over him and was distressed, saying:
            <quote>Even if he does not restore me anything and you command, all the days
               of my life I will consent that he shall live with me without ill-feeling, and
               I will never remind him of this matter</quote>. And so that brother came, repenting 
            and weeping and with his face bowed down to the ground, and bitterly
            accusing himself, in such a way as he could not have been accused by one
            who hated him. When that blessed man saw his penitence, and all of us
            alike greatly wondered and marvelled at the grace which had opened his
            heart and caused him thus to repent and to act in this way (and all who
            heard the story wondered and marvelled at it), then he in this way received
            thanks from everyone in place of punishment. And the blessed man received<pb n="592"/><pb n="390"/>
            him, and laid a penance upon him, and absolved him. And he hired an ass
            for him; and that brother set out, and so he went and brought all the articles,
            not having forgotten anything. And thenceforth he continued to repent
            of his offence like a guilty man, and he was diligent in showing repentance
            for it, insomuch that we on our part left him in this condition, admiring
            what he had done and thanking God.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of a certain brother who was caught by the enticement of temptation
            to theft and afterwards came to repentance is ended.
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
