<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/828">Mari the Solitary</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/828 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            Whereas therefore we find in ancient traditions that men of ancient times
            set themselves earnestly and diligently to make memorials of the performance
            of various things that were performed before their times and in their days,
            insomuch that in the course of the times down to the present time they
            have now reached us even in our own days, which are all that are recorded
            severally in the Holy Scriptures, firstly, in order that the power and
            miracles and actions of God wrought through them and in their days
            might be known to everyone for his own glory, secondly, for a memorial
            and remembrance of the righteousness of the same just and righteous men,
            who at different times endeavoured to please God and do his will, thirdly
            again, that those who should afterwards read and receive it through the
            <pb n="625"/><pb n="423"/>writings might be imitators of their practices, and eager to run the course
            of religion like them, since then, as we said before, we ourselves observed
            all these things, we considered it to be a matter of right and religion
            now also to make a record of the upright men and strenuous workers
            of religion, our fathers and brothers, who like bright stars shone by their
            practices all the time of their lives, and earned the privilege of being
            gathered together by a good ending and laid in this place, in this holy
            convent of us Syrians above the house of the holy Mar Mama, which by the
            help of the grace of God was at this time erected through the instrumentality 
            of our meanness<note></note>; the head and first of whom is the great man of
            God Mare who was named by everyone <quote>the solitary</quote>, and by others <quote>he
               of his patches</quote>, on account of the pieces of unsightly and ill-matched rags
            of hair and of wool out of which he had put together his clothing and
            coyering and sewn them together in ill-matched fashion. This saint then
            was by birth (yévos) from the country of the Amidenes<note></note>, that is from Ingilene
            from a village called Beth Marka<note></note>, which is indeed in our neighbourhood,
            <pb n="626"/><pb n="424"/>and, while this man was a layman, and was powerful of stature and of
            more than ordinary strength, he became also a son of the covenant<note></note> in the
            church of his village. And, when he had completed about thirty years,
            even as many were advising him and his parents that he ought to form an
            alliance, and when his parents were making preparations for the wedding
            function, and the day arrived on which they were to celebrate the wedding,
            suddenly Grace, which had secretly seen that he was to be <quote>a chosen vessel</quote><note></note>
            for the glory of his Lord, dawned in his heart and on his mind, and he
            resolved instead of bodily communion, to which many accidents are attached
            and against which is set the dissolution of death, to pursue spiritual 
            communion, bearing his Lord's gentle and light yoke<note></note> upon his neck, and
            placing his cross upon his shoulder and going after him. And so he rose
            in the middle of the night and prayed to the Lord to direct his way that
            he might go after him, and grant him the privilege of doing his will; and
            he directed his way to the great man of God, Paul the anchorite, who was
            also a performer of mighty works and miracles, a record of whose history
            <pb n="627"/><pb n="425"/>we have also introduced at small proportion and in defective fashion into
            the histories which precede this<note></note>. When then the blessed Mare reached
            this man, and presented to him a request to grant him the privilege of living
            with him and receiving training from him, he received him on his promising
            him repentance toward God, having given him much instruction in the
            ordinances and labours of monasticism. And so he remained with him five
            years, imitating his divine practices, and decreeing for himself severe labours
            of fasting and prayer and protracted recitation of service, and constant vigil,
            so that he gave himself rest for one hour or two only for the sake of the
            demands of nature, and through the whole extent of the night he performed
            a constant series of inclinations and genuflexions with prayer, and besides
            these things barefootedness and austerity and abstinence, and humility
            and sorrow, and tears. And by all these things he used to train himself
            in religion, and subdue his body and bring it into subjection with sorrow
            and repentance, insomuch that many were surprised at his labours, and even
            that holy old man himself, when he saw the immoderate severity of his
            practices, would strongly reprove him, and admonish him not to exceed the
            <pb n="628"/><pb n="426"/>bounds of moderation in his dealing with his body; a thing which he also
            repeated to us ourselves, when we once came to the holy old man in order
            to be blessed by him and receive his prayer, and to visit the blessed Mare
            also, concerning the severity of his practices how he exceeded the bounds
            of moderation in his dealing with his body, insomuch that in the hardness
            of winter, when snow was lying about a man's stature high, he would go
            out to the mountains without an outer garment, having nothing on his feet
            below or above, and thus he would cut wood and make great loads, and
            thus he would carry them, cleaving the snow and sinking into it, so much
            so that blood would flow and drop from the whole of the flesh of his feet,
            and even so he would not pay attention to them. And, when we learned
            from the holy man about such severity, inasmuch as we were acquainted
            with him from his childhood<note></note> and with the family (yévos) of the blessed
            Mare, we used to admonish him earnestly to accomodate himself to the will
            of his spiritual father. But he fell on his face weeping and saying, <quote>Forgive
               me, my fathers; the body has not received what the contumacy of its arrogant 
               behaviour against the soul deserves, and I have not yet done to it
               <pb n="629"/><pb n="427"/>anything adequate to my sins and the vices in my soul which arise from
               the body; but I am contriving means to bring it into subjection and subdue
               it, that even now it may cease injuring my soul</quote>, with many similar things
            which he would repeat to us with affliction and with tears; so that, when
            we were hearing them, we were surprised at the earnestness of his will and
            the affliction of his mind. But, when he had completed five years with
            that blessed man, since he was still being constantly pestered by his parents
            and by his kin (yévos), for this reason he determined to remove completely
            from parents and kin (yévos) and from all acquaintances, insomuch that,
            having asked for prayer and release from the blessed man his master, he
            set out on his journey and departed from all the countries of Syria, and
            came to the countries of Egypt and Thebais; and thenceforth he used to go
            to and fro in the desert of the saints, and. he would betake himself to certain
            great men and solitaries, and ask for their prayers, and eagerly observe
            their practices, and set himself to imitate their labours with all his soul,
            insomuch that after these things he gave himself to the life of a recluse in
            one of the deserts; and thus he thenceforth went on distinguishing himself
            <pb n="630"/><pb n="428"/>by laborious practices for a long period of time.
            And, when he had completed about 15 years in this conflict (ayov), a great disturbance arose in the
            city of Alexandria on account of the faith<note></note>, insomuch that many were
            expelled and driven from their places, men who would not consent to conform
            to the Chalcedonian communion. And they came even to the blessed Mare
            himself; and, when they had pressed him greatly and he did not acquiesce
            in their communion, they drove him also out and expelled him from his
            cell. And from such a reason as this he was seized by a vehement desire
            to go up to Constantinople, so that he applied himself to dealing a severe
            reproof to the king and queen; and he went up and reached the royal city.
            But with regard to the blessed man's entry into the presence of the king
            and queen, and the rough character of his meeting with them, and the
            insulting words which he addressed to them, and his audacity and his 
            contemptuous conduct moreover to them of this we have not thought it well
            to make a written record<note></note> in the history of his life not only on account
            <pb n="631"/><pb n="429"/>of their violence<note></note>, and the insults and the contemptuous conduct which he
            used toward the rulers of the world, but further also because perhaps, even
            if they had been written, the difficulty of believing among the hearers would
            be very great and not small, that these things could easily be said not only
            to kings, the holders of the power of this world, but even also to contemptible
            and mean persons. But, when he sternly rebuked the royal pair as we
            have said with<note></note> such freedom (ñağóncía) and sternness, which he had indeed
            possessed from his boyhood, they as by the grace of God accepted it from
            him humbly and with fear without violent action, as from a great man and a
            perfect solitary, especially because they saw the freedom (apnoía) of his
            speech, that he spoke and rebuked and reproved courageously and without
            fear, not being frightened by the crown or alarmed by the purple, and they
            said, <quote>This man is in truth a spiritual philosopher</quote>; his dress being as we
            described it above, hideous through the patching together of unsightly and
            ill-matched rags differing from one another, and fastenings whereby they
            were joined together by unsightly cords of hair and of wool, insomuch that
            <pb n="632"/><pb n="430"/>every aperture (?)<note></note> made by a fastening of his garments covered more than
            two or three fingers' lengths, insomuch that no mean poor man in the world
            was anywhere to be seen who was clothed in them or perhaps would
            ever consent to be clothed in them, not even if he had nothing to cover
            his nakedness. But, when the victorious king observed these things, he
            greatly wondered at him and gave him a promise that he would do for him
            whatever he commanded; and yet more the believing queen held him as a
            great and righteous man, and continued entreating him to remain with her
            in her palace (λτov), that he might speak to her words of profit. And,
            while she on her side was making this request of him upon her face<note></note>, he on
            the other hand answered her with stern reproofs. And, when she saw
            that he would not comply with her wishes, she quietly ordered her own
            treasurer (coxenoos) to hring her a hundredweight (xsvrnváptov) of gold,
            thinking that by this she would soften the blessed Mare and make him yield.
            And, when it came and she offered it him bound up, and began entreating
            him to accept it and divide it between the poor and his needs, then after
            gazing sternly at it he grasped the bag (uapoutiov) containing the hundred-<pb n="633"/><pb n="431"/>weight 
            (xevτnváρtov) in one hand, and hurled it and threw it no small distance,
            so that all the chamberlains and everyone who saw it were seized with
            great astonishment, to think that he was so powerful and of such well-knit
            frame, as we stated at the beginning, and since he had flung<note></note> it to a distance
            just as if it were something full of light apples, saying to her, <quote><quote>Thy money
               go to perdition with thee</quote>, because through this you wish to tempt me
               and mock me</quote>. And after answering her with many other stern words
            which we refrain from recording he left her and went out; and she remained
            in distress and fear, and she and all her chamberlains as well were wondering 
            at the blessed man's bodily strength, how he thought nothing of
            throwing a weight of a hundred pounds (írpa) of gold to such a distance,
            insomuch that the story was heard over the whole palace (rctrov) and over
            the whole of this city, and was spoken of with astonishment by many
            persons. When the blessed man was passing along a street of the city,
            his eyes were fixed on the ground, since he had determined in his mind never
            to see the face of men in it. And he left it; and so he went over to Sycae
            beyond the water<note></note>, and climbed the mountain to the north-west of it, where
            <pb n="634"/><pb n="432"/>there are also graves; and there he resided and performed the labour of
            his practices, satisfying his needs with wild herbs. But the queen, because
            she was a believer and knew that she had distressed him in the matter of
            the hundredweight of gold (xEvтnvάptov), made careful search for him; and
            on learning that he had left the city and was dwelling on the other side
            among the mountains sent some of her most distinguished chamberlains to
            entreat him to forgive her, and as a favour to herself to receive from her
            something that his needs required, whatever he wished. And, having
            taken much trouble and with difficulty discovered him, because he used to
            move from place to place, they delivered an earnest request to him as they
            had been ordered, and, absolutely refusing to grant their request, he sent
            her a message through them, <quote>Think not that you possess anything which
               God's bondmen need, except religion if it exists in you</quote>. And, when those
            who were sent came back again and she learned where he was, she sent
            yet again; and thenceforth they used to pester the blessed man every day;
            and he was compelled to remove to other places; and again they would find
            it out and discover him. And thenceforth many persons used to repair to
            him to receive his prayer; and they were specially astonished at seeing his
            <pb n="635"/><pb n="433"/>unsightly clothing. And he asked and palm-leaves, were brought to him,
            out of which he supplied his needs by the work of his hands, since he absolutely 
            refused to allow anything to enter his mouth except from the labour
            of his hands. And, if he was prevented from working with his hands on
            account of those who came to and fro to him, he would go two and three
            days, and sometimes even a whole week, and then taste bread, except wild
            herbs<note></note>; and sometimes he would feed on the berries of the bushes, and
            sometimes on the nuts of the trees. But in the winter-time he was compelled 
            to put up a hut for himself on one of these heights, and shelter himself
            in it from the severity of the winter. And, while he was thus dwelling
            peacefully on these mountains, Satan the hater of good things did not
            overlook it and leave him untried, but he set up robbers (pcrns) against him,
            ten men, who, having seen the chamberlains and the other great senators
            (cuyxnnrxös) coming to and fro to the blessed man, thought that he was
            receiving gold and storing it in his hut; and so in the middle of the night
            they fell upon him and surrounded him, and they flung out their hands to
            <pb n="636"/><pb n="434"/>seize him and bind him. But he, being stronger than they, threw their
            hands of him as if they were sick and tortured (?)<note></note> men, and he went on
            entreating them, saying, <quote>Nay, my sons, do not lose your soul. Why do
               you seek me the poor man?</quote> But they on their side said to him: <quote>Unless
                  you give us the gold which the queen is sending you, we will kill you at
                  once.</quote> But he returned them answer, saying: <quote>Take it, my sons, that to
                     me no gold has ever (rov) been sent by the queen, or by others. And, if
                     I desired gold, I should not be residing here</quote>. When he had said these
            words, one came back with a club and gave him a severe blow, and they
            all surrounded him, having also drawn their swords. And, when he saw
            that they had set themselves to kill him, and he did not mollify them by
            entreating them with gentle words, he looked straight at the one who was
            holding the club, and seized and dragged the club out of his hand; and he
            seized his hair with one hand, and threw him on his face. And another
            ran up to smite him with the sword, and he on his side smote him with the
            club, and stopped him; and his sword fell and he took hold of him, and
            threw him on the top of his companion, and the third, and the fourth. When
            <pb n="637"/><pb n="435"/>the others saw it they began to run away, and he ran after them; and he
            overtook three more of them; and of every man whom he smote with the club
            he made himself master; and thus he mastered seven of them. And he
            returned and bound the seven of them, and set them in a row, and he
            collected their swords and their clubs, and placed them together on one side;
            and he sat down and jeered at them saying: <quote>I begged you, my sons, saying,
               <quote>Leave me alone</quote>, and <quote>Why do you seek the poor man?</quote> And I was distressed that 
               you did not comply with my request. And now, my sons, rest and
               be quiet till the morning</quote>. And, lying as they were bound and disgraced,
            they went on adjuring him to release them and to be merciful to them, and
            not to deliver them up. But he on his side went on jeering at their valour,
            and saying to them: <quote>Learn never again to trust to your valour, and do
               not at any time (TOT) despise and look down upon a poor man</quote>. And, 
            when he had been admonishing them till the morning, those also who came
            to him saw them, and they went on threatening to deliver them up to the
            prefect (Cwxpxos). But he on his side would not consent, but released them
            and sent them away with much advice and admonition; but their clubs and
            their swords he took from them. But three of them ran away and escaped
            <pb n="638"/><pb n="436"/>from his hands. When these things had thus fallen out, and it had become
            known to the king and the prefect (ünaxos) and the rest of the senators
            (cuyxnnrxós), these wondered at him and spoke much about him. Moreover
            there came a chamberlain also as well; and on seeing the swords and the
            clubs and learning about the rest he was surprised; and he took the swords
            and the clubs, and brought them in and showed them to the queen and the
            king; and on seeing them they said: <quote>Here besides power of prayer power
               of arm was also required</quote>. And, when he had for many years<note></note> been.
            dwelling on these mountains in this way and distinguishing himself by
            excellent practices, he was hard pressed by his bodily requirements through
            the fact that the work of his hands was not sufficient for his requirements
            and for hospitality to poor brothers, and further that he had determined
            in his mind never to support himself on the labour and sweat, that is on
            the sins, of others<note></note>. And, while he was going about on these mountains
            and among the villas (wpotsrsov), he saw a villa<note></note> suited for a life of retreat,
            and he considered that, if he performed spiritual employment in it, it would
            <pb n="639"/><pb n="437"/>suit him for manual labour also as well and for the employment of providing
            for his necessary requirements. And so he spoke to one of the chamberlains<note></note>, 
            and he hought it from another chamberlain for live pounds (Aires)
            of gold<note></note>, and thenceforth he used to sow and reap in it, and supply his
            own private needs and those of those of the other people who used to visit
            him, and of the poor. And, when he had completed five years in it, while
            many persons among the magnates and others used to visit him, there happened 
            the beginning of the great plague in the year eight hundred and fifty-three; 
            and, while he was practising mighty spiritual labours, and subduing
            his body and bringing it into subjection<note></note> by tilling the ground for his necessary 
            bodily requirements, and was reproving and admonishing and teaching
            all who visited him by the spiritual teaching of the divine scriptures, and
            stoutly always reproving the king and queen with great freedom (ñaßßncía)
            without fear, and everyone marvelled at his teaching and at his deeds and at
            his words, and at the stoutness of his soul in addition to that of his body and
            in addition to his thoughts<note></note>, then by the sudden destruction ot the plague, as
            <pb n="640"/><pb n="438"/>has been stated above, everyone was in perturbation and doubt and confusion,
            insomuch that the blessed man passed his time in affliction and great sorrow,
            and occupied himself with constant prayer and petition to God, while he asked
            of God, and a revelation was made to him about his own personal departure
            also after a short time. Then he sent a pressing message to the chief men
            of the palace (parov), asking them to send him craftsmen and supplies
            that he might make a tomb for strangers and also for himself. And, when
            the craftsmen and the supplies had been sent to him, and men to superintend
            the work, in a few days he built these two great houses, the strangers'
            tombs, and completed porticoes, and built a martyrs' chapel also as well
            between them, and he also made a coffin (?)<note></note> for himself, in which he was
            privileged to be laid<note></note>. But, when he had completed the work, and knew
            that the day was at hand that had been told him in the revelation about his
            end, then, the coffin (?)<note></note> being open which he had prepared for himself
            to be laid in it, while he was kneeling and praying on behalf of the whole
            world of men, on the third day he yielded up his spirit. And, this having
            <pb n="641"/><pb n="439"/>been made known to the king and queen, with great zeal they sent some
            of the leading and eminent men of the palace (Taλátov), chamberlains and
            senators (cuyxnrx) and bishops and elergymen and many monks, and
            thus they buried the blessed man's body with a great procession. We have
            recorded these few things out of many for the sake of a memorial and in
            order to gain his blessing and his prayers, having passed over many of his
            labours and of his practices on account of the length of the history.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of father Mare the solitary is ended<note></note>.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
