<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/830">Leontius</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/830 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            The character therefore of this blessed Leontius the presbyter was very
            like that of the blessed Aaron; insomuch that they accordingly vied with one
            another; and thus also one would be eager to excel the other in modes of life,
            and to surpass him in spiritual labours, and to imitate him in humility and
            to resemble him in obedience, and that in all matters they should be imitators
            of religious practices, and especially in love toward one another and toward
            everyone. But this devout Leontius was by birth (yévos) from Ingilene from
            a village called ʿbwbnt; and he lived in the holy monastery of the blessed
            Mar Samuel". And, occasion having once called him to go up himself to the
            <pb n="646"/><pb n="444"/>royal city with some blessed men from the same convent, he conceived a
            desire to live with us and with the blessed Aaron and the rest, and he remained
            with us, living a whole-hearted and laborious life, so that once on learning
            about a certain excellent man who was passing his life in great labours
            of pilgrimage he was moved with zeal himself also to labour in the same
            course with the other blessed man who was called Kashish" and was a
            member of our own convent and had been brought up with us from our
            childhood. And so both of them went forth in this zeal for pilgrimage, each of
            them separately, while both also let their hair grow long in secular fashion,
            in order that they might not be recognised and honoured by men as monks.
            When they had been thus travelling in the regions of the east and the west
            and the south each of them separately for many years, and when the brunt
            of trials had fallen heavily upon them, after some years they came to us,
            that is first the blessed Leontius. When he had for some time been labouring
            with us in the service of God in saving persons from paganism also, he at
            last attained to ordination as a presbyter, even as the blessed Kashish also
            who named himself John, who was a presbyter, himself also too attained to
            ordination to the great and honourable yoke of the episcopacy"; that is,
            <pb n="647"/><pb n="445"/>both of them were with compulsion and by great effort brought to this against
            their will by the use of many artifices. When the blessed Leontius had
            completed twenty years more or less in the convent that is with us in divine
            employments with constancy and earnestness, then he finished the course
            of his practices and departed from the world, and he too was laid with the
            blessed Aaron. But the blessed John, who is also Kashish, was still in the
            body when these things were written, engaged in the same divine practices
            and living in advanced old age.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the blessed Leontius is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
