<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/831">Abraham the Priest</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/831 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            This blessed Abraham therefore, the old man, was by birth (yévos) from
            the district of Sophanene, from a village called such-and-such<note>Or <quote>Flḥt</quote>. The reading is doubtful.</note>. This man,
            <pb n="648"/><pb n="446"/>having at a certain time come to the royal city, betook himself to us; and,
            having been received by us as a stranger, on the second day he cast himself
            down weeping and entreating to be received by us, and admitted to the
            monastic order (rzyua). And we on our side, observing the burden of his
            old age, thought that his request was a pretext and not genuine, and<note></note> we
            continued closely examining him, that he might let us know the true reason
            of his coming to the royal city, and if he had any fact to tell us about his
            intention, and we would not fail in anything that we could do to help him.
            And he, having cast himself upon his face and weeping, continued swearing
            to us <quote>I have no concern in this world, except to repent for my sins, and if
               may be admitted to the monastic habit (yux), that in it I may serve and
               please God during this remnant of life which he has appointed for me</quote>.
            And, after much conversation had been held with him concerning these
            things, we allowed him to make trial of his own self, while we also on our
            part observed his perseverance. And, when he had thus completed two
            years, being constant in fasting and prayer and constant vigil by night, and
            humility and obedience, while he was also always entreating to be admitted to
            <pb n="649"/><pb n="447"/>the order and the beloved habit (oxña) of monasticism, so also upon many
            testimonies and admonitions he was admitted to the monastic habit (gyiua).
            And, while he was accomplishing the labour of his practices every day with
            many tears and much earnestness and humility, and when he had reached the
            period of five years after his training, he was on account of his marvellous
            modes of life by constraint and much compulsion admitted to ordination to
            the presbyterate. But after a short time his bodily son also whose name was
            Zwṭʾ, and his brother's son whose name was Daniel from Syria came to
            him, having learned about his modes of life, and that he had been admitted
            to the monastic habit (cxi). And, when they saw him thus lahouring in
            the practices of religion, God opened their own heart also as well, and they
            began to request that they also as well might be admitted to the honoured
            monastic habit (oxña). And while he himself from that time continued giving
            them much admonition and correction and teaching, he was presenting a
            petition on their behalf that they might be received. And, this having also
            been done in order to gratify him, they also as well were taught<note></note> the devout
            monastic habit (ryrus), living a whole-heartod and obedient life, with all
            earnestness and religion. After a period of some years they also were
            <pb n="650"/><pb n="448"/>admitted to the rank of the diaconate; and thenceforth for many years they
            earnestly and whole-heartedly and obediently occupied themselves with
            us in the work of the ministry in the district of Asia in converting men from
            the deceitfulness of paganism, gratifying our soul every day by their
            earnestness and whole-heartedness and diligence, with the old man Abraham
            and the devout Aaron and Leontius the presbyters, with all the other
            strenuous workers their other brothers, of whom also too we shall one after
            another make record, each one of whom worked and laboured strenuously
            in his time without weariness in the householder's vineyard<note></note>, that is in the
            great salvation which God's grace wrought in our times, consisting in the
            conversion of many thousands from the worship of fiends and the ceremonies
            of idolatry to the fear of God. While then we were engaged in the same
            ministry in the districts of Caria, Daniel the deacon ended his course in the
            same ministry, seeing wonderful visions, and it having been revealed to
            him that he would be carried away to the blissful country; and, having fallen
            asleep, he was laid in the monastery called that of Gordiana hard by the
            city of Antioch in Caria. And, when we returned to the royal city, the
            blessed Abraham himself also ended the course of his life-practices in a
            <pb n="651"/><pb n="449"/>good old age; and he was laid with his blessed spiritual brothers Aaron
            and Leontius. And the blessed Zwṭʾ was afterwards admitted to the honour
            of the presbyterate, and he took over the charge of the whole convent and
            all its belongings with great diligence and much single-mindedness, insomuch
            that he laboured at the completion and restoration of the building of the
            martyrs' chapel of this monastery<note></note> and wearied himself excessively beyond
            his strength, together with all the rest of our brothers, and by their means
            it was completed, when we ourselves had gone back again, and were engaged
            in the work of the ministry in the same districts of Asia. And, when after
            the space of a year and a half we came back, and saw the product of
            his labours and his industry, we were astonished and gave thanks to God,
            though for fear of pride we did not tell him openly (?)<note></note>. At the same time he
            also too was brought to the consummation of death, and gained the privilege
            of being laid by the bones of his father the holy old man.
         </p>
         <p>
            It is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
