<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/832">Bassianus, Romanus, and Simeon</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/832 -->
         <head>Next the Forty-First History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1630">Bassian</persName> the Solitary, And
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2040">Romanus</persName> the Presbyter and Visitor of the Great Convent of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/233">Thel 'Adda'</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n450-1"></ptr>,
            and of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2093">Simeon</persName> the Archimandrite<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n450-2"></ptr>, Who Are Laid in the Sepulchre With
            These Holy Old Men<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n450-3"></ptr>.</head>
         <p>
            To describe the rest of the practices and asceticism and manner of life
            in the desert of this blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1630">Bassian</persName> the presbyter and solitary, things which
            we have not seen nor heard, seemed to us superfluous; but, when for a short
            time we had received the privilege of intercourse with the great blessed man of
            God, in his labour and his speech and the affliction of his tears and his
            teaching, while he mourned and wept first for his disturbance and his ejection
            from the desert, which (he said) was brought about through the violence and
            contentious conduct of other solitaries, then afterwards also, when we were
            making inquiries of him with regard to the affliction shown by his many
            floods of tears and constant sighs, he showed greater distress by grievous
            <pb n="653"/><pb n="451"/>sobs, saying, <quote>Who then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>), pray, is there even if he were a man
               possessing a heart of stone who would not weep over the delusion and
               captivity and destruction of the race (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) of men? For lo! everyone is running
               against himself contrary to religion, and everyone is with all his strength
               intent upon evil things with naught to hinder, and we all behave ourselves
               like men without God, and like deaf animals without law (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>) and without
               fear of the dreadful judgment to come, and everyone is of his own will
               casting himself into the pit of destruction unto destruction; and by all this
               destruction of Adam's race a festival has been created for Satan and joy for
               the fiends who are carrying away the race (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) of Adam that was fashioned
               in love and after its deviation was rescued; and now lo! the hosts of darkness
               are mocking at its destruction, and rejoice to be carrying many to participate 
               in the torment of their destruction. In regard of these things,
               our father, who would not weep, who would not be afflicted, who would not
               wail, who would not make mourning like a jackal, and lamentation like a
               jackal's whelp, since the force of error and destruction has borne away men
               who are bought by the blood of God and rescued by his cross?</quote>. While
            the blessed man was repeating these things and more than them in his
            <pb n="654"/><pb n="452"/>affliction, all who heard him were marvelling; and, despising all this confused
            life, they also as well were being brought to afflictions and tears with him,
            everyone marvelling at the blessed man's labour and affliction and teaching.
            While he was doing and teaching these things, a revelation was made to him
            concerning his end and his departure after a few days, while he said,
            <quote>Pray also for the miserable sinner, for at the end of twenty days I shall
               depart from the body</quote>, having also adjured my meanness, <quote>Bury this my
                  sinful body in your monastery, and pray for me</quote>. When we had been saying
            these many things, and that sabbath-day<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n452-1"></ptr> was at hand, he rose and prayed
            and offered the oblation, and gave it to many, having received it also himself,
            and bade farewell to all. And during the night he became ill, and on the
            twentieth day he fell asleep; and so we carried him in a procession over the
            water to our monastery<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n452-2"></ptr> according to his injunction; and his holy body was
            buried and laid in the same tomb according to his injunction; by whose
            prayers together with those of all the saints who please God may all we
            sinners who provoke our Creator be admitted to mercy. Yea and Amen!
            And the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2040">Romanus</persName> who also was a great and whole-hearted old man,
            <pb n="655"/><pb n="453"/>who was <foreign>apocrisiarius</foreign> of the great convent of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/233">Thel 'Adda</placeName>, who himself also
            as well lived in the same house of a certain great and believing man in
            which the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1630">Bassian</persName> also fell asleep, was also afterwards himself too
            brought to the departure from the bodily life, and himself also was laid in
            the same grave with the rest of the blessed men.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1630">Bassian</persName> the solitary and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2040">Romanus</persName> the presbyter is ended.
         </p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n450-1">Near Antioch (Wright, CBM., p. 498).</note>
            <note xml:id="n450-2">There is nothing about Simeon in the ch., nor is he mentioned in the subscription. See Introd., p. VII.</note>
            <note xml:id="n450-3">In B the title is: <hi rend="singleQuote">A history concerning the blessed B. the solitary by the same Mar John of Asia</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n452-1">I.e., the day on which he was to go to his rest.</note>
            <note xml:id="n452-2">See p. 431, n. 3.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
