<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/833">Mari, Sergius, and Daniel</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/833 -->
         <head>Next the Forty-Second History, of the Three Blessed Archimandrites, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1876">Mari</persName>,
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2070">Sergius</persName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1672">Daniel</persName>, 
            Who Themselves Also as Well Are Laid in the Same House.</head>
         <p>
            These three blessed men therefore ended their courses here in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">royal 
               city</placeName>. This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1876">Mari</persName> was by birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Anzetene</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n453-1"/>, and received
            training from a blessed great man of God, who himself also was named <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1876">Mari</persName>,
            a man of labours and a <persName>Nazirite</persName>, besides being also versed in the Scriptures
            and a doctor, and was at first a clergyman of the church also, but at last,
            <pb n="656"/><pb n="454"/>seeing his error and the course of the world's times, left all his property,
            and went out and sought for himself a monastery outside his village, the
            name of which was <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2794">Hula</placeName> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ύλη?</foreign>); so that he himself also was called <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1876">Mari</persName> of
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2794">Hula</placeName>; and thus he mortified himself by mighty labours, asceticism and self-abnegation, 
            and much watching, and fasting and prayers, so that men
            marvelled at his practices, even as he stubbornly endured many conflicts
            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of persecution arising from the heretics. And, whereas in the previous
            histories we have recorded a small proportion of facts about this same
            blessed man<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n454-1"/>, we now forbear to relate his history. This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1876">Mari</persName>
            therefore is this man's disciple, who took upon himself his master's obedience
            to the full, and in practising it even went beyond him, in constant fasting
            and perfect abstinence, and much watching, with the rest of the excellent
            and devout rules of monasticism, so that, when he had lived to a long period
            of years, his body was dried up and enfeebled from the severity of the
            labours; and he also lived a considerable time in the convent with us both in
            the east and in the west. And after his master's decease he himself with
            other disciples was thenceforth gaining distinction, so that he also endured
            <pb n="657"/><pb n="455"/>much persecution; who also in the persecution came to the same <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">royal
               city</placeName>, and afterwards ended his course here in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">royal city</placeName>.
         </p>
         <p>
            This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2070">Sergius</persName> was archimandrite of the convent called that of the
            house of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2784">Mar Gyln</placeName>, in the territory of the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2737">Amida</placeName>; and moreover the
            blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1672">Daniel</persName> also was archimandrite of the monastery called that of the
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2822">Mšyk’</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n455-1"/> in the district of Sophanene; both of whom together came up hither
            to the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">royal city</placeName> for the sake of the needs of their convents, they also too
            being famous for devout practices of excellence and monastic labours. And,
            while they were trusting to human assistance for their convents, something
            which they had perhaps not expected so quickly suddenly overtook them
            both, that is the consummation of death, one after the other, in twenty days;
            and they were laid in the place of sepulture of this convent, together with
            all the other many blessed men, monks and laymen, many excellent men
            who are not recorded, whose bodies were interred in the same place; through
            whose prayers with those of all the saints may God grant us all forgiveness
            <pb n="658"/><pb n="456"/>of since with them, and stablish this convent which received their coffins with
            all the other holy convents to his glory for ever and ever. Amen!
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the three blessed archimandrites. <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1876">Mari</persName>, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2070">Sergius</persName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1672">Daniel</persName>, is ended.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n456-1"/>
         </p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n453-1">Syr. <hi rend="singleQuote">hanzit</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n454-1">Ch. 9. There however he is called Mare.</note>
            <note xml:id="n455-1">V. D. and L. render <hi rend="singleQuote">Tabernaculorum</hi>, and would therefore appy. read <!-- eb, Syriac. -->.</note>
            <note xml:id="n456-1">Ms. om.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
