<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/834">Abraham, Cyriacus, Barhadbeshabba and Sergius</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/834 -->
         <head>Next the Forty-Third History, of the Four Excellent Deacons, Earnest
            in Religion, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1547">Abraham</persName>, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1664">Cyriac</persName>, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1625">Barhadbshabba</persName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2069">Sergius</persName>.</head>
         <p>
            As for these four devout deacons therefore, strenuous workers and earnest
            performers of the divine ministry which was carried out in the districts of
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2747">Asia</placeName> for the sake of delivering from the error of paganism souls which from
            the beginning from the foundations of the world had been sitting in the
            darkness of idolatry, when each of them laboured earnestly with us down to
            the end of the life that is derived from the body, so that these devout men also
            were laid together in the sepulchre, while all of them were by birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>)
            <pb n="659"/><pb n="457"/>from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n457-1"></ptr>, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1664">Cyriac</persName>, who laboured with us for some years before everyone
            after these first old men<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n457-2"></ptr>, was by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/134">Maiferkat</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n457-3"></ptr>,
            and the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1547">Abraham</persName>, who was powerful in word and in deed, and
            above all in body, was by birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from the country of the Persians, and
            gratified our spirit more than others by his earnestness, being adorned wtih
            abstinence and with self-abnegation and with zeal and humility and obedience, 
            and with all spiritual qualities, and as to <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1625">Barhadbshabba</persName> too he was
            by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2798">Ingilene</placeName>, from a village called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2745">Arʿa Rabtha</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n457-4"></ptr>, who
            also was adorned with earnestness and ready to show obedience, and very
            zealous in reciting service, and the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2069">Sergius</persName> moreover was by his
            birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) an <persName>Armenian</persName>, who also underwent great conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) in the
            work of the ministry of the house of God; and the four of them with all the
            rest gained a blessed ending, since amid the same spiritual employment and
            the tiring nature of the countries and the high rugged mountains of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2747">Asia</placeName>
            each one of them ran zealously and mightily in his time, and was strengthened 
            to abolish paganism, and overthrow idolatry, and uproot altars and
            destroy shrines (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ναός</foreign>) and cut down trees in ardent religious zeal; and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n457-5"></ptr> each
            <pb n="660"/><pb n="458"/>one of them in his time together with the holy old men who were before
            them worked earnestly, and all of them also toiled and laboured with us with
            joy and great earnestness in building ninety-two churches and ten monasteries 
            in four provinces (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ύπαρχίας</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n458-1"></ptr>, which were erected by the help of the
            heavenly power; a thing which justice also requires us to bring into the
            record of memorials of blessed character for the sake of a future good remembrance 
            for all these strenuous workers, in order that we may not be reproached
            by righteousness for having seen and known their labours and troubles.
            and done injustice to their memories, especially since we marvel and wonder
            at the dispensation of God's mercy, and his just and inscrutable judgments, how
            in a short time he led them all one after another to the end of this tumultuous
            life and to the gathering together of their bodies, which he caused to lie
            by one another, and all of them to his eternal rest from the vexation of the
            body, while we on our part are still bound in the ropes of our sins and
            involved in bodily temptations in this life of turmoil, and of vanity and vexation 
            of spirit<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n458-2"></ptr>.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1547">Abraham</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1664">Cyriac</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1625">Barhadbshabba</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2069">Sergius</persName>
            the deacons is ended.
         </p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n457-1">I cannot reconcile this with the statements following.</note>
            <note xml:id="n457-2">Leontinus and Kashish (?); see ch. 39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n457-3">Martyropolis.</note>
            <note xml:id="n457-4">See p. 56. It was perhaps the author's native place (p. 61).</note>
            <note xml:id="n457-5">Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n458-1">See p. 416, n. 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n458-2">Eccl., I, 14; 11, 17, 26; IV, 4, 16.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
