<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/835">Tribunus</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/835 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            This excellent blessed man Tribunus therefore, who in a lay station
            carried out spiritual practices, was by his birth (yévos) from the district of
            Sophanene, from a village called Beth Rwmntʾ<note></note>; a man who from an early
            age had been taught religion, and was constantly occupied in fasting and
            prayer and constant attendance in churches and monasteries with the great
            and excellent blessed men, and used to hear and learn the psalms and the
            Scriptures, even as his parents also set themselves to teach him to read and
            write Greek, and he besides Greek learned Syriac also<note></note>, and meditated, as
            it is written, <quote>on the law of the Lord day and night</quote><note></note>. While then he was
            constantly occupied in reciting service and reading the Scriptures in Greek
            and Syriac, and while his parents desired to yoke him in worldly intercourse
            with a wife, and expected that he would also be their heir, because he was
            indeed their only child, and<note></note> advised him to take a wife, as she had been
            <pb n="662"/><pb n="460"/>betrothed and provided, he on his side opposed, and he would answer his
            parents, saying, <quote>As for me why should I go and fall into the turmoil of
               this world, and give material to sin and death? If I indeed obey you, then
               I shall also be bound by the world and many sins, and, if it happens that I
               beget children, they will be spoil for death, and I shall again sit mourning
               for them</quote>; and the many other things which, as he often repeated in our
            presence, he would answer to his parents, so that they were reduced to great
            distress, because they saw that the devout young man so despised the
            world and all that is in it; since indeed they relied upon riches, houses and
            estates and lands, and male and female slaves, and saw that he who they
            thought was heir of these things spurned and despised them, and would not
            consent to look at them at all, but was constantly occupied with religion
            and spiritual employment, and used to have recourse to saints who were
            stylites and recluses and laboured in the excellent life, and attached himself
            to them, and was taught, so that thenceforth they held him as a beloved son
            in all the convents, and especially in the devout convent of Fyṭr the devout
            and great blessed men Habib and Zʿura, who shine at the beginning of
            these histories<note></note> like rays of light; so that after the decease of Habib the
            <pb n="663"/><pb n="461"/>mighty in spiritual strength, when his perfect disciple Zʿura at last earned
            the privilege of succeeding him in the administration, and also of ascending
            the pillar and accomplishing the course of his practices on it, and, when
            this blessed Zʿura had for a period of some years while in an earthly body
            been engaged in heavenly and sublime employments on a column between
            earth and heaven, by the envy of the enemy of righteousness a persecution
            was stirred up against him by those who honoured the synod of Chalcedon,
            and that so violent that they brought the blessed man down from his pillar,
            and he was expelled with all his convent; and he, when these things were
            inflicted upon him, without delay hastened to the royal city to utter a reproof
            on account of these things, as have been recorded by us at short length
            in the histories relating to these things; and he took the devout Tribunus
            with him in lay attire (xña) as an interpreter of the Greek tongue. And
            so he went up with him, and lived with his disciples and with him, imitating
            their practices and occupied in spiritual employment; insomuch that he was
            consequently desirous of being admitted to the devout monastic habit
            (xx) also, and the blessed men would not allow him, saying <quote>It is
               <pb n="664"/><pb n="462"/>better both for you and for us that you should go in and out of the city and
               the palace (waórtov( as a layman, and carry communications (doxpives) for
               us, and not go about the city clad in the habit (xua) and cause the habit
               (cyfuc) to be made an object of mockery</quote>. And so he performed the service
            of the old man and of his convent all the days of his<note></note> life, insomuch that he
            gained easier entry and more freedom (appnoía), and they even thrust the office
            of a count on him under constraint by his<note></note> command, saying, <quote>This will be no
               impediment to your practices; and, when you wish, it is easy for you to give
               up the office. But for the sake of our communications (droxpivss) take it upon
               you</quote>. And so under constraint he accepted an earthly employment, while
            the whole of his own mind and energy was constantly occupied in heavenly
            employments and bound up in them. When after some years during which
            he had served the blessed man the blessed man departed from the world,
            then the excellent blessed man remained in the cell in which he dwelt in the
            city, accomplishing the labour of his practices on a great scale, having also
            added to his spiritual labours the extra labour of hospitality and the relief
            of the poor, living and delighting also in voluntary poverty, and rejoicing
            in it, so that, if it happened also that there was a superfluity of anything
            <pb n="665"/><pb n="463"/>in his cell, he would set himself to scatter it among the needy. Since many
            of the chamberlains and of the distinguished members of the senate (súyXλNTOS)
            were acquainted with him because of the blessed man<note></note>, and moreover loved
            him on account of his venerable manner of life, and used to beg him to do
            them the favour of dwelling with them, or even only to stay with each of
            them, and to receive some gift from them, so also he would flee and shrink
            as from the perpetration of an evil act, saying, <quote>My sins are enough for
               me; and to share in other men's sins", or to refresh myself by the sweat
               of others I will never consent</quote>. And so he was constant in maintaining a
            life of retirement and the performance of righteous acts, though he had
            reached old age, still hoping to attain the habit (xñuz), passing most of
            his days in this our convent and that of the blessed Zʿura, while he also
            practised handiwork for his needs, some carpentering; and moreover he made
            partridge-cages (xλw6ós) and sold them, and gained his living, with his two
            slaves, who also served him devoutly; for, when they went out to monasteries 
            or anywhere, then they also continually practised vigils and fasting and
            <pb n="666"/><pb n="464"/>recitation of service and constant prayers in company with all the members
            of the convent; and, when they were remaining continuously in the cell,
            the blessed Tribunus was constantly occupied in the same way night and
            day, and what is especially deserving of admiration is that he rejoiced in
            poverty and took pleasure in scarceness; so that, if it happened that at any
            time he actually had a superfluity, he was much displeased at this, and set
            himself to scatter and to spend his superfluity; so that he took pleasure in
            scarceness, giving thanks. I wish therefore to set down and place on record.
            something about a temptation of his and about the man's courage and the
            conflict (yov) which he sustained. This man then had once thought of
            changing his place of residence; and he went out and was going round the
            mansions, looking for a tenement convenient for him to live in; and, having
            found 'inn<note></note> written and fixed up on the door of a certain mansion, he asked
            for the porter (ooтiápios) to go up and show him the tenement. And, since
            the porter (ooviάptos) himself was not there, but as if by the opposition of
            Satan his wife was present, who was a young woman and was very worldly
            in her appearance, she said to him <quote>Come with me and I will myself show
               <pb n="667"/><pb n="465"/>you the rooms that are advertised</quote>. And, when she had taken the key
            (xλɛida) and gone up and opened them, they both went in. And, as he was
            going round to look, while she on her side was displaying a snare of sin
            before him, a sinful passion was aroused in her, and she went on madly
            laughing in his face, while she also seized him, and began as if by the
            kisses of sin to grasp him and entice him to fall with her. And, as he was
            rebuking her and flinging and casting her hands off him, she on her side all
            the more as if by the machination of the devil, who was desirous of catching
            the brave man by a snare, and setting a blemish on his beauties and staining
            him, he<note></note> yet more entered into her, making her madly grasp the blessed
            man, while she also threw herself in front of him to tempt him to lasciviousness, 
            intertwining herself with him with all the lasciviousness and
            violence of impurity and adultery, using<note></note> foul words which we do not wish
            even to write down and pollute the ears or mind of the hearer and record.
            But the man armed with the divine power flung and threw her off and
            withdrew himself from her, reproving and rebuking her sternly and saying,
            <quote>The Lord rebuke you, woman, and the fiend who clothed you in so much
               shamelessness and wickedness that you should dare to defile the path of
               <pb n="668"/><pb n="466"/>intercourse with your husband, and hold intercourse with another in violation
               of the law (vöuos), and think to stain me the sinner with you</quote>. And so
            this brave man like Joseph the just fled and left that house and all that
            neighbourhood in great trepidation, so that he would relate these things to
            us and to many others, about the battle and conflict (żywv) which he had, and
            about the machination of the evil one who was bitter against the wise
            merchant in order to make spoil of his merchandise. And so, being illustrious 
            for the excellence of this manner of living, he ended his life heroically,
            bearing good testimony, and he too as well was laid in the sepulchre of our
            convent.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of Tribunus the count is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
