<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/836">Isaac</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/836 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            As therefore it is written that <quote>a city that is built upon a mountain cannot
               be hid</quote><note></note>, so also the light of the excellent manner of life of perfect men who
            <pb n="669"/><pb n="467"/>have employed themselves in works of excellence cannot be concealed.
            This blessed Isaac therefore was by his birth (yévos) from the city of Dara, and
            he had also a wife and children and a house, and the office of a <foreign>protector</foreign><note></note>,
            while he was constantly occupied in fasting and prayer and constant
            vigil, and in perpetual alms, so that out of the fervour of divine zeal he left
            house and wife and children as it is written<note></note> for the sake of the hope of the
            promise of eternal life, and departed, and came to the royal city. And,
            having entered the ministering office<note></note> (Sixxovía) of those who bathe the sick
            at night, and laboured with them in the labour and service of the house of
            God, he began to be known and honoured by many. And, being constantly
            occupied in practices of asceticism and so on, he secretly formed the plan of
            engaging in another spiritual employment; and so he secretly went out to one
            of the hospitals (evodoxas) that was a little way from the city and hired
            himself out in it as a sick-attendant. And he took off all his clothes and sold
            them and gave to the poor; and he bought some hempen sackcloth and
            clothed himself in it. And thus he was henceforth a diligent attendant on
            the sick, since the affair of the sick openly gave him an opportunity and an
            <pb n="670"/><pb n="468"/>outlet for his secret manner of life, for his watching and vigilance and the
            recitation of service by night, he being vigilant and regular and diligent and
            standing before the sick, and busying himself about ministering to them
            and relieving them, so that all to whom he ministered blessed him, and
            continually prayed for him; but the other sick-attendants with the superintendent 
            (evodoɣáptos) and all who were with him marvelled and wondered at
            the diligence and watching and fasting of the vigilant and diligent blessed
            man Isaac. But his wife, having learned that he had gone to the royal city,
            herself also too quickly went out after him, and she went about for a long
            time seeking him, insomuch that she learned from others that he was attending 
            on the sick in such-and-such a hospital (čevodoxεtov). And, when she
            went and asked about him and he heard about it, he hid himself from her for
            a long time, while she lay in wait and went up and down to see him, and
            was quite unable to do so. But at last he sent her a message: <quote>Go away
               from here, do not lie in wait and go up and down. You cannot see my face
               now; but go away now and wait, keeping quiet; and at the end of
               two months you shall come and see me</quote>. Having therefore received his
            word and put confidence in his truthfulness, knowing indeed that he would
            <pb n="671"/><pb n="469"/>not break his word, she withdrew and went away and sat quiet until the
            end of two months; and after that time, having gone with confidence to see
            him in the morning, she found that he was dead, and had been laid on a bench
            (oxapvíov), and wrapt in a sheet; and that woman by her wailing and
            lamentation and weeping declared the truth of the miracle, and the foreknowledge 
            and<note></note> that in the exercise of discretion and humility for God's sake, and
            not as a man in need, he had submitted to minister to the sick. And so
            everyone who heard of it was astonished, and a great number of people.
            hastened to accompany the blessed Isaac to the grave; and thus his body was
            buried with a great procession and much honour, everyone marvelling and
            wondering at him and serving God.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the perfect blessed man Isaac is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
