<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/839">Severus, Theodosius, Anthimus, Sergius and Paul, Patriarchs</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/839 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            It seemed to us a necessary thing and one that is very proper that by
            means of written memorials the history also of the perfect blessed fathers
            and great and spiritual pastors, the arch-fathers, the five patriarchs, Severus,
            Theodosius, Anthimus, Sergius, and Paul, should be given to the knowledge
            <pb n="685"/><pb n="483"/>of posterity in writing, among whom the blessed Severus like a valiant and
            heroic man first distinguished himself in mighty and intense conflicts (żywv)
            of persecution, having been chased from the city of Antioch, and departed
            to the city of Alexandria, and withdrawn to the deserts of Egypt, while he
            carried out to the full the monastic model in which he had before also
            lived a life of austerity and poverty, and he engaged in a splendid conflict
            (άyúv) of contention against Julian of Halicarnassus". Besides him moreover
            the blessed Theodosius also besides was chased and departed from Alexandria.
            While these were in banishment", the blessed Anthimus, who was bishop
            of the city of Trebizond, was summoned³ to the royal city, and on account
            of the excellence of his mode of life he was raised to the throne (0póvos) of
            the royal city itself; and, when he had retained the administration of that
            great throne (povos) for a considerable number of years", and had heard and
            learned about the persecution of the blessed men Severus" and Theodosius,
            and investigated and learned the reason of their banishment, which is the
            evil faith of the synod of Chalcedon, he chose for himself like the great Moses
            to undergo affliction with his brothers, and not for a short time take his
            <pb n="686"/><pb n="484"/>pleasure" among the evil impieties of Chalcedon. And so he spoke much
            with the king and made entreaty to him with regard to the peace of the
            churches, and with regard to summoning his brothers, and, when no attention 
            was paid to him, he took his pall and laid it on the altar before the
            king himself and departed, while he also wrote letters to the two patriarchs,
            as they also composed synodical letters to him²; and thus they made union
            with one another, and all the party of the believers was affected with great
            joy. But, when the queen saw the king's wrath against the blessed Anthimus 
            on account of what he had done, and his great threatening, she took
            him and hid him in a chamber in her palace (Taλátov), in order that men
            might not know what had befallen him, except only herself and two chamberlains 
            her accomplices, while even the king and everyone else might
            think that she had removed him and banished him entirely outside the city.
            And so for this reason the blessed man was in great peace, while he also
            performed his honourable labours and his great practices; because he had
            in fact been a monk before and he was so afterwards also, who never tasted
            bread, and also never drank wine, and had passed twenty-five years in this
            great abstinence, it having been in fact the whole time of the episcopate and of
            <pb n="687"/><pb n="485"/>his patriarchate; and thus he carried out the rule even after his expulsion
            also down to the end of his life, when he had also completed a space of ten years
            in hiding, until many thought that he was dead, until the time of the queen's
            death", and so he was discovered and made known, and he was received by the
            king, while he also made peace with him, and held him in great honour,
            till the end of the blessed man's life, and he used to make entreaty
            with regard to the peace of the church. But the blessed Severus had before
            these things been summoned by the king to the royal city on account of
            the peace of the church; and under great pressure from everyone he came,
            saying, <quote>Since it is everyone's will lo! I will go up, but it is impossible
               that anything whatever will be done by those who are in power</quote>; and so
            he went up, and passed two years" a labouring and teaching. And, when
            he saw that his statement that nothing would be done was being accomplished, 
            he went back to the southern regions of Alexandria, constantly
            occupying his time in the desert in retreat and asceticism and studying the
            writings of the fathers, and perfectly carrying out great labour and an
            abstemious life. And, when he had completed a period of some years in
            <pb n="688"/><pb n="486"/>his banishment, he fell into a sickness; and afterwards they carried him from
            the desert to a city of Egypt called Ksoi", and there he ended the course of
            his conflict (άyóv), and went to the Lord".
         </p>
         <p>
            But the blessed Theodosius, patriarch of Alexandria, also had been
            bravely contending in the conflict (ayov) of persecution for a considerable time,
            during all the lifetime of king Justinian, and did so after his death", even
            to the present time, which is the year eight, hundred and seventy-seven",
            (a new king having also succeeded in the same year, who is Justinian's sister's
            son, who also promises with the help of the blessed Theodosius to bring about
            the peace of the church), having carried on a contest for about thirty years
            in exile (¿oplx) from place to place and from country to country. And" he
            also as well ended the course of his practices in the same year, in the same
            royal city, nine months after the death of the same Justinian the king",
            nothing whatever having been done in the matter of the union of the church.
            And he completed thirty-one years and a half" in the conflicts (żyúv) of
            <pb n="689"/><pb n="487"/>persecution and exile (opia) from place to place, having also gained distinction 
            and renown all over the commonwealth (orsia) of us Romans, and he
            went in heroic fashion to the Lord. A period of some years therefore
            after the death of the blessed Severus the blessed Sergius succeeded him in
            orthodoxy (opodoíz)", who was by his birth (yévos) a man of Thella², a learned
            and well-read mam, and among men renovned and well-known and honoured,
            and as regards God devout and given to fasting and a Nazirite, and a keeper
            of vigils, and a lover of quietude, and of reading the Scriptures and the
            exposition of the fathers, so that he was skilful in his speech, and a man of
            understanding."
         </p>
         <p>
            This man therefore, having attained ordination (ystoorovic) to the patriarchate 
            while in the royal city, and presided over the church, teaching and
            comforting and edifying and establishing everyone in the truth for three
            years after he had received the right hand of the high-priesthood of Antioch,
            ended his course, and was carried from the life here to our Lord in the same
            royal city. After three years from this man's decease a certain Alexandrine
            whose name was Paul attained the high-priesthood of the same see, that is
            <pb n="690"/><pb n="488"/>outside in banishment; who also down to the present day after king Justinian's
            death is in the body with archbishop Theodosius."
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the five blessed patriarchs who distinguished themselves in exile
            (opic) in the time of the persecution is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
