<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/840">Jacob</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/840 -->
         <head>Next the Forty-Ninth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> the Bishop and
            Brave and Valiant Combatant (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγωνιστής</foreign>) ..</head>
         <p>
            It would not therefore be easy for any one to approach the task of relating
            the history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> without fear, a history which transcends all
            the extent of the limits of narrative, a man whose story is higher than all
            words and all understandings; but out of love of truth we will through our
            poor language and in our contemptible writing make both a memorial of a
            few of his own excellencies and a picture of the exhalation of his spiritual
            beauties. This saint therefore and veritable man of God from his boyhood,
            while he also was by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/200">Thella</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n488-2"/>, was trained in the celebrated 
            convent of the monastery called that of Fsiltha<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n488-3"/>, but some cause
            <pb n="691"/><pb n="489"/>summoned him together with the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3258">Sergius</persName> whom we mentioned
             above<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n489-1"/>, who also attained the honour of the high-priesthood through the
            blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName>, with him first to go up to the royal city on account of the
            faith<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n489-2"/>. And, when they had been received with great honour by the believing 
            queen, and she had given them also a house and the rest of what they
            needed, thenceforth the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> dwelt alone in a little cell, in great
            retirement and arduous labours, and asceticism beyond measure, and in
            extraordinary poverty moreover in mode of life and in clothing, since he
            would cut one thick and ugly cloak of withes (?) into two, and out of its
            halves make what was required for his clothing and his scanty covering<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n489-3"/>, and,
            though the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3258">Sergius</persName> also as well did as he did and associated himself
            with him in fasting and vigil and constant recitation of service, yet he fell
            very far short of the standard of his retirement and his severe practices, on
            account of the communications brought by many who used to come to them
            and with whom he was required to speak; but the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> entirely
            refused to take part in these things, and refused also to appear during the
            <pb n="692"/><pb n="490"/>day outside his cell. But, when he had been engaged for a period of about
            fifteen years in these labours in the same royal city in his cell, then by the
            provision and at the instigation of the believing queen he was under great
            pressure summoned to the episcopacy, together with another blessed man
            from the country of <placeName>Arabia</placeName> whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3266">Theodore</persName>; because the party of
            the believers had diminished and a deficiency had moreover arisen in the
            order of the priesthood over all the commonwealth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πολιτεία</foreign>) of the party of
            the believers. And, when both had received the high-priesthood, that is the
            blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> that of the city of <placeName>Edessa</placeName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3266">Theodore</persName> that of <placeName>Hirtha</placeName> of the
            Saracens<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n490-1"/>, then he armed himself with divine strength, and went out to the
            work of his ministry, while he thenceforth began to pour out the priesthood
            derived from him copiously over the regions in all the eastern districts, like
            a great river in the days of <persName>Nisan</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n490-2"/>, having entered upon the high road of
            heroism at a vigorous spiritual pace without ceasing or resting night and
            day, while in accordance with the saying of the apostle he clothed himself in
            the breastplate of righteousness, and girded his loins with the perfection of
            faith, and took hold of the shield of salvation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n490-3"/>, while he was at all times.
            carrying on a contest on behalf of the truth <quote>on the right hand and on the left,
               <pb n="693"/><pb n="491"/>in glory and in dishonour</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n491-1"/>. And so in the upper and lower countries, while
            he was running the vigorous course of heroism without ceasing from the
            Persian frontier even as for as the royal city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">Constantinople</placeName>, and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>
            and all the countries, and fulfilling the work of the ministry to all the orthodox
            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξοι</foreign>) believers, not only by organizing the clergy and the giving of the
            priesthood, but also by consoling and comforting and edifying and strengthening 
            and teaching all the party of the believers everywhere<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n491-2"/>; so that consequently 
            his fame was carried over all quarters, and in every country and city;
            so that all the synodite bishops from all sides were exasperated, and made
            threats against him to arrest him and tear him in pieces. And, while they
            were running after him with menaces in all quarters, he was sheltered by
            the divine grace, and was not delivered into the hands of his pursuers, and of
            those who sought his life<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n491-3"/>. For, whenever he went to any district, he would
            complete all the work of his ministry in one night perhaps and one day, and
            would pass the next night thirty or forty miles or more farther on; and,
            whenever news of him was heard in one district, and his pursuers went out
            after him, the brave man would be found in his heroism fulfilling his work in
            <pb n="694"/><pb n="492"/>another district, while those who were running after him to the right and to
            the left were found beating the air (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άήρ</foreign>), and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n492-1"/>, exasperated and biting their
            fingers, they would turn back with great shame, filled with bitterness and
            confusion and gnashing their molars against the man mighty in his Lord,
            and that while news of him was flying about to-day in one quarter and tomorrow 
            in another; while for his part he resolutely refused to allow even a
            travelling-companion to carry any gold<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n492-1"/> or silver or bronze with him, or any
            food upon the journey, though he would travel extended stages (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μανσίων</foreign>) at a
            vigorous pace, since on many days they would traverse more than the miles of
            the stage (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μανσίων</foreign>), while he would not consent to the fast and abstinence
            being broken; insomuch that on many days men could not travel with him
            and minister to him more than a short time, since they could not hasten on
            with his old age and support and endure his abstinence; while he also would
            not consent to avail himself of the use of an animal for riding or for driving,
            but he used to accomplish his travelling on foot, since besides being
            strengthened by divine grace he further also possessed a sound body by
            nature. And thus he would accomplish the course along the road of
            <pb n="695"/><pb n="493"/>righteousness, and would make an addition to the party of the believers every
            day in every place, among <persName>Greeks</persName> and among <persName>Syrians</persName>; so that his fame
            which was in every place sorely exasperated the adversaries, and disturbed
            them and made them run after him over the roads and districts and quarters.
            And, when the report of him reached this place, the news of him would
            further rouse excitement over an unlimited space in one day, while consequently 
            pursuers and horses would run after him in droves from all sides,
            meeting one another; insomuch that as chance would have it those who were
            pursuing him often met the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> himself, and asked him about
            himself, saying, <quote>Have you heard any secret news of that deceiver <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName>
               anywhere there?</quote>, and he on his side would name to them a place no small
            distance behind him, saying: <quote>Yes, I have heard from some men who were
               saying that he was in such-and-such a place, and was going about there;
               and, if you set out, perhaps you will catch him.</quote> Having heard<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n493-1"/> these
            things from him as a piece of secret information and supposing him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n493-1"/> to be a
            partisan, they would leave him himself, and run after him in accordance with
            the story that he had told them<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n493-1"/>. And so their outward eyes were closed
            <pb n="696"/><pb n="494"/>as well as their inner ones, that they might not recognise the blessed man,
            while it was not these only who were exasperated and disturbed by the news
            of him, but also the king himself, who gave no small amount of gold to those
            who promised to capture the blessed man, bishops and many monks and
            several laymen; so that many, when they saw his intentness and his eager
            desire and the gift that he gave for the capture of the blessed man, and that
            everyone who promised to capture him received from him a large quantity
            of gold, as much as he asked, used consequently to deceive him, and promise
            and receive gold, from two hundred and three hundred darics, and go out.
            And there are some of them who while they were making search with great
            diligence in every place, in deserts and on mountains and in cities and in
            villages, were dazed and wearied, while they were unable to find the bondman
            of God on account of his abstemiousness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n494-1"/>, though these things continued to
            be carried on in this way for many years, indeed even till after king Justinian's
            death, while the blessed man was strengthened in his Lord, and was confident
            like a lion, and accomplished his ministry, causing the priesthood to flow
            like great rivers over the whole world of the Roman dominions; so that, if a
            man take upon himself to say that a hundred thousand were ordained by him,
            <pb n="697"/><pb n="495"/>I do not think he will depart from the truth; even as no small number of
            bishops and two patriarchs<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n495-1"/> also received ordination (<foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροντονία</foreign>) from him and
            from others who were with him as is enjoined in the canons. First he took
            two admirable blessed men whose names are <persName>Eugene</persName> and <persName>Conon</persName> and entered
            the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, and there with other bishops he made them also as
            well bishops, and so he went out; and with them he heroically performed the
            work of the ministry, which has been going on even down to this first year
            of the reign of Justin the king<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n495-2"/>, though he has now reached an honoured
            old age, though he does not fall short of the work of youth. For, as we
            declared at the beginning of the history that is concerned with him that the
            history that is concerned with him cannot be related in accordance with what
            he is, so also we state now at the end, having recorded a small portion of the
            conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of the blessed man's contests and of his pursuits and his work
            for the glory of God, who chose him and strengthened him and set him up
            in his church in the time of the persecution, in order that we may all be
            assisted by his prayer together with that of all the saints Amen and Amen!
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the brave and valiant blessed man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> the bishop and combatant
            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγωνιστής</foreign>) is ended.
         </p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n488-2">Constantina.</note>
            <note xml:id="n488-3">Sc. <hi rend="singleQuote">the quarry</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n489-1">P. 487.</note>
            <note xml:id="n489-2">According to the spurious life (see Appendix) for a conference with the Chalcedonians; but, if he became a bp. in 542 (ch. 50) and lived 15 yrs in C.P., he must have come in 527, which is before the time of the conferences.</note>
            <note xml:id="n489-3">See p. 319, n.2. The meaning may also be that he used half for clothing and half for a night-covering. From this attire he got the nickname <hi rend="singleQuote">Burd'aya</hi> or <hi rend="singleQuote">Burd'ayna</hi> (the man of the patchwork garment); cf. p. 423.</note>
            <note xml:id="n490-1">Also called Hirtha d Nu'man (p. 145). The mention of Theodore and his see had been omitted in the ms. and is supplied from ch. 50.</note>
            <note xml:id="n490-2">April.</note>
            <note xml:id="n490-3">Eph., VI, 14-17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n491-1">II Cor., VI, 7. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n491-2">The sentence is left unfinished.</note>
            <note xml:id="n491-3">Jer., XLIV, 30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n492-1">Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n492-2">So I emend from the interpolated life (see Introd., p. XIV, n. 7).</note>
            <note xml:id="n493-1">Ms. om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n493-2">The same story is told of Simeon of Beth Arsham (p. 145).</note>
            <note xml:id="n494-1">This appy. means that he was able to travel so rapidly because he travelled so light and did not get stop to take food.</note>
            <note xml:id="n495-1">Sergius and Paul.</note>
            <note xml:id="n495-2">566.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
