<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/841">Jacob and Theodore</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/841 -->
         <head>Next the Fiftieth History, Concerning the Same Two Bishops, the Excellent And
            Divine Blessed Men <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3266">Theodore</persName>, Who Were Together in the Royal City At 
            The Time of the Persecution I and Concerning the Active Work That Was Performed By 
            Them During the Same Persecution, by the Instigation and the Command of the Believing <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora the Queen</persName>.</head>
         <p>
            Before these things therefore, in the sixteenth year of the reign of Justinian<note></note>, 
            after the time of the martyrdom of the blessed combatant (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγωνιστης</foreign>)
            for religion <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3222">John</persName> bishop of the city of <placeName>Thella</placeName> at the hands of Ephraim of
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2610">Antioch</placeName>, when a lack of priests had consequently arisen in the countries of
            the east and of the west, and especially of bishops, then the glorious Hereth
            Bar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3214">Gabala</persName>, the great king of the <persName>Saracens</persName>, with many others asked the
            Christ-loving queen <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName> to give orders that two or three bishops might
            immediately be instituted by the orthodox (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξοι</foreign>) in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName>. And, since
            the believing queen was desirous of furthering everything that would assist
            <pb n="154"/><pb n="500"/>the opponents of the synod of Chalcedon, she gave orders and two blessed
            men, well-tried and divine persons, whose names were <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3266">Theodore</persName>, 
            were chosen and instituted, one for <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2791">Hirtha</placeName> of the <persName>Saracens</persName><note></note>, that is
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3266">Theodore</persName>, and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> for the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2605">Edessa</placeName>. And, while the blessed
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3266">Theodore</persName> exercised authority in the southern and western countries, and the
            whole of the desert and Arabia and Palestine, as far as <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, the blessed
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName>, having armed himself with religion, and clothed himself in the zeal of
            heroism, extended his course over all the countries not only of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName> and the
            whole of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/576">Armenia</placeName> and of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2763">Cappadocia</placeName>, all of which down to the little ones'
            were especially distinguished and strong in orthodoxy (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξοι</foreign>) no less
            than <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName>, and besides these<note></note> in the countries also of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/55">Cilicia</placeName> and the
            whole of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2799">Isauria</placeName> and of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1531">Pamphylia</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1532">Lycaonia</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1533">Lycia</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1525">Phrygia</placeName> and
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1472">Caria</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2747">Asia</placeName>, and in the islands of the sea <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/714">Cyprus</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1534">Rhodes</placeName>, and
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1529">Chios</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1478">Mitylene</placeName>, and as far as the royal city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/586">Constantinople</placeName>, in which
            also besides all the countries he displayed the course of heroism, and filled
            <pb n="155"/><pb n="501"/>the ranks of the priesthood, and spread orthodoxy (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξοι</foreign>) abroad, who not
            only marshalled priests and supplied all quarters, but further also in keen
            religious zeal did not shrink even from making provision for ordaining and
            appointing high-priests, that is bishops, also in every place; so that, since
            he was careful to observe the regulations of the canons which command
            that without three bishops no bishop shall be instituted, he contrived to
            bring with him two monks of good repute for excellence of life, one from
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/55">Cilicia</placeName> and one from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2799">Isauria</placeName>, and proceeded to the royal city; and, having
            received the advice and permission of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName> patriarch of
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, who had been detained in the same royal city by way of exile
            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) on behalf of the truth of the faith, the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> with the above-mentioned
            monks directed his path to the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>, after fully
            carrying out the ministry of the priesthood in all the countries from the royal
            city as far as the sea-coast of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1532">Lycaonia</placeName>; and so he entered <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>; and,
            after he had been in communication with the saintly men there, in accordance
            with the mandate received from the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName> the patriarch, they
            assembled, and made these two blessed men bishops, one whose name was
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1336">Conon</persName> in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2722">Tarsus</placeName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/55">Cilicia</placeName>, and the other whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3208">Eugene</persName>
            <pb n="156"/><pb n="502"/>in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2714">Seleucia</placeName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2799">Isauria</placeName><note></note>; and so he took them and came back to
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName> with admirable zeal. And so in accordance with the provision of
            the canons they made metropolitans, that is archbishops<note></note>, one whose name
            was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3207">Dimet</persName><note></note> from the monastery of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2802">Aphthonia</placeName><note></note> in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2809">Laodicea</placeName>, and
            another whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3222">John</persName> from the monastery of the house of Mar <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2760">Bzy</placeName>
            in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2714">Seleucia</placeName> in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName><note></note>, and another from those who were instituted at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName> 
            who was mentioned above, whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1336">Conon</persName>, in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2722">Tarsus</placeName> in
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/55">Cilicia</placeName>, and the other whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3208">Eugene</persName> in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2714">Seleucia</placeName> in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2799">Isauria</placeName>; and
            the other bishops also in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName> as follows, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3222">John</persName> from the monastery of the
            house of Mar <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/343">Bassus</placeName> in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2642">Kenneshrin</placeName><note></note>, and another whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/71">Sergius</persName>
            from the monastery of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2802">Aphthonia</placeName> in <placeName>Charrhae</placeName>, and another whose name was
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3222">John</persName> from the monastery of the house of Mar <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/351">Hanina</placeName> in <placeName><foreign>Sura Romanorum</foreign></placeName>.
            And, when they had set up bishops for the various cities of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName> as has
            been described, afterwards they went up to the royal city, and in our presence 
            they ordained a patriarch in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2610">Antioch</placeName>, a man whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/71">Sergius</persName>
            from the city of <placeName>Thella</placeName>, who was living in the royal city and was versed
            <pb n="157"/><pb n="503"/>in religious learning. And, when he had completed three years, he departed from the world; and after a time again they ordained a man whose name
            was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/72">Paul</persName> from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>. About this man many controversies arose<note></note>,
            and continue to the present time when these things were written. And
            again in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2735">Amida</placeName> they ordained as metropolitan a man whose name
            was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3209">Eunomius</persName>, who had been expelled with others among the same clergy
            of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2735">Amida</placeName>, in the same royal city. And for the countries of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/715">Egypt</placeName>, by the
            mandate of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName> the patriarch, they ordained twelve
            bishops at once in the royal city itself, for various cities of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2847">Thebais</placeName> and of
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/715">Egypt</placeName> besides a large number of clergy; inasmuch as the patriarch <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/784">Theodosius</persName> would not consent to ordain priests after he had left his see. And
            afterwards the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> and his companions went out to the countries.
            of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2747">Asia</placeName> for the second time, and they ordained four bishops in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2747">Asia</placeName>, one in
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2666">Ephesus</placeName> a man whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3222">John</persName> the Syrian, the converter of the pagans<note></note>,
            and in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2719">Smyrna</placeName> a man whose name was Peter<note></note>, and another whose name was
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3222">John</persName> in the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2829">Pergamum</placeName>, and another whose name was Peter in the
            city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2856">Tralles</placeName>. And after these things they crossed to the island of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1529">Chios</placeName>
            <pb n="158"/><pb n="504"/>and set up a bishop in it, a man whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2032">Kashish</persName><note></note> from the monastery 
            of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3222">John</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2666">Ephesus</placeName>, both of whom were from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">the monastery</placeName> of the
            house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3222">John</persName> at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2735">Amida</placeName>. And again they went back and crossed to
            the regions of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1472">Caria</placeName>, and there they set up two bishops, one whose name
            was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/72">Paul</persName> in a city the name of which is <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2741">Aphrodisias</placeName><note></note>, and another whose
            name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3228">Julian</persName> in a city the name of which is <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2732">Alabanda</placeName><note></note>. These are all
            the bishops and archbishops, who are in number twenty-seven, besides two
            patriarchs whom the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> ordained with all the other bishops,
            besides many clergy in all the eastern and western countries. Many of all
            these were instituted in our presence, and with regard to the truth of all
            these things we give confident and truthful witness that they were done as
            above, and we have made a commemorative record of them for the knowledge
            of posterity; but of the sublime manner of life of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName>, and his
            courage and perfection, we have made a record in the preceding history.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of two bishops the excellent and divine blessed men, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">James</persName> and
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3266">Theodore</persName>, is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
