<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/844">Priscus</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/844 -->
         <head>Next the Fifty-Third History, of the Divine Blessed Man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2024">Priscus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n525-1"></ptr>.</head>
         <p>
            [....]<note></note>
            we came to the conclusion that this was rather (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μάλλον</foreign>) one of those poor in
            spirit to whom a blessing is given by our Lord<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n525-2"></ptr>, and he conducted himself in
            this way in spiritual knowledge in order to attain to excellence.
            Then, having learned that he did not beg for anything from anyone, we sent him a
            <pb n="180"/><pb n="526"/>present of one <foreign>tremissis</foreign> by a <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3720">certain gentlemen</persName> who was occupied with us in
            God's service, that it might assist him to supply his needs, and in order that
            we might thereby discover the object that he had before him. But this man
            who was in very truth poor in spirit on seeing the <foreign>tremissis</foreign> began to run
            away at a rapid pace, since he was in fact not advanced in years; and the man
            who brought the <foreign>tremissis</foreign> to him began to run after him, adjuring him to
            stop. But the blessed man, having put a distance between himself and
            many (?)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n526-1"></ptr>, stopped on account of the adjurations, saying to him, <quote>Wherefore,
               man, are you worrying yourself and worrying me the poor man?</quote> He said to
            him, <quote>The abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>) sent you this present because he heard that you were
               in need. Take it and supply your need</quote>. That man said <quote>For my part I
                  do not need this. But say to the abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>), Run that you may attain<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n526-2"></ptr>. If
                  you have one follis, I will take it</quote>. Then, having seen that he had run away
            from the <foreign>tremissis</foreign>, he gave him ten <foreign>folles</foreign>; and he on his side stretched out
            his hand and took one <foreign>follis</foreign>, and ran away. And so that man came, and
            related all these things to us. Then we were assured that that poor man was
            a spiritual person, and a bondman of God, and was poor of his own will for
            the sake of eternal life. After these things in the time of the winter-cold.
            <pb n="181"/><pb n="527"/>having seen that he was uncovered and sore bested, we bought him a tunic
            and a cloak, and sent them by that man, begging him to put them on and
            warm himself during the winter. But he on seeing them turned his face
            away, and showed displeasure against him, saying, <quote>Go your way, man,
               wherefore do you worry me the poor man?</quote> The man who was sent by us
            answered him, <quote>The abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>) out of charity and because of the hardness
               of the winter bought them and sent them to you</quote>. He on his side says to
            him: <quote>Go say to the abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>), Send things that last, and do not try to
               concern yourself about stripping naked lest you be stripped naked<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n527-1"></ptr></quote>. And
            so he would not consent to accept them. And from that time the man who
            was with us began to mark times and observe him, because he too was an
            earnest and zealous man, and by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) a Cappadocian. And one
            day, as was that poor man's custom, he went secretly outside the city to some
            enclosed garden-land hidden by trees and reeds to pray; insomuch that
            that gentleman observed him, and secretly went out after him, standing
            facing him; and he saw him standing in prayer with his hands stretched out
            to heaven, and suddenly an awe-inspiring spectacle that was laid upon his
            face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>), and flashed like lightning, and rays of fire were proceeding
            <pb n="182"/><pb n="528"/>from his face (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόσωπον</foreign>), and an awful bow of fire that was stretched out above
            him while he stood within it, and a great light surrounded him. And, when
            that man saw this awful spectacle on that poor man as he was praying, he was
            frightened, and fell on his face on the ground. And after a little time he rose
            and fled and came to us at a great pace, shaking and trembling and weeping:
            insomuch that we ourselves were alarmed at the sight of him, and were brought
            to a state of sudden fright, inquiring what was the cause of his agitation and
            fright. And he swore to us by God the Ruler of all the ages, <quote>I saw all this
               spectacle on that poor man, without falsehood or any exaggeration; and my
               heart quaked, and my limbs shook, and I fled, leaving him standing thus in
               that awful splendour, and I fled<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n528-1"></ptr>, so that I never again had the power and
               the boldness to lift my eyes toward him.</quote> And during the whole of the
            day he was in a condition of stupor and tremor and perturbation from that
            awful spectacle; but at night he went and found him in the place where he
            used to sleep, and he fell at his feet, weeping and trembling from his fear.
            But the blessed man knew the cause of his fear, and said to him: <quote>Wherefore, 
               man, did you come out after my poverty, to inquire into things which do
               not concern you?</quote>. And, adjuring him by the living God, he continued
            <pb n="183"/><pb n="529"/>beseeching him to inform him what he was. And he also required oaths from
            him that he would not make any disclosure or give any information to men
            about him. And he on his side said: <quote>Only from the abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>) I cannot
               conceal it; but to others I will give no information whatever.</quote> Then he
            answered him, adjuring him and saying: <quote>Do not make demands or
               inquiries of me about many things; it is enough for you to know that I am a
               stranger and a poor man, and for the sake of the hope of my eternal life I am
               enduring labours and buffetings in strange lands, and in this poverty in which
               you now see me; and not I only, but we are seven brethren who are secretly
               labouring in this fashion, and once in the whole week we meet together in one
               place, and receive consolation in one another's company, and comfort and
               edification; and thus each of us returns to his place and to his employment.
               I have given you the information; see that you do not make yourself the cause
               of my moving from this city, in which I have much peacefulness, and especially 
               the fact that I am reckoned a madman by them, and there is no one who
               speaks with me or who worries me. And beg the abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>) that, though
               these things are known to him, he will leave me as I am, and not show any difference 
               toward me.</quote> The man who was with me having repeated all these
            <pb n="184"/><pb n="530"/>things to me, I sent and begged him, if possible, to come to us secretly at suppertime, 
            and eat with us<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n530-1"></ptr>, and he would not consent, sending me a message
            that we should attend to things that are helpful and lasting. One night I was
            suddenly attacked by the disease of fever; and in the morning, when the man
            who was with me who used to go to that poor man saw him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n530-2"></ptr>, as he swore
            with fearful oaths by God, <quote>Before I on my side spoke to him, he first said
               to me: <quote>The abbot (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άββάς</foreign>) was attacked by fever during the night. Go say
                  to him, <quote>Wherefore did you eat dry food and drink a vinegar-posset (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πόσκα</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n530-3"></ptr>
                     with cold water?</quote></quote>. And, when I on my side said to him, <quote>Sir, who showed
                        you this?</quote>, he said to me <quote>My heart showed me that he did so, and in consequence 
                           of the vinegar and the cold water he fell ill</quote></quote>; so that, when that
            man came, and informed me of these things, I was struck with great astonishment 
            and wonder, and I gave thanks to God who dwells in his saints. With
            regard to many other characteristic things which that man used to relate that
            he saw in that poor man, and moreover that one of his companions came
            to him and saw him with him, and he himself refused to speak to him, in
            consequence of the large number of these we have on account of the length
            <pb n="185"/><pb n="531"/>of the history refrained from speaking. But, when we had departed to another
            place, that saint ended his course in the same city and was buried; and,
            when we came and heard of it, we were much distressed at having been
            deprived of his society, even at second-hand. And we made great endeavours
            to discover the coffin which held his holy remains; and in consequence of the
            great pestilence which had occurred<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n531-1"></ptr> and the numbers that were laid above
            him we could not do so. These things we have recorded for the glory of
            God who strengthens and helps all that trust in him.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the divine blessed man <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2024">Priscus</persName> is ended.
         </p>
         <noteGrp>
            <noteGrp>
               <note xml:id="n525-1">The beginning is lost.</note>
               <note xml:id="n525-2">Matth., V, 3.</note>
               <note xml:id="n526-1">I can make nothing else of this. We require <hi rend="singleQuote">put a great distance between himself and his pursuer</hi>. It is probably a phrase for <hi rend="singleQuote">run very fast</hi>. V. D. and L. have <hi rend="singleQuote">procul</hi> for the whole clause.</note>
               <note xml:id="n526-2">I Cor., IX, 24.</note>
               <note xml:id="n527-1">The meaning perh. is that whoever wears earthly clothes will eventualy be left naked through their wearing out. V. D. and L 's <hi rend="singleQuote"><foreign xml:lang="ln">curare nudatum</foreign></hi> is not in the Syr.</note>
               <note xml:id="n528-1">Sic syr.</note>
               <note xml:id="n530-1">As this was not later than 542 (see below), J. was probably living in the house of Probus (see Introd., p. VI).</note>
               <note xml:id="n530-2">The sentence is left unfinished, and the sense completed in another form.</note>
               <note xml:id="n530-3">This word (= <foreign>posca</foreign>) is not known in Gk., but the Syr. implies in a Gk. form.</note>
               <note xml:id="n531-1">542.</note>
            </noteGrp>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
