<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/845">Caesarea</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/845 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            The history therefore of this woman also, great before God and before
            men, was one that could not but excite great admiration, a woman who from
            a great royal race" brought herself down to humiliation undertaken for
            <pb n="186"/><pb n="532"/>the sake of God and the promised life and" to a mean position, and betook
            herself to the habit (a) of the solitary and monastic life and sought refuge
            in it². In admiration therefore and confessing that we are not capable of
            compassing the beauties of the history of this blessed woman, we set
            ourselves for the sake of God's glory and the profit of the hearers to record
            as it were a small measure taken from the sea of spiritual riches, addressed
            to those who love matters of spiritual profit. This divine blessed woman
            therefore, who was called by name Caesaria, and by her birth (yévos) came
            originally from the city of Samosata [....]" 
            to do, when we came to her the in city of Alexandria"; so that when she saw
            us she was filled with great joy, and received great consolation. But we
            found her engaged in severe labours of recitation of service and of quietude
            and intense supplication, and constant prayers and frequent genuflexions and
            asceticism beyond measure, and especially in the case of a woman like this
            <pb n="187"/><pb n="533"/>who had been reared in endless luxuries, and had grown accustomed to royal
            habits, who suddenly came to be cut off from all these things, and subjected
            herself to asceticism beyond measure, so that she completely cut herself off
            from eating bread, and every other day she would feed on cooked herbs with
            salt and vinegar without oil and moist rolls, and she used to sleep on sackcloth 
            on the ground, but on the sabbath and the first day of the week under
            pressure from the bishops and many blessed men she consented that a little
            oil should be put on the herbs for her; so that, having found her living in all
            this asceticism and hardship, we continued blaming her and advising her to
            give up high things and embrace moderate things, lest being unable to
            endure she might either lose her strength or fall into severe illness and be
            forced from necessity (żvżyzn) to give it all up. But the blessed woman, when
            she heard us speak of illnesses, continued praying and saying: <quote>Would that
               God had granted me bodily illnesses all the days of my life, in order that I
               might possess health of soul only.</quote> Moreover, since she thirsted after the
            spiritual gain of the excellent life, though she was wise and learned in the
            reading of the Scriptures and of all the fathers, it pleased her greatly to ask
            <pb n="188"/><pb n="534"/>and inquire" about the passions of the soul and of the body and about thoughts,
            so that after spiritual conversation all day we spent many nights in this way
            in discussion and helpful speech, while the blessed woman condescended
            to make confession and say, <quote>I have here more than seven hundred volumes
               in number of all the fathers, to which my intellect and my attention have
               been devoted for many years, insomuch that now my mind has no rest and
               my soul also is stirred with passion night and day to hear from you the word
               of God, and about discernment of passions and observance of commandments,
               and about the other spiritual things.</quote> One day, while we were sitting
            occupied in speech and divine conversation, suddenly that blessed woman fell
            on her face on the ground before me, filling me with amazement and alarm
            by suddenly doing this, while I said to her, <quote>Wherefore have you done this,
               and laid a weight upon me the mean one? be so good as to rise and tell me
               what it is that you command</quote>. But she would not consent to rise, saying,
            <quote>I will not rise hence unless you give me your word before God that you will
               agree to my request and do what I require of you.</quote> And, being troubled
            in my mind because she was lying on her face, I said to her: <quote>Be so good
               <pb n="189"/><pb n="535"/>as to rise, and what you command, if it is within my power and capacity,
               I will do.</quote> And so she reluctantly rose; and she began to request me,
            saying: <quote>Now that I have left my house and my property and come out to
               settle down in retreat and weep for my sins, and here my soul is in the same
               turmoil, I make this entreaty of you, to save my soul, and go privily to the
               inner desert and search out for us a place in which there is a well of water,
               and come and take me secretly with one chamber-woman and one chamberlain 
               only that we may settle down in retreat, and be quit of the evil things of
               this world, and of all its turmoil, for I thought to escape from it but have not
               yet succeeded.</quote> When therefore we heard that she intended to do these
            things, we would not promise to agree to her request, and to be ourselves the
            ministers of these plans, because we saw that they were unnecessary, and
            they were beyond her capacity and strength and condition; and, besides many
            arguments that we arrayed before her on these matters, we were afraid lest
            this ardour and the plans came from the evil one, while we further explained
            and showed her that these plans if put into effect by her would even bring
            danger (xívduvos) upon her, the danger of the destruction involved in the
            scattering of all the souls that had gone out with her. Then in distress and
            <pb n="190"/><pb n="536"/>tears she said, <quote>It is from these very persons above all that I seek to flee.</quote>
            And we continued admonishing her very strongly in order to suppress her
            thoughts, saying, <quote>Know that you are an old and feeble woman, and your
               nature is not strong enough to hold out against these thoughts of yours and
               endure and struggle; for neither indeed has the assault of temptations yet
               fallen upon you, and you have not been tried by the cunning of the fiends;
               and therefore we advise you to give up these plans, being satisfied with having
               left your country and your house and gone out into a strange land to dwell
               in the monastery that you have built.</quote> With great labour therefore we
            succeeded in restraining her ardour from going out into the inner desert, while
            she showed vexation and annoyance toward us because we did not yield to her
            in this matter. And so, when she had built and completed the monasteries
            in a grand and admirable style, and had bought a large gold-mine (xpusopetov)"
            for them", she made one monastery for men, and one for women, in
            which she herself also thenceforth performed severe and sublime labours, for
            fifteen years, though she declined the headship of the same monastery, but
            sent to another monastery, and took thence a certain blessed woman great in
            <pb n="191"/><pb n="537"/>her modes of life whose name was Cosmiana, and her she appointed archimandritess, 
            she herself submitting to her like an insignificant and poor sister.
            And so she continued to labour till the end of her life, which happened after
            fifteen years". And so she completed the course of her practices heroically,
            bearing great testimony and undergoing mighty conflicts (żyóv).
            And she died and was laid in this monastery, which even to the present
            day is called the monastery of Caesaria the patrician. These few memorials
            taken from the blessed woman's labour and practices we have recorded for
            the glory of God and the profit of those who are desirous of spiritual profit.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the blessed Caesaria the patrician is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
