<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/846">John and Sosiana</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/846 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            This perfect woman Sosiana therefore, when her husband departed from
            <pb n="192"/><pb n="538"/>the world, whose name was John<note></note>, after they had lived together thirty
            years, and as is said lived all these years in purity, never holding carnal
            intercourse with one another, but living in devoutness and honour and
            holiness, occupying themselves in fasting and prayer, and genuflexion and
            recitation of service and watching by night, while hair-mats were laid down
            for them each apart, and in this way they passed the whole length of the
            night-hours, kneeling and lying on their faces, and weeping in prayer and
            mighty crying to God, without this becoming known to many. When then
            this excellent John departed from the world, bearing this great testimony,
            and moreover Caesaria the patrician also as well whom we mentioned above
            had gone out to the desert, i. e. first to Alexandria<note></note>, this excellent blessed
            woman Sosiana therefore laded three of her slaves with all her husband's
            splendid clothes, great cloaks (avidia) of pure silk (620ontxóv) and valuable
            raw silk garments (praça), with colours - and pictures (rxroüpa)<note></note>, and
            <pb n="193"/><pb n="539"/>the other clothes of high price, and sent them to our meanness<note></note>, adjuring
            and beseeching us, <quote>Let all these be cut into such sizes as you think fit,
               sir, and let handsome crosses and corners (yovia) be put upon them, and
               let them be made into cloths and veils, and distributed among the holy
               altars as you shall decide, because I made this vow to the Lord God.</quote>
            We then on seeing these things marvelled greatly, thinking in ourselves,
            <quote>The thing would not be right that we should cut up articles of clothing
               each of which is well worth more than a pound (λiтpa) of gold", but rather
               (užλov) that these should be sold for a great price, and given to the
               poor"</quote>. And so with this thought in our mind we went to the excellent
            woman herself, in order to give her this advice. But the excellent woman
            fell upon her face, saying, <quote>Sir, since I made this vow before God, that
               all the fine clothes belonging to myself and to my husband whose soul
               is at rest should be made into cloths and veils, and crosses and gilded
               corners (ywvíz) should be put upon them, and they should be distributed
               among the holy altars of God, together with all the silver which God
               gave us, for the sake of the love of God whom I have loved be my helper,
               <pb n="194"/><pb n="540"/>and perform this service for me also as well, because this also as well
               is of God; and divide these among all the churches and monasteries
               which God established through you", or wherever God puts it into your
               mind; and from the poor, as far as in me lies, I trust in God that nothing
               will be taken away by me; since for my part I have no one except God
               my Lord and my Creator and my Saviour and my Life-giver</quote>. And
            from that time stitchers were summoned and came; and cloths and veils and
            napkins (vn) were cut out according to the size of each article of clothing; 
            and men came who were occupied in gilding and decorating them in
            a marvellous manner, and inscribing her own name and her husband's, while
            she also continued to bring clean and marvellous linen cloths and Persian
            cambrics, and they were all overlaid<note></note>. And, when all her husband's clothes
            had been cut up, she went on to bring her own fine clothes in no small
            number, and the woven gold also was upon them, and fine figures made
            of various silks and raw silks (pératz), and pure silk (6λoonpizóv), and so on.
            And, while we were again thinking, <quote>Perhaps it would have pleased God
               more that they should be sold and given to the poor</quote>, and were saying so to
            her and she on her part was insisting on cutting them up, we were frightened
            by our Lord's expression in the gospel (ɛúzyyehov) about the fine ointment of
            <pb n="195"/><pb n="541"/>great price which the woman poured on his head, when also the advice
            and desire of Judas the traitor which he proferred contrary to what was
            right and proper was blamed<note></note>, and we ceased advising that woman so and
            standing in the way of her wish. And, when all her valuable clothes had
            been used up, until she was left with the cheap ordinary clothes that she
            was wearing only, when we were finding fault with her in this matter, that
            she might leave herself what she needed, yet we did no good whatever,
            since she said, <quote>Do not pity me in this matter, sir, since I have not a single
               day in the life of the body beyond this year; and, if I spare these, whence
               do I know if courtezans (ópva:) will wear them, and I on my part shall be
               called to account for them?"</quote> And on hearing this declaration, which she
            plainly made in advance about the end of her life, we said : <quote>If this has been
               revealed to you, you do rightly in sending all that you have in advance</quote>.
            When all her precious articles of clothing had been used up, and we had
            begun out of the multitude of them to distribute to the east and to the west
            everything that came to hand, then she brought her silver which amounted
            to many pounds (λírpa), and it was given up and chalices and patens were
            made, and many dishes (ívaza) and spoons, and they were distributed by
            <pb n="196"/><pb n="542"/>us everywhere, as God knows, while she also with her own hands distributed 
            all the rest of the contents of her house to all who were in need, while
            the blessed woman rejoiced and gave thanks to God. But we on our side
            were noting the time which she fixed beforehand with regard to her end,
            to see if it was near as she had stated. And, when the end of that year
            approached, five days before, she fell into an illness; and she sent and called
            us, begging us to set forth incense, and make expiation for her, saying,
            <quote>Sir, pray for me, for the sinner; for lo! after five days I am going to our
               Lord, to make answer (anoλoyía) for my sins. But for God's sake remember
               me the wretched one in your acceptable prayers to God</quote>. And thus while
            we were constantly with her on the fifth day as fixed by what she had said
            she fell asleep in peace, while everyone was overcome with astonishment;
            and they thanked and praised God, and ran to receive a blessing from her
            holy body.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of some excellent persons, John and Sosiana, is ended.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
