<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/847">Peter and Photius</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/847 -->
         <head>Next the Fifty-Sixth History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2011">Peter</persName>, Who Himself Also
            Was Chancellor and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3014">Photius</persName> the Chartulary With the Rest of His
            Companions, From the Same Household<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n543-1"></ptr>.</head>
         <p>
            The history of the excellent blessed men <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2011">Peter</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3014">Photius</persName> also besides
            is therefore worthy of being committed to written records; men who were
            themselves the first, even before the blessed patrician Caesaria herself, to
            prepare the way for that household, in that both of them together were
            thought worthy to despise the world, and treat all its affairs with contempt,
            and go out and go to the desert. And, in order that they might first be
            instructed and taught in a convent and in the subjection of monasticism, they
            entered a great and renowned <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2777">convent</placeName> in the Ennaton<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n543-2"></ptr> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName> which
            is called that of the Fathers and were received in it, giving themselves to
            humility and submission and poverty and obedience, and sorrow and fasting
            and prayer, and watching and manual work, men who had been accustomed
            to a high and luxurious life, who suddenly came to abstinence and the other
            labours, so much so that all the inmates of that convent great and small used
            to marvel at them, and were astonished at their type of life and sorrow and
            <pb n="198"/><pb n="544"/>tears, and their humility and obedience; so that at the time when we came
            to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n544-1"></ptr> we went to that convent to see them for the sake of the blessed 
            men themselves, inasmuch as we were acquainted with them, and
            moreover on account of the report of their manner of life, when they felt great
            joy, and would discuss with us fights against thoughts and the other works
            of excellence. When then they had completed about eighteen years in that
            monastery in spiritual practices, the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2011">Peter</persName> had<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n544-2"></ptr> a <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3654">brother</persName> and a <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3655">sister</persName>
            wearing the lay garb (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχήμα</foreign>), as they too were living a great life in practices
            of excellence, so that they and their <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3656">slaves</persName> used to learn the psalms, and kept
            hours of prayers and service as in a monastery of recluses, while they also
            directed their steps to the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2718">Smyrna</placeName> for the sake of the quietude of a
            strange land, and there thenceforth they lived a religious, devout, pure life,
            so that all that city used to marvel at them and at their practices. They
            therefore used to write and worry the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2011">Peter</persName> to come and visit them
            and encourage them, and let them be consoled and comforted by one another,
            which the blessed man was also constrained to do, not for the sake of bodily
            <pb n="199"/><pb n="545"/>relationship, but because he knew that they were spiritual persons in manner
            of life. But, when he had come and seen them and comforted them, he
            set his face to return to his monastery, and they would not let him, weeping
            and adjuring him by the living God not to leave them; and thus he was
            constrained to stay. And, when he had completed five years with them,
            he was raised by force to the bishopric<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n545-1"></ptr>; and, when he had completed four
            years, he departed from the world with his other <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3654">brother</persName>, having lived a
            spiritual and divine life. But their <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3655">sister</persName> the holy old woman remained in the
            bodily life a long time, down to the writing of this history, having further
            multiplied her spiritual practices many times.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2011">Peter</persName> the chancellor and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3014">Photius</persName> the chartulary
            is ended.
         </p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n543-1">Sc. that Caesaria.</note>
            <note xml:id="n543-2">See p. 325, 384.</note>
            <note xml:id="n544-1">This must have been on his 2nd visit to Egypt (541), for he had known them before, which must have been in CP. (p. 539, n. 1), where he had never till after his visit to Egypt in 534. Further, since they were in CP. in 535 and left it before Caesaria, his visit to Caesaria in Egypt must also have been in 541; see p. 532, n. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n544-2">Sic syr. Cf. p. 397, l. 15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n545-1">Of Smyrna (p. 503). Since he was ordained with the author, the date was not earlier than 558 (p. 508, n. 1, and Introd., p. V.), and therefore, if the figures are correct, he left CP. not later than 535, but as J. saw him in CP. in 535 (p. 544, n. 1), it was not earlier than that year, so that his ordination and J.'s are fixed to 558.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
