<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/848">Theodore Castrensis</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/848 -->
         <head>Next the Fifty-Seventh History, of the Blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2108">Theodore</persName> the Kings
            Chamberlain and <foreign>Castrensis</foreign>, Who, While He Was in the Body, Practised
            A Heavenly and Divine Mode of Life.</head>
         <p>
            This blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2108">Theodore</persName> therefore held a high office in the royal palace
            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>), having previously been in the service of a great man before God
            (and he was great among men also) whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2558">Mishael</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n546-1"></ptr>, who also
            was further the king's <foreign>praepositus</foreign><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n546-2"></ptr>, a Christian and merciful and ascetic
            man, and was moreover perfect in all spiritual things, insomuch that he
            underwent exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) for the sake of the truth of the right faith, that he
            might not communicate with the <persName>synod of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName></persName>, insomuch that he spent
            a considerable number of years in the exile (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>), and so was at last invited,
            and came in, and was restored to his place, and completed his time<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n546-3"></ptr>, and
            retired, having lived many years in all religious habits, while like an ordinary
            <pb n="201"/><pb n="547"/>man he used to work and labour with his hands at carpentering and building
            and carving, and sell and give to the poor, besides all the rest of his wealth,
            while he lived an ordinary and poor life, down to extreme old age, and thus
            departed from the world bearing great and noble testimony. This man then
            the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2108">Theodore</persName> imitated with another brother of his whose name was
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3224">John</persName>, so that they were both chamberlains of the king, while living in fasting 
            and constant prayers, and sorrow and tears and works of charity, both
            luring the life of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2558">Mishael</persName> and also after his death for many years.
            And, because the blessed man was feeble and sickly of body, and the more
            so from watching and fasting and abstinence, he asked king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName>, who
            was also edified by him and loved him and in whose eyes he was honoured,
            that he might retire as <foreign>castrensis</foreign><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n547-1"></ptr>, in order that he might escape and retire
            from the turmoil of the palace (<foreign xml:lang="grc">παλάτιον</foreign>), and settle down in quietude, and
            devote himself to the practice of religion only; insomuch that the king assented
            to his request and carried out his desire, and ordered him to retire as
            <foreign>castrensis</foreign>, because he<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n547-2"></ptr> serves two years only<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n547-3"></ptr>, many offices being subordinate
            <pb n="202"/><pb n="548"/>to him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n548-1"></ptr>, and large profits coming in to him, and in two years like the <foreign>praepositus</foreign> 
            he retires, and like him expends<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n548-2"></ptr> much wealth. The illustrious blessed 
            man therefore retired, and completed two years; and he was released
            and retired with much gold and great wealth. And then he began eagerly
            and joyfully to scatter that gold, and to sow all his wealth in good soils which
            are the hands and bellies of the poor, since he would thenceforth load two
            of his confidential servants<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n548-3"></ptr> during the night, and himself put on a cape and
            cover his head, and would go out and distribute it all night with his own
            hands, not trusting any man, giving the poor not two or three darics only,
            but sometimes even ten, and sometimes eight, and six and seven, while
            consequently the poor of the city were not enough for him, but he used also
            to go out to the suburbs beyond the sea on all sides, crossing and scattering
            his wealth profusely and without stint; so that in the space of one year he
            scattered more than fifteen or twenty hundredweights (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κεντηνάριον</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n548-4"></ptr>, until he
            had used up all the gold. And his slaves and all who were attached to him
            <pb n="203"/><pb n="549"/>began to murmur and find fault with him, so that they received us and many
            others with many complaints against him, inasmuch as we had been habitually 
            in his company from the beginning; so that, when we saw that his
            soul was thus intoxicated with the fervour of divine love, and no worldly
            property was regarded by him, and while we and everyone were wondering
            at the disposition and zeal of the man of God, we used to say to him
            <quote>It is written <quote>First teach them to show charity among those of their
               household</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n549-1"></ptr>. Beware lest by feeding a large number of people you strip
               these quite bare and dissipate it on others</quote>. But the blessed man would say,
            <quote>This is our boast before God, that I and they may be thought worthy to
               receive the command (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έντολή</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n549-2"></ptr> and then die. These do not know the thing
               that is helpful. We trust that what is given away will be preserved in the
               heavenly storehouse in the treasury of God, <quote>where thieves do not break
                  through nor steal</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n549-3"></ptr>. For who then (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άρα</foreign>) can guarantee me life till the evening?
               And, if it has happened that the end overtake me and this which has been committed
               to me remain after me, who will tell me into whose hands it will come?
               <pb n="204"/><pb n="550"/>and perhaps those who find it will spend it on harlots, and I shall be called
               to answer for it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n550-1"></ptr>. And if, sir, you advise me so, I will now do your
               bidding</quote>. Then he freed his slaves, and gave gifts to them, and to the
            freeborn who were attached to him, saying, <quote>See, be no longer grudging,
               and do not murmur</quote>; so that, seeing the man's disposition and zeal, we
            abstained from going on to address further words to him on these matters.
         </p>
         <p>
            After therefore he had used up all his gold, he often threw a hundred-weight 
            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κεντηνάριον</foreign>)<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n550-2"></ptr> upon us also<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n550-3"></ptr> that we might take it and distribute it
            with him; so that, when we refused to take it, in the fervour of his love he
            would send it to the regions of <placeName>Asia</placeName> and throw it upon us perforce. And
            thenceforth he began to sell his silver and his valuable clothes, and give to
            the poor, with such thoroughness and liberality that eventually nothing was
            left for him except a few necessaries. And thenceforth he began to live
            sparingly and those with him, though they were still murmuring against him
            and finding fault with him. But he said to them several times, <quote>You do not
               think the things of God but those of men<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n550-4"></ptr>, and you concern yourselves about
               <pb n="205"/><pb n="551"/>your belly and your purses; and you do not know that we gave away the whole
               of what was given us by God that he may give us many times as much, and
               we may not be called to account for it through administering it badly.</quote>
            But, after he had come to want, and was rejoicing and delighting himself,
            king <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName> heard of it, and he sent and called for him, and continued
            upbraiding him for having thus suddenly dissipated his property completely;
            and he gave him a bounty of a thousand darics every year. But the excellent
            man out of the very bounty itself used to perform acts of bounty, while he
            rejoiced and exulted that he had been thought worthy to receive bounty.
            And so thenceforward he lived in a villa called <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2841">Sema</placeName> (?), where <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2558">Mishael</persName>
            whose soul is at rest was laid, being constantly occupied in fasting and
            prayer, and much watching, and living a life devoted to all religious habits,
            and he would not consent to recline upon a couch (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άκούβιτον</foreign>) like a great man,
            and eat, but used to sit like a poor man, while we and many others were
            reclining, and begging him to do the same, and he would not comply, saying,
            <quote>It is prescribed for us to enter by the narrow gate, and that we should
               not walk in the way that is broad that leads to destruction<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n551-1"></ptr></quote>. And thus this
            man of God began and ended in this brave conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>), while he had now
            <pb n="206"/><pb n="552"/>become dried and shrivelled from the labours of asceticism, and the whole
            of his body had become like dry wood. And thus he ended his life in that
            same villa, and was laid above the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2558">Mishael</persName>. But his brother <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3224">John</persName>,
            who also imitated his mode of life, lived a long time after him; and he also
            ended his course in the practices of religion.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2108">Theodore</persName> the king's chamberlain and <foreign>castrensis</foreign>
            is ended.
         </p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n546-1">For these words see text, n. 3. For M. see Sev., <title>Select Letters</title>, I, 17; XI, I; <title>C. S. C. O.</title>, t. XXV (1), p. 15; Jo. Mal., <title>Exc. de Ins.</title> (ed. De Boor), 92. He may be the deacon of <title>Sel. Letters</title>, I, 63; III, 3; but, if so, one would expect J. to say that he took orders in his old age. If he is the M. of Jo. Ant., <title>Exc. de Ins.</title> (ed De Boor), 43, he must have lived to most extreme old age.</note>
            <note xml:id="n546-2">Sc. <foreign xml:lang="ln">sacri cubiculi.</foreign></note>
            <note xml:id="n546-3">See p. 547, l. 16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n547-1">This is a difficult phrase, which I understand as above. Appy. he wished to resign the chamberlainship and become <foreign xml:lang="ln">castrensis</foreign>, because he could thenr retire altogether after 2 years (see n. 3). The <foreign xml:lang="ln">castrensis</foreign> was a kind of purveyor to the court, originally the quartermaster of a camp (Pauly-Wissowa, s. V.).</note>
            <note xml:id="n547-2">Sc. the <foreign xml:lang="ln">castrensis</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n547-3">In <title>Cod. Just.</title>, XIII, XXV, I, this provision is laid down with regard to the chief <foreign xml:lang="ln">castrensiani</foreign>, but it is hard to see how it can have applied to the <foreign xml:lang="ln">castrensis</foreign> himself, still more to the <foreign xml:lang="ln">praepositus</foreign>, a higher officer of state.</note>
            <note xml:id="n548-1">Sc. the <foreign xml:lang="ln">castrensiani</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n548-2">I cannot render <!-- eb, Syriac. --> in this context otherwise. Appy. the meaning is that large sums pass through his hands. V. D. and L.'s translation of all this passage bears no relation to the Syr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n548-3">The word usually means <hi rend="singleQuote">eunuchs</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n548-4">20 <foreign xml:lang="grc">κεντηνάρια</foreign> would be about £ 90.000 = fr. 2.269,800, an almost incredible sum.</note>
            <note xml:id="n549-1">I Tim., V, 8 (?).</note>
            <note xml:id="n549-2">Cf. p. 75, l. ult. <!-- eb, Syriac. --> is perh. an emph. form of <!-- eb, Syriac. -->. Cf. <!-- eb, Syriac. --> (p. 285, l. 4, and p. 620).</note>
            <note xml:id="n549-3">Matth., VI, 20.</note>
            <note xml:id="n550-1">Cf. p. 285, l. 541, l. 10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n550-2">Circ. £ 4500 = fr. 113.490.</note>
            <note xml:id="n550-3">An obvious contradiction.</note>
            <note xml:id="n550-4">Id., XVI, 23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n551-1">Id., VII, 13.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
