<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/10510">History of the Monastery of John Urtaya</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/10510 -->
         <head>Next the Fifty-Eighth History, Concerning the Original Foundation of The
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">Holy Convent</placeName> of the House of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName>John at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, and Who Were Its
            Heads and Founders From the Beginning, i.e. From the Year Seven
            Hundred of <persName>Alexander</persName>, and Down to the Year Eight Hundred And
            Seventy-Eight of the Same</head>
         <p>
            It did not therefore seem to us to be just and a fitting thing that we should
            withold the good deposit which was committed to us by old men our holy
            <pb n="207"/><pb n="553"/>fathers concerning the original foundation of this our <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">holy convent</placeName> of the
            house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName> at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, and concerning the great old men who were
            the founders and builders of it from the beginning; but it seemed to us to
            be right and very proper that through this our narrative we should hand
            down and transmit to the rest of its inmates the history concerning it even
            as we received and truly and accurately learned it, as we received and
            learned through tradition from three seniors advanced in years, who were
            inmates of it from the time of its great earlier prosperity, that is especially
            from the great senior Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName> archpresbyter of this same <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, who
            had been an inmate of it for a long time, who himself also as well received it
            from ancient seniors of protracted life who were before him, who were inmates
            in it from its earliest foundation. But this blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName> lived even in our
            times, and down to the year eight hundred and fifty of <persName>Alexander</persName><note></note>; and he
            gained distinction also in the conflict (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of persecution; and he fell asleep
            and finished the course of his great and divine practices in the second exile
            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">έξορία</foreign>) itself in the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2769">Claudias</placeName>, in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2795">monastery called that of the
               Huts</placeName>, while the whole <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> also dwelt in it for about twelve years<note></note>, and
            built it and set it up and made plantations there. As then we received and
            <pb n="208"/><pb n="554"/>learned from these blessed men, that is in the first place from this blessed
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName>, we record the history, which he often related in our presence; which
            is as follows. Before this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> was firmly established, there were a few
            huts on its site, which were called (the informant stated) those of Mar Afwrsm,
            who himself also gained distinction for a considerable time in the conflict
            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of seclusion. Then the blessed Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName>, by whose name the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>
            was called, came about the year seven hundred<note></note>, and made another hut for
            himself a little distance from the earlier ones in the same place, and shut
            himself up in it, who was also thought to be an <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaya</placeName> and so called for some
            such reason as this. Because (the informant stated) he was a zealous man and
            an expounder and a teacher, he used to go in and out of the country of the
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaye</placeName><note></note>, warning and teaching and expounding and correcting many,
            insomuch that he learned the language of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaye</placeName>, so that for such a
            reason he was thought to be and was called an <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaya</placeName>, though by his birth
            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) he was a Syrian.
         </p>
         <p>
            While then the blessed man was winning distinction in the labour of
            seclusion, and gaining renown and reverence from many, two other blessed
            <pb n="209"/><pb n="555"/>men came to him, and they also were renowned and famous men, and
            teachers and firstrate scribes, one of whom was named <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName> and the other
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3227">Jonathan</persName>, who had been living in the monastery of the Edessenes<note></note> at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>,
            who transcribed many books, which by virtue of their wills (<foreign xml:lang="grc">διαθήκας</foreign>) have
            been handed down in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> even down to the present day itself. And
            in consequence of the blessed man's renown and in consequence of his beautiful 
            manner of life the blessed men <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3227">Jonathan</persName> begged him that
            they might be granted the privilege of living with him; and he accepted
            them, and they took up their abode with him, while they also too with him
            and in his company received more teaching and instruction in the labours
            of asceticism and the teaching of religion. When then the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> had
            begun to advance and progress, so much so that with all its belongings it
            in a great fashion attained to a large increase in buildings and belongings
            and increase of the brotherhood up to the number of fifty men, then the blessed 
            Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName> ended the course of his practices, and departed from the world,
            having left as his successor in the government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> the blessed
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName>. But the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3227">Jonathan</persName> had removed from the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> during
            the blessed man's lifetime; and when he had fallen asleep he came back, and
            <pb n="210"/><pb n="556"/>lived with the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName>, and they lived together in brotherly and
            spiritual fashion, until the decease of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName>; so that, when this
            man had made a great addition to the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, he also as well departed from
            the world; and over the government of it after him he left the blessed
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3227">Jonathan</persName>. And this man again by great knowledge and sound government
            brought about an increase in all the belongings of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>; and afterwards 
            he also as well departed from the life here; and the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3217">Job</persName> was
            appointed to succeed him; and this man also governed excellently and lawfully 
            and spiritually all his days, and he departed from the world of distresses
            to the country of joys; and the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> was appointed to succeed
            him at the head of the monastery, who was also a native of the city. This
            man (the informants stated) had a house in the city, and an old mother,
            and brothers and a considerable number of kinsmen<note></note> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>). And, when
            he had been governing the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> excellently for a long time, unfounded
            ill-feeling was stirred up against him (they stated) by certain members of
            the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> who suspected of him that he was secretly providing for his
            household and making them gifts from the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>; and, while he for his
            part defended himself from these charges on every point, they on their
            <pb n="211"/><pb n="557"/>side could not abandon such a suspicion, but (the informants stated) by the
            operation of <persName>Satan</persName> contended the more against him, so that afterwards (they
            stated) he himself also besides was instigated by the impetuosity of anger,
            and gave up not only the headship and the government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, but
            even residence in it as well, having bound himself by stern oaths not to
            reside in it longer, nor taste even water that belonged to it as long as he
            lived. And so he left it, and went into the city and lived there in retreat
            and devoutness in his house; while after a time (they stated) he used to sigh
            and distress himself and weep with sobs, because he had been overreached
            by the evil one and robbed of residence in his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>; insomuch that at
            last he would go out and visit it and look into it while they begged him to
            take food in it, and he would not consent to taste anything whatever from
            the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>; but at last (they stated) he used to make all the provision for
            his meals at home, even to cold and hot water and herbs, and so he would
            bring it out from his house and eat it in the monastery, while he sighed all
            the days of his life that he had been thus overcome by passion. And his
            successor was a brave and valiant blessed man, whose own name also was
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName>, who from the beginning of his government began to win distinction
            and show prowess and gain renown on a great and extensive scale,
            <pb n="212"/><pb n="558"/>while he also in a short time greatly increased and extended the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>,
            being also formidable and severe and stern toward all the chief men and
            magnates of the city and of the district; insomuch that his fame penetrated
            even to the king<note></note>, and he was summoned by an order to the royal city.
            and went up and was received with great honour, so that in addition to great
            presents he gave him a village also as well for which he asked in the district
            of <placeName>Ingilene</placeName> the name of which was <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2824">Narda</placeName>, for which he had asked on account
            of the usefulness of its wooded heights and so on. But on coming down
            from the royal city and seeing the spaciousness and magnitude of the heights
            he cut off half of it and gave it to the monastery of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/358">the village of Zuknin</placeName><note></note>
            who had asked him for it, since he indeed loved them as his brothers. And
            he began to raise his own <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> of the blessed Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName> to the number of
            four hundred men; and this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> grew and increased in the blessed man's
            days beyond all the convents round the city. And on account of the perfection 
            of his character and the sublimity of his mode of life great constraint
            was put upon him, and he was made bishop in the land of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaye</placeName> in the
            district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Anzetene</placeName><note></note>; and, when this happened, both he and all the members
            of his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> were smitten with sorrow and distress, and they continued
            begging and entreating him to appoint a head and governor for them in his
            <pb n="213"/><pb n="559"/>place, while he refused to do this, saying to them, <quote>Now that I for my part
            have been deprived by my sins of residence with you, do you look out, and
            deliberate among yourselves, and the man whom you know to be suited for
            you set over you as head, lest eventually you find fault either with me or
            with someone else</quote>. But they argued the more with him, saying, <quote>We
            will not allow you, our father, to depart hence until you appoint a head for
            us in your place</quote>. Again (the informant stated) he on his part answered
            them, saying, <quote>If you insist that I shall set up a governor for you in
            my place, think not that I shall make an appointment in the way that you
            suppose and appoint men who are thinking about themselves; but whoever
            appears to me to be fitting I will appoint for you. And beware lest in the
            end he be displeasing to you and you murmur</quote>. And, as they again continued 
            to press him in this way, he gave orders and the bell sounded, and
            they all stood up for service. And, having spoken at great length and given
            warning and instruction in his clear speech, he gave orders and the archimandrite's 
            hood and wand were brought, and laid before the altar. Then
            (the informants stated) the blessed man turned and looked behind him at the
            lines of the companies, and passed down the middle and laid his hand
            on a certain old man who held a low place among the members of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>,
            <pb n="214"/><pb n="560"/>and drew him out, dragging him by force, and brought him before the altar
            (whose name also was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName>), while he objected and wept and refused.
            And he on his side made a prayer and took him and clad him in the hood
            of the archimandriteship, and put the staff of the pastorate of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>
            in his hand, even as he came from the occupation of shepherd of a flock,
            and from a village called Thella d Mikhana<note></note>, and all his life and even after
            his death, and even to the present time in the same <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> he was called
            <quote>Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> the shepherd</quote>. But the old man continued saying with sobs
            and with much weeping, <quote>How is it, sir, that you appoint me a plain man
               (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ίδιώτης</foreign>) and a shepherd to govern such a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> as this?</quote> But the blessed
            man answered him, saying, <quote>Remember our Lord's saying to Peter when
            he says, <quote>Henceforth thou shalt catch men to life</quote>"; even as you now after
            being shepherd of a dumb flock of animals shall carry out the duties of
            shepherd of a rational flock of men</quote>. But those who were in high and
            prominent place, and thought of themselves that they were wise and
            learned and teachers, and of whom each one was confident concerning
            himself that it would be he who would be raised by force to the governorship,
            when they saw that he had appointed an old man and a shepherd who held
            <pb n="215"/><pb n="561"/>a low place to the governorship, showed displeasure and indignation and
            found fault and began to murmur. And, when the blessed man saw it, he
            said to them: <quote>You know, my sons, that for my part I at first committed
            the matter to your discretion. But, now that you threw the burden upon
            me, I on my side thought this old man fitter than all of you to administer
            the affairs of this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, while I know also what I have done and whom I
            have appointed, a man whom I have seen for a long time, and, while I observe
            all of you, and see that each concerns himself only with himself and his
            gratification, see that this man is vigilant and energetic and earnest,
            and eager to promote the interests of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>. And for all these reasons
            it is to him that I have entrusted and am entrusting my place. And he who
            obeys him, and receives and pleases him receives and pleases me; and he
            who strives with him and opposes him is superfluous in this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName></quote>.
            When these things had been carried out in this way, and the blessed bishop
            had given his blessing and prayed and gone to the district to which he had
            been summoned, then many stood forth in envy and bitter strife against the
            same blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> saying, <quote>He set as head over us a man who is a
            peasant and a shepherd holding a low place</quote>. And so they made one company 
            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κοινήν</foreign>), and rose up in strife, and separated themselves; and sixty men
            <pb n="216"/><pb n="562"/>left the monastery in one body for such a reason as this. And they went
            and occupied a site and built a monastery for themselves and a well-known
            martyrs' chapel which exists even to the present time, in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2751">village called
               that of Beth Bar ʿrubtha</placeName><note></note>. But the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> was strengthened, and
            began to act with vigour and show firmness, and to display proper energy in
            all the government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, and great carefulness for all its belongings,
            and for the canons and regulations and all the spiritual ordinances in it,
            while he also began to walk in every point in the footsteps of the blessed
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> the great his predecessor, in speech and in wisdom, and sound
            knowledge, and orderly and honourable conduct, insomuch that he also as
            well gained great renown over the whole <placeName>East</placeName>. But after a time came the
            blessed Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3251">Samuel</persName> also besides who also founded the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> called after
            his name, having first set up a standing-post for himself, and taken up his
            position on it. And, when he began to build the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, the blessed
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> used to give him much assistance, since, after the city-gates were
            shut, he would take a party of forty and fifty men, and they would
            go and work with them, and give assistance all the night, and thus they would
            return to the monastery in the morning; because (the informant stated)
            <pb n="217"/><pb n="563"/>when they were shepherds also they used to feed the flocks together, so that
            (the informant stated) jesting with one another they would say, <quote>Woe to
            us if God requires from us the stolen sheep that we have eaten</quote>. And so
            (it was stated) the two heroic old men distinguished themselves by great
            modes of life, together with all the other convents their brethren. In the
            days of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> the shepherd therefore <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2286">Kawad</persName> king of the
            <persName>Persian</persName>s came against the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName> in the year eight hundred and
            thirteen<note></note>; and he took it and carried off captives from it, while he also
            razed the monastery too to the ground, and piled its wood and its stones
            and its clay on to the <quote>mule</quote><note></note> which he had set up against the city. The
            story of these events was related to us<note></note> by an old man with venerable
            white hair whom<note></note> once when we had set out to go into the desert of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>
            we found in the country of Palestine beyond <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> in a monastery called
            that of Mar <persName>Thomas</persName> at Beth <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1508">Gubrin</placeName>, so that, when we had first zealously
            directed our course to the <placeName>city of Alexandria</placeName>, and had arrived at this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, 
            we found that venerable old man sitting, though he was unable to
            <pb n="218"/><pb n="564"/>see from age. But, when we approached him to make obeisance to him
            and receive his blessing, he asked us saying, <quote>Whence are you, my sons?</quote>
            And we on our side answered him, saying, <quote>We are, sir, from the district
               of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName></quote>. When he on his side heard the name of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, he was struck
            dumb and shed copious tears with sobs. And, when that old man had been
            violently weeping and sobbing for a long time, he said : <quote>If I ask you, my
               sons, do you know anything in the territory of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>?</quote>, and we answered
            him, <quote>Be so good as to ask, sir; and what we know we will say</quote>. But
            the old man asked us about this our own <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, saying, <quote>Is there a
               monastery called that of the house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName> on the north of the city by
            the side of the wall and has it been built?</quote> And we said to him <quote>Yes, sir.
            It has been built and it exists, and it is in fact from it that we come</quote>.
            When the blessed man heard this, he yearned the more toward us, while he
            also betook himself to showing emotion by weeping with many sobs, saying,
            <quote>I, my sons, was an inmate of that monastery, from the days of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName>
            the great who became a bishop, when I was a boy, when the numbers also
            amounted to four hundred men. And, when <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2286">Kawad</persName> came to <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, we fled
               and we all went inside and took up our abode in the school (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σχολή</foreign>) called
               <pb n="219"/><pb n="565"/>that of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Urtaye</placeName> within the wall, about three hundred men, the rest
            having been scattered and fled. And, when the city was taken and the
            <persName>Persians</persName> came in and began to slaughter, we all stood up sorrowing and
            weeping for the service of our death and of our lives' end, slaughter being
            now set before our eyes. And, when the <persName>Persian soldiers</persName> arrived, and they
            came in and saw long rows of men standing, they began a fearful slaughter
            among us. And, having beheaded ninety of us in one massacre while
            our eyes beheld it, they then ceased slaughtering; and they took us and
            carried us away as captives, while they also made spoil of all the belongings
            of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>. But, when the city was thrown open, God delivered us
            and strengthened us and many of us escaped. And from that time I fled
            from all that country; and I made a vow to God not to see it again</quote>.
            And so that old man was piteously relating all these things to us with great
            emotion and many tears; so that for a long time he was unable<note></note> on account
            of his sobs to relate them before us. And again another old man of many
            days (and he too had venerable white hairs), who during the same times of
            the prosperity of this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> had been in his boyhood an inmate in it,
            <pb n="220"/><pb n="566"/>who was in the renowned <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/1528">monastery of the Orientals at Edessa</placeName><note></note>, who was
            called <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3239">Paul</persName> of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/724">Arzen</placeName>, who also departed from the world a few years before
            during the persecution of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, used all his days in the presence
            of many persons to tell about the prosperity of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, saying:
            <quote>Before the deportation by <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2286">Kawad</persName> we numbered four hundred men in it;
               and so prosperous and extensive was the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> of the blessed Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName>,
            that, since their space was too much confined for the purposes of occupation
            by the same <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, they formed the plan of building for themselves a
            large house for a chapel. And so the masons of the city applied themselves
            to hewing out metopes (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μέτωπα</foreign>); so that, when the blessed men wished to
               convey them to the monastery after the gate (<foreign xml:lang="grc">πόρτα</foreign>) of the city was shut at
            dusk, they used to go out and fetch them in one line from the monastery
            right up to the quarries (<foreign xml:lang="grc">λαοτομία</foreign>) themselves; and thus they would hand on
            the stones and pass them from one to another, and they are passed down
            their lines till they enter the precincts and are piled upon the building, and
            thus that extensive building was built, though it was not completed on
            account of the deportation by the <persName>Persians</persName> and the scattering of the brotherhood; 
            so that, since a heap (?)" remained after the <persName>Persians</persName>, a large
            <pb n="221"/><pb n="567"/>portion of the monastery was quarried and built from it; and the whole of
            the martyrs' chapel dedicated to <persName>Kyra Maria</persName> was also built from it, and
            further much was also quarried and brought in from it for the church and
            the city.</quote><note></note> And its kiln is still standing. But this <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> was rebuilt on
            a smaller scale, both in buildings and in the number of the brotherhood.
            But the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName>, who was also called <quote>the shepherd</quote>, ended the
            course of his practices, and <quote>died in a good old age</quote><note></note>. And to succeed him
            in the government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3200">Cosmas</persName> was appointed, who
            also showed himself an excellent governor and head; and he governed
            during his days in tranquillity and quiet, having lived the whole of the time
            of the reign of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2265">Anastasius</persName>; and so he fell asleep in his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> in peace<note></note>.
            And to succeed him in the headship and government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> the
            blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3255">Sergius</persName> was appointed, who by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) came from the village
            of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2780">Gadara</placeName> which was in the north; who in the first persecution that arose
            against the church was the first to go out in banishment with all the rest
            of the convents, and gained distinction in the conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of persecution,
            <pb n="222"/><pb n="568"/>and in all the labours of monasticism, as well as in excellent government all
            the time of his life. And he ended his course during the same persecution;
            and he died and was buried in the monastery called that of Mar <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2813">Mama</placeName><note></note>.
            But to succeed him a great blessed senior was appointed whose name was
            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3263">Symy</persName><note></note>; who by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) was a native of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/724">Arzen</placeName><note></note>; who with his two
            predecessors <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3255">Sergius</persName> and <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3200">Cosmas</persName> were<note></note> in our days, since we indeed in the
            days of the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3255">Sergius</persName> and the others who succeeded him received the
            privilege of residing in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>. When then after the decease of the
            blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3255">Sergius</persName> they were urging the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3263">Symy</persName> to take up the government, 
            he continued objecting and refusing, saying, <quote>Allow me, my brothers,
            to repent and make entreaty on account of my sins, because I have not one
            day beyond three years and a half in the body</quote>. And, since not even after
            his prophecy also (which was shown to be exact truth) did he escape, but
            they constrained him and he took his place at the head with earnestness as
            it is written excellently and like a teacher, expounding and admonishing
            day and night with service and with vigil, he would also at all times
            <pb n="223"/><pb n="569"/>adjure and warn everyone to bestow care and earnestness upon finding
            spiritual life, and many were in fact enlightened by his teaching, and by
            his admonition were brought to open their hearts and to sorrow and tears,
            wondering and giving thanks to God. But his prayer and the gift of revelations 
            and of prophecy was of such a kind that not only did he gain knowledge 
            of his departure beforehand and prophesy it, but even concerning many
            other things also, insomuch that at the beginning he spoke and uttered
            many prophecies to our own mean self also, of which we truthfully assert
            that none has fallen to the ground or fallen short of the pronouncement
            uttered by him even down to this very day; which we refrain from recording,
            lest we be thought to be desirous of displaying great things about ourself.
            When therefore this man had completed the time which he decreed for
            himself, some days before he called and blessed and commanded and warned
            everyone, and so according to the decree which he laid down he ended his
            course during the same persecution in the country of the <placeName>East</placeName> in <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2834">the monastery 
               called that of the Poplars</placeName><note></note>, in which also the whole community was
            residing. But after five years, when the recall from banishment came, we
            ourselves were privileged to carry and convey his holy bones into the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>
            <pb n="224"/><pb n="570"/>of the house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName> itself<note></note>. And to succeed him there was appointed
            our blessed master and teacher from our boyhood, whose name was <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">Abba</persName>;
            who also was by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) from the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/724">Arzen</placeName><note></note>; and he was
            reverend and imposing in his speech and in his appearance. But after four
            years of his government occurred the entry into the city-convents themselves
            at the beginning of the reign of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName> the king. And, when we had
            completed about seven years and a half in the convents themselves, the
            envy of those who ruled the churches was aroused, and the persecution was
            renewed over the whole of the <placeName>East</placeName>, through the descent of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2274">Ephraim</persName> patriarch
            of the city of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2610">Antioch</placeName> to the <placeName>East</placeName>; and all the convents were again expelled,
            and they went together to the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2834">monastery</placeName> which they had previously built and
            took up their abode in it, which was called that of the Poplars. And after a
            little time they were expelled thence, and the convents were divided; and the
            blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">Abba</persName> with all his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> went away, and they went into the steep
            towering mountains of the village called ʾbdhyr<note></note>; and we took up our
            abode there in a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2826">monastery called that of the Nut</placeName>. And after three years<note></note>
            we left and went into the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2769">Claudias</placeName>, and took up our abode in the
            <pb n="225"/><pb n="571"/>monastery of the Huts<note></note>, which we also mentioned above in our history. And
            the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3183">Abba</persName>, having been arrested and maltreated by the <persName>Synodites</persName>,
            fled and went up to the royal city; and, when he had passed some time there
            with the concourse of believers that had been gathered from every quarter
            by the believing queen <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName>, and had a great reception from her, and
            had been there five years, then it was his pleasure to return to his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>,
            while the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> was still in the district of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2769">Claudias</placeName>, and he ended his
            course there <quote>in a good old age</quote><note></note>; so that, when after a space of three years
            we ourselves too went down from the royal city, we took his holy bones
            also as well and sent them to the city-convent itself<note></note>. And to succeed him
            in the government of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3185">Abraham</persName> was appointed, who
            by his birth (<foreign xml:lang="grc">γένος</foreign>) was from <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/2758">Anzetene</placeName><note></note>, and was a great and earnest administrator 
            in all the spiritual and bodily affairs by which a <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> is
            maintained. And, when this man had completed some years, he also as
            well fell asleep and was laid in the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, since he had gone for the
            purpose of visiting it, and fell asleep and was buried in his monastery, as he
            desired and prayed<note></note>. After him was appointed the blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3255">Sergius</persName> of
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, who comes of a distinguished family from the city itself, called the
            <pb n="226"/><pb n="572"/>house of Bar <persName>Deba</persName><note></note>. This man was placed by his parents in the same <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> 
            from his childhood, and he was brought up in it from the days of the
            blessed <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3200">Cosmas</persName> the archimandrite, and he gained distinction also in all the
            conflicts (<foreign xml:lang="grc">άγών</foreign>) of persecution from the beginning down to the present year,
            which is the year eight hundred and seventy-seven, the year in which <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2284">Justinian</persName>
            departed from the world<note></note>, having first been buffeted in every place with all
            the old men his fathers who had lived since the beginning of the persecution
            while he endured and remained firm. But at last, when he was appointed
            to the headship of the <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, he increased in strength and prowess and
            firmness, while he was more frequently driven from district to district and
            from place to place, uttering thanks and praise at all times; a man who,
            having been at first luxurious and delicate and smart as being a citizen, and
            at last come to himself<note></note>, and been smitten with remorse and brought himself
            into a religious frame of mind, turned his face away from all visible
            things, and came to despise clean clothes and delicious foods and unguents
            and so on, and clothed and covered<note></note> himself with garments of hair, and
            embraced asceticism and abstinence, and fasting and services and protracted
            prayers by day and night, and what is more admirable than all, the practice
            of observing the divine commandments, having stored up in his mind the
            <pb n="227"/><pb n="573"/>words of our Saviour who says, <quote>He who loveth me keepeth my word</quote>,
            and again <quote>Let your speech be <quote>Yea, yea</quote> and <quote>Nay, nay</quote>.</quote><note></note>, and so decided
            it for himself that an oath should never proceed from his mouth. And he
            persevered and kept and maintained his resolution even down to the present
            time also, since he is actually in the body even down to the present time also
            during the persecution of his <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName>, as well as of all his brethren the other
            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> in the district of <placeName>Izla</placeName><note></note> in the same persecution, down to the present
            time which is the year eight hundred and seventy-nine<note></note>, from the year eight
            hundred and thirty-two<note></note>, which makes forty-seven years from the beginning
            of the persecution of the same down to the year stated above.
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of the original foundation of the holy <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/399">convent</placeName> of the house of Mar <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3218">John</persName>
            at <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/8">Amida</placeName>, and who were its heads and founders from the beginning is finished.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
