<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/850">Jacob Baradaeus (Translation of His Body)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/850 --> <!-- eb, I cannot find spear/850 so I have merely attached persNames and placeNames for now. -->
         <head>A Writing of<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n614-1"/> Mar Cyriac Bishop of <placeName>Amrna</placeName> About the Same<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n614-2"/> Holy Mar <persName>James</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n614-3"/>.</head>
         <p>
            When then Mar <persName>James</persName> the bishop from the holy convent of <placeName>Fsiltha</placeName> had
            departed to our Lord a considerable time before, and the patriarch Mar
            <persName>Athanasius</persName> had arisen upon the see of <persName>Peter</persName> the great<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n614-4"/>, <persName>Phocas</persName> king of the
            <persName>Romans</persName> again expelled the orthodox (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξοι</foreign>) bishops from their sees and
            appointed heretics<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n614-5"/>, but by the judgments of God the Persian king Khosrau
            <pb n="269"/><pb n="615"/>son of <persName>Hormizd</persName> came and took all the country east of the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName> in war<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n615-1"/>;
            and by God's provision and queen <persName>Shirin</persName>'s advice he<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n615-2"/> expelled the bishops
            of <placeName>Chalcedon</placeName> from the cities east of the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>, and appointed orthodox
            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">όρθόδοξοι</foreign>) bishops in their places, viz. in <placeName>Amida</placeName> Mar <persName>Samuel</persName>, and in <placeName>Edessa</placeName>
            Mar <persName>Isaiah</persName>, and in <placeName>Rhesaina</placeName> Mar <persName>Addai</persName>, and in <placeName>Thella</placeName> Mar <persName>Zakkhai</persName>; and so
            in every district and city<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n615-3"/>, while they agreed in everything with the blessed
            patriarch. At this same time therefore, when Mar <persName>Zakkhai</persName> bishop of <placeName>Thella</placeName>
            had heard and learned of the holiness of the blessed Mar <persName>James</persName>, he was
            zealous for the Lord and for that holy soul and exerted and bestirred himself,
            and sent four blessed men from his convent, and two of the clergymen of the
            city (and he supplied them with a swift animal and money) to go to the monastery
            of <placeName>Casium</placeName> in which he fell asleep, and steal him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n615-4"/> thence. And he laid
            down a law (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>) for them as to how they should act and dispatched them.
            Now those who went were sent in the year nine hundred and thirty-three of the
            <persName>Greeks</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n615-5"/>. And at the same time <persName>Heraclius</persName> king of the <persName>Romans</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n615-6"/> came, and
            took all the country east of the <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>, and drove the <persName>Persians</persName> as far as
            <pb n="270"/><pb n="616"/><placeName>Nisibis</placeName> which is on the frontier<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n616-1"/>. And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n616-2"/> the members of the monastery went
            in the days of the devout Mar <persName>Stephen</persName> who was termed Shbiliya<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n616-3"/>; and, having
            gone and arrived at the monastery of <placeName>Casium</placeName>, they went into the monastery
            and prayed and came near<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n616-4"/> and were blessed by the holy Mar <persName>James</persName>, and
            by<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n616-5"/> the brothers of the house. And on being asked whither they were
            travelling they answered <quote>We are envoys of the church of <placeName>Syria</placeName> to the pope.
               of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>.</quote> Then they were received with much honour. When then<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n616-6"/>
            they had remained there two days, in accordance with a plan and trick that
            had been concerted by them on the way, one of these monks<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n616-4"/>, the envoys,
            set up a wail being possessed by a demon<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n616-7"/> and foaming and went out of his
            mind<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n616-4"/>. And his companions began to be distressed and weep; and in
            sorrow they went on to fasten their companion to the sarcophagus of the
            <pb n="271"/><pb n="617"/>holy Mar <persName>James</persName>, in order that he might learn how<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n617-1"/> to steal that holy body,
            while his companions on his account slept<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n617-2"/> with him close by the sarcophagus 
            itself. But during the night they would bore, and in the day cover the
            borings that they had made. And, when the task had become easy for them,
            they took the keys (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κλείδα</foreign>) of the monastery to themselves, that their task
            might be easily accomplished<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n617-3"/>. Then they said to the members of the
            monastery of <placeName>Casium</placeName>, <quote>We, sirs<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n617-4"/>, since we have a letter with us, cannot
               remain here with this sick man<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n617-5"/>; but we will leave one of us with him and
               a swift animal, in order that, when the Lord pleases and he recovers, he may
               quickly join us at <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, in the holy convent of <placeName>Marth Zoila</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n617-6"/>, but pray
               for us</quote>. And, having gone thence, they came as far as <placeName>Palestine</placeName> on their
            return; and the man who had feigned madness and his companion rose by
            night and took the body of the holy Mar <persName>James</persName>, and wrapped it in silk
            shrouds, and came on the swift animal to their companions in <placeName>Palestine</placeName>
            according to the agreement that they had made with one another.
         </p>
         <pb n="272"/><pb n="618"/>
         <p>
            But the blessed men the members of the monastery of <placeName>Casium</placeName>, when
            they rose in the morning and saw that the saint's body had been taken
            away, lifted up their voice in weeping and in sobs; and they went in all
            directions after them, and did not find them<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n618-1"/>; and they returned to their
            monastery mourning. But the blessed men departed from <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, themselves 
            and the clergymen, and rapidly arrived at the city of <placeName>Thella</placeName>, carrying 
            his holy body with them. And, when the bishop<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n618-2"/> and the clergy
            and the citizens<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n618-3"/> heard of it, they went to meet it with lights and incense
            and songs of praise, and carried it round the whole city, accompanying it
            with spiritual odes, and chants of the Holy Spirit. And then they<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n618-4"/> wrapped
            it round and laid it in his monastery, the convent of <placeName>Fsiltha</placeName>, in the temple
            which the saint had built in his lifetime<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n618-5"/>, and it is there for the assistance
            and healing of all men<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n618-6"/>, and for the honour and praise of Christ his<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n618-7"/> God;
            <pb n="273"/><pb n="619"/>to whom and to his Father with his<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n619-1"/> Holy Spirit be praise and honour
            and worship and exaltation, now and always and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n619-2"/> for ever and ever. Amen!
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of Mar <persName>James</persName> bishop of <placeName>Edessa</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n619-3"/> is ended.
         </p>
         <p> <!-- See this note. Also, this colophon seems to apply to the whole collection of lives. -->
            This history was written by the industry of Mar <persName>Theodosius</persName> presbyter and
            stylite of the monastery of <placeName>Fsiltha</placeName>, in the days of Mar <persName>Stephen</persName>, archimandrite 
            of the same convent, in the year a thousand and fifty-two
            of <persName>Seleucus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n619-4"/>.
         </p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n614-1">C ins. <hi rend="singleQuote">the holy</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n614-2">C <hi rend="singleQuote">Marde, how the bones of the</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n614-3">C ins. <hi rend="singleQuote">came from the monastery of Casium to his monastery</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n614-4">Sc. the apostle, not surely, as M. Kugener thinks, the patriarch Peter of Callinicius.</note>
            <note xml:id="n614-5">Nothing is known of this, and in Phocas' time there were no Monophysites in open possession of sees.</note>
            <note xml:id="n615-1">C <hi rend="singleQuote">a short time</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n615-2">C <hi rend="singleQuote">the king and Shirin the queen ordered and</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n615-3">C ins. <hi rend="singleQuote">priests and clergymen were appointed</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n615-4">C <hi rend="singleQuote">to fetch his body</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n615-5">622.</note>
            <note xml:id="n615-6">C <hi rend="singleQuote">Greeks</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n616-1">622-9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n616-2">C <hi rend="singleQuote">of the Greeks and the Persians. And H. instituted a persecution against the church, because bp. Isaiah of Edessa did not give oblation to the king in the great church of Edessa, because the bishop demanded of the king that, unless he anathametized the synod of Chalcedon in writing, he did not give him the oblation (sic). And for this reason Christians without number who stood firm and held fast were oppressed; and those who did not show constancy returned to the heresy of Chalcedon. At that time</hi>; cf. Mich., p. 409.</note>
            <note xml:id="n616-3">Sc. <hi rend="singleQuote">the man of the path</hi>(?).</note>
            <note xml:id="n616-4">C om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n616-5">C <hi rend="singleQuote">greeted</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n616-6">C ins. <hi rend="singleQuote">they were travelling on the road, they deliberated thus: <hi rend="singleQuote">As soon as we reach the monastery, one of us will purposely have a seizure, that on this pretext we may be able to approach the place where the saint is</hi>. And when</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n616-7">C <hi rend="singleQuote">convulsed</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n617-1">C <hi rend="singleQuote">they might setthemselves</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n617-2">C <hi rend="singleQuote">were</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n617-3">I give the sense from C; see n. on text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n617-4">S <hi rend="singleQuote">sir</hi> C <hi rend="singleQuote">my brothers</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n617-5">C <hi rend="singleQuote">our companion</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n617-6">C <hi rend="singleQuote">Mar Zoilus</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n618-1">C <hi rend="singleQuote">anything</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n618-2">C <hi rend="singleQuote">bishops</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n618-3">C <hi rend="singleQuote">men of his city</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n618-4">C ins. <hi rend="singleQuote">came to his monastery and</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n618-5">C <hi rend="singleQuote">it with great honour, since he had been educated and trained in it, in the monastery of Fsiltha</hi>. The date was probably 21 Mar., 622. J. is celebrated on 21 Mar., 31 July, and 28 Nov.; and, as 31 July is the day of his death or burial, and 28 Nov. arises from a confusion with J. of Batnae, 21 Mar. is probably the date of his translation, and was in fact a Sunday in 622.</note>
            <note xml:id="n618-6">C <hi rend="singleQuote">who take refuge at his coffin</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n618-7">C <hi rend="singleQuote">our</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n619-1">C <hi rend="singleQuote">the</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n619-2">C om.</note>
            <note xml:id="n619-3">C <hi rend="singleQuote">the holy Mar J. of Fsiltha who is Burd'ana (his prayer be with us in both worlds)</hi>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n619-4">741. This colophon comes from S only. See Introd.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
