<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/850">Jacob Baradaeus (Translation of His Body)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- See spear/850 -->
         <head></head>
         <p>
            When then Mar James the bishop from the holy convent of Fsiltha had
            departed to our Lord a considerable time before, and the patriarch Mar
            Athanasius had arisen upon the see of Peter the great<note></note>, Phocas king of the
            Romans again expelled the orthodox (op96dožo) bishops from their sees and
            appointed heretics, but by the judgments of God the Persian king Khosrau
            <pb n="269"/><pb n="615"/>son of Hormizd came and took all the country east of the Euphrates in war<note></note>;
            and by God's provision and queen Shirin's advice he expelled the bishops
            of Chalcedon from the cities east of the Euphrates, and appointed orthodox
            (opQadoYoi) bishops in their places, viz. in Amida Mar Samuel, and in Edessa
            Mar Isaiah, and in Rhesaina Mar Addai, and in Thella Mar Zakkhai; and so
            in every district and city<note></note>, while they agreed in everything with the blessed
            patriarch. At this same time therefore, when Mar Zakkhai bishop of Thella
            had heard and learned of the holiness of the blessed Mar James, he was
            zealous for the Lord and for that holy soul and exerted and bestirred himself,
            and sent four blessed men from his convent, and two of the clergymen of the
            city (and he supplied them with a swift animal and money) to go to the monastery
            of Casium in which he fell asleep, and steal him thence. And he laid
            down a law (vópos) for them as to how they should act and dispatched them.
            Now those who went were sent in the year nine hundred and thirty-three of the
            Greeks<note></note>. And at the same time Heraclius king of the Romans<note></note> came, and
            took all the country east of the Euphrates, and drove the Persians as far as
            <pb n="270"/><pb n="616"/>Nisibis which is on the frontier<note></note>. And the members of the monastery went
            in the days of the devout Mar Stephen who was termed Shbiliya<note></note>; and, having
            gone and arrived at the monastery of Casium, they went into the monastery
            and prayed and came near and were blessed by the holy Mar James, and
            by the brothers of the house. And on being asked whither they were
            travelling they answered <quote>We are envoys of the church of Syria to the pope.
               of Alexandria.</quote> Then they were received with much honour. When then
            they had remained there two days, in accordance with a plan and trick that
            had been concerted by them on the way, one of these monks, the envoys,
            set up a wail being possessed by a demon<note></note> and foaming and went out of his
            mind<note></note>. And his companions began to be distressed and weep; and in
            sorrow they went on to fasten their companion to the sarcophagus of the
            <pb n="271"/><pb n="617"/>holy Mar James, in order that he might learn how<note></note> to steal that holy body,
            while his companions on his account slept<note></note> with him close by the sarcophagus 
            itself. But during the night they would bore, and in the day cover the
            borings that they had made. And, when the task had become easy for them,
            they took the keys (xλeîda) of the monastery to themselves, that their task
            might be easily accomplished<note></note>. Then they said to the members of the
            monastery of Casium, <quote>We, sirs", since we have a letter with us, cannot
               remain here with this sick man"; but we will leave one of us with him and
               a swift animal, in order that, when the Lord pleases and he recovers, he may
               quickly join us at Alexandria, in the holy convent of Marth Zoila", but pray
               for us</quote>. And, having gone thence, they came as far as Palestine on their
            return; and the man who had feigned madness and his companion rose by
            night and took the body of the holy Mar James, and wrapped it in silk
            shrouds, and came on the swift animal to their companions in Palestine
            according to the agreement that they had made with one another.
         </p>
         <pb n="272"/><pb n="618"/>
         <p>
            But the blessed men the members of the monastery of Casium, when
            they rose in the morning and saw that the saint's body had been taken
            away, lifted up their voice in weeping and in sobs; and they went in all
            directions after them, and did not find them<note></note>; and they returned to their
            monastery mourning. But the blessed men departed from Palestine, themselves 
            and the clergymen, and rapidly arrived at the city of Thella, carrying 
            his holy body with them. And, when the bishop<note></note> and the clergy
            and the citizens<note></note> heard of it, they went to meet it with lights and incense
            and songs of praise, and carried it round the whole city, accompanying it
            with spiritual odes, and chants of the Holy Spirit. And then they<note></note> wrapped
            it round and laid it in his monastery, the convent of Fsiltha, in the temple
            which the saint had built in his lifetime<note></note>, and it is there for the assistance
            and healing of all men, and for the honour and praise of Christ his<note></note> God;
            <pb n="273"/><pb n="619"/>to whom and to his<note></note> Father with his Holy Spirit be praise and honour
            and worship and exaltation, now and always and<note></note> for ever and ever. Amen!
         </p>
         <p>
            The history of Mar James bishop of Edessa<note></note> is ended.
         </p>
         <p> <!-- See this note. Also, this colophon seems to apply to the whole collection of lives. -->
            This history was written by the industry of Mar Theodosius presbyter and
            stylite of the monastery of Fsiltha, in the days of Mar Stephen, archimandrite 
            of the same convent, in the year a thousand and fifty-two
            of Seleucus<note></note>.
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
