<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 41</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 41, pp. 205-209.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="41">
            <pb n="205"/>
            <head>XLI</head>
            <head>A letter which he wrote to one of the brethren who loved solitude concerning how
               Satan contrives to divert the zealous from constant solitude under the pretext of the
               love of relatives and honoured men; and that it is becoming that all should be
               despised in the eyes [of the solitary] compared with the knowledge of God which is
               found in solitude as may be seen in the example of our ancestors</head>
            <p>Because I know that thou lovest solitude and that Satan, knowing the intention of thy
               mind, impedes thee in many respects under the pretext of excellence, in order to
               divert thee from this comprehensive and manifold excellence, o virtuous brother, I
               was anxious to help thy good will as one limb helps its partner, with an excellent
               word, which I have received from prudent men and from the writings of the Fathers and
               from experience. For if a man does not despise honour and dishonour and bear for the
               sake of solitude abuse and derision and loss, nay even blows, and become an object of
               laughter and be reckoned mad and foolish by those who see him, he <pb type="external"
                  n="308"/>cannot master the advantages of solitude. For if a man once open the door
               to [worldly] things, Satan will not cease to bring unto him men under every pretext,
               a continual, innumerable series of associations. Therefore, my brother, if thou
               lovest the veracious discipline of solitude without distraction and shocks and sudden
               pauses, as it has been eminently practised by the ancients, thou wilt be able to
               carry out this laudable desire by trying to resemble thy Fathers and by retaining in
               thy mind, as if it were written down, the memory of their histories [ascertaining]
               that those of them who loved complete solitude, did not care to practise love of
               their fellows at the cost of distracting themselves, neither were they ashamed of
               avoiding such persons as were reputed to be in honour.</p>
            <p>And though they were thus, devoted to complete solitude, yet they were not deemed by
               those who know and are wise, <pb n="206"/>to despise their brethren, nor were they
               thought of as scorners or destitute of distinctions, as it was pretended by some in
               the way of apology against those who honour quiet and reclusion more than meeting
               their fellows. For the man that has experienced the quiet of his cell does not avoid
               meetings because he despises his fellow, but because of the fruits he gathers from
               solitude.</p>
            <p>How did they practise reclusion? Aba Arsenius would not meet with any one. Aba
               Theodore, when meeting anyone, was like a sharp sword; he did not greet anyone when
               he happened <pb type="external" n="309"/>to be outside his cell. But the holy
               Arsenius did not even greet him that came to greet him. Once one of the Fathers went
               to see Aba Arsenius who opened, thinking that it was his servant. When, however, he
               saw who it was he prostrated himself. And when the visitor sought to persuade him,
               saying: Rise, o father, that I may greet thee, were it only in the doorway, then I
               will go, the saint protested saying: I will not rise until thou goest; and he did not
               rise until the other had left him and was gone. Thus the blessed one acted, lest they
               should come again if he once gave way to them.</p>
            <p>'One of the Fathers' — pay careful attention to this phrase lest thou think perhaps
               that Aba Arsenius despised his visitor on account of his mean estate; but it was one
               of the Fathers who spoke to him.</p>
            <p>But we have also a strong proof from another side, lest thou say that he despised
               one, but received another favourably on account of his high position and conversed
               with him. No, in his reclusion he avoided alike all kinds of association; and in his
               eyes to despise the association with high or low for the sake of solitude, and to
               bear the reproaches of all in view of the honour of solitude and silence, was one and
               the same thing. We know namely that once the blessed Theophilus, the archbishop of
               Alexandria, visited him accompanied by the judge of that place, because they longed
               for the honour of seeing the saints. As he sat with them he did not comfort them even
               with a single word such as would have been fitting their high position, although they
               were very eager to hear his speech. <pb type="external" n="310"/>And when the
               archbishop tried to bring him to speech, the solitary was silent for a short time,
               and answered, saying: If I speak to you, will you remember what I say? They promised
               to do so. Then the solitary said to them: Wherever you hear that Arsenius is, do not
               come near to that place.</p>
            <pb n="207"/>
            <p>Doest thou see the wonderful way of the man? Doest thou see how he despised the
               honour of men? The blessed one knew how to gather the fruits of solitude without a
               thought to the fact that he was in the presence of the katholikos, the head of the
               whole church. But he thought thus: I am now dead to the world; what profit will a
               dead man give the living? He was vituperated for this in a loving way by the blessed
               Macarius who said to him: Why doest thou flee from us? The holy solitary made a
               wonderful praiseworthy apology: God knows that I love you; but I cannot be with God
               and with men.</p>
            <p>Another time the archbishop sent him a message concerning this subject. The solitary
               answered, saying: 'If thou comest I shall open the door to thee. But if I open to
               thee, I shall open to every one. And if I open to every one, I shall not remain
               here'. This wonderful doctrine he had heard from none other than from a divine voice,
               saying: 'Arsenius, flee from men and thou shalt live'. None of the idle men who seek
               an occupation, will venture to refute this message by his objections or to speak
               against it, as if to seek peace proceeded <pb type="external" n="311"/>from human
               invention. For this is a doctrine from heaven.</p>
            <p>The opinion that this was said to him with a view to reclusion and retreat from the
               world only, not with the intention that he should also avoid the brethren, is refuted
               thereby that, when he had retreated from the world and was abiding in the monastery,
               he again prayed to our Lord in order that he should know to live well. 'O Lord', he
               said, 'teach me to live', thinking that now he would hear another message. The divine
               voice proclaimed the same words again, adding as in explanation: 'Flee and be silent
               and keep in solitude. Though the sight of and intercourse with the brethren be very
               profitable to thee, still intercourse with them is not as profitable as withdrawal
               from them'.</p>
            <p>When the blessed Arsenius, while he was still in the world, had heard by divine
               revelation the order to withdraw from it, and when the same had been said to him
               while he was with the brethren, he knew certainly that in order to acquire a
               steadfast life, not only withdrawal from lay people was necessary but from every
               human being. Lest any one should venture to speak against the divine voice, it was
               also said to Aba Antonius in a revelation: 'If thou desirest to be in solitude, <pb
                  n="208"/>do not only go to the Thebaïs, but to the heart of the desert. If now God
               in this way commands us to <choice><sic>witdraw</sic><corr>withdraw</corr></choice> from all, and wishes that His friends
               dwell in solitude, who should then, for other reasons, cling to intercourse and the
               vicinity of men? <pb type="external" n="312"/>If watchfulness was profitable and
               withdrawal helpful to Antonius and Arsenius, how much more then to the weak? And if
               the solitude of those whose words and the help that is inspired by the sight of them
               the whole world needs, is estimated by God higher than their usefulness to mankind in
               its entirety, how much more will this be the case with him that is not able to guard
               even his own person properly.</p>
            <p>We know another of the saints whose natural brother was ill. He lived as a recluse in
               a different cell. During the whole period of his brother's sickness he restrained his
               mercy, so that he did not go out to visit him. When the sick man was on the point of
               departing from this world, he sent his brother a message to this effect: Come that I
               may see thee before I depart the world, even if it be in the night. Then I will take
               leave from thee and go to rest. The blessed one, however, was not to be persuaded
               even at this time, when natural mercy usually is stirred, to transgress the voluntary
               borders, saying: 'If I go out, my heart will not be pure before God, for I despise
               visiting spiritual brethren, should I then honour nature above Christ'? So his
               brother died without his having seen him.</p>
            <p>No one, therefore, should consider the weakness of feelings as an insuperable and
               invincible reason, nor as a providential institution, implying the denial of
               solitude. If the saints subdue nature which is so strong, and Christ, though despised
               in His children, loves to be where solitude is honoured, what other necessity should
               then exist which could not <choice><sic>de</sic><corr>be</corr></choice> despised when it presents itself? The
               commandment: Love the Lord thy God <pb type="external" n="313"/>with thy whole soul
               and with thy whole heart<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n208-1"/> and more than the whole world and nature and what
               belongs to nature — is accomplished when thou abidest in solitude. And also the
               commandment ordering the love of our fellow men, is included in it. Wilt thou acquire
               the love of thy fellow-man, according to the commandment of the Gospel, within
               thyself, then withdraw from him. Then the flame of his love will burn in thee and <pb
                  n="209"/>thou wilt run to see him as if thou wouldst see the angel of light. Doest
               thou further desire that thy beloved ones long after thee? See their faces at fixed
               days only. Verily, experience is the teacher of all. Be in health.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n208-1"> Deuteronomy 6,5</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
