<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 35</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 35, pp. 152-180.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="35">
            <head>XXXV</head>
            <head>A treatise in questions and answers concerning constant behaviour and every kind of
               excellence which is eminently useful for those who have stripped off the world and
               dwell in the wilderness, for recluses and for those who in voluntary mortification at
               all times expect the crown of righteousness</head>
            <p>The disciple says: Which are the bonds captivating the mind [and withholding it] from
               running after evil things?</p>
            <p>The teacher says: The constant search after wisdom and desire for the teachings of
               life. For bonds stronger than these against the unruliness of mind do not exist.</p>
            <p>The disciple says: Where is the limit of the course of <pb type="external" n="225"
               />wisdom for those who seek it, and where does the course of teachings end?</p>
            <p>The teacher says: The way of this course is foreign to any limit, to such an extent
               that even the holy angels do not reach perfection. The course of wisdom is without
               end. It ascends to such a height that it mingles with God him that follows it. And
               even this is a sign of its unlimitedness, that its distinctions are without end;
               wisdom is God.</p>
            <p>The disciple: What is the first and principal way leading towards wisdom?</p>
            <p>The teacher: That a man seeks God with all his might and that he is quick in seeking
               Him with his whole person, so that he even does not dislike to give up and throw down
               his life on account of his love.</p>
            <p>The disciple. To whom is it becoming to be called a man of understanding?</p>
            <p>The teacher. He that really understands that there is a limit to his earthly life, is
               also able to put a limit to his sins. What knowledge or understanding is greater than
               this, that a man has wisdom to depart this life without harm, while his limbs are <pb
                  n="153"/>are not strained with the odour of desires, nor his soul with the filth
               of their sweetness? If a man subdues his impulses in order to penetrate into the
               mysteries of all classes of beings, and is filled with insight into all kinds of
               knowledge, so to say, yet his soul is defiled by the filth of sin so that he cannot
               hope on account of the witness of his soul that he shall safely reach the harbour of
               trust — then there is none more foolish among the creatures than such a man who,
               though being constantly occupied <pb type="external" n="226"/>by his works, is
               brought by them to the hope of this world only.</p>
            <p>The disciple. Who is really strong?</p>
            <p>The teacher. He that during the temporary troubles by which the glory of his
               victorious power is hidden, does not long after the comfort by which a shameful life
               is enveloped and which at all times compels those who find it, to drink the goblet of
               sighs.</p>
            <p>The disciple. Is it harmful to his course towards God, if a man makes a pause is his
               labour?</p>
            <p>The teacher. It is not possible for a man to come near to Christ without troubles,
               nor can his righteousness be preserved unchanged without them. When righteousness
               already acquired is bereft of labours which served to augment and at the same time to
               guard it, it resembles a treasure which of a sudden finds itself without guardians,
               or an athlete who is stripped of his arms while a host of enemies surrounds him; or a
               ship that is left in the ocean without the utensils of her equipment; or a garden
               rich in fruits from which is cut off the fountain that watered it.</p>
            <p>The disciple. Who is the illuminated in his impulses?</p>
            <p>The teacher. He who is able to understand the bitterness hidden in the sweetness of
               the world and who withholds his mouth from drinking its goblet. Who zealously
               enquires after the salvation of his life and who does not cease from running, up to
               the day on which he is freed from the world; who shuts the gates of his senses, lest
               the love of the world enter and dwell within him and bereave him of his hidden
               treasures.</p>
            <p>The disciple. What is the world and how can we <pb type="external" n="227"/>recognize
               it and how can it do harm to those who love it?</p>
            <p>The teacher. The world is a whore and by the desire of its beauty it attracts those
               who see it so that they love it. And he that during a short time has been entangled
               in its love is not able to escape from its hands, before it has stripped him even of
               his life and sends him from its house through <pb n="154"/>death, bereaved of all.
               But a man recognizes it as soon as he endeavours to leave its darkness. Then he is
               able to see the many cords of its nets. As long as he is in it, he cannot see its
               ensnarements. For it is not only its disciples and sons and captives which are within
               its fortress, but also the renunciators, ascetics and those who have once broken its
               bonds and were once above it — those also it now gradually begins to entangle in its
               service, making them litter for its feet.</p>
            <p>The disciple. Now that thou hast convinced me of the fact that the world really
               suffocates those who dwell in it and of how difficult it is to understand its
               artificial bonds, I beg to learn first, what is the first impulse to the mind's doubt
               concerning the world, since its bonds are so very sweet and the schemes of its
               fetters are hidden?</p>
            <p>The teacher. When the deliberation of the love of his soul awakens in him, this
               impulse of deliberation begins to make the world hated in his eyes and it throws into
               him doubt concerning it.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="228"/>The disciple. Whence comes this emotionality which
               brings about that which appeared always praiseworthy and beautiful, now suddenly
               appears as ugly, so that he repents his life and his previous knowledge, thinking
               that he did not think rightly concerning the world?</p>
            <p>The teacher. In the first place it is nature which <choice><sic>beakoning</sic><corr>beckoning</corr></choice> to him in
               silence, awakens in him the critical impulse as to the unstable duration of the world
               and of the future and of its course and as to the <choice><sic>ephemere</sic><corr>ephemeral</corr></choice> nature of
               those who enter into it, so that he considers this world as a place of transition for
               those who enter into it; as also for the many generations before him, the number of
               which is unlimited. They have entered it as an inn for a night and left it as
               travellers on a journey over the whole earth, without thinking of return. Some of
               them kings, some governors, some wise, some honoured. Some of them scribes, some
               orators, some judges, some commanders of armies. Some of them possessors of riches,
               some lords of goods. And now after their death there is neither the order of their
               degrees, nor the crowns of their government; nor their dreadful thrones, nor their
               lordly pleasures, nor the praise of those who honoured them, nor the love of their
               friends, nor the luxuriant pleasures of their bodies, nor the comely beauty of their
               grace, nor their proud majestic stature, nor their erudite <pb n="155"/>mind, nor
               their spirit rich in impulses, nor the rich effusions <pb type="external" n="229"/>of
               the <placeName>Gihon</placeName> of their learning which streamed from their mouth and captivated by its
               grace the heart of the hearers.</p>
            <p>They have slept in <placeName>Sheol</placeName> for long years as if it were one night. And it is not known
               how many years they yet have of this long sleep, nor when the dawn of resurrection
               will rise for them and awaken them from their slumber. And to consider for what
               purpose they are left in this state, causes great suffering; and he will think of how
               many generations are cloistered under this earth, forgotten [now]. And I too will
               pass as any one of them. Cursed be riches and comfort. And under this deliberation,
               great confusion will arise in his heart and his spirit will be filled with suffering.
               And on account of the severity of suffering he will pour forth tears in great sorrow.
               Then he will despise the world and bewail his life and lament over his soul with
               various bitter lamentations. And with sighs he will say to himself: Where wilt thou
               be, my miserable soul and where wilt thou find thyself after my death? Perhaps even
               this deliberation will rise in him: Would I had not entered the world of creatures
               and I had not left the womb!</p>
            <p>In this kind of lamentation he will shed sweet tears because of the sorrow of his
               heart, and moisten his garments with his tears. And forthwith this world will be in
               his eyes as a prison and its first sweetness will be more bitter than any bitter
               thing and the love of his life and its desirable beauty will seem the type of
               hell.</p>
            <p>Then his mind will turn to scripture which will awake in <pb type="external" n="230"
               />him faith in the resurrection and the end awaiting all the things of this world,
               and in the promises given to those who have lived well in the world and the divine
               judgments threatened against the transgressors of the law and against those who,
               during their short lifetime have lived in the broad way of sin. And then, as one who
               has discovered some light, he throws away the burden of sorrow, and great joy is
               awakened in him, because he has found a hope, excellent and true. These things and
               the like, nature is not able to prompt from his inward emotion: they are understood
               from the words of scripture by faith alone. Man is not able to acquire instruction
               concerning himself wholly from nature and from the critical impulses which are within
               him. Concerning the dealings of God in the Past and in the Future we are able to earn
               this <pb n="156"/>instruction from the scriptures or from spiritual revelation. Then
               by the rays of faith and scripture the eye of the spirit will be enlightened and the
               natural critical faculty will radiate and man will be incited to care for his soul.
               And further he will think of means to make his life free from the world, so that,
               before departing the body, he will be able to prepare for himself provisions useful
               for the world to be.</p>
            <p>The disciple. How can man wholly give up the world?</p>
            <p>The teacher. By desire of the future good that is recollected, which divine scripture
               sows in his heart with the sweetness of its words full of hope. When the things that
               are thought to be glorious and delightful and in which man is entangled, are not
               contrasted with the desire of still more excellent things, <pb type="external"
                  n="231"/>the spirit is not able to despise its former love.</p>
            <p>The disciple. But nature is weak and not able to give up suddenly all its former
               customs and embrace a life of troubles.</p>
            <p>The teacher. If the greatness of the future life does not cause a man's spirit in the
               greatness of wisdom to compare it with the miserable shortness of this temporal life,
               it is not possible for him to take heart to bear troubles in order to begin his
               course on the way of the new world. Pray, compute in thy mind the number of years of
               this our place and elevate thyself as much as possible, and compare it with the days
               of the future world, and say whether that which thou givest is equal to what thou
               wilt receive.</p>
            <p>And, considering what thou leavest and what thou wilt receive in stead of it, say
               whether thy exchange is an equal one. Therefore the wise, while he wonders at the
               greatness of that world and its unlimited life over against the shortness of temporal
               life, will say: The number of man's days if he lives long, are a hundred
               years<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n156-1"/>; this is like filling a bucket from the sea or taking one corn of
               sand. A thousand years in this world is not as much as one day in the world of the
               righteous<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n156-2"/>.</p>
            <p>The disciple. And what shall we do with the body? As soon as it is surrounded by
               distress, the desire of the will towards the good is relaxed as well as its former
               zeal.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="232"/>The teacher. This will usually happen to those the half
               of whose being has sought God, whereas the other half has remained in the world. This
               means that their heart is not yet <pb n="157"/>free from earthly things, but they are
               in doubt, sometimes looking behind, sometimes forward; and I think that the sage
               admonishes those who approach the way of God in this state of indecision, saying: Do
               not approach it doublehearted, but approach it as one who sows or as one who reaps.
               And our Lord, seeing that among those who wish to renunciate completely, there are
               some in such a state of mind, that their will is ready but their thoughts are drawn
               backwards by fear of troubles, on account of their love of the body which they have
               not yet thrown away — He will take from them this lassitude of mind saying to them
               briefly: If any man will come after me, let him first deny himself<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n157-1"/>. What is
               the denial that is spoken of here? It is the denial of the flesh. And one who is
               destined to suffer crucifixion, he accepts the thought of death, and goes forth, as
               one who does not think that he has any further share in this life. This is [what is
               meant by] taking up the cross and following me. The cross denotes the will prepared
               for any trouble. And declaring why this is so, Me says: Whoever will save his soul in
               this world, will lose it in the true <pb type="external" n="233"/>life<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n157-2"/>. And
               whoever will lose his individuality here for my sake, will find it there. This means:
               he that sets his steps on the way of crucifixion and yet still cares to think of this
               bodily life, bereaves his soul of the faith for which to suffer he is gone out.
               Because this thought does not allow him to approach trouble; but, being always with
               him, allures him gradually and makes him leave the centre of the struggle for blessed
               life. Such thoughts grow in him till they have overpowered him. But he whose mind has
               complied with the loss of his self for the sake of finding the love of Me, he will be
               preserved, without harm, for life everlasting. This is, he who gives up his life for
               my sake will find it.</p>
            <p>This means: make free thy soul as it were from thyself and prepare it for a complete
               loss of life. If the departure from this life finds thee in this state of mind, I
               will give thee life everlasting, according to my promise. And if thou perseverest in
               this life, I will show my promise in thee later as a confirmation of the future
               goods. Therefore, thou wilt find that immortal life when thou despisest temporal
               life. If thou enterest the strife with such a preparation, all that was most
               sorrowful and <pb n="158"/>difficult, will be contemptible in thy eyes. The
               preparation of such a will even is not a struggle for his life in his mind, <pb
                  type="external" n="234"/>even when peril of death threatens him. In short: If a
               man does not hate his temporal life, because of love of the future life, he cannot
               bear troubles.</p>
            <p>The disciple. In what way can a man cut off his former customs and accustom himself
               to a life of privation?</p>
            <p>The teacher. The body is not to be persuaded to live in need, so long as it is
               surrounded by things of luxury and relaxation. For the sight of [worldly] things,
               their splendour and existence kindles in it a desire for them. Therefore justly our
               Saviour has commanded those who follow Him, in the first place to renunciate and to
               leave the world. First He frees them from the causes of relaxation; then He commands
               them to begin work. And our Lord himself, when He began His strife with the Devil,
               combated him in the dry and desert wilderness. And <persName>Paul</persName> also commands those who bear
               the cross of Christ to leave the town. So we will leave the town with Him, bearing
               his disdain, which He also suffered without the town.</p>
            <p>By the abandonment of the world and what belongs to it, man easily forgets his former
               customs and his trouble will not last a long time. But the coming near to [worldly]
               things easily relaxes the fervour of the spirit. It is also becoming and very
               profitable in the strife, that a man's life be ordered with the utmost privation and
               indigence, free from all things that <pb type="external" n="235"/>excite [the desire
               of] comfort. When thus the causes leading towards relaxation are removed from man, he
               will not be tormented by the double strife, the outward and the inward one. Lo, how
               much easier is the strife if the things a man desires are afar off and not near,
               alluring the thoughts by their aspect.</p>
            <p>Thus we see that there is a double strife. When a man's way of life is poor and his
               wants are small, he will not look with desire at these things even when indigent and
               he will content his body with little, because even the body is despised and
               contemptible in his eyes; and he does not approach unto it because of its beauty and
               the pleasure it gives, but only in order to sustain nature.</p>
            <p>These ways easily lead man to asceticism, without harm and strife and deliberations.
               It is becoming for a man to refrain from the sight of those and to remain far from
               those things, <pb n="159"/>against contact with which he can be on his guard only
               with a great effort. This I do not say in view of things of the belly only, but also
               in view of those things which by their temptation put to the test the solitary's
               freedom and the avoiding of which he has promised in his bond with God. So I mean
               also the sight of a woman's face, the sight of superb things, superb persons and
               their luxury, splendid persons and their garments, all things belonging to
               worldliness also speaking and hearing concerning them. For the affections possess a
               strong power, <pb type="external" n="236"/>when [worldly] things are near, to weaken
               the stragglers and to turn aside their mind. If the sight of beautiful things spurs
               on the mind to follow their service with zeal, it is well known that also those which
               are the contrary of beautiful, have the power of captivating the mind. And if further
               harm does not happen than that the quiet mind is cast into strife, there is this loss
               at any rate, that a man by his own will is thrown from peace into perturbation.</p>
            <p>If one of the saints, an industrious father, thought the sight of a man with a
               womanlike face a harm for the mind and an injury in the strife, when once he
               approached one of the convents, who then should neglect other [dangers]; for this
               blessed man was not to be persuaded even to enter and prostrate himself there. This
               wise father deliberated with insight thus: 'if it should come to my memory even only
               in the night I pass here, that there is here such a thing, this would be a great
               loss'. And therefore he did not enter the convent. 'I am not afraid, my brethren' [he
               said]. 'But wherefore useless strife'? This means, that even such recollections
               hinder the serenity of my service.</p>
            <p>For all the things which belong to this body and against which a man must guard
               himself by a great effort, will cause him little strife as long as they are at a
               distance from him. Thus even when they are near, so long as a man uses the pleasant
               things [of this world] with fear, he desires their proximity only because of the use
               which is in them.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="237"/>We see that many roots are buried and hidden under the
               earth, of which no one has any knowledge as to their existence while it is summer,
               because of the force of the sun and the strength of heat. But when the raindrops
               reach them and the influence of the fragrant air, then all of them suddenly begin to
               show themselves <choice><sic>whereever</sic><corr>wherever</corr></choice> they are buried. Doest thou not <pb n="160"
               />see, that by the strong heat of asceticism and the rays of the grace of solitude,
               the affections leave thee in quiet; but if thou approachest the things [of the
               world], thou shalt see that all of them are quickened and thrust up their heads from
               their places, that is: if they smell just a little of the odour of comfort.</p>
            <p>These things I have said in order to show that no one should have confidence before
               he dies and departs this life and how helpful in our strife flight and withdrawal
               from the world are. Those things which we are ashamed to recollect secretly, we must
               also fear to meet. And we may not tread down the heart and despise conscience. For in
               a lonely place without contact [with the world] we have to examine our body in order
               to acquire training in endurance.</p>
            <p>There is also another thing, more important than the rest: namely as often as that
               which is a cause of strife, is afar from a man, even if he be vexed in mind he will
               not fear that, vanquished by desire, he might employ it on account of its being
               near.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="238"/>The disciple. If a man has thrown away all impediments
               and has entered the arena, what is the beginning of his strife against sin, and where
               does he start fighting?</p>
            <p>The teacher. This much is known to every one, that all strife against sin and its
               desires is to be preceded by the labour of fasting, especially if one is combating
               inward sin. And the token of hate against sin and its desires, visible in those who
               are engaged in this invisible strife, is this that they begin with fasting.</p>
            <p>Afterwards comes standing during the night. He that during his whole life loves the
               use of fasting, is a friend of chastity. As at the root of all the boons of the world
               and of all its evils, is sexual pleasure and the relaxation of sleep which incites to
               impure cohabitation, so the beginning of the holy way of God and of all virtues, is
               founded upon fasting and strict punctuality in the service of God, with the
               crucifixion of the body during the whole night in the strife against the pleasure of
               sleep.</p>
            <p>Fasting is a strengthening of all the virtues, the beginning of the struggle, the
               crown of the Naziraeans, the beauty of virginity and sanctity, the preservation of
               chastity, the beginning of the way of Christianity, the father of prayer, the
               fountain <pb n="161"/>of placidity, the teacher of quiet, and the forerunner of all
               good qualities. As the delight of light belongs to sound eyes, <pb type="external"
                  n="239"/>so the desire of prayer follows fasting with discernment. For as soon as
               a man begins to fast, his mind forthwith will be desirous of intercourse with God. A
               fasting body cannot endure lying on its bed during the whole night. For fasting
               naturally excites vigilance unto God; not only by day, but also during the night. And
               the empty body of him that fasts does not grow fatigued in the struggle against
               sleep. And though his senses are weak, his mind is awake unto God in beseechings. It
               is better to neglect service for weakness caused by fasting, than on account of
               indolence caused by food.</p>
            <p>To dwell at length upon the beauties of fasting is not necessary. Many of the
               teachers and fathers have spoken about the victories of fasting and the many
               beautiful things originating in it. And all books inform us concerning the importance
               of fasting and the victories it has given generation after generation, and concerning
               the mighty help afforded by it, and the high praise deserved by those who fast. And
               by experience it is known to every one, that it is the fountain of all good
               [qualities].</p>
            <p>As long as the seals of fasting are on a man's mouth, his mind meditates on the
               soul's penitence, his heart sends forth prayers and his face is dark with sadness.
               Evil impulses are afar from him; neither is gladness seen on his brow at all. For he
               is an enemy of desires and idle occupations. There has never been seen a man who was
               fasting with discernment who was subjected to evil desire. For fasting is a
               storehouse of all virtues. And he that despises it, makes all virtues totter.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="240"/>As the first commandment imposed upon our nature in the
               beginning was against the tasting of the food, and in this point the head of our race
               fell, therefore those who strive for the fear of God begin the building there where
               the first injury originated, when they begin the task of keeping His commandments.
               And also our Saviour, when He manifested Himself to the world at the <placeName>Jordan</placeName>, began
               from that point. For when He had been baptised, the spirit led Him into the
               wilderness, and then He fasted forty days and forty nights. And all those who follow
               His steps, base the beginning of their struggle upon this action. That weapon was
               polished by God, who should despise it without being blameworthy? If the lawgiver has
               fasted, to <pb n="162"/>which guardian of the law is it not necessary to do
               likewise?</p>
            <p>Till then the human race had not known victory, and <persName>Satan</persName> had never experienced
               defeat on the part of our nature; through this weapon, however, he was vanquished for
               the first time and the first victory was won which set the crown on the head of our
               nature. — Thus it is that as soon as this weapon appears in the hand of a man,
               immediately fear falls upon the deliberations of <persName>Satan</persName>, that head of rebellion, and
               at once his mind is struck by the recollection of that defeat in the desert and that
               first defeat he had to suffer. His strength will be broken when he sees the weapon
               which our commander has placed in our hands. As soon as he sees this weapon worn by
               any man, he knows that this one is prepared for the strife. What weapon is stronger
               than this and which gives <pb type="external" n="241"/>encouragement to the heart in
               the struggle with evil spirits as hunger for Christ's sake does? To the degree in
               which a man's body is fatigued and kept down at the time when the hosts of <persName>Satan</persName>
               surround him, to the same degree his heart is supported by confidence. And he that is
               constantly in this state, will at all times be burning with zeal as it were with
               fire.</p>
            <p>Constant fasting is a symptom of zeal and fervour in war. Even that zealot <persName>Eliyah</persName>
               took upon him this tribulation when he fought for the divine law. Forty days he
               restrained his mouth from food, during the long walk through the desert.</p>
            <p>Fasting reminds those who practise it of the spiritual commandments; for it was a
               mediator in the ancient law and by the grace of our Lord <persName>Jesus</persName> we have received it.
               But what more shall I say concerning its merits which are known to every one? He that
               despises fasting, will also be weak and without vigour in the other good works,
               because he lacks the weapon by means of which the godlike athletes have been
               victorious. And he that from the beginning shows in himself a sign of relaxation,
               gives his adversary a chance of victory and enters battle in a state of deprivation.
               And it is certain that he will leave it, without the victory, because he has bereaved
               himself of the force which divine zeal had stirred in him. Thus he begins strife in a
               state of cold in stead of in a state of heat. For his limbs are not clad with the
               flame of hunger, namely of fasting during which the mind endures the strokes of all
               hard and unexpected events motionless.</p>
            <p>It is said concerning many of the holy martyrs that, when <pb n="163"/><pb
                  type="external" n="242"/>they were informed by a spiritual revelation or by one of
               their friends, regarding the day on which they would receive the crown, they did not
               taste anything the preceding night, nor did they take any food. But from the eve till
               morn they would stand in prayer, awake, praising God in songs and glorifications and
               hymns and spiritual melodies, being joyful and exalting and expecting that moment as
               people destined to enter a bridal house. They expected, while in a state of fasting,
               to receive the blow of the sword and to be crowned with the crown of the
               confessorship.</p>
            <p>And we too have to keep this state of preparation perpetually, o my brethren,
               expecting invisible martyrdom and the winning of the crown of holiness, [being on our
               guard] lest in any of our limbs a sign of unbelief be given to our enemies. Thus our
               outward senses and our inward impulses being clad with all the weapons of God, we
               shall receive this crown deserving it and so we shall go in unto His glory with the
               holy martyrs, striking our enemies with amazement. For without labour nobody wins the
               crown, as the teacher, the great <persName>Diodorus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n163-1"/> says. For it is well known that it
               would be most unworthy that merchants may not bring home riches without labour and
               dangerous storms, and that yet the righteous should expect the remuneration of the
               crown, without injury and labour for the sake of righteousness.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="243"/>The disciple. Many are those who perform these labours,
               yet do not perceive rest as to the affections, nor peace as to the deliberations.</p>
            <p>The teacher. The affections hidden in the soul, o my brother, cannot be
               <choice><sic>apeased</sic><corr>appeased</corr></choice> by the works of solitaries which are performed with the body
               alone, nor do these hinder the deliberations from being constantly stirred by the
               senses. These labours guard man against being vanquished by desires and against harm
               caused by the demons. But they do not give peace and rest unto the soul too. Labours
               cause apathy and mortify our limbs on the earth and give rest on the part of
               deliberations, only if they are combined with solitude, when also the outward senses
               rest from <choice><sic>turbulance</sic><corr>turbulence</corr></choice> and have become addicted during some time, to the
               service of wisdom. Until a man refrains from meeting his fellow-man and until he
               checks <pb n="164"/>his limbs from mingling with many things, and concentrates his
               self, — he will not be acquainted with his affections. For solitude, the blessed
               <persName>Basilius</persName>, the shining torch of the whole world, says — is the beginning of the
               purification of the soul. For when the outward senses have rest from outward
               turbulence, then the mind will return from distraction unto its place and the heart
               will be stirred to examine the inner impulses of the soul; and if it perseveres well
               it will reach in its course even the purification of the soul.</p>
            <p>The disciple. Is it not possible for the soul, if it be strong, to be purified while
               having connections with the outward world?</p>
            <p>The teacher. If a tree is watered every day, when will <pb type="external" n="244"
               />its roots become dried up? A vessel whose contents increase daily, when will it be
               empty? If purity be nothing else than to forget the dealings belonging to non-freedom
               and to have peace from their recollection, and if a man, either personally and
               practically, or through others, renews in his soul by the medium of the senses this
               recollection, viz. the knowledge of evil things, when shall he be purified from them?
               Or when shall he be liberated from the strife with outward things, so that it will be
               possible to see inward things and gain peace? When the heart is defiled every day,
               when can it be purified from filth?</p>
            <p>Perhaps it cannot even dominate practice, not to speak of purifying the root. For it
               stands in the centre of the camp and every day its ears are struck by the rumour of
               battles, how then can it venture to proclaim peace to itself? But if it be far from
               these, then it will be able to grant peace to the inward things gradually. Before the
               stream from above has been shut off, the nether waters will not dry up.</p>
            <p>But when a man has found solitude, the soul is able to expel the affections and to
               test its own wisdom. Then the inward man will be stirred unto spiritual service and
               day by day he will perceive the hidden wisdom moving in his soul.</p>
            <p>The disciple. What are the true marks and the undubitable signs that from a man's
               labour the hidden fruits are beginning to show themselves in the soul?</p>
            <p>The teacher. When he is deemed worthy of the gift of <pb type="external" n="245"
               />tears, flowing abundantly and without compulsion. Tears are to the mind the sure
               distinction between the bodily and the spiritual state, between the state of
               apperception and that of purity. As long as one has not yet received this gift, the
                  <pb n="165"/>labour of his service is still in the outward man, and this to such
               an extent that he does not even perceive anything of the hidden service of the
               spiritual man. When he begins to leave the bodiliness of this world and moves in that
               territory which lies beyond this visible nature, then at once he will reach the grace
               of tears. And from the first apartment of that hidden behaviour these tears will
               begin and they will conduct him to the complete love of God. When he has reached this
               point, tears will be so copious that he drinks them with his food and his drink, so
               constant and abundant are they. This is a true token of the mind's leaving this world
               and its apperceiving the spiritual world. And the more the mind approaches unto this
               world, the more these tears will diminish. And when the mind is wholly in the worldly
               things, it will also be completely without tears, and this is the sign of its being
               enveloped by the affections.</p>
            <p>Some tears cause a burning heat, others render fat. All tears which flow for grief
               and distress of heart caused by sins, make the body lean and burning with heat. And
               often when these tears are shed, one will even feel that his marrow is injured. Man
               will necessarily enter this order of tears first. <pb type="external" n="246"/>Then
               by them the gate leading to the second order will be opened for him, an order which
               is by far superior, because it contains the sign of the receiving of mercy. What is
               this? Those tears which have their origin in insight, make the body fat; they flow
               spontaneously and compulsion has no share in them. They also anoint the body and the
               aspect of the face is changed. For a joyful heart renders the body beautiful. These
               tears moisten the whole face when the mind lives in solitude. The body acquires by
               them as it were some sustenance and joy is diffused over the face. Whosoever has
               experienced these two varying states, will understand.</p>
            <p>The disciple. What is the resurrection of the soul, namely if ye be risen with
               Christ?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n165-1"/></p>
            <p>The teacher. This is what is said by the apostle in another place: For God who
               commanded the light to shine out of darkness, hath shined in our hearts<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n165-2"/>.
               Resurrection he calls leaving the old state, which in the likeness of Hell hindered
               him from seeing the light of the Gospel rise, so to say, which <pb n="166"/>is the
               breath of life in the hope of the resurrection by which the dawn of divine wisdom
               rises in the heart, so that he now is a new man in whom is nothing of this world. As
               it has been said: A new heart also will I give you; and a new spirit will I put
               within you<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n166-1"/>. Then in truth Christ is imprinted on them, by the spirit of
               wisdom and revelation, in knowledge concerning Him.</p>
            <p>The disciple. What is, in short terms, the power of the practice of solitude?</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="247"/>The teacher. It mortifies the outward senses and
               quickens the inward impulses. Intercourse, however, works in the inverse way.</p>
            <p>The disciple. What is the cause of the visions and revelations granted unto some? To
               others however, who have laboured more than the former, such things are not
               granted.</p>
            <p>The teacher. The causes of revelations and visions are many, not one. The first cause
               of revelations and visions is God's will to give a token of His mercy; in this case
               God provided men with them in order to help them. Some take place on account of
               divine providence. These are the common cases. The rest take place in order to
               strengthen and to encourage the weak, and to console and instruct them.</p>
            <p>[An instance of those revelations which take place by] providence are the angels
               which were seen at the side of the grave, and those which at the Assumption appeared
               unto the Apostles who were both distressed and stupefied and in confusion on account
               of the Lord's departure from them. And at once two angels appeared who stood by them
               in white apparel, and those which appeared in the prison and in any place where [the
               apostles] fell into the hands of men. Unto single persons and unto the other saints
               after them they appeared, and even to this day. For these three classes of men such
               visitations are usually provided: for those who are simple and irreproachable above
               measure; or for holy and perfect persons; or for those who on account of fervent zeal
               have fled from <pb type="external" n="248"/>the world; abandoning it entirely in
               despair and retiring from any part inhabited by men, following God, naked, without
               hope or help from anything visible, assailed by the fear of desolation or surrounded
               by the peril of death from hunger or illness or <pb n="167"/>any evil whatever and
               near to dejection. That such consolations happen to some people, whereas others who
               are their superiors in works remain without anything of that kind, is in the first
               place founded on purity or non-purity of the heart, I mean. A second cause is
               certainly this, that as long as a man receives consolation from his fellow-man or
               from any of these visible things, such [heavenly] consolations do not happen to him,
               safe only by providential decree and this bears a common character.</p>
            <p>But our discourse is for solitaries. A witness to this is one of the saints who has
               announced that there came a voice unto him saying: Enough of consolation from and
               intercourse with men! Another witness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n167-1"/> to this is he who led a solitary life
               in reclusion, and often tasted from consolations granted by grace, and divine care
               often became visible to him in manifest apperception; but when he came near the
               inhabited world and sought these things as usual, he did not find them. He besought
               God that the truth concerning this matter might become <pb type="external" n="249"
               />known to him, saying: Perhaps, my Lord, grace has been withdrawn from me on account
               of my episcopal rank? It was said to him: No. But then, there was the desert, there
               were no men, but God provided for thee. Now, there is the inhabited world and men
               provide for thee. — So we say that it is impossible for a man to share in visible as
               well as in spiritual consolation.</p>
            <p>The disciple. Are vision and revelation one, or are they different in fact as they
               are different in names?</p>
            <p>The teacher. There is a difference between vision and revelation. The name of
               revelation covers the two, because it denotes the revealing of a thing that hitherto
               was hidden and now becomes manifest in any way. But not all that is revelation is at
               the same time vision. But what is vision is also called revelation, because it is a
               hidden thing which is revealed. But not all that comes to be revealed and known, is
               vision.</p>
            <p>Revelation is usually connected with what is intelligible and tasted with the
               intellect. Vision, however, always happens in similitudes; as those things which were
               ministered unto the ancients, be it in the depth of sleep, or in the state of waking;
               sometimes clearly, at other times dimly, while he to whom the <pb n="168"/>vision was
               given often did not know whether he saw awake or in sleep. Even after he had regained
               consciousness, he did not know whether the thing had in reality happened to him, or
               as in a dream. Sometimes a voice of help was heard; <pb type="external" n="250"
               />sometimes a symbolical representation was seen; sometimes there was a clear
               apparition, face to face, and sight and speech, questions and intercourse; and those
               holy hosts appeared to those who were worthy. It is clear that in the desert and the
               wilderness and in lonely places and in places of retreat from the world, such things
               happen; where man decidedly needs them, because he has no help from any side.</p>
            <p>Revelation of those things which are apperceived intellectually, is received through
               purity. And the latter only belongs to the initiated and perfect.</p>
            <p>The disciple. When any one has reached purity of heart, what is the token thereof?
               And when shall he know himself whether his heart has come to purity?</p>
            <p>The teacher. When he sees all men in a good light, without any one appearing to him
               unclean or defiled. Such a man has really reached purity. If this were not true, how
               could it be possible to fulfill the word of the Apostle: When a man possesses all
               excellence, he reckons every one superior to himself in heart and truth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n168-1"/>.</p>
            <p>But when he has reached the point mentioned, he whose eyes are pure, does not see
               evil.</p>
            <p>The disciple. What is purity and where is its limit?</p>
            <p>The teacher. I think that purity is oblivion of those kinds of knowledge which do not
               belong to nature, those namely which nature has found in the world. Its limit
               consists therein that we are freed from that knowledge to such a degree that we reach
               the original simplicity and integrity of nature in the <pb type="external" n="251"
               />way of a child, apart from small exceptions only.</p>
            <p>The disciple. It is possible for a man to reach this order?</p>
            <p>The teacher. Ay. One of the Fathers was come so far, that he repeatedly asked his
               pupil whether he had eaten bread or not. And one of the saints who was then an old
               ascetic, had become so pure and simple and had reached such a perfection and
               serenity, that he was nearly as a babe, having forgotten all <choice><sic>wordly</sic><corr>worldly</corr></choice>
               things. And perhaps many will not <pb n="169"/>believe us what we say (for it is a
               real wonder) that even at the oblation of the Eucharist he could not observe [the
               fast] so as to receive the Eucharist; he did not even know whether he had observed
               [the fast] or not, till his disciples kept watch on him in his cell and brought him
               to the sanctuary, as a little boy. So very serene and pure was this blessed man. And
               being thus in worldly things, in his soul he was perfect with God.</p>
            <p>The disciple. Which meditation and occupation should a man have in his reclusion and
               solitude, lest his intellect should be found to be occupied with accidental
               deliberations?</p>
            <p>The teacher. Thou askest what shall be the meditation of him that is dead to the
               world in his cell. Should a man who is zealous and whose soul is awake, need to ask
               what his work should be in his solitude? What is the meditation of the solitary in
               his cell but weeping? Should he be able to turn his gaze from weeping towards a
               different deliberation? Which <pb type="external" n="252"/>meditation would be more
               profitable? For his dwellingplace, lonely like the grave and deprived of all worldly
               pleasures, teaches him that his service consists in weeping. And even his name turns
               him into this direction; for he is called <persName>abila</persName>, which means: bitter in heart. All
               the righteous have departed this world with weeping. If the saints would weep and
               their mouths at all times were filled with their tears and they thus departed this
               world, who should not weep then? The consolation of the recluse is born from weeping.
               If those who were victorious have shed tears in this world, how then should he that
               is covered with wounds dare to abstain from weeping? If before the housefather his
               beloved is laid dead, should he need instruction concerning the thought which should
               move him to tears? Thy soul which is dead in sins is laid before thee, thy soul which
               is of greater value to thee than the whole world. If we come to solitude, we can also
               get accustomed to weeping. Therefore we should steadily beseech our Lord to give us
               this. If we receive this gift, excellent above any other, through weeping we shall
               reach purity. And when we have reached it, it will not be taken from us again, to the
               day on which we shall depart the world.</p>
            <p>Blessed therefore are the pure in heart who at all times enjoy this delight of tears
               and through it constantly see our Lord. While tears are in their eyes, they are
               deemed worthy <pb type="external" n="253"/>of seeing His revelation at the height of
               prayer; for they even <pb n="170"/>know of no prayer without tears. And this is what
               has been said by our Lord: Blessed are they that mourn: for they shall be
               comforted<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n170-1"/>. For by mournfulness a man reaches purity of soul. When therefore
               our Saviour says: Blessed are they that mourn: for they shall be comforted, He does
               not explain what comfort is. When the solitary is deemed worthy on account of his
               mournfulness to pass beyond this place of affections and to reach the plain of purity
               of soul, where he will find a consolation that will not leave those who have found it
               — then it is clear that the consolation which at the completion of mournfulness is
               received through purity, is promised by our Lord to the mournful. For if any one
               weeps constantly, the affections will not approach his heart; for weeping lies beyond
               affectibility. If tears are able to efface from the mind of him that mourns and weeps
               for but a short time, the recollection of the affections, what shall we say about him
               who has imposed upon himself a definite service during day and night? Who knows the
               profits of weeping, save those who have given themselves to it? All the saints desire
               this [means of] introduction; and by weeping, a gate is opened before them through
               which they enter that place of consolation, in which the footsteps of God's love are
               impressed by revelations.</p>
            <p>The disciple. But because man is not able to adhere to this practice, on account of
               the body's weak nature, it is necessary for him to have some other thing serving
                  to<pb type="external" n="254"/>captivate his mind, lest the affections should
               assail him through the idleness of the intellect.</p>
            <p>The teacher. The affections are not able to assail the soul and to trouble the
               solitary whose heart is cut off from the world by dwelling lonely in the complete
               solitude of the desert, separated from all the sounds and voices of the commotion of
               mankind — unless he neglect his duties, especially that of being occupied with the
               scriptures and the profitable deliberations with which he is occupied, by the
               excellent understanding of which paltry thoughts are driven away from him and his
               mind is not able to free itself from them, but [in this state] he gazes upon the
               whole world, because of the great delight of that occupation by which the intellect
               is completely satisfied in that extreme loneliness of the desert. So he looses <pb
                  n="171"/>consciousness of himself and forgets his nature and he becomes as one who
               is mad without any recollection of the world; especially when he thinks of God's
               greatness, the glory of His nature and His wondrous works and when he recollects how
               high his own despicable being has been elevated. To think about Him and to dare
               foster such thoughts for the sake of delight and to get drunk at all times by
               ecstatic impulses as in the life after resurrection, are things greatly promoted by
               solitude, because the intellect has the opportunity of being with itself, in the
               peace that has its origin in solitude. At the same time it will adapt its
               recollections to the aim of its course, and it will direct itself towards the glory
               of the world to be, the hope preserved for the righteous, life in spiritual emotion
                  <pb type="external" n="255"/>wholly originating in God. This is the new way of
               life, without recollection and without emotion concerning anything in this world. And
               when he is satisfied with these things his contemplation turns from them towards the
               things of this world in which he is still abiding, saying with amazement: O the depth
               of the riches both of the wisdom and knowledge and unsearchable mind of God! How
               unsearchable are His judgments and His ways past finding out<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n171-1"/>. Since He has
               prepared a different world which is so amazing, into which He shall introduce all
               rational beings and keep them without variance in life without end. What then is the
               reason why He has made this world first, which He has made large and has provided
               with a great many species, and has made a place of a multitude of affections? And He
               has set us first in this world and implanted in our nature a strong love of its own
               life; then He expels us from it, gradually, by death and prescribes to us a long
               interval in a state without sensual apperception, like stones and wood, a state
               during which He destroys our image and pours out our mettle and mixes it up with the
               earth. And He permits our building to be demolished and ruined, till it has lost all
               likeness with [its previous] composition. Then, at the time appointed by His wisdom,
               working according to His free will, He resurrects us in a different likeness which He
               knows and introduces us into that new order; and not only us, but also the holy
               angels, who do not need the use of this world <pb type="external" n="256"/>on account
               of their amazing nature. For all of them are nearly <pb n="172"/>perfect, awaiting
               the resurrection and the elevation of our fallen state, when the human race shall
               rise from the dust, and its fallen state be quickened unto new life. For on account
               of us they are hindered from entering, till once the gate of that new world will be
               opened, which they expect. For even the class of the angels sighs with us in that it
               sees us loaded with the weight of the body while it hopes and expects the revelation
               of the children of God, so that it itself may be freed from slavery that perishes, in
               the freedom of the glory of the children of God<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n172-1"/>.</p>
            <p>First he will free this whole [world] from its state so that it is reduced to
               nothing, analogous to the first state of the body. Then he will elevate himself
               intellectually beyond the beginnings of the creation of the world, when there was no
               creation nor anything, no heaven, no earth, no angels, nor any of the created things.
               Then of a sudden he will bring all things into existence, his will being sufficient
               to effect that all is before him in a state of perfection. Then he will descend in
               his mind and visit all God's creatures. And in his high and wondrous works the wisdom
               of his creating power will show itself. His power subdues all minds, the amazing and
               powerful strength of his creating force brings into existence out of nothing a
               creation with innumerable different kinds.</p>
            <p>Then he will think of how He again will destroy this, so that perishes the wondrous
               order, the ornament of kinds, the <pb type="external" n="257"/>prescribed course of
               the creatures, the times and occasions, the harmony of night and day, the useful
               seasons of the year, the embellished earth, the different kinds sprouting from it;
               the fine buildings of the cities and the beautiful palaces in them; the continual
               course of mankind, nature submitted and tormented from man's entering it until he
               leaves it.</p>
            <p>And how suddenly this wonderful order will be destroyed and how a new world will
               begin in which no recollection whatever of the first creation will occur to any man's
               mind, in which there will be a different mode of life, different deliberations and
               different thoughts. Then human nature will no longer recollect this world nor the
               former way of life in it. For the gaze of their mind will be captivated by the sight
               of that [new] order, and it will not be able to turn in its memory <pb n="173"
               />towards the races of flesh and blood; for as soon as this world is destroyed, the
               new one will begin<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n173-1"/>.</p>
            <p>O mother that suddenly has been forgotten by the sons which she has borne and
               educated and instructed — and in the twinkling of an eye they are gathered unto
               another bosom, and have become real sons of the barren one that which has never
               borne. Rejoice, o barren, thou that didst not bear, at the sons which the earth has
               borne to thee. And the mind thinks in amazement, of how a new world will take the
               place of this, and of when its beginning will be; and of how long these bodies will
               lie in that state, body and dust mingled together; and what like that mode of life
               will be; and in what likeness this nature will rise and in what way it will come to
               the second creation.</p>
            <p>By such thoughts rest will spread over the mind. And the <pb type="external" n="258"
               />apperception of its bodily state will vanish; and it will remain a long time in
               silence, wondering at the incomprehensible deeds of God. At that moment the solitary
               will kneel down and render thanks with many tears to God who is wise in His works,
               and whose deeds are incomprehensible, as are also the secrets of His exalted mind,
               concerning what He has done and what He will do. What heart of stone would not become
               unconscious under such impulses, struck with silence and stupor, and turned away from
               the emotions of senses and impulses? Blessed is he who has been deemed worthy of
               these things. Blessed is he who has thought of this, day and night. Blessed is he who
               has been occupied with these things during his whole life. To every man this thought
               is useful, but especially to him that lives in solitude. And it is becoming that
               these recollections should always be with him. These indications a man should take to
               mind and, having finished prayer, he should think of them and meditate upon them.</p>
            <p>When he is occupied with these thoughts, there will be no room for foreign
               recollections in his spirit, which could hinder him from the constant recollection of
               God. And if at first he does not perceive the profitable influence of these things,
               on account of his being distracted, he should not be dejected. When the husbandman
               casts seed on the earth, it is not <pb n="174"/>possible that he should see the oars
               at the same time. Dejection and despondency are connected with sowing. It is sweet to
               the peasant to eat of his bread; but his sweat is still <choice><sic>sweater</sic><corr>sweeter</corr></choice>.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="259"/>This thought, in solitude, will pour endless delight
               into the heart and will quickly draw the mind towards unspeakable ecstasy. Blessed is
               he to whom this fountain has been opened and who drinks from it at all hours of the
               day and the night.</p>
            <p>The disciple. What is the acme of all the labours of asceticism, which a man, when he
               has reached it, recognises as the summit of his course?</p>
            <p>The teacher. When he is deemed worthy of constant prayer. When he has reached this,
               he has touched the end of all virtues and forthwith he has a spiritual
               dwelling-place. If a man has not received in truth the gift of the Comforter, it is
               not possible for him to accomplish constant prayer in quiet. When the spirit takes
               its dwelling-place in a man he does not cease to pray, because the spirit will
               constantly pray in him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n174-1"/>. Then, neither when he sleeps, nor when he is awake,
               will prayer be cut off from his soul; but when he eats and when he drinks, when he
               lies down or when he does any work, even when he is immersed in sleep, the perfumes
               of prayer will breathe in his soul spontaneously. And henceforth he will not possess
               prayer at limited times, but always; and when he has outward rest, even then prayer
               is ministered unto him secretly. For the silence of the serene is prayer, says a man
               clad with Christ. For their deliberations are divine impulses. The motions of the
               pure mind are quiet voices with which they secretly chant psalms to the Invisible
               One.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="260"/>The disciple. What is spiritual prayer, and how are we
               made worthy of it?</p>
            <p>The teacher. It is the psychic impulses which partake of the influence of the Holy
               Spirit, on account of veracious purity. One man in ten thousand is found worthy of
               this. It is a symbol of the future way of existence, for nature is elevated and
               exempt from all the impulses from the recollection of things in this world. It does
               not pray, but the soul perceives the spiritual things of the world beyond (which is
               something greater than the mind of man); the understanding of these is kindled by
               spiritual force. — It is inner sight, and <pb n="175"/>not the impulse and the
               beseeching of prayer. It has its starting point in prayer. Because such men have
               reached the summit of purity and because at all times their inner emotions are
               stirring in prayer — as I have said before — the Spirit, whenever it looks at them,
               will find them in prayer; and from there it will conduct them by contemplation, which
               is interpreted spiritual sight. They do not want prolonged prayer nor the defined
               order of frequent service.</p>
            <p>For the recollection of God alone will be sufficient for them, and at once they will
               be governed by love, as if captives. But because of this state they are not
               absolutely negligent, but attribute honour to prayer by standing on their feet at
               fixed times; but they do not practise continual prayer.</p>
            <p>For we see that the holy <persName>Antonius</persName>, when standing on his feet <pb type="external"
                  n="261"/>in the prayer of the ninth hour, perceived that his mind was taken up.
               And another saint found himself in ecstasy for four days, while he stood in prayer
               with outspread hands. And, on examination, it will be seen in the stories of many
               others that they were found in the well known attitude of prayer, when granted this
               gift. A man is deemed worthy of this, when he puts off outward and inward sin, by
               observing the commandments of our Lord, which are anterior to this state. If one will
               practise these in his own degree, it is inevitably necessary for him to forsake all
               human things. This means: he shall put off the body and be outside it, so to speak;
               not its nature, but the use of it. There is nobody who has practised these things in
               the sense of the lawgiver, and with whom sin has persevered to dwell.</p>
            <p>Therefore our Lord has promised in the Gospel, that He shall make His dwelling-place
               the man who observes these things.</p>
            <p>The disciple. And what is the perfection of all spiritual fruits?</p>
            <p>The teacher. This is when man is deemed worthy of the complete love of God.</p>
            <p>The disciple. And how can he that has reached this point, acquire certainty?</p>
            <p>The teacher. Every time when the thought of God is stirred in his spirit, the heart
               will become hot with love at once, the eyes will shed multitudinous tears; for love
               is accustomed to shed tears at the recollection of the beloved. He <pb n="176"/>that
               is in this state will never be found destitute of tears, <pb type="external" n="262"
               />because he is never without abundant recollection of God, so that even during sleep
               he speaks with Him. Love is accustomed to practise these things and this is the
               accomplishment of man in this life.</p>
            <p>The disciple. He that after many labours and fatigues and victories fought and won,
               is assailed by the thought of haughtiness that is based upon the beauty of his
               excellence, when he recalls the many labours he has borne — how can he restrain his
               thoughts and regain watchfulness so as not to give way?</p>
            <p>The teacher. When he knows that he falls from God as a withered leaf falls from the
               tree, then he will also know his own strength and recognise whether he has acquired
               these virtues by his strength and whether he could have withstood all the struggles
               face-to-face if God had withdrawn from him His help and had left him alone in his
               strife with <persName>Satan</persName> without being accompanied by that force that usually accompanies
               the victorious combatants in their struggles. For here their strength, or better
               their weakness, comes to light. So that it is God's care for man which at all times
               guards and strengthens him and through which he overcomes all classes of men, be it
               in the struggle of chastity, or in the sufferings of martyrdom or in the other
               hardships while he suffers for the sake of divine things.</p>
            <p>This is well known and no doubt concerning it is possible. For how else could nature
               vanquish this mighty force of never resting allurements which have their seat in
               man's members <pb type="external" n="263"/>and torment him and yet he does withstand
               them? How is it that others which love and long after the same purity, are not able
               to reach it, though they strive after it, nay daily they are cast back, tormented and
               sad and weeping over themselves, whereas thou bearest easily the difficulties of
               nature, which are so hard, and yet thou art not oppressed by them? Or how were it
               possible that another should endure in his sensitive flesh the cutting iron and the
               combs in all his members without being vanquished by suffering under all kinds of
               tortures, whereas else he could not endure a little thorn inserted under his nail?
               But these totally diverse tortures he bears without suffering in the natural way. How
               should this be possible unless some force, apart from that of nature, were sent to
               him and <pb n="177"/>from another direction and unless this force restrained and
               mitigated the force of the tortures?</p>
            <p>There is nothing that withholds us from mentioning here a story that is really
               amazing to one who hears it. Because we have pointed to God's care for man which
               makes him victorious in all battles for the sake of excellence, it would not be
               becoming to omit this story. Socrates, in his work on the history of the church, when
               mentioning the Roman emperors, relates in a succinct way the evil which the members
               of the church had to suffer under <persName>Julianus</persName>; then passing on to <pb type="external"
                  n="264"/>particulars he tells a story of that which happened in the city of
               <placeName>Antioch</placeName>.</p>
            <p>A certain adolescent, <persName>Theodore</persName> by name, was brought by the heathens before
               <persName>Sallustius</persName>, to whom the jurisdiction in these matters had been entrusted. He gave him
               up to suffering and torture, commanding that his whole body should be combed. Then he
               set him free from torture, thinking that he was dead. But God was the saviour of that
               blessed man, who lived for a long time after his testimony. For <persName>Rufinus</persName>, who has
               written about ecclesiastical things in Greek, says that a long time after he had
               conversation with this blessed <persName>Theodore</persName>. He asked him whether he had felt the pain
               keenly when being tortured. The latter answered that he had been conscious of pain to
               a very trifling extent only. For a young man had been standing near him, wiping off
               the sweat of the struggle and strengthening his soul and making the time of the
               struggle of the tortures a delight to him. O, for God's compassion, how near is His
               bounty to those who begin the warfare for His sake in order to bear sufferings for
               Him gladly. Do not injure God's bounty to thee, o man.</p>
            <p>If it is manifest, that thou art not the victor but that thou art as an instrument
               and that the Lord wins the victory for thee whereas thou obtainest the name of victor
               as a present, what then hinders thee from beseeching at all times the same power,
               that thou mayest always obtain the same victory as a <pb type="external" n="265"
               />witness? Hast thou not heard, o man, from of old and from the beginnings of time,
               how many champions have fallen from the height of their victories because they have
               injured grace?</p>
            <p>On the same subject. The gifts of God unto the human race being many and various,
               there is also a difference in their smallness or greatness in relation to those who
               receive them.</p>
            <pb n="178"/>
            <p>Though all of them are wonderful and glorious, one is more than the other in glory
               and honour. One degree is higher than the previous one, according to the word of
               scripture.</p>
            <p>And further, that a man be elected to practise good works and a steady behaviour,
               this is one of the principal gifts of Christ. But many forget this grace, namely
               those whom God has distinguished above others so that they belong to the receivers of
               His gifts, even to the degree that they are elected to the service of the Lord; then,
               in contrast to the gratitude which was always on their lips, they turn aside to
               presumption and become haughty in mind. And though they have been made worthy to
               serve God with pure behaviour and spiritual labours, yet they do not deem themselves
               receivers of grace but as those who deserve this through God, forgetting that they
               have been elected from the rest of mankind unto familiarity with Him and knowledge of
               His mysteries. Nor do they tremble in their whole soul when they think of how their
               comrades, who fostered the same thoughts, were suddenly <pb type="external" n="266"
               />deprived of that strength with which they had been entrusted, and of how in the
               twinkling of an eye they lost the great honour they had possessed and declined
               quickly unto lasciviousness and turned towards the base behaviour of the irrational
               animals. And because they know not the strength of their soul, nor perpetually
               recollect Him that made them worthy of the great boon of serving Him and of abiding
               in the honour of His kingdom and that made them comrades of the spiritual beings and
               brought them near unto the behaviour of the angels, He rejects them from their
               service. Thus He shows to them by the sudden variations of their behaviour, that it
               was not by their own [strength] that they adhered to a steady behaviour under all the
               assaults of nature and the demons and the other impediments, but that this strength
               was a gift from Him.</p>
            <p>What other men cannot even endure to listen to, on account of its difficulty, this
               they have endured a long time without being vanquished, because the strength that
               accompanied them was able to help them under all circumstances and to guard them at
               all times. Accordingly, since they have forgotten this, the word has been fulfilled
               in them. Namely as they have not willed concerning themselves that they should know
               God, viz. their Lord who has made the service of the spiritual beings descend to
               earth, God has delivered them up to vain <pb n="179"/>knowledge and so they have
               received in person the retribution which their forgetfulness had deserved.</p>
            <p>The disciple. Is it possible that a man should so to speak daringly leave the
               dwellingplaces of men suddenly and <pb type="external" n="267"/>go naked into the
               uninhabited desert and the terrible wilderness in beautiful zeal and that he should
               die there from hunger or from the absence of shelter or the like?</p>
            <p>The teacher. He that has prepared a dwellingplace for the beasts before He created
               them and who provides their wants, will not neglect those who fear them, especially
               when they follow Him simply, without forethought. He whose will accords with God in
               all things will never, for fear of bodily evils and dangers, consent to adhere to a
               filthy behaviour and to endure a life of humiliation because he fears troubles. But
               he will count it an exquisite and delicious thing to become estranged to the whole
               world in purity of behaviour, and to lead a life of deprivation among hills and
               mountains and to wander in the haunts of beasts and not to lead a life of filth, in
               bodily comfort, delivering up his soul so that it be for ever destitute of a pious
               and pure behaviour unto God, to whom belongeth the glory and the honour and who
               preserves us in His goodness and sanctifies us by His spirit to the honour of His
               name, that we may praise Him worthily all the days of our life, Amen.</p>
            <p>For one of the saints says<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n179-1"/>: The body becomes a comrade of sin; for it is
               afraid of troubles, thinking it may receive an injury and have to give up its life.
               For the spirit of God oppresses the body so that it dies; it is well known that it
               cannot vanquish sin unless it die. Who desires that our Lord should dwell in him,
               will oppress his body and minister unto his Lord those spiritual fruits which the
               apostle describes; and he will guard his soul against the works of the flesh which
                  <pb type="external" n="268"/><persName>Paul</persName> describes. For the body that is mingled with sin
               takes pleasure in the works of the flesh. And the spirit of God takes pleasure in its
               own fruits. When the body is weak by fasting and mortification, the soul is
               spiritually strong through prayer. When the body is vehemently oppressed by solitude
               and penury and its life is near its term, it will beseech thee: Leave me a while to
               behave with moderation. Now I give directions because</p>
            <pb n="180"/>
            <p>I know by experience that evils are of this nature. And when thou releasest the body
               somewhat from oppression, giving it some comfort by sparing it so that it can take
               breath again, then it will whisper to thee quietly again and again: Let us leave even
               the wilderness. For its allurements are very strong; [it says]: from now onward we
               shall be able to behave well, even in the neighbourhood of the inhabited world. For
               we have been put to the test in many things and we shall be able to continue this
               [behaviour] even there. Put me to the test and if I do not comply with thy will, we
               can begin anew for the desert lies before us. — But do not believe [the body] even if
               it beseeches and promises greatly, for it will not keep its promises. When thou hast
               granted it some of its wishes, it will drive thee on towards greater concessions from
               which thou canst not retract thy steps. When thou art dejected on account of thy
               being filled with troubles, say to thyself: Doest thou desire this filth and this
               sordid life? And if the body says to thee: It is a great sin that thou killest
               thyself, — say to it: I kill myself because I cannot live purely. I will die now and
               not further see my soul's essential die away from God. It is <pb type="external"
                  n="269"/>better for me to die now for the sake of purity than to live a shameful
               life in the world<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n180-1"/>. This death I willingly choose on account of my sins. I
               kill myself because I have sinned before God and will not further rouse His anger.
               What to me is life afar from God? I will bear these evils and through them I will not
               be a stranger to heavenly hope. Why have I been created in the world, if I simply
               enter and leave it? And what should God profit by my life in the world, if I lived
               badly in it? On the contrary, I would but rouse His anger.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n156-1">Cf. Ps. 90,10</note>
            <note xml:id="n156-2">Cf. Ps. 84,11</note>
            <note xml:id="n157-1">Matthew 16,24</note>
            <note xml:id="n157-2">Matthew 10,39</note>
            <note xml:id="n163-1"> One of the London Mss. has: Basil</note>
            <note xml:id="n165-1">Coloss. 3,1</note>
            <note xml:id="n165-2">2 Cor. 4,6</note>
            <note xml:id="n166-1">Ez. 36,26</note>
            <note xml:id="n167-1">See Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n168-1">Cf. Philippians 2,3</note>
            <note xml:id="n170-1">Matthew 5,4</note>
            <note xml:id="n171-1">Romans 11,33</note>
            <note xml:id="n172-1">Cf. Rom. 8,21. On the following passage cf. the
               Introduction.</note>
            <note xml:id="n173-1">The two sentences which follow could be an interpolation; the
               sentence "And the mind thinks" etc. is the direct continuation of the present
               one.</note>
            <note xml:id="n174-1">This is apparently the meaning of the sentence, which in the
               original is not quite clear.</note>
            <note xml:id="n179-1">Introduction p. 32</note>
            <note xml:id="n180-1">See p. 31, 97</note>

         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
