<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 27</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 27, pp. 132-136.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="27">
            <head>XXVII</head>
            <head><pb type="external" n="195"/>In how many different ways the sight of incorporeal
               beings is received by human nature</head>
            <p>All simple and subtle kinds of rational bodies can be attained to by the apperception
               of human nature in three ways: by personal density [which is a] non-essential way; by
               personal subtlety [which is a] non-essential way; by true contemplation which is
               essential sight.</p>
            <p>The first way is dominated by the senses; the other by simple psychic sight; the
               third by the natural force of the spirit. Further one is dominated by will and
               reason; one by will and psychic light and all that strengthens the latter.</p>
            <p>Will is in the first place cause; and these are the children of freedom, even if at
               the time of use freedom and will are silent, so long as influence is active and
               potent. And one only is dominated by the demonstrating [power], even without the will
               of the recipients and essential knowledge, even as the senses are the recipients of
               all accidents without the will.</p>
            <p>These three ways are ministered by holy forces which mingle themselves with us for
               the sake of our instruction and in order that we may find life. Those who are impure
               have power to minister two of them, which they may use when they come <pb
                  type="external" n="196"/>near unto us, for perdition, not for profit. To the third
               kind they do not approach with the purpose of using it, so as to acquire power over
               us to lead us astray.</p>
            <p>For it is not possible for the children of darkness to approach light; the demons do
               not possess the power to set into motion the natural insights of the mind. The holy
               angels, however, possess this faculty of setting into motion and of <pb n="133"
               />illuminating. The demons, however, possess the false insights, the children of
               darkness, as their power and government. From the illuminated the recipient takes
               light, from the dark, darkness. And what is the reason that this was given to those,
               and not to these? The insight which every one of these teachers shows and teaches, is
               first seen by him in his own person, and learnt and tasted; then he is able to
               transmit to us the truth of things on account of their true knowledge concerning
               them, which they have found first by the swift attaining power of the light and pure
               mind. The demons also possess swiftness, but no illumination. Swiftness is different
               from illumination. The former without the latter leads its possessors to destruction
               and insipidity; the latter teaches truth, the former sham truth; for light shows the
               veracity of things entirely and it becomes greater or less in accordance with
               behaviour.</p>
            <p>From their knowledge the holy angels pour out into us, through the emotions caused by
               things, that which they taste <pb type="external" n="197"/>and acquire first and thus
               transmit to us. And these secondary teachers also set into motion in us, in
               correspondence with their knowledge, emotions caused by things. In the domain where
               they have no freedom, it is necessary [for them] to quicken in us right deliberations
               concerning these things. As I have said, therefore, this may be certain to thee, that
               even if we were able to receive it, they would not be able to teach us true
               contemplation, though they should be acquainted with it from of old. Every member of
               one party or the other — holy angels or those of the opposite group — teaches and
               incites us, the disciples, to behave according to his own behaviour.</p>
            <p>To me this is true: that the mind of itself, even without the mediation of the holy
               angels, tends towards the good, even without instruction, but that it is unable to
               receive the knowledge of evil things without the mediation of the demons or the
               senses, [and is unable] to tend towards them of its own accord. In our nature good is
               implanted, evil not. And all that is foreign and is taught from without, needs an
               intermediary. What is planted within, however, unfolds itself naturally, even without
               instruction, even if dimly. But even though our nature tends of its own towards the
               good, it is unable, without the tutorship of the holy angels, to increase this and to
               be illuminated by it. We have them as teachers, as they have each <pb type="external"
                  n="198"/>other, namely those who are lower [have for their teachers] <pb n="134"
                  /><pb type="external" n="198"/>those who are more instructed and enlightened than
               themselves. So they have each other [for teachers] up to the one who, has as a
               teacher the holy Trinity. And even he [does not receive instruction] of his own, but
               he has as a teacher the mediator <persName>Jesus</persName>, through whom he receives [instruction] and
               transmits it to those who are on the same plan and lower.</p>
            <p>I think also this. As we naturally do not at all possess the force to be moved by
               divine contemplation, and we share in this deficiency with all heavenly beings, it is
               only by grace, without exercise or computation [on our part], that we are moved by
               something which naturally is foreign to the human and angelic mind. For contemplation
               concerning the godhead is not to be compared with other kinds of contemplation; for
               we possess contemplation as to their natures through our participation in the twofold
               nature that is theirs, because of that which is in us and also in them; but we do not
               participate in the nature of the Essence, nor do we possess contemplation concerning
               Him. As the faculty of being set into motion by this contemplation does not naturally
               belong to any of the rational beings of the first and middle class, it must be a gift
               of grace in all heavenly and earthly minds[i].</p>
            <p>It is not like other faculties caused by nature, however illuminated and purified.
               But I think — and this is true — that the mind of us, children of man, is to be
               conducted [only] by revelations and insights so far as to reach this essential
               contemplation which is the same as true revelation; without their <pb type="external"
                  n="199"/>mediation, however, our mind could not be conducted. And our mind does
               not possess a <choice><sic>strengh</sic><corr>strength</corr></choice> like that of those high and exalted beings who
               receive all revelations and contemplation from the Essence, without an intermediary.
               But even they [receive these revelations] through an image of the Essence, not from
               the Essence itself. So that our mind also is in the same degree as the other classes,
               not able to receive revelations and contemplation of their own, without an
               intermediary, but only from <persName>Jesus</persName> who sways the sceptre of the Kingdom. The other
               classes, viz. other primary classes receive [revelations] by handing them down one to
               the other, concerning all matters of government and the understanding thereof (not
               concerning the Essence), from the first to the second and so on till the mystery has
               gone through all the classes.</p>
            <p>But many are the mysteries which remain in that one primary <pb n="135"/>class
               without spreading through the other classes, because, apart from that one, they are
               not able to receive such a great mystery. There are other mysteries again which
               proceed from the primary class and are revealed only to the second, but are preserved
               there in silence; the other classes do not perceive them. Others again are revealed
               to the third and fourth classes. There are also [differences of] superiority and
               inferiority of revelation in the case of individual angels. Some of them <pb
                  type="external" n="200"/>are rich in revelations and mysteries of a high order are
               revealed unto them, and they receive plentiful light. Some are lower and their
               impulses are too weak for these mysteries. And thus among the spiritual classes there
               is excellency and deficiency, superiority and inferiority concerning the receiving of
               revelations. Apart from that upper class which is the primary of all classes, the
               remainder without exception receive contemplation and hints concerning the entire
               divine government from their fellows. And if this is the case with them, how much
               less are we able, without them and without an intermediary, to receive such
               mysteries. But as often as an apperception falls in the minds of the saints, this
               revelation of whatsoever mystery it be, comes from these [heavenly beings]. When it
               is allowed by God, revelation is handed down by each higher class to that which is
               lower, unto the lowest; in the same way, when it is allowed by the godhead, the
               mystery is handed down by those who are worthy of it unto human beings.</p>
            <p>By their intermediary, at any rate, the saints become receivers of the light of
               contemplation, by which they behold the praised Essence[j], which is a mystery which
               they do not learn from each other. Those [higher beings] are administering spirits,
               which are sent to those who are to inherit life through the apperception of such
               insights of the truths as are peculiar to them.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="201"/>In the world to be, however, this kind of transmission
               will be annihilated. For then one will not receive the revelation of God's glory for
               the delight of his soul, from his comrade, but it will be given to every one himself
               in so far as is in accordance with the measure of his excellency, and as he is deemed
               worthy of by the Lord of the Universe; but he will not receive the gift through his
               comrade, as is the case in this world. For there are none who learn and none who
               teach and none who desire to receive from their comrades what fails themselves. For
               one giver reveals himself there without intermediary unto <pb n="136"/>all receivers.
               And those who receive all spiritual delight receive from Him. So that they do not
               perceive Him by means of single insights but by [direct] revelation of Himself,
               without the outward intermediary of impulses. There is abrogated the degree of the
               learner and the teacher and every one's swift love is fixed on one.</p>
            <p>Also I say that even those who are scourged in Hell are tormented with the scourgings
               of love. Scourgings for love's sake, namely of those who perceive that they have
               sinned against love, are more hard and bitter than tortures through fear. The
               suffering which takes hold of the heart through the sinning against love is more
               acute than any other torture. It is evil for a man to think that the sinners in Hell
               are destitute of love for the Creator. For love is a child of true knowledge such as
               is professed to be given to all people. Love works with its force in a double way. It
               tortures those who have <pb type="external" n="202"/>sinned, as happens also in the
               world between friends. And it gives delight to those who have kept its decrees. Thus
               it is also in Hell. I say that the hard tortures are grief for love. The inhabitants
               of heaven, however, make drunk their soul with the delight of love[k].</p>
            <p>Some one was asked when one could believe that he had been deemed worthy of
               forgiveness of sins. He answered: when he perceives that he inwardly hates them with
               a complete hate, and that his mode of life is the contrary of what it previously was.
               He who is in such a state, will trust that his sins have been forgiven by God, on
               account of the witness borne by the conscience of his soul, according to the word of
               the Apostle. The heart which does not blame is a witness concerning itself.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
