<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 58</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 58, pp. 273-277.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="58">
            <pb n="273"/>
            <head>LVIII</head>
            <head><pb type="external" n="407"/>On those who live in the neighbourhood of God and pass
               all their days in a life of knowledge</head>
            <p>Blessed is he that leads a watchful life in this world. A certain Father had written
               on all the walls of his cell various things, and all kinds of thoughts, and admirable
               words on every context. He was asked: What are these, o Father? He answered: These
               are deliberations of justice that occur to me through the angel that is with me and
               through the right impulses of nature. I write them down when I am in these
               apartments, in order that I may be occupied with them in the time of darkness, and
               that they may save me from error. So a man ought to do all his days.</p>
            <p>A certain Father was called happy by his own thoughts which praised him thus: In
               stead of the world that passes, thou hast been deemed worthy of the indestructible
               hope. The Father said to them: Why do ye call me happy, while I am still alive? I do
               not know what will happen to me till my death. I am still on the way; happiness is
               not certain before I have reached my home.</p>
            <p>Indeed, this is a just deliberation. It is becoming that we should appoint our day of
               death as the term of victory. Before death, he that triumphs is no real victor. For
               his enemies are living and the way is before him, and he does not know <pb
                  type="external" n="408"/>where he may be entangled; for his way is not safe, and
               he has not yet reached the time of trust. Thus he that is entangled in evil things
               has not to be dejected; for it is possible for him to gain life, as he is still
               alive. There is hope for him as well as for the one that behaves well. Why doest thou
               rebuke the sinner, o man? The labours of thine own merchandise have not yet entered
               the harbour; the hope of him over whom thou art extolling thyself, has not been cut
               off by God. It is possible that within a short time he will surpass thee in
               excellence and come nearer to God than thou art. For death has not yet come and
               concluded his affair, nor thine. Many vicissitudes happen to a man during <pb n="274"
               />his life. But it is God who looks to the end and not to the things in the middle.
               There have been many righteous who fell from their righteousness, and sinners have
               come up and taken their place. Therefore the righteous should not extol himself, he
               is still alive; nor shall the sinner be dejected, for God is near to him if he seeks
               Him, and prepared to receive him when he changes his behaviour and turns towards Him.
               If thou hast wrought righteousness without perceiving the taste of its profit, then
               be not amazed.</p>
            <p>Until a man becomes humble, he does not receive the wages of his service.
               Remuneration is not given for service, but for humbleness. He that wrongs the latter,
               looses the former.</p>
            <p>He who has taken upon him the service of excellence is <pb type="external" n="409"
               />inferior to him that has first taken upon him the excellence of service. Excellence
               is the mother of afflictions; from afflictions humbleness is born. The gift is given
               for humbleness. Consequently remuneration does not belong to excellence, nor to pains
               for its sake, but to humbleness which is born from it. Now if humbleness fails, the
               other ones are vain. The service of excellence is the observance of the commandments
               of our Lord. The excellence of service is steadiness of mind, which is established by
               humbleness and watchfulness. Where the power [necessary] for the performance of the
               former ones fails, the latter is received instead of them. So Christ does not seek
               the service of the commandments, but the steadiness of the soul, for the sake of
               which He also has laid commandments upon rational beings. The body works with the
               right and with the left part, equally. But the mind, as is becoming, is either
               justified or condemned.</p>
            <p>Some serve life by left-hand things, through wisdom from God; and some acquire sin
               under the appearance of acquiring divine things. Shortcomings in sundry things in
               which those who are watchful are entangled, are permitted by God in order to guard
               their righteousness, that their trespasses and failures may become to them a cause of
               humbleness.</p>
            <p>Humbleness protects many men for their service, not only withholding them from
               haughtiness, but by the recollection their [trespasses] they become humble and
               receive higher wages.</p>
            <p>Without blows a gift cannot be kept. A gift without <pb type="external" n="410"
               />temptations is found to cause the destruction of those who have received it.</p>
            <pb n="275"/>
            <p>If thou hast served well before God, and He has given thee a gift for thy
               steadfastness regarding Him, in order to spur thee on the more and to give thee joy
               in thy service, then let Him give thee knowledge so as to know how it is necessary to
               humble thyself; otherwise he would appoint a prosecutor or take it again from thee,
               lest there should be a chance for its being lost. It is not given to every one to
               guard riches without damage.</p>
            <p>The soul that takes upon itself the trouble of excellence and lives in the veracious
               fear of God cannot be without daily afflictions. Virtues and afflictions are
               interwoven.</p>
            <p>He who abandons troubles also abandons excellence entirely. Who clings to excellency,
               clings to afflictions. If thou desirest excellence, thou givest thyself over to all
               afflictions. Excellence is the mother of afflictions; afflictions are the mother of
               humbleness. For God does not desire that the soul should be without care. And he that
               desires this, his mind is found to be without God's will. By care I do not mean care
               concerning bodily things, but concerning the oppression that persecutes virtues. For
               before we reach true knowledge, which is the revelation of hidden things, we have to
               come near to humbleness through temptations. He that is found to be without
               afflictions in his excellence, for him a door unto haughtiness is opened. How can he
               who desires this [excellence] be without affliction in his mind? It is not possible
               that the mind remain <pb type="external" n="411"/>in humbleness if there is no reason
               for blows. And it is not possible that without humbleness it should remain in
               perpetual supplication unto God, in serenity.</p>
            <p>First man is removed from the thought of his duty in his mind, then the spirit of
               haughtiness approaches him. At first the angel of care suffers this, but afterwards
               it withdraws itself from him. As long as the angel is near him, he provides him
               solely with thoughts of righteousness. But when he has wronged the angel and it has
               withdrawn itself from him, then a foreign power approaches him, and no single just
               thought will furthermore be in him. Haughtiness comes before ruin, says the
               sage<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n275-1"/>; so humbleness before a gift. By the quantity of haughtiness which is
               found in the soul, is judged the scale of ruin which is on the point of being sent to
               it by God.</p>
            <pb n="276"/>
            <p>For none of the sins does God withdraw from man, leaving him wholly because He
               dislikes him, until He finds the mind seized with haughtiness or blasphemy. And the
               former [of these two] becomes the cause of the latter.</p>
            <p>Those who in their mind leave the way of humbleness and so become devoid of divine
               help, either fall into the impurity of lasciviousness, or into blasphemy, or into
               mental ruin.</p>
            <p>Those who extol themselves on account of excellent behaviour, usually fall into evil
               lasciviousness; those who extol themselves on account of knowledge and mental
               discipline, into blasphemy or trouble of mind.</p>
            <p>Haughtiness is not the state in which such deliberations <pb type="external" n="412"
               />pass through the mind, nor when the mind is sometimes overpowered by them, but when
               the mind clings to them. It is manifest that even for such a one there is repentance.
               But when he loves haughtiness, he does not know how <choice><sic>the</sic><corr>to</corr></choice> repent. If he does
               repent, he does not cling to haughtiness. Not that the evil man sins or commits a
               fault against God, but that he clings to his evil [is the great thing]. For the
               former denotes the weakness of nature, the latter audaciousness of the will.</p>
            <p>Also by praises on the part of his fellowmen is a man's mind struck with madness,
               when he desires to perform among them deeds which are above his measure, in order
               that the glory of his greatness may increase, and men may perceive that he is very
               near to God. Many have excelled in behaviour and were rich in gifts from God and have
               been honoured with the gift of [performing] signs. But afterwards they became changed
               and received a blow from God, the same men that were so honoured before. The cause of
               this was that they were not able to bear the many gifts which they had received and
               were drawn towards haughtiness and were rejected by God as dross and became foreign
               to the high rank in which they were. And many who were quiet and firm in mind, whose
               words were weighed, whose behaviour was chaste, whose knowledge was envied, have
               become an object of fear for those who know them and a lamentable aspect for those
               who see them.</p>
            <p>With loud weeping raise thy voice unto God and beg for <pb type="external" n="413"
               />humbleness. Fill thy mouth with thy tears and stray ashes on thy head. Do not rise
               from the earth nor lift up thy head <pb n="277"/>from the ground, before God has
               shown thee mercy and has made thee to pass away from this life, saved; or till He has
               compassion upon thee and gives thee humbleness. And do not desist from mourning
               before perceiving that thou hast received it, lest thou shouldst be found suddenly as
               one of these<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n277-1"/>.</p>
            <p>And even when thou hast received [humbleness], do not lift up thy eyes, nor look
               towards the sky, nor satisfy thy eyes with the aspect of men nor let thy heart have
               rest from fear and prayer. Perhaps thou wilt be saved from the evils which are
               prepared by the demons, in this discipline full of darkness, narrow, with many
               stumbling-blocks, incomprehensible to human nature.</p>
            <p>Believe me, my brother and consider my words as true: thou art not able to understand
               all the power of the demons, and thy knowledge is not sufficient to remain standing
               before their artifices. Let now therefore be poured out within thee a stream of
               light, in which the love of Christ is found and by which thou art conducted within
               the wall of divine mercy, to the honour of the humbleness which thou hast found.</p>
            <p>When thou enterest into the darkness of temptations where the light withdraws itself
               and thou art given over to be tempted in that thick darkness of the soul into which
               those enter who are abandoned by God and given over to the demons, then thou wilt
               know that thou findest thyself face<pb type="external" n="414"/>to-face with them as
               a child that does not know where to go. All thy knowledge will be <choice><sic>confuse</sic><corr>confused</corr></choice>
               as a little child. Thy mind which was firm in God, thy veracious knowledge, and thy
               sound spirit will be in the midst of the ocean of doubts.</p>
            <p>By one thing canst thou vanquish them: by humbleness alone. As soon as thou takest
               hold of this, their whole power vanishes. Do not take it for [a sign] of the health
               of thy soul when thou goest thy course in serenity through thy joy in God, but when
               thy being bound up with [earthly] things does not turn thy mind away from the love of
               God or thy neighbour, nor thy connection with several persons from thinking of our
               Lord, to whom be the glory. May He keep us near to Him and in intercourse with Him.
               Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n275-1">Proverbs 16,19</note>
            <note xml:id="n277-1">who have been described in the above passage</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
