<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 61</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 61, pp. 286-287.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="61">
            <pb n="286"/>
            <head>LXI</head>
            <p>For which causes God admits temptations to His friends</p>
            <p>By the love which the saints show unto God in return for what they bear for the sake
               of His name in that they undergo trials without leaving the excellency which God
               loves, their heart acquires freedom to look towards Him without a veil and to ask
               from Him with confidence.</p>
            <p>Great is the power of prayer in freedom of speech. Therefore He allows that His
               saints are tried by all afflictions, on the way towards Him, in order that they may
               acquire freedom of speech and may experience His help and His care for them in that
               He is found to be their saviour in danger; and in order that His friends may acquire
               wisdom through temptations so that they are not dull and destitute of training. So
               through temptation they acquire knowledge concerning everything, and are not laughed
               at lightly by the demons.</p>
            <p>For if He would train them by good things only they would lack training in other
               things and they would be as blind men in trials. And if someone should say: He guides
               them without training and without selfknowledge [the conclusion would be] that He
               wished them to be like oxen and asses who possess <pb type="external" n="428"/>no
               freedom whatever. There is even no taste in the good, when a man has not first been
               tried by temptations of evil and afterwards finds it and when he does not use it as
               his own, in knowledge and freedom. How sweet that knowledge is which has been
               acquired through training and the experience of labours, and how much strength it
               imparts to him that has found it after many personal experiences, is known to those
               who are acquainted with the help afforded by it.</p>
            <p>They learn the weakness of nature and the help afforded by divine power when He first
               withdraws power from them while they are in temptations. Then they perceive the
               weakness of nature and the strength of temptations and the wickedness of the Fiend,
               [perceiving] of which nature their Fiend is, with which nature they are clad, and how
               they are guarded by divine power; and how, though they run and are uplifted, <pb
                  n="287"/>when the divine power withdraws itself from them, they become weak before
               all passions.</p>
            <p>Through all this they acquire humbleness, and press close to God, expecting His help
               and persevering in prayer. How could they have acquired all this, if they had not
               experienced myriads of evils, without God's caring for their being surrounded by
               them? 'And lest I should be exalted through the abundance of revelations, there was
               given me a thorn in the flesh, the messenger of Satan'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n287-1"/>.</p>
            <p>Man acquires also a confirmed faith by temptations, through experiencing divine help,
               when it is granted several times. And furthermore he is without fear and acquires
               courage by temptation, on account of the training he acquires.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="429"/>Temptation is useful to every man. The virtuous are
               tempted in order that their riches may increase; the lax, in order that they may be
               preserved from injuries; the sleepy, in order that they may be armed with alertness;
               those that are afar off that they may come nearer to God; the housemates, that they
               may approach with freedom of speech.</p>
            <p>A son that is not trained, cannot profit by the riches that are given to him from his
               father's house. Therefore God tempts and vexes first, then He shows His gift. Glory
               to that Lord who by strong drugs brings us the delight of health. There is no one, to
               whom the time of exercise is not hard; and there is no one, to whom the time during
               which he is obliged to drink the potion of temptations, is not bitter. But without
               this, a sound constitution cannot be obtained. Even to endure is not of our own. How
               should a clay vessel endure the vehemence of the waters, if the divine fire had not
               hardened it? If we <choice><sic>daign</sic><corr>deign</corr></choice> to ask in humbleness fervently and perseveringly,
               we shall receive everything.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n287-1">2 Cor. 12,7</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
