<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 10</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 10, pp. 78-80</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="10">
            <pb n="78"/>
            <head>X</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="115"/>On the words of the Scriptures being spoken as it were
               to patients in moderation lest they should wholly abandon the living God. But this
               should not be taken by us as a reason for greater freedom regarding sin</p>
            <p>The encouragement which our Fathers give us in their writings and the help towards
               repentance which is in the writings of the Prophets and the Apostles, should not be
               taken by us as a reason to disregard the threats of the divine acts of judgment, nor
               the punishment which God has decreed firmly against the <choice><sic>trangression</sic><corr>transgression</corr></choice>
               of the borders which should not be passed, through the mouth of all His saints and by
               means of all kinds of laws, in order to eradicate sins. As if the hope of repentance
               could be reason for us to strip from ourselves the feeling of fear in order to sin
               more freely and without dread. These [threats] are confirmed by the seals of the word
               of God, in all the scriptures of our salvation, and by the [divine] decrees fixed
               against them, [threatening] all kinds of terror. Some of these He has partly revealed
               to the many or to the few [people] by the punishments He brought upon them in order
               to show that He hated sin. Or why then were drowned in the Deluge the generations of
               the days of Noah? Was it not on account of the vileness of lasciviousness, because
               they had violated the <pb type="external" n="116"/>beauty of the daughters of Kain?
               In that time there was no love of money nor adoration of idols, nor sorcery, nor wars
               waged [by men] against one another.</p>
            <p>Or again, why were five towns of the Sodomites for ever burnt? Was it not because
               they had given way to lust of the flesh, which had taken possession of them according
               to its good pleasure, consisting in all kinds of impurity? Was it not because of the
               fornication of one man that in Israel, the firstborn of God, there fell twenty-five
               thousand by the plague in an instant? Why then was Simson rejected by God, Simson,
               the man of strength, the Naziraean from the womb, the sanctified to God, whose birth
               was annunciated by an angel like that of John the son of Zecharia, through whose hand
               [God] wrought marvels and signs, and who by the supernatural strength <pb n="79"
               />which God infused into his body smote a thousand men with the jawbone of an ass and
               became a saviour and a judge unto Israel? Was it not because he made impure and
               defiled his hallowed limbs by intercourse with a harlot, that the Lord left him and
               gave him into the hands of his enemies? David, the heart of God, for whose excellence
               the promise made unto the righteous Fathers was carried out in his offspring from
               whom sprouted Christ the Saviour of the whole world — was it not by adultery with one
               woman and for the feebleness of one moment that from a glance of his eye he got an
               arrow in his soul and wrought evil against himself from within his own house; for the
               son which was to come forth from his loins was to pursue him?</p>
            <p>And this happened although he showed repentance and the <pb type="external" n="117"
               />Lord said to him: Also have I put away thy sin; thou shalt not die<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n79-1"/>, and he
               wept a flood of tears so that he moistened his bed during the nights.</p>
            <p>I return to what I was saying before: Why then did distress and destruction hit the
               house of Eli the priest, the righteous old man, a priest and a judge of Israel during
               forty years? Was it not because of Pinehas and Hophni his sons who treated the women
               scornfully that came to pray in the tabernacle, though he himself did not sin, at any
               rate not wilfully, but only in so far as he was silent and reprehended with words
               only, without showing fervour against the fornication of his sons, so that the
               judgment of the Lord took revenge on them? And lest any one should think that the
               Lord shows His zeal only against those who are sinners in their lifetime, He also
               displays it against this audacious sin hated of Him, in the case of those who are
               near to Him, His priests and judges and the heads of the people and against those men
               who were holy unto Him and by whose hands He had done wonderful things, yet whom,
               when they violated the laws He had laid down, He did not spare. As is written in
               Ezechiel where He says to the man whom He orders to smite the people of Jerusalem
               with a hidden sword: Begin before my altar and do not spare, neither old man nor boy
               nor youth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n78-2"/> to show that it was the people near to Him, those who walked in
               fear <pb type="external" n="118"/>and chastity before Him and performed His will. The
               saints <pb n="80"/>of the Lord and those near to Him are good works and a pure heart.
               But when they reject the ways of the Lord's will, He also rejects them and puts them
               away from before Him and takes His grace from them.</p>
            <p>And why then did the judgment of the Exalted smite Belshazzar by the sign of the
               hollow hand? Was it not because he had behaved audaciously against the holy vessels
               which he had taken from Jerusalem and in which he drank with his concubines? And in
               the same way the judgment of the Exalted will of a sudden smite him who in abandoned
               audaciousness uses for worldly purposes the limbs that once were set apart for the
               holiness of the Lord, just as Belshazzar was smitten who behaved audaciously against
               the holy vessels taken from the sanctuary of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Therefore we should not make use of the confidence in repentance and the heart-giving
               words of the scriptures as a motive for disregarding the words and the threats of the
               Lord and disdain Him by evil deeds, disdaining thereby also the limbs that once we
               have offered as a sacrifice for the ministration of His sanctuaries and for the use
               of His service.</p>
            <p>Verily we are the sanctified of the Lord and the Naziraeans abstaining from women, as
               Elijah, Elisha and the prophets and the other sanctified Naziraeans and holy virgins
               by whose hands great and amazing things were done, who spake with God face to face;
               and as those who lived afterwards, John the virgin and the holy Simeon and the other
               preachers of <pb type="external" n="119"/>the New Testament who sanctified themselves
               to the Lord and received mystic secrets from Him, some from His own mouth, others by
               revelation. And so they became mediators between God and mankind, and the receptacles
               of His revelations and the preachers of the Kingdom to the inhabitants of the
               world.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n78-1">Cf. 2 Samuel 12,13</note>
            <note xml:id="n78-2">Ezekiel 9,6</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
