<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 11</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 11, pp. 80-82.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="11">
            <head>XI</head>
            <p>Whereby the beauty of solitary life is to be preserved and how it can be a cause of
               God’s being glorified</p>
            <p>It is becoming for the solitary to be in every way a vision of stimulation unto those
               who look at him, so that because of the beauties which radiate from him on all sides
               as the rays <pb n="81"/>of the sun, even the enemies of truth unwillingly acknowledge
               that the Christians have a well-founded hope; and from every side they will flow to
               their place of refuge, and thus the head of the church will be elevated above its
               enemies.</p>
            <p>Thus the glory of the solitary's deeds will be a stimulus for many to withdraw from
               the world. And [it is becoming] that he be reverenced by every one on account of his
               excellence, so that the mouth of the members of the church will be opened on his
               account and their head exalted above all creeds.</p>
            <p>The pride of Christ's church consists in the behaviour of the solitaries. Therefore
               it is becoming to the solitary that the beauties of his habits shine on all sides; in
               the humble attitude of his limbs, in the simplicity of his habit, in his elevation
                  <pb type="external" n="120"/>above visible things, in the veracity of his
               renunciation, in his rigorous fasting, in his being continuous silent, in the
               subduing of his senses, in the continence of his aspect, in his not being quarrelsome
               with other people for any reason, in the sparingness of his speech, in his being pure
               from rancour, in his discriminate conscious simplicity. And [it is becoming for him]
               that it be known that he is alien to this harmful and fleeting life and near to true
               and spiritual life, from his constantly being by himself, from his being unknown
               among men, from his not being tied to any one by the bonds of comradeship and
               intimacy, from his quiet dwellingplace, from the small space of his habitation, from
               his few and mean utensils, from his avoiding men, from his constant prayer, from his
               hating and avoiding honour, from his not being bound by temporal life, from his great
               patience, from his endurance in temptations, from his keeping aloof from rumours and
               from inquiries into worldly affairs, from his constant care for and meditation upon
               his true country, known by his sad countenance and his shrivelled face<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n83-1"/>, from
               his constantly weeping night and day, and above all from his cautious chastity and
               his freedom from covetousness in small and great things.</p>
            <p>These are, in short, the manifest beauties of the solitary <pb type="external"
                  n="121"/>which testify to his being wholly dead to the world and near unto
               God.</p>
            <p>It is becoming for him to think of these things constantly in order to acquire
               them.</p>
            <pb n="82"/>
            <p>If any one asks: Wherefore are these lengthy descriptions necessary? I answer: they
               are very necessary. For if any one search for them, one by one, in himself, and if
               any fail him who cares for his life, he can ascertain from these distinctions his
               deficiency in any of the virtues. And thus these descriptions may become to him
               admonitions. And if he possess personally all the things described and also those
               omitted, the knowledge of them is given him [in this way] and so he will become a
               cause of God being praised among men and angels. And then he may prepare for his soul
               a place of rest before departing this world.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n81-1">ܡܚܪܟܘܬܐ ܕܐܦܘ̈ܗܝ</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
