<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 53</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 53, pp. 261-262.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="54">
            <head>LIV</head>
            <head>Other explanations concerning Maggenanutha<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-1"/></head>
            <p>Although we have already spoken on this subject in an other context in the foregoing
               disquisitions<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-2"/>, when an opportunity offered itself, yet we do not object to
               elucidating the subject further here.</p>
            <p>Maggenanutha denotes help and guardianship and also the receiving of the heavenly
               gift. As for instance: The Holy Ghost shall come and the Power of the Highest shall
               overshadow thee<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-3"/>. And: Thy right hand shall save me<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-4"/> which is a
               prayer for help. And: I will defend this city to save it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n261-5"/>.</p>
            <p>So we understand two kinds of action in the maggenanutha granted by God unto mankind;
               one is symbolical and intelligible; the other practical. The former is connected with
               the holiness which is received through divine grace; this means: by the influence of
               the Holy Ghost a man is made holy in body and soul, as is the case of <persName>Elisha</persName> and <persName>John</persName>
               and <persName>Mary</persName> the blessed among women. But because this is incomparable <pb n="262"/>and
               above that which happens to the rank-and-file of creatures we have to come to that
               partial [holiness] which is granted unto the other saints, in the relation between
               the limbs and the body.</p>
            <p>The mysterious kind of maggenanutha — as the [gifts] <pb type="external" n="391"
               />imparted unto each of the saints — is a kind of influence which possesses the mind.
               And when man is deemed worthy of this maggenanutha, the mind is snatched away in
               ecstasy and expanded by some divine revelation. And as long as the influence
               possesses the mind, man is exalted above the emotions of psychic deliberations, on
               account of his communion with the Holy Ghost.</p>
            <p>And this is what was said by the Apostle in the form of a prayer unto the Ephesians,
               when he desired to explain to them this mystery: May the God of our Lord <persName>Jesus</persName>
               Christ, the Father of glory, give unto you the spirit of wisdom and revelation in the
               knowledge of Him: the eyes of your hearts being enlightened<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-1"/>. What is the
               result of this? That ye may know what is the hope of His calling and what the riches
               of the glory of His inheritance in the saints, and what is the exceeding greatness of
               His power to us-ward who believe<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-2"/>.</p>
            <p>This is one symbolical kind of maggenanutha, that when this power overshadows a man,
               he is deemed worthy of the glory of the new world, by revelation. And this is the
               part that has fallen to the lot of the saints by light concerning which the blessed
               <persName>Paul</persName> says, that those are deemed worthy of it who have received sanctification of the
               mind from the Spirit, on account of their holy and excellent behaviour<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-3"/>.</p>
            <p>Another kind of maggenanutha is that whose action manifests itself practically. It is
               the intelligible power which constantly covers a man and broods over him, removing
               from him any injury or accident that threatens to approach his body or soul,
               something not to be perceived visibly by the mind, but <pb type="external" n="392"
               />clear and evident to the eye of faith, such as was frequently experienced by the
               saints; as is written: The angels of the Lord encamp round about them that fear Him
               and deliver them<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-4"/>. And: Many are the afflictions of the righteous but the
               Lord delivers them out of them all<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n262-5"/>.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n261-1">Inspiration, revelation, incarnation a. s. o.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-2">Syriac text, pp. 107, 160</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-3">Luke 1,35 naggen; to overshadow is only a faint rendering. The
               original means rather to envelop and to overpower.</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-4">Ps. 138,7</note>
            <note xml:id="n261-5"><choice><sic>Ps.</sic><corr>Is.</corr></choice> 37,35</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-1">Ephesians 1,17 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-2">ib. 10,18 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-3">cf. 2 Thess. 2,13</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-4">Ps. 34,7</note>
            <note xml:id="n262-5">Ps. 34,19</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
