<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 1</title> <!-- I noticed you're adding spaces. Please don't do that. -->
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 1, pp. 1-7</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="1">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head>I</head>
            <p>The fear of God is the foundation of excellence; for excellence is said to be the
               offspring of faith. It is sown in a man's heart, when he allows his mind to confine
               the wandering impulses to continual meditation on the order of things to come, away
               from the distractions of the world. As to the foundation of <pb type="external" n="2"
               />excellence, the first among its peculiar elements is the concentration of the self,
               by freeing it from practical things, upon the enlightened word of the straight and
               holy ways, the word that by the inspired Psalmist is called the teacher.</p>
            <p>There is scarcely to be found a man who is able to bear honours, or possibly such an
               one exists not; because man is very prone to err, even if he be an angel in his
               way.</p>
            <p>The foundation of the way of life consists in accustoming the mind to the words of
               God and the practice of patience. For the draught provided by the former is helpful
               towards acquiring perfection in the latter; and, further, increased development
               towards accomplishment in the latter, will cause a heightened desire of the former.
               And the help provided by both of them will quickly bring about the rise of the whole
               building.</p>
            <p>No one is able to come near to God save only he who is far from the world. For I do
               not call separation the departure from the body, but from the bodily things.</p>
            <p>Excellence consists therein that a man in his mind be a void as regards the world. As
               long as the senses are occupied with [outward] things, it is not possible for the
               heart to rest from <pb n="2"/>imagining them. Nor do the affections cease, nor evil
               thoughts end except in the desert and the wilderness.</p>
            <p>While the soul has not yet become drunk by the faith in God, in that it has received
               an impression of its powers, the weakness of the senses cannot be healed and it is
               not able to tread down with force visible matter which is a screen before what is
               within and not perceived [by the senses].</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="3"/>Reason is the cause of freedom<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2-1"/> and the fruit of
               both liability to err. Without the first, the second cannot be. And where the second
               fails, there is the third bound as it were with halters.</p>
            <p>When grace is abundant in man, then the fear of death is despised on account of the
               love of righteousness. He finds many arguments in his soul [proving] that it is
               becoming to bear troubles for the sake of the fear of God. And those things which are
               supposed to injure the body, and to repel nature injustly, which consequently are of
               a nature to cause suffering, are reckoned in his eye as nothing in comparison with
               what is expected to be. And his mind convinces him firmly of the fact that it is not
               possible to recognize truth without gaining experience of the affections, and that
               God bestows great care upon man, and that he is not abandoned to chance. Especially
               those who are trained in praying unto Him and who bear suffering for His sake, see
               [these truths] clearly [as if painted] in colours. But when little faith takes root
               in our heart, then all these things are felt as contrary, not as serving for testing
               us.</p>
            <p>And that we are not always successful in trusting in God, and that God does not care
               for thee as it is supposed, is often insinuated by those who lay ambushes and shoot
               their arrows in the darkness.</p>
            <p>The foundation of man's true life, is the fear of God. And this does not consent to
               dwell in the soul as long as there <pb type="external" n="4"/>exists the distraction
               of [outward] things. For the heart, by the service of the senses, is turned away from
               the delight in God.</p>
            <p>The inward impulses are bound up in their sensible faculty with the senses
               administering to them.</p>
            <p>The doubt of the heart introduces fear into the soul. But faith is able to make manly
               the mind, even under the cutting off of the limbs. As long as the love of the body is
               strong in thee, thou art not able to be courageous and without fear <pb n="3"
               />because of the many adversaries that are constantly present in the neighbourhood of
               him who is loved.</p>
            <p>If any one is fond of honour, he cannot be without causes of distress.</p>
            <p>There is no man, whose mind suffers not likewise a change with things, in whatever
               respect it may be.</p>
            <p>If there is a second apperception of the senses, which generates and gives birth to
               desire, as <persName>Euagrius</persName> says, then those who dwell in doubt must keep silence, promising
               to preserve their mind in peace.</p>
            <p>Not that one is chaste from whom evil impulses that intended to combat him, are
               withheld, but he whose uprightness of heart renders chaste the gaze of his mind, so
               that he does not audaciously enter upon lascivious thoughts; and the saintliness of
               his heart is testified by the gaze of his pupils, which are guarded faithfully, so
               that bashfulness screens, like a curtain, the hidden place of his thoughts. So that
               his purity<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3-1"/>, like that of a chaste virgin, is faithfully guarded for
               Christ.</p>
            <p>There is nothing so apt to banish lascivious customs from the soul, and to restrain
               inciting memories which quicken the wild flames in the body, as burning for the love
               of teachings, and prosecuting investigations concerning the meaning of the <pb
                  type="external" n="5"/>words of the scriptures.</p>
            <p>When the impulses are immersed in delight, after [having tasted] the wisdom contained
               in the [divine] words, by means of the faculty that absorbs information from them,
               then every man will leave the body behind him. Forgetting the world and all that is
               in it, he will also banish from his soul all recollections on which are based the
               images of the material world. And often the soul in its thoughts during ecstasy will
               desist from the use of the wonted deliberations — natural practice — by reason of the
               novel [experiences] which reach it from the sea of their mysteries.</p>
            <p>Even when the mind is floating on its upper waters, without being able to make its
               impulses deep as the depth of the waters (so that it can see all the treasures in its
               abysses) — still meditation, by its [power of] love, will have sufficient force to
               bind the thoughts firmly together with thoughts of ecstasy so that they are checked
               from thinking of and running after <pb n="4"/>the nature of the body. As one of
               those, who are clad with God says: "Because the heart is weak, it is not able to bear
               the evil influences that reach it from without, nor the struggle within. For you
               know, that the evil thoughts of the body are strong. And if the heart is not
               accustomed to teachings, it is not possible to bear the troubled thoughts of the
               body.</p>
            <p>As the heaviness of the weight [impedes] the quick swaying too and <choice><sic>froo</sic><corr>fro</corr></choice> of the
               tongue of the balance in the wild winds, so bashfulness and fear [impede] the
               aberration of the mind. And that which is an indication of deficiency in the former,
               is also a [sign] of the dominion of freedom<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4-1"/> in the latter. <pb type="external"
                  n="6"/>Just as in that case any additional decrease is the cause of the scales
               swaying too and <choice><sic>froo</sic><corr>fro</corr></choice> with greater ease, having no solid foundation, so in this
               case, by the abolition of fear from the soul on account of freedom, the balance of
               the mind is able to turn aside quickly. So the faculty of emotion comes in the
               consequence of freedom; and inconstancy of the mind is the consequence of the faculty
               of aberration<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4-2"/>. Be wise enough to lay a foundation for thy course in the way of
               God; in a few days it will bring thee before the gate of the Kingdom, without
               windings in the way<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4-3"/>.</p>
            <p>Do not in the way of those who are educated by teachers look at the words which in
               the way of test, are intended to elevate thy behaviour, in order that thy soul may be
               elevated by the height of sight that is in them. Distinguish the purport of the word
               in all the stories thou findest in the scriptures so thou wilt be able to make thy
               soul deep so that it may dwell with the great wisdom that is in the waitings of
               enlightened men.</p>
            <p>Those who, by grace, are directed in their behaviour towards illumination, perceive
               constantly as it were an intelligible ray running between the words [of the
               scriptures]. This ray distinguishes for the mind the simple speech from those things
               that are said in spiritual loftiness in order to expand the soul.</p>
            <p>He who simply reads lofty words, his heart will also remain simple and devoid of the
               holy power, that imparts to the heart a sweet taste by the meanings that stupefy the
               soul.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="7"/>All things are accustomed to move towards that which is
                  <pb n="5"/>akin [to them]. And the soul that possesses something of the spirit, on
               hearing anything wherein a spiritual force is hidden, fervently embraces that which
               it hears; and yet a tale that is told spiritually and wherein a great force is
               hidden, is not able to arouse every one unto admiration.</p>
            <p>A word concerning excellence requires a heart free from the earth and earthly
               occupations.</p>
            <p>If a man's mind is beset with care for transitory things, tales concerning excellence
               will not incite his thought to the desiring of its possession.</p>
            <p>Solution from matter precedes the bonds in God<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5-1"/>. And though, as if by
               Providence of Grace, in some people the latter precede the former, so that love
               covers love, in the usual order of Providence the common sequence is otherwise. So
               thou hast to keep the common order. If Grace in thee comes first, it is for its own
               sake. If it does not, then, along the way that every man goes by tradition, ascend
               the spiritual tower.</p>
            <p>Everything which is mentally performed and the commandment of which is fulfilled thus
               also, is entirely invisible to the eyes of the flesh; whereas every thing which is
               performed in practice, is wholly of a composite nature. For it is only one
               commandment that necessitates these two, viz. theory and performance. Because
               corporeity and non-corporeity and the <pb type="external" n="5"/>adaptation of the
               two belong to all. Therefore the enlightened intellect — as has been ordered formerly
               by the blessed <persName>Moses</persName> — understands in a twofold way the commandment [lying at the
               bottom of theory and practice]: the simple as well as the complex is understood.</p>
            <p>Works performed carefully by the pure, do not remove the impression of the
               recollection of previous reprehensible things; but they abolish in the mind the
               painful nature of recollection, so that what has passed through the mind often
               enough, now becomes something excellent.</p>
            <p>The longing of the soul for the acquiring of excellence vanquishes the desire of its
               partner<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5-3"/> for visible things.</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>All things have their mean. Lacking that, even those things the use of which is apt
               to help, may turn aside and become harmful without meeting any obstacle.</p>
            <p>If thou wishest to have mental communion with God, by acquiring the impression of
               that delight that is not subject to the senses, then cling to mercy. For the holy
               beauty is formed by that element within thee, which resembles mercy<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6-1"/>. And all
               the practices of mercy bring the soul, immediately, into communion with the unique
               splendour of the divine glory<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6-2"/>.</p>
            <p>Spiritual unification is a perpetual recollection, that is vivid in the heart without
               variation, with burning love. By constancy <pb type="external" n="9"/>in clinging to
               the commandments, it acquires the force to remain in union and there is found, in a
               way neither secondary nor natural, matter for spiritual vision, in which the soul may
               confide absolutely. So a man is drawn towards ecstasy by the closing of the two
               classes of senses: those of the flesh and those of the soul. There is no other way
               towards spiritual love which is modeller of invisible images, than to begin in the
               first place with mercy in accordance with the word of our Lord who commands it to
               those who obey him, in connection with the perfection of the Father, the
               foundation.</p>
            <p>Very different is the word of practice from words of beauty. Even without experience
               wisdom knows how to adorn its words and to speak the truth even without having any
               acquaintance with it, and to express itself concerning excellence without any
               experience of [practical] performance. A word proceeding from practice, is a treasure
               to confide in. But idle wisdom is a pawn causing shame it is as when an artist paints
               water on walls, without being able to quench his thirst by it; or as a man who dreams
               beautiful dreams.</p>
            <p>He who from practical experience speaks about excellence, brings the word to his
               hearers as it were from the capital won by his own commerce; and, as from the stock
               of his soul, sows his teachings in the ears of his audience. He opens his mouth
               freely before his spiritual sons, in the manner of old <persName>Jacob</persName> before chaste <persName>Joseph</persName>,
               [saying]: I have given thee one portion above thy brethren, which I took out of the
               hand of the Amorite with my sword and with my bow<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6-3"/>.</p>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p><pb type="external" n="10"/>So every man whose behaviour is stained, will love
               temporal life; so will also he who falls short of knowledge. Some one has well said:
               The fear of death distresses a fleshly man. But he who has a good witness in himself,
               will desire it as life.</p>
            <p>Do not reckon as a truly wise man that one whose mind is subject to fear on account
               of temporal life.</p>
            <p>All good and evil things which befall the body have all of them, to be reckoned by
               thee as dreams, which thou canst escape from not only by death, but whwich often leave
               thee even before death and disappear.</p>
            <p>If thy soul is bound to some of them, then estimate them as thy possession for ever,
               accompanying thee also in the world to be. If they are beautiful, then rejoice and
               thank God in thy mind. If they are evil, then be sorry and sigh and seek to be
               delivered from them while being in the body. If any good is done to thee, open or
               concealed, then be sure that thy mediators concerning it have been baptism and faith,
               by which thou wert called in <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> unto good works; to whom and to the Father
               and to the Holy Ghost belong praise, honour and adoration, now and always and for
               ever and ever. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1-1">Title taken from the end of VI on p. 99. All reference applies to
               the pages of Bedjan's text.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2-1"> This term has nearly always the meaning of free will. Cf.
               Introduction.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3-1">Reading ܕܟܝܘܬܗ in stead of ܕܟܝܘܬܗ̇</note>
            <note xml:id="n4-1">Cf. p. 2 note 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4-2">Cf. Introduction.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4-3">Cf. Book of the Dove, Sentence 85: "Every serene soul seeks its
               original country, and directs itself towards it on the straight way, which is the
               nearest". And the inscription of chapter XVII: On the short paths to God.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5-1">Cf. beneath p. 40 and Basilius: Λουθῆναι δεῖ τὸν δεσμὸν τῆς
               προσπαλείας τοῦ βίου τὸν ἀληθινῶς τῷ θεῷ ἀκολουθῆσαι μέλλοντα (Antonius et Maximus,
               p. 22). And Philo 1 380 39: δεσμὰ μὲν οἷς πρότερον ἐσφίγγετο ἃ περιῆψαν αἱ τοῦ θνητοῦ
               βίου κεναὶ σποδαὶ, πάντα λύσας… πρὸς τὴν τοῦ ἀγεννήτου παγκάλην καὶ ἀοίδιμον θέαν
               ἐπειχθῆναι. — Plotinus, Enneades IV, 8, § 1 points to the Platonic origin of the
               comparison, and uses it himself § 4, speaking of the soul: ἐπιστραφεῖσα δὲ πρὸς
               νόησιν λύεσθαί τε ἐκ τῶν δεσμῶν, καὶ ἀναβαίνειν….</note>
            <note xml:id="n5-2">the body</note>
            <note xml:id="n6-1">Reading ܠܗܿ instead of ܠܗ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6-2">Cf. Chapter LXXXI.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6-3">Genesis 48,22.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
