<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 78</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 78, pp. 360-361.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="78">
            <pb n="360"/>
            <head>LXXVIII</head>
            <head>On the profit [arising] from the flight from the world the method of which has been
               thought out by the Fathers through prudent examination</head>
            <p>Strong indeed and difficult and very hard is the struggle which arises when things
               are near. And though a man may be excellent and vigorous, when things causing battles
               and strife are near, fear clings to him. Then he falls easier than when Satan
               personally meets him in battle. For when a man <pb type="external" n="537"/>is not
               far from those things which the heart is afraid of, the fiend has constantly the
               opportunity [to assail him]. And if it happens that he sleeps a while, the fiend can
               easily destroy him. For there the body is in danger of being injured, at any rate it
               has to be kept afar from sin. But here it is the soul that receives an invisible blow
               and it cannot fatigue the fiend so that he gives up fighting against it. For these
               things are of themselves able to move against it the disturbance of struggle at any
               time. And willingly it lets itself be captivated by them, without any one arousing
               strife against it from without. But the soul is in strife with itself through the
               allurements of those things which are arranged before the senses of the body, as has
               been said somewhere; for as soon as the soul is captivated by the injurious meetings
               with the world, these meetings become stumbling-blocks to it; or, as has also been
               said: The soul is naturally vanquished, when it meets those things.</p>
            <p>Therefore, because the ancient saints who have walked in these ways knew that the
               mind is not always healthy so as to be able to remain in one attitude, without
               deviation, and vigilant, because there is a time that the soul becomes enveloped in
               darkness without being able to look at those things which cause injury — they have
               examined prudently and [resolved to] put on renunciation, as a weapon. For it frees
               from many struggles, as has been written. For some have escaped from sins, through
               their poverty and have migrated towards the desert where there is nothing to cause
               affections, <pb n="361"/>so that, when a time comes when they are weak, nothing is
               found to give occasion to fall.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="538"/>I say: anger and desire and rancour and glory and the
               like are slight, because of the desert, and by it [those solitaries] were protected
               as by an invincible tower. Then every one of them was able to accomplish his strife
               in solitude, there where the senses found no support so as to become fiends by
               injurious meetings. Better for us is death in our struggle, than life with
               falling.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
