<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 66</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 66, pp. 312-316.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="66">
            <pb n="312"/>
            <head>LXVI</head>
            <head><pb type="external" n="465"/>A letter which he sent to his friend in which he
               expounds some things concerning the mystery of solitude and how it is that many
               neglect this wonderful service because they are not acquainted with it whereas the
               main part of them cling to sitting in the cell because this is the current monkish
               tradition. Together with a collection of short sayings useful for those who practise
               solitude</head>
            <p>Now that thou hast inculcated in me the duty to write to thee on those things which
               are necessary, I inform thy love by this my writing, in accordance with the promise
               which I gave thee. As I have found that thou art determined to practise sitting in
               solitude, with painstaking behaviour, so I from my side will describe to thee in
               simple words, that which I have heard from discriminating men concerning this
               service, combining the concentrated sense of their words with personal<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n312-1"/>
               experiences [gathered] by practice. And thou, on thy side, wilt profit by being
               occupied with this letter in thy usual diligent way, because with the discrimination
               of wisdom thou approachest the concise terms of the lecture of this letter, and not
               in the usual groove. And thou shalt take them as some elucidation of the rest of thy
               lecture, because of the great insight and power hidden in them. For the mind is
               greatly strengthened by such a lecture and it takes from it a <pb type="external"
                  n="466"/>weapon against distraction of the thoughts and against dejection which is
               wont to rise from the hardship of labours and the prolonged sitting in solitude. And
               it casts behind it the world with attention to its practices, through the radiancy
               with which it is clad [by the sight of] those things which it meets; <choice><sic>the</sic><corr>that</corr></choice>
               which is the aim of this letter, [namely to make known] what is dwelling and service
               in solitude, and what mysteries are hidden in this discipline which are not observed
                  <pb n="313"/>by many, and what events the prudent try to reach by solitude; and
               wherefore they reject the righteousness which is practised among men, fleeing from
               the sight of the world and choosing the troubles and struggles which are connected
               with quiet and lonely dwelling. On account of this insight and on account of those
               things which are found in this letter [readers] will call these solitaries who pass
               their life in this world in concentrated sitting by themselves happy. To those who do
               not perceive these things, admonition and advice, concerning the order of solitude
               are vain. Here however I write to the wise, and I give advice in love.</p>
            <p>If thou seekest imperishable life during thy short days, o brother, then let thy
               entry unto solitude take place with discrimination<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n313-1"/>, that thou mayest find
               the profit which awaits the wise in the path of solitude. Scrutinize its service and
               do not run after a name. Enter, be profound and bold, learn and acquire and train
               thyself in all the amazing and liberating distinctions of the ways of service in
               solitude. Then thou wilt understand, with all the saints, what is the height and the
                  <pb type="external" n="467"/>depth and the length and the breadth of this
               illimitable discipline, because of the illimitable riches which its merchants seek to
               acquire. And thou wilt not rest, until thou art trained in all the ways of its
               service<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n313-2"/>.</p>
            <p>From every human practice, at its beginning, some profit is expected when it shall be
               realised; this it is which moves the intelligent to lay its foundations. And this aim
               makes the mind heroic, so as to bear the difficulties of the matter. The mind even
               gathers some consolation from it by looking towards it. And after the fashion of an
               officer of the law, it apprehends the mind, till the matter is accomplished. So, in
               the eyes of the discriminate, the aim of the severe service of solitude is the
               harbour of mysteries towards which the mind looks, from the time when it lays the
               first foundations till the end of the work of building. And as the eyes of the
               helmsman look to the stars, so, in all his long and difficult labours, the inner gaze
               of the solitary, during his whole course, is directed towards the aim which he has
               fixed in his mind the first day when he gave himself to sailing the rough sea of
               solitude, till he shall find the pearl for the sake of which he has <pb n="314"
               />entrusted himself to the not-to-be-explored floods of the ocean. And his gaze of
               hope makes light to him the whole burden of service and the difficulties full of
               danger which meet him in his course.</p>
            <p>But he that, as soon as he enters solitude, does not set this aim to the profit [he
               wishes to gather] from his service, labouring at random as a man that combates the
               air, will never during <pb type="external" n="468"/>his life escape the spirit of
               despondency. And one of two things will happen to him: Either, no longer bearing the
               insupportable burden, he will be vanquished and give up solitude altogether; or, if
               he adheres to it, his cell becomes a dungeon in which he is tormented. And because he
               does not know that he may expect the consolation which is born from the service in
               solitude, he is not able to implore through his heart's pain or to beseech in
               passionate prayer or to embrace the token which our merciful Fathers, from love of
               their posterity, have left to us in their writings, whereby we could gain our
               life.</p>
            <p>One of them has said: To me the profit of solitude is this, that where I withdraw
               from the camp in which my abode is fixed, my mind becomes void of the occupations of
               war and turns to a service which is more profitable.</p>
            <p>Another: Solitude cuts off causes which give a new turn to the deliberations and
               within its walls there grow old and tasteless the recollections of previous things.
               And when the old matter has disappeared from the intellect, the mind returns to
               nature in order to direct it.</p>
            <p>Another: I run to meet solitude, with this aim, that in my heart the sentences of
               recitation and prayer may become sweet. And when my tongue has been made silent by
               the delight of their understanding, I fall, as it were, asleep, my senses and my
               emotion being benumbed. And when by prolonged solitude my heart has acquired peace
               from the trouble of recollections, solitude sends me continually waves of gladness
               which arise from emotions which burst forth from within unexpectedly and <pb
                  type="external" n="469"/>suddenly, to the delight of my heart; the which, running
               against the ship of my soul, and [withdrawing it] from the sounds of the world and
               from the life of the flesh, immerse it in the deepest depths of quiet in God.</p>
            <p>Another: The degree of thy hidden things thou canst understand by thy different
               emotions. I mean the perpetual ones, not those which are set astir by accident and
               are made to <pb n="315"/>pass by time. There is no one clad with flesh whose house is
               not visited by some traveller belonging to the two various states of good and of
               evil. If he is disprudent, by those of deficiency, through nature, the fathers of
               children. If he is faithful, by those of elevation, through the leaven of grace which
               He has mixed with our nature, the parents of the kingdom on high.</p>
            <p>Another: Choose the delightful service of continual vigils, by which all the Fathers
               have put off their old man and have become worthy of the renewal of the intellect. At
               these times the soul perceives that immortal life, by which apperception it throws
               off the garment of darkness and becomes the recipient of spiritual gifts.</p>
            <p>Another: It is not possible that a man, while seeing many faces and hearing various
               sounds foreign to spiritual meditation, and speaking and having intercourse with the
               like, should keep his mind free so as to gaze at himself secretly, to remember his
               sins, to hide his thoughts, and to look at those which come, and to become familiar
               with hidden prayer.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="470"/>Further it is impossible for a man to subdue the senses
               by the domination of the soul without solitude and alienation from men because the
               initiated soul becomes united to them and involved with them as in one person and is
               dragged along with their impulses, if it does not hold vigil with hidden prayer. And
               then, how vigils and alertness with prayer and recitation, will delight and gladden
               and give joy and make pure the soul, is well known to those who have practised these
               things during their whole life, in veracious asceticism.</p>
            <p>And thou, o man who lovest solitude, place before thee, as a mark, these indications
               based upon the words of the Fathers, and direct the course of thy service towards
               them, and before all things, judge which are those which suit best the aim of thy
               service. Without them thou canst not be mature in true knowledge; try to show thy
               endurance especially in them.</p>
            <p>Silence is a symbol of the future world. Speech is an organ of this world. A man who
               fasts is trying to acquire likeness with the nature of the spiritual beings.</p>
            <p>Through his continual silence and fasting a man becomes distinguished that in his
               hidden state is constantly occupied with the service of God. By these mysteries is
               accomplished, even through those invisible forces, the holy service of the Essence
                  <pb n="316"/>which governs the world. Some men who have been marked <pb
                  type="external" n="471"/>off to enter the divine mysteries, have been signed with
               such seals as these; some of them have been entrusted with the guidance of a strong
               people; others have even acquired power over the elements and, midst great
               admiration, the species<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n316-1"/> of nature have obeyed their commandments; others
               have been entrusted with the office of examining, for the universal renovation, the
               secrets that were hidden in the mysterious silence of the Lord of the universe. And
               it would not have been beautiful, if with a full belly and a mind distracted by
               wantonness, such mysteries had been administered, or if the <choice><sic>sanits</sic><corr>saints</corr></choice> had
               ventured to elevate themselves to intercourse with God and unto His secret mysteries,
               unless with weak limbs and a colour livid by the pain of hunger, and a mind conscious
               of its reason by its having renunciated all earthly deliberations.</p>
            <p>When, on account of a long abode in thy cell and troublesome labours and secret
               observance and restraint of the senses from all contact, the power of solitude gets
               hold of thee, thou wilt find first that joy which from time to time, without a cause,
               dominates thy soul. Then thy eyes are opened to see God's creative power and the
               beauty of the creatures, in accordance with the degree of thy purity. And when the
               mind by this sight has been snatched up in ecstasy, night and day become one to it in
               its admiration of the glorious works of God. And then the apperception of the
               affections is taken away from the soul by the delight of this sight. And by it the
               soul enters <pb type="external" n="472"/>the two degrees of intelligible revelations
               which belong to what lies higher than purity.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n312-1">lit.: near</note>
            <note xml:id="n313-1">Cf. The Book of the Dove, p. 19</note>
            <note xml:id="n313-2">Text has plural</note>
            <note xml:id="n316-1">ܟܝ̈ܢܐ</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
