<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 15</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 15, pp. 87-89.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="15">
            <pb n="87"/>
            <head>XV</head>
            <p>On the course of the solitary career, succinctly and without prolixity, and on the
               question how and at what time its virtues are born one form the other</p>
            <p>Lucidly and distinctly, the course of virtues shows itself so.</p>
            <p>Erom works performed by compulsion, in solitude there is <pb type="external" n="128"
               />born a blazing and immeasurable heat, which is generated in the heart by fervent
               deliberations, newly born in the spirit.</p>
            <p>Works and watchfulness polish the mind by their heat and give it sight. And sight
               gives birth to the fervent deliberations mentioned, because of the depth of psychic
               sight which is called contemplation.</p>
            <p>Contemplation gives birth to fervour; from this fervour sight given by grace is born;
               and then outbursts of tears begin. At first partial ones; this means that a man's
               tears will flow several times every day. Then he will come to [the state of] tears
               without a break. Through the tears the soul receives peaceful deliberations. From
               peaceful deliberations it rises unto serenity of insight. And by serenity of insight
               a man reaches the sight of hidden things. For purity is brought about by being free
               from war.</p>
            <p>And after these the mind will reach that which is denoted by the symbol of the brook
               in Ezekiel the prophet <ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n87-1"/>, a symbol which contains the type of those three
               psychic stages which are near to divine things and of which the third is the utmost
               which a man can reach.</p>
            <p>The beginning of all these is a good will unto God and various works in solitude and
               that uprightness which is born from severe reclusion from the world.</p>
            <p>It is not necessary to enumerate the distinctions between the works, for they are
               known to every man. But as soon as any one occupies himself with them it is not
               possible that he deteriorate; I know, on the contrary, that he will profit by <pb
                  n="88"/><pb type="external" n="129"/>them. They are the following: the work of
               hunger, of reciting, waking during the night, according to every one's strength;
               frequent prostrations, several times in the day and often during the night. Some will
               perform thirty prostrations at one time, salute (the cross]<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n88-1"/> and go away from
               it. Some will perform even a greater number. Others will prolong prayer during three
               hours and stay in concentration while prostrated, without compulsion and without
               distraction.</p>
            <p>These two varying states show the great richness of grace, which works in various
               ways with every man according to his measure, be it that he multiplies the number [of
               his prayers] on account of his fervent ardour, be it that he acquires quiet in his
               soul so that he reduces to one the large number of his former prayers.</p>
            <p>As to the question of the cause of that other prayer and its duration without
               compulsion, it seems to me that it is not becoming for us to treat such things in
               detail, by describing their nature in speech or writings lest the reader, being
               unable to understand anything of it, should judge it to be something insipid or, if
               he should be acquainted with these things, should despise him who is not able to
               cross the border of certain things. From the one blame, from the other laughter would
               be the consequence; and thus I would become a barbarous writer to such ones,
               according to the word of the apostle <pb type="external" n="130"/>concerning him that
               speaks in prophecies<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n88-2"/>.</p>
            <p>But he who is desirous to know these things should know that their course has been
               described above. He may combine works with deliberation, by the grace of our Lord.
               And what practically happens in these states he may experience personally.</p>
            <p>Stay therefore in thy cell and the cell will teach thee everything.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n87-1">Ez. 47</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-1">Cf. p. 140</note>
            <note xml:id="n88-2">Cf. 1 Cor. 14</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
