<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 73</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 73, pp. 337-340.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="73">
            <head>LXXIII</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="502"/>The concise sense of the [foregoing] section together
               with explanations of what has been said</p>
            <p>The concise sense of the foregoing section is to communicate to us that at every
               moment<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n337-1"/> of the four and twenty hours of the day, we are in want of
               repentance. The explanation of the denotation of repentance, in its real practical
               sense, is continual mournful supplication in contrite prayer, offered to God for the
               forgiveness of previous sins; and petition to be guarded against future
               ones<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n337-2"/>. Therefore our Lord also has sustained our weakness by prayer: Watch
               and pray, that ye enter not into temptation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n337-3"/>. And: Pray, and do not
               faint<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n337-4"/>. And: Watch ye therefore, and pray always<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n337-5"/>.</p>
            <p>Ask, and it shall be given unto you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be
               opened unto you; for every one that asketh receiveth; and he that seeketh findeth;
               and to him that knocketh it shall be opened<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n337-6"/>. And he corroborates His word
               strongly and exhortates us strongly by the parable of the friend who went to his
               friend in the middle of the night and asked him for bread. 'Verily, I say unto you,
               though <choice><sic>ho</sic><corr>he</corr></choice> will not rise and give him, because he is friend, yet <pb n="338"
               />because of his importunity he will rise and give him as many as he
               needeth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n338-1"/>. And ye also: Pray and do not faint<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n338-2"/>. Blessed is the
               unspeakable encouragement of the Giver, who exhorts us saying: Ask from me and I will
               give you gifts. <pb type="external" n="503"/>And He will also provide you with all
               that is profitable, according to His knowledge. "These words are full of
               encouragement and great confidence.</p>
            <p>And as our Lord knows that He does not take away liability of deviation before the
               cup of death [is drunk], and, this being so, that man is near to a change from
               excellency to deterioration, and nature susceptible of accidents — therefore He urges
               us to continual beseechings. For if there were in this world a place of security
               whereto a man could go and thenceforth his nature would be exempt from need and his
               service from fear — then He would not have exhorted us towards prayer nor would He
               have urged us diligently. In the world to be men will not offer prayers unto God,
               with beseechings concerning various things. For in that place of freedom our nature
               will no longer be susceptible of variation, nor bound by the fear of opposition, but
               perfect in every way. Therefore His care not only drives us unto prayer and
               watchfulness, but even scourges us with the whip of temptations, in view of the
               subtlety and incomprehensibility of those things which continually happen to us and
               superate the power of our knowledge, things among which we are found continually and
               involuntarily. And even although our mind be firm and willed to the good, yet often
               His care scourges us with temptations, as the blessed Paul says: Lest I should be
               exalted through the <choice><sic>abondance</sic><corr>abundance</corr></choice> of the revelations, there was given me a
               thorn <pb type="external" n="504"/>in the flesh, the messenger of Satan to buffet me.
               For this thing I besought the Lord thrice that He might take from me temptation
               (namely that I might in freedom perform the work which He had ordered me). And He
               said unto me: My grace is sufficient for thee: for my strength is made perfect in
               weakness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n338-3"/>.</p>
            <p>Therefore<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n338-4"/>, my Lord, if this is thy will, and our childish nature so much
               needs a master who rules and exhorts that even a man who is so fond of thy love as I
               am and so <pb n="339"/>zealous a follower of good that he does not see the world at
               all because of his drunkenness in thee, so that thou hast brought me so far as to see
               revelations and visions which a fleshly tongue is not allowed to interpret, and to
               hear the sound of the service of the spiritual orders, so that I am deemed worthy of
               sight full of spiritual sanctities, that such a man as I with all this is not able to
               guard his own person, I who am a man perfect in Christ, — because there is still
               something which because of its subtleness resists the power of my knowledge — I that
               possess the mind of Christ — [if all this be so] then, my Lord, I rejoice at my
               illnesses, at troubles, reclusions, bonds, compulsions, on the part of nature or on
               the part of natural beings, or on the part of the fiend of nature.</p>
            <p>Joyfully, therefore, I will bear my illnesses, namely my temptations, which the power
               of Christ brings upon me. If, with all these, I still require the rod of temptations
               in order <pb type="external" n="505"/>to augment thy influence upon me and that I may
               be guarded by thy presence, I <choice><sic>known</sic><corr>know</corr></choice> that there is none whom thou lovest
               better than me.</p>
            <p>And because thou hast made me greater than many others and hast not given to any of
               my fellow Apostles what thou hast given to me — namely to know the glorifications of
               thy powers; and because thou hast called me an elect vessel and hast entrusted me
               with the guardianship of thy love; because of all these and that I know that the
               preaching of thy gospel has made excellent progress, while I am free from the bonds
               of temptations on account of all these things I know that thou wouldst have given
               <choice><sic>men</sic><corr>me</corr></choice> freedom, if this were profitable to me. But thou hast not wished that I
               should be without trouble and without care in this world; and thou werst not anxious
               to promote the preaching of thy gospel to the same degree as thou werst anxious that
               I should profit by my temptations, and my soul be kept healthy with thee.</p>
            <p>Therefore, o thou who art discriminating, if the gift of the temptations be so great
               that a man, even if he be as exalted and advanced in spiritual state as Paul's degree
               was, still requires fear and watchfulness and gathers profit by meeting temptations,
               who then can reach a place of security in the world of mortality full of robbers, and
               receive stability<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n341-1"/> (which <pb n="340"/>was not given to the holy angels, lest
               they should become perfect before us), thus receiving before all people, — spiritual
               and bodily ones — such a gift that, according to his wish, he should be without
               varying states at all, without a temptation even approaching to his
               deliberations?</p>
            <p>The order of this world, according to the conception of all <pb type="external"
                  n="506"/>holy writings, is this, that even if we received a thousand blows every
               day, our mind would not become humble and we would desist from the course in the
               arena; but that on account of one small cause, we gain the victory possibly and win
               our crown. This world is an arena and a running place. And this time is a time of
               struggle. And the time and the place of the struggle are not subject to a law. This
               means: the King does not set a terminus to his warriors, till the struggle is ended
               and all the world is gathered within the gate of the king of kings and it is examined
               there who has been constant in the war and has not been defeated, and who has taken
               to flight. How often will it happen that a man who was good for nothing and
               constantly beaten and thrown down because of his want of training, and who was always
               in a state of weakness, will snatch the banner from the hand of the valiant warriors
               and make his name famous above that of the doughty ones, the able and knowing
               battle-troops, and receive the crown and gifts which are honoured by all his
               fellows.</p>
            <p>Nobody, therefore, should give way to despondency. Only: he should not despise
               prayer, nor neglect to ask help from our Lord. And let us take this to heart, that,
               as long as we are in this world and dwelling in this body, even if we are lifted up
               unto the vault of heaven, it is not possible to be free from toil and injury and
               care. This is the sum of it all. Pardon me. What exceeds this is superfluous.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n337-1">Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n337-2">Cf. Book of the Dove, p. 6 and note 3</note>
            <note xml:id="n337-3">Matthew 26,41</note>
            <note xml:id="n337-4">Cf. Luke 18,1</note>
            <note xml:id="n337-5">Luke 21,36</note>
            <note xml:id="n337-6">Matthew 7,7 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n338-1">Luke 11,8</note>
            <note xml:id="n338-2">Luke 18,1</note>
            <note xml:id="n338-3">2 Corinthians 12,7 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n338-4">The following passage is put into the mouth of Paul.</note>
            <note xml:id="n339-1">ܠܐ ܡܨܛܠܝܢܘܬܐ</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
