<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 5</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 5, pp. 42-55</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="5">
            <head>V</head>
            <p>God has made great the honour of man, by the twofold teachings he has given him. And
               from every side He has opened for him a door through which he has access unto
               knowledge.</p>
            <p>Ask from nature a true witness concerning thyself, then thou wilt not err. If thou
               goest yet astray, let thyself be taught by that second witness who will bring thee
               back to the way from which thou hast erred.</p>
            <p>A distracted heart cannot help but erring. And wisdom will not open its gate before
               it.</p>
            <p>He who is able to understand through essential knowledge to what a degree of equality
               all men will come in the end, will not seek another teacher concerning the
               contemptability of the world.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="61"/>The first book given by God to the rational beings, is
               the nature of the created things. Written teachings have been added only after
               aberration.</p>
            <p>He who does not willingly remain far from things causing sin will be drawn towards
               them involuntarily. Things causing sin are wine and women, riches and bodily health.
               They are not to be called sin in themselves, but on account of man's weakness and
               their unlawful use, nature is easily drawn by them — more easily than by any other
               thing — towards different sins and therefore there is need of peculiar caution in
               regard of them. If thou rememberst continually and recognisest truly that thou art
               weak, thou wilt never overstep the borders prescribed by watchfulness. Despised above
               all things among men is poverty. But much more despised by God is haughtiness of
               heart and a disdainful spirit.</p>
            <p>Among men riches are honoured; by God a humble soul.</p>
            <pb n="43"/>
            <p>When thou intendest to begin with one of the virtues, first prepare thyself, lest, by
               the evil things which it causes, thou shouldst fall into doubt concerning the
               truth.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="62"/>If the Evil one sees some one beginning with one of the
               virtues in the fervour of faith, he attacks him by vehement and terrible temptations,
               with the intention that he be frightened by them, so that the love of his mind may
               abate and his fervour not rise again to bring him near to the works of God. And thus,
               because of fear of temptations accompanying good works [he hopes that] nobody will
               practise them anymore. Thou, however, prepare thyself to meet the evil things
               accompanying virtues, bravely and strongly; and then begin. If thou doest not expect
               evil things, do not begin with excellence. The man who is in doubt concerning the
               Lord, is persecuted by his own shadow; at the time of satiety he will be hungry and
               at the time of peace his ruin will be heavy. But whoever confides in God, his heart
               will be strong and his honour will be manifest before the crowds and his glory before
               his enemies.</p>
            <p>The commandments of God are better than the treasures of the whole earth. He who
               acquires His laws in his heart, will find the Lord in them. He who meditates upon God
               in the night, will acquire Him as a housemate. He who is pliable to His will, will
               find the angels of heaven his teachers.</p>
            <p>He who trembles before sins will pass without stumbling even through a dangerous
               place and at the time of darkness he will find a light within himself. If any one
               tremble before sins, his footsteps will be guarded by the Lord and mercy will precede
               his failures. He whose faults are small in his own eyes will fall into those which
               are worse than the former ones and it will be necessary that he pay for them
               sevenfold. Sow alms in humility and thou wilt reap mercy in the court of justice.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="63"/>Whereby thou hast lost goods, thereby thou shalt acquire
               them again. If thou hast to pay a penny to God in some way or other, He will not
               accept a pearl from thee in its place. For in this case that thing is necessary.</p>
            <p>If thou hast lost chastity, let not fornication take its place. If thou givest alms
               as a reparation, He will not accept them from thee; He postulates saintliness for
               saintliness. And if thou wrongest not the poor, let not unjust possession take the
               place of that. While thou art refraining from bread, let not injustice usurp its
               place so that thou must struggle with some other thing.</p>
            <pb n="44"/>
            <p>Oppression is eradicated by compassion and renunciation. If thou leavest the plant in
               its place, thou wilt have to struggle with some other thing, according to the word of
               the great teacher Mar Afrem.</p>
            <p>Take care not to light against heat during summer in clothes destined for winter.
               Thus each will reap, with the contrary of that with which he sows injustice. And
               every illness he will combat with its peculiar antidotum. Now thou art deadly wounded
               by envy; while thou strugglest against sleep. When sin is still green, eradicate it,
               lest it cover the whole ground. He who neglects an evil thing while it is small, will
               find it at last a hard master and he will go in bonds before it. He who treats it
               severely in the beginning, will easily rule it. He who bears injustice with gladness
               while victory is in his hand, he has received from God the consolation of his faith
               clearly <pb type="external" n="64"/>manifested. And he who bears oppression in
               humility, has reached perfection. The angels will admire him. There is no profitable
               action more difficult and more meritorious.</p>
            <p>Do not believe thyself strong before thou hast been led into temptations and thou
               hast found thyself steadfast in them. In all things thou hast to try thyself in this
               way.</p>
            <p>Acquire glory on account of the faith of thy heart, then thou wilt tread upon the
               neck of thy enemies, and thou wilt find thy mind humble. Do not confide in thy
               strength lest thou be left to the weakness of thy nature and thou learnest thy
               weakness in thy fall; nor in thy knowledge, lest thou be surrounded in thought with
               hidden ambushes and becomest confused.</p>
            <p>Acquire a humble tongue; then disdain will never hurt thee; and pleasant lips; then
               thou wilt be found a friend of every one. Do not boast of any thing with thy tongue,
               because among creatures there is nothing exempt from change and thy shame will be
               double when thou art found the contrary [of what thou didst boast of]. Everything of
               which thou boastest before men, will surely be altered by God, so that thou mayest
               have a cause for humility so that thou judge God's knowledge to be all, and believe
               not that there is anything true in creatures. And when thou thinkest thus, thy eyes
               will at all times be fixed upon Him.</p>
            <p>[Divine] care surrounds all men at all times; but it is not seen, save only by those
               who have purified themselves from <pb n="45"/>sins and think of God perpetually. To
               these then it is revealed <pb type="external" n="65"/>clearly; for when they have
               been led into great temptations for the sake of truth, then they receive a faculty of
               perception clearly as if with the eyes of the flesh. [They receive it] when they want
               it, in a sensible way, in accordance with the kind and the cause of the temptation,
               in order to strengthen their courage. As in the case of Jacob and Joshua the son of
               Nun, Hananya and his companions, Petrus and others, to whom the figure of a man
               appeared in order to encourage them and to console their faith.</p>
            <p>If thou sayest that these things were acts of Providence of a universal nature, let
               then the holy martyrs console thee, who sometimes together, sometimes one by one in
               separate places have suffered for God. Not only a hidden force was with them, by
               which the members of their bodies were fortified against being hanged in irons and
               against torments of all kinds, things beyond natural power — but sometimes also holy
               angels were seen by them manifestly, in order that every man should know that God's
               care is with those who suffer for His sake for any reason, so that they themselves
               might receive encouragement and their torturers be ashamed. For as the former were
               made conspicuous by such visions, to the same degree the latter were tormented by
               their endurance.</p>
            <p>And what shall we say about many of the solitaries and strangers and true monks, who
               have made waste land habitable and an encamping ground of the angels, who visited
               them on account of their worthy behaviour? As true comrades [serving] one Lord the
               heavenly hosts mingled [with them] in their <pb type="external" n="66"/>dwelling
               place, solitaries who during their whole life loved solitude, who made holes and
               rocks their dwelling places, who gladly suffered cold and heat for the love of God.
               And because they left the earth and loved heaven like the angels, the angels have not
               concealed themselves from their sight. But sometimes they taught them concerning
               behaviour. And again they answered the questions they asked them concerning other
               things. And sometimes the angels showed them the way when they wandered through the
               desert; sometimes they delivered them from temptations; sometimes they saved them
               from some net of danger which suddenly, without their foreseeing it, threatened them,
               some serpent for instance, or falling from a rock, or a stone that suddenly fell down
               with violence from a height.</p>
            <pb n="46"/>
            <p>Sometimes, also under the attacks of the open battles of Satan, the angels showed
               themselves to them manifestly, and clearly announced that they were sent in order to
               help them and encouraged them by their words. Sometimes also they cured their pain
               and healed some injuries which had befallen them in some way or other, by the touch
               of their hands. Sometimes again they imparted to their bodies, which had been
               weakened by abstention from all food, by their words or by the sudden <pb
                  type="external" n="67"/>touch of their hands, a force foreign to nature, adducing
               in some secret way a force unto the lowered nature. Sometimes they brought them food,
               warm bread and olives, and to some of them various fruits. Others they informed
               concerning the time of their death. And how long must be the enumeration of things
               concerning the love of the holy angels towards our race and concerning the care they
               showed unto the righteous, as great brothers who fostered and guarded their little
               ones. All this serves to make clear for every one how near God is to His friends and
               how much care He bestows on those who entrust their life to His hands and follow Him
               with a serene heart.</p>
            <p>If it is certain to thee and thou believest that God cares for thee, thou needest not
               be anxious for thy body nor have care concerning the guiding of thyself by means. But
               if thou cloubtest this and desirest to care for thyself, without God, thou art more
               wretched than any man, and what does life mean to thee? Throw thy care on
               God[#n46-1], that thou be strengthened against all fear. He who once has entrusted
               his life to God, will dwell in mental peace.</p>
            <p>Without renunciating possessions, the soul cannot be liberated from confusion of
               thought. And without quiescence of the senses, peace of mind cannot be
               perceived[#n46-2]. And without <pb type="external" n="68"/>entering into temptations,
               spiritual wisdom cannot be acquired. And without constant reciting, subtlety of
               thought cannot be learned. And without the deliberations being set at peace the mind
               cannot be moved by hidden mysteries. And without the confidence of faith one cannot
               venture to throw his soul amidst sorrowful and hard circumstances. Without the
               practical experience of God's care the heart is not able to confide in God. And when
               the soul does not taste sufferings for the sake of Christ, it is not united with Him
               in knowledge.</p>
            <pb n="47"/>
            <p>Deem him a man of God, who constantly takes upon himself the lot of want, being moved
               by great compassion. He who does good to the poor finds God his provider. He who
               suffers want for His sake finds Him to be a great treasure. God does not need
               anything; only He rejoices when anyone satisfies or honours His image[#n47-1] for His
               sake.</p>
            <p>When anyone asks thee and thou hast, do not say in thy heart: I will keep it for
               myself in order to have more comfort by it and I will let him pass quickly; God will
               provide for him from another; I will bestow it upon myself. Do not speak thus. For in
               this way think iniquitous men, and people who do not know God deliberate thus,
               fostering such thoughts. But a righteous man does not give his honour to another one
               nor does he let slip the opportunity for bounty. God will provide for him certainly
               in some other way; if He knows that he is in trouble. God will not abandon any one.
               But thou art willing <pb type="external" n="69"/>immediately to leave God's honour
               and to throw His bounty from thee. On the other hand rejoice if thou possessest and
               give, saying: Glory to thee, o God, who hast granted unto me that I find some one to
               comfort. And if thou possessest not, rejoice the more, thanking God with many
               thanksgivings, saying: I thank thee, o God, who hast granted me the honour of
               becoming poor for Thy sake, and who hast deemed me worthy to taste sufferings
               enjoined in Thy commandments namely illnesses and poverty such as the saints have
               tasted who have gone this way.</p>
            <p>And if thou art ill, say: Blessed are those who find in the things which God sends us
               for our profit, the aim for which God has destined them. God sends sickness for the
               sake of the health of the soul.</p>
            <p>One of the saints once said: The following I have taken as a sign. When a solitary
               does not serve God in the right way, and is not zealous in His works, God certainly
               will send him a temptation to occupy his thoughts, lest he be wholly idle and, by
               complete idleness, his mind turn aside to thinking of the things of the left hand.
               But if he is not willing to think of excellence, the influence of the temptations
               will cause him to think of it and not to think of idle things. This God does with
               every man who loves Him. When He sees that he begins <pb n="48"/>to disdain His
               works, he sends a heavy sorrow in order to make him wise and to chastise him.
               Therefore, when such <pb type="external" n="70"/>people call to Him, He does not pay
               attention, nor does He hasten to free them, till they have become weary and know that
               they have to bear these things on account of their neglect. 'When ye spread forth
               your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you; yea, when ye make many prayers, I will
               not hear'[#n48-1]. Even if this was said to others, still it is certainly applicable
               to those who leave the way. But if God is so compassionate, why do we then so
               frequently knock at His door in trouble and pray, and yet He turns away from our
               prayer? He says: Behold, the Lord's hand is not shortened, that it cannot save; nor
               His ear heavy, that it cannot hear. But your iniquities have separated between you
               and your God, and your sins have hid His face from you, that He will not
               hear[#n48-2]. Remember the Lord at all times, then He will remember thee when evil
               approaches unto thee. He has made thy nature a receptacle of accident. And in the
               world where He has created and left thee He has made frequent the causes of accidents
               and temptations. He has made thy nature a small receptacle of these things. Evil
               things are not far from thee, neither are they a few in number. For they rise from
               within thee when He gives a sign, and from under thy feet and from the place where
               thou art standing. But like one eyelid is near the other, so temptations are near the
               children of men.</p>
            <p>With wisdom God has provided these things for thee in this way, for thy profit, that
               thou mayest continually knock at His door and that, for fear of sorrowful events, the
               thought of Him may constantly recur to thy mind and thou be near to God in constant
               prayer and sanctified by constant thought of Him in thy heart.</p>
            <p>And when thou callest unto Him and He answers thee, thou <pb type="external" n="71"
               />wilt know that thy saviour is God. And thou wilt perceive thy God who has created
               thee and is thy provider and preserver, therein that He has made in thy behalf two
               worlds. One for thy instruction, as it were a school for a short time; and another
               one, a paternal home and thy abode for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>He has not made thee apathetic, lest thou shouldst desire divine rank and receive
               what Satan received. Nor has He made <pb n="49"/>thee incapable of error or, lest
               thou shouldst be like the beings which are bound and thou shouldst receive thy good
               and thy evil without profit or remuneration as the other corporeal beings on the
               earth. How many blows and humiliations together with thanksgivings are born from the
               capacity for affections, and fear, and also error, is manifest for every one so that
               it should be known that our zeal for righteousness and our turning aside from evil
               are of our will, and that the honour and disdain, caused thereby, should be put to
               our credit. Thus we are put to shame and we fear on account of disdain; but we thank
               God and press towards the good on account of honour.</p>
            <p>All these instructions He has multiplied for thee, lest freed from them on account of
               thy not needing them or thy nature not being capable of them, exalted above fear and
               affecting things, thou shouldst forget God and turn away from Him and invent many
               gods. For though subjected to affections and want, which scourges were sent against
               them on account of paltry <pb type="external" n="72"/>riches and short-lived temporal
               power and precarious health, — still many have not only invented many gods, but have
               even ventured in their insanity to pretend to be of divine nature.</p>
            <p>Therefore He has turned thee away from all these things through that which troubles
               thee from time to time, lest He should be angry with thee on account of thy turning
               aside and destroy thee from before Him in punishment.</p>
            <p>I omit the ungodliness and the sins that arise from health and lack of fear and
               comfort, even though that which has been mentioned above should not happen[#n49-1].
               Therefore, by sufferings and distress He has caused thee frequently to recall Him in
               thy heart; and by fear of adversities He incites thee to turn towards the gate of his
               mercy. By liberating thee from these [troubles] He sows in thee causes of love unto
               Him. And when thou hast found love he brings thee near to the honour of the sons; He
               shows thee the richness of His bounty and the steadfastness of His care for thee.
               Then He will make thee perceive the holiness of His honour and the hidden mysteries
               of the nature of His greatness. How shouldst thou have become acquainted with these
               things if there had not been adversities? For through these the love of God is able
               to increase, viz. by understanding His acts of bounty and by recalling His various
                  <pb n="50"/>acts of care. All this good is born for thee from things causing
               grief, if thou knowest to give thanks.</p>
            <p>Therefore remember God, that He may remember thee constantly; and when He remembers
               thee and saves thee, thou wilt receive all these goods. Forget Him not in idle
               distraction, lest He also forget thee in thy temptations.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="73"/>In prosperity be near to Him and obedient, that thou
               mayest have freedom of speech with Him in trouble because of thy constantly being
               near to Him in thy heart by means of thy prayer. Sit before His face all thy time,
               thinking of Him and recollecting Him in thy heart, lest, seeing Him only after long
               thou shouldst lack freedom of speech with Him on account of bashfulness. A high
               degree of freedom of speech is born from constant intercourse. Constant intercourse
               with men is of a bodily nature; that with God is psychic meditation and offerings in
               prayers.</p>
            <p>On account of its intensity this meditation is sometimes mingled with ecstasy. For
               the heart of those who seek the Lord rejoices. Seek the Lord, ye sinners and be
               strengthened in hope in your thoughts. Seek His face by repentance at all time and
               you will be sanctified by the holiness of His face and you will be purified from your
               unrighteousness. Speed unto the Lord, ye unrighteous, the Lord who forgives
               unrighteousness and effaces sins. For He has sworn: I have no pleasure in the death
               of the wicked; but that he turn from his way and live[#n50-1]. I have spread out my
               hands all the day unto a rebellious and disobedient people[#n50-2]. And why will ye
               die, O house of Jacob?[#n50-3] Turn unto me, then I will turn unto you[#n50-4]. And
               by Ezekiel He says: When the wicked turns from his way unto the Lord and do that
               which is lawful and right, the sins he has<pb type="external" n="74"/>committed will
               not be remembered but he shall live, sayeth the Lord[#n50-5]. Thus it is also with
               the righteous; when he turneth from his righteousness and comitteth sin and iniquity,
               the righteousness he has done will not be remembered but I will lay a stumbling block
               before him and by the iniquity he has done he shall die if he remains steadfast in
               it[#n50-6]. Why is this? Because the iniquitous will not stumble on account of his
               iniquity after he turns unto the Lord. But the righteousness of the righteous <pb
                  n="51"/>will not save him when he sins, if he builds his building on that
               foundation.</p>
            <p>And to Jeremia He spake thus: Take a roll of a book, and write therein all the words
               that I have spoken unto thee, from the day of Josia the king of Juda even unto this
               day. It may be that [the house of Juda] will hear and fear and they may return every
               man from his evil way and turn again unto me, that I may forgive their sins[#n51-1].
               And the sage has said: He that covereth his sins, shall not prosper. But whoso
               confessed! and forsaketh them, shall have mercy from God[#n51-2].</p>
            <p>And Jesaja, who was rich in revelations, says: Seek ye the Lord and call ye upon Him
               when ye have found Him. And when He is near let the sinner forsake his way and the
               unrighteous man his thoughts. Let him turn unto me and I will have mercy upon him and
               to our God for He will abundantly pardon. For my thoughts are not your thoughts
               neither are my ways your ways[#n51-3]. Wherefore do ye[#n51-4] spend money on that
               which is not bread? and your labour for that which satisfieth not? Hearken diligently
               unto me, and eat ye that which is good. Come unto me, hear and your soul shall
               live[#n51-5]. <pb type="external" n="75"/>When thou keepest the ways of the Lord and
               doest His will, then thou wilt confide in the Lord. Then thou wilt call on Him and He
               will answer thee; thou wilt cry and He will say: Lo, here I am.</p>
            <p>The wicked when evil befalls him has confidence in God to call on Him. And he is not
               able to expect His salvation, because he has left His ways in the days of his
               prosperity.</p>
            <p>Seek a helper for thyself before thou hast to struggle.</p>
            <p>Seek a physician for thyself before thou art ill. Pray before distress has reached
               thee then in the time of distress thou wilt find prayer(?) and it will answer thee.
               Pray and ask before thou stumblest. Prepare thy gifts before thou makest a vow, they
               are thy provisions.</p>
            <p>The ark was constructed in time of peace. A hundred years before its wood was
               planted. So when anger came, the wicked who had been comfortable in their wickedness,
               were confounded. But the ark was a refuge for the righteous.</p>
            <p>The wicked shuts his mouth during prayer. Inward baseness takes away freedom of
               speech from the heart.</p>
            <pb n="52"/>
            <p>Steadfastness of the heart makes tears of joy to flow during the imploration [of
               God].</p>
            <p>Strong endurance of injustice borne by free will purifies the heart. Endurance of
               injustice is based on contempt for the world. That a man remains steadfast during
               oppression without being distressed, is caused by the fact that the heart begins to
               see the truth. Joy on account of oppression and injustice borne by free will, exalts
               the heart. No one can bear oppression and injustice with a glad will, save those
               whose deliberations have wholly become dead to the world.</p>
            <p>Those whose thoughts are wholly filled with the odour of <pb type="external" n="76"
               />this life, are made to blaze with anger at once through vain glory; or they fall
               into thoughts of spite, born of [the love of vain glory]. O how difficult is this
               excellence, and how honoured it is with God! He who denies this behaviour, has to go
               abroad and to leave his country. It is difficult for a man to accomplish this exalted
               excellence in his country; the eminent and the strong only are able to bear the grief
               that is born of this behaviour, among their acquaintances and also those who in their
               lifetime have become dead to this life and have abandoned hope of the consolation of
               this time. As Grace is near to humility, so are difficult accidents to
               haughtiness.</p>
            <p>The heart of the Lord is towards the humble, to comfort them. The face of the Lord is
               against the haughty to humiliate them. Humility receives compassion, continually. But
               hardness of heart and unbelief meet hardships continually that seem hopeless till of
               a sudden evil rises against them and they are delivered to destruction.</p>
            <p>Make thyself small among men, then He will exalt thee even above the heads of the
               people. Let thy prostration be low before all men and be the first to salute; then
               thou wilt be honoured more than he who brings gold from Ophir. Be despised and
               rejected in thine own eyes, then thou wilt see the glory of God within thyself.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="77"/>Where humility sprouts, there glory will rise. If thou
               strivest publicly after dishonour among men he will make thy honour great. And if
               thou art humble in thy heart, He will show thee His glory in thy heart. Be disdained
               in thy greatness, not great in thy being disdained. Learn to be disdained, while
               being full of the honour of the Lord; not, to be honoured while being injured by
               ulcers within. Reject honour, then thou <pb n="53"/>wilt be honoured. Do not love it,
               lest thou be rejected. If thou pursuest honour, it will flee from thee. If thou
               fleest from it, it will rise for thee from the place where thou hidest thyself and it
               will be a herald of thy humility to every one.</p>
            <p>If thou givest thyself to disdain in order to be honoured, the Lord will confound
               thee. If thou rejectest thyself for the sake of truth He will command the creatures
               to praise thee. And they will reveal to thee the glory of the creator who from
               eternity speaks through them and they will glorify thee as the creator, because thou
               art His true image. [d]</p>
            <p>Has anyone found a man whose behaviour is exalted, who is despised among men and who
               is enlightened and wise and poor in spirit? Blessed is he who has humbled himself in
               all things, for he will be magnified in all things. He who has humbled and made
               himself small for the sake of God, will be glorified by God. And whoever for His sake
               is hungry and thirsty, He will give to drink him from His good a wine causing a
               drunkenness that never leaves those who drink it. And he who goes naked for His sake
               will be clad by Him with a garment of glory. And he who is poor and indigent <pb
                  type="external" n="78"/>for His sake, his consolation will be established in His
               true richness. Make thyself disdained for the sake of God, then thy glory will be
               great, even if thou doest not perceive it.</p>
            <p>During thy whole life deem thyself as a sinner, then thou wilt found to be a
               righteous man during thy whole life. Be despised though wise, and do not err in thy
               wisdom. Be simple in thy wisdom and do not assume the appearance of being wise if
               thou art simple. If humility elevates the despised how,[e] much more will it elevate
               the honoured.</p>
            <p>Flee from praise, then thou wilt be praised. Fear haughtiness, then thou wilt be
               exalted. For pride was not assigned to the children of man, nor haughtiness of heart
               to those born from a woman.</p>
            <p>If thou hast voluntarily renunciated the whole body of the world, do not quarrel with
               anyone concerning small parts of it.</p>
            <p>If thou hast rejected glory, flee from those who hunt praise.</p>
            <p>Flee from possessors as from possessions. Depart from the luxurious, as from luxury.
               Flee from the lascivious, as from fornication. If the memory of their habits troubles
               the mind, how much more if one see and be near to them. Be near to the excellent;
               through them thou wilt be near unto God.</p>
            <pb n="54"/>
            <p>Be an ascete with the humble, to learn from his ways. If to see his habits is
               profitable to those who see him, how much more the character of his behaviour and
               teachings received from his very lips.</p>
            <p>Love the poor; through them thou wilt find mercy. Do not approach unto the
               quarrelsome, lest thou be compelled to leave thy peaceful customs.</p>
            <p>Flee not from the ugliness of the illness of the sick, for thou art also clad with
               flesh. Do not contend with the bitter in <pb type="external" n="79"/>heart, lest thou
               be beaten with the rod with which they are beaten and seeking a consolator, wilt not
               find any. Do not reject the cripples lest thou enter Sheol with them.</p>
            <p>Love the sinners but reject their works. Do not despise them because of their
               shortcomings, lest thou be tempted by the same. Remember that thou sharest in the
               stink of Adam and that thou too art clad with his illness. To him who needs
               passionate prayer and soft words, do not give blame in stead, lest thou cause his
               destruction and his soul be demanded from thy hand. Resemble the physicians who use
               cold medicines against symptoms of fever.</p>
            <p>Compel thyself to show honour to thy fellow man, when thou meetest him; and kiss his
               hand and his foot, and warm thy heart with love unto him, piously. And take his hands
               several times and place them upon thy eyes and caress them with great honour. And
               attribute to his person beautiful things, that do not belong to him. And also when he
               is absent, speak about him fine and beautiful things and call him by several
               honourable names. By these things and the like, thou compellest him not only unto the
               desire of beautiful things, since he will be ashamed of the renown thou imputest him
               without his deserving it and so thou wilt be able to sow in him the seed of excellent
               things, but by means of these habits and the <pb type="external" n="80"/>like to
               which thou accustomest thyself, thou wilt found in thyself peaceful and humble
               customs and be liberated from many severe struggles, against which others learn to
               guard themselves by steady works. And not only this. But if he, who receives these
               honours from thee, has any shortcoming or fault of will, he will easily acquire from
               thee healing, if thou lettest him clearly perceive [it] but for an instant only; for
               he will be ashamed because of the honour shown to him and because of the sign of love
               he constantly perceives in thee.</p>
            <pb n="55"/>
            <p>This be thy aim regarding all men. And when thou becomest angry at any one and
               zealous for the sake of faith, or on account of his evil works, or thou reprehendest
               and vituperatest him, then be cautious. We all have a just judge in heaven. But if
               thou art merciful and seekest to turn him unto the truth, thou hast to suffer for
               him. And with tears and in love thou must speak to him without being enraged against
               him, effacing all sign of hostility from thy face. Love does not know how to be
               angry; it is not indignant, it does not despise so as to cause suffering. Wherever
               the sign of love and knowledge is present, it is profound humility rising from the
               inner mind.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n46-1"> Ps. 55,23.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46-2"> Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n47-1"> viz. man</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-1">Is. 1,15</note>
            <note xml:id="n48-2"> Is. 59,1 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n49-1"> viz. that creatures pretend to be of divine nature.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-1">Ez. 33,11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-2">Is. 65,2.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-3">Ez. 33,11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-4">Zach. 1,3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-5">Cf. Ez. 33,9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n50-6">Cf. Ez. 33,8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-1">Cf. Jeremia 36,2 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-2">Prov. 28,13.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-3">Is. 55,6-8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-4">The Syriac text adds not.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51-5">Cf. Is. 55,2 sq.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
