<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 21</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 21, pp. 110-111.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="21">
            <head>XXI</head>
            <p>On that which happens during prayer [unto those who live] in solitude</p>
            <p>Who is he that knows that delightful bending of the knees, when the tongue is silent
               and the heart silently utters some glorification, and its delightful emotion does not
               abate, the <pb type="external" n="163"/>body resting on the knees in silence? Blessed
               who eats from these things perpetually. But they do not happen at will, nor when one
               seeks them. This is in part the delight which is given for the consolation of him who
               walks without a blame before the Lord in the course of solitude.</p>
            <p>If he continues this course in all simplicity, and seeks the purity of his service,
               and if his behaviour is worthy, after some time he will be deemed worthy of the
               things mentioned above.</p>
            <pb n="111"/>
            <p>As to those who are novices in this course and who have a fixed aim, Grace at first
               will make them apt for the taste of these and similar things by recitation and it
               will draw their thoughts towards its self, away from earthly thoughts. Then they will
               work and wake and pray without becoming fatigued. Unto those who are trained to some
               extent in the mysteries of solitude, apperceptive power during prayer and service
               will be imparted.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
