<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 38</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 38, pp. 194-197.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="38">
            <head>XXXVIII</head>
            <head><pb type="external" n="291"/>Short sentences concerning the distinction of the mind’s
               impulses</head>
            <p>Pusillanimity is a sign of despondency; the mother of both is negligence.</p>
            <p>A timorous man shows that he suffers from two illnesses: from love of the body and
               from want of faith. Love of the body is a sign of unbelief. But he that despises it,
               shows concerning himself that he trusts God and expects the future things.</p>
            <p>If there is anyone who has approached God without being troubled, try then on thy
               part to resemble him.</p>
            <p>Courage of the heart and contempt for danger arise from one of two causes: either
               from hardness of heart, or from a deep belief in God. The former is accompanied by
               haughtiness, the latter by humbleness of heart.</p>
            <p>It is impossible for a man to acquire confidence in God, if he has not before
               fulfilled His will in part. Confidence in God and manliness of heart rise from the
               testimony of conscience. For on account of the true testimony of our mind we acquire
               confidence in God. The testimony of the mind has its origin therein that a man is not
               despised by his soul for neglect of his duty, as far as this is possible.</p>
            <p>If our heart does not despise us, then we are frank with God. Frankness has its
               origin in a firm behaviour and in an unstained mind.</p>
            <p>It is hard to serve as a slave to the body. He that is aware of his hope, though to a
               small extent, will refuse to <pb type="external" n="292"/>serve again the stern will
               of this hard master.</p>
            <p>Endurance in perfect silence and preservation of solitude arise from one of three
               causes: from the [love of] glory among fellow-men; or the fervent zeal for
               excellence; or a certain <pb n="195"/>inward working of God towards which the mind is
               attracted. He that is destitute of the two latter causes, will suffer from the first
               as it were by necessity.</p>
            <p>Excellence does not consist in many manifest distinctions of bodily performances, but
               in a heart prudent in its hope, accompanying the works with a right intention. For
               often these performances do not favour service, and the mind will be able to gain
               profit even without them. But without the prudence of the heart the body cannot
               profit even when it performs service. For if there is an opportunity to perform
               beautiful works, a godly man cannot refrain from showing his love, in the performance
               of manifest deeds. The former kind is always <choice><sic>succesful</sic><corr>successful</corr></choice>; the latter
               sometimes, and sometimes not.</p>
            <p>Do not reckon it a small thing when the causes of the affections are afar off and
               removed from a man. The stirring of the inferior limbs which comes quickly into
               existence, without deliberations, that is to say impure pleasure which springs from
               under a wall with fervour and captivates the soul with madness, <pb type="external"
                  n="293"/>the will being of no use — undoubtedly arises in the body from a repleted
               belly.</p>
            <p>As a strong weapon in this strife reckon this, that a man be far from seeing women.
               What nature works by its power, even the foe cannot work it. Do not think that nature
               will forget till death that which God has sown and hidden in its roots, serving for
               the carrying on of our race and for testing us by strife. So every desire, whatever
               it be, is lulled to sleep in our limbs by keeping things at a distance; and its
               memory is given over to absorption and oblivion.</p>
            <p>Thoughts of far off things which make a simple passage through the mind, are
               different from the dark and cold impulses that arise from the soul itself. Those
               thoughts also which arise from living contact which immerses the mind in a sight not
               to be forgotten and which excites passion near-at-hand, feeding it as oil feeds the
               flame of the lamp which was already flickering and nearly extinguished, are different
               from the stirring of the sea of the body through the impulses which agitate it
               against the ship of the mind.</p>
            <p>The emotionability which exclusively rises from nature and which by God the creator
               has been deposited in us in order to educate the world of the body, is not able,
               without an increase from without, to bereave the will of its clearness, to <pb
                  n="196"/>confuse it so that it lose its chastity. For God does not impart strength
               to nature so that it overcome the virtuous will.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="294"/>But when a man is defeated by anger and by desire, it is
               not that which lies in nature which compels him to leave nature's domain and to cut
               the bonds of duty, but it is something which we add to nature by the intermediary of
               the will. All that God has made, He has made beautiful and in due proportions. And as
               long as the measure of natural things is rightly preserved in us they do not cause us
               to be swept from the way of God's law as it were by a deluge; only peaceful impulses
               stir in a body provided with the faculty of emotions, so long as we only know that
               passion exists, but not so when we also experience that it allures, or that it
               troubles the course of chastity and that it causes confusion or that it changes the
               state of peace into anger. If, however, we sometimes crave for things of the senses
               which are usually the source of unnatural anger, or for copious food and drink, or
               for constantly having the opportunity of seeing a woman near us, or of hearing tales
               about her which use to enflame in the body the fire of desires — then we cause the
               natural state of peace to be changed into that of bestiality, be it on account of the
               many humours in the arteries, or by various sights of [worldly] things.</p>
            <p>It occurs also on account of that abandonment that arises from presumption. But this
               does not really belong to this category. The former cases we call strife for freedom
               and they belong to the common way of nature. Strife through abandonment arising from
               presumption we experience when we are occupied by labours and watchfulness for a long
               time and <pb type="external" n="295"/>then, in spite of them, the force of desire
               rushes in upon us with unnatural vehemence. But in other cases such events take place
               on account of our relaxation.</p>
            <p>When nature is augmented in force by the senses or by the belly, it is not to be
               persuaded to keep henceforth the original measure of its stamp. He that rejects
               troubles and loneliness is involuntarily compelled to love sins. Without these we are
               not able to remain far from spiritual allurements. The latter diminish in accordance
               with the growth of the former. For troubles dissipate the pleasure of the affections;
               consolation, on the other hand, strengthens and induces them.</p>
            <p>So it is clear that God and His angels rejoice at troubles;</p>
            <pb n="197"/>
            <p><persName>Satan</persName> and his servants, however, at consolation. For if God's commandments are
               performed under bodily tortures and we reject these, it is clear that we contrive to
               reject Him that is the giver of the commandments. As by the affections, which are the
               offspring of consolation, we annihilate that which is the cause of excellence, namely
               hardship, so we make room for the affections to the same extent as we admit
               consolation. For in a tortured body deliberations cannot be distracted by idle
               things. When a man bears tortures with gladness, he has also strength enough to check
               the deliberations; because even the deliberations do not abhor labours.</p>
            <p>Thus, when a man flogs himself with troubles, on account of the recollection of his
               previous sins, God, on His side, will <pb type="external" n="296"/>care for his
               peace; because He rejoices when He sees that the sinner himself has executed a
               judgment against himself because of his deviation from His way — a sign of
               repentance. And as he greatly troubles himself, so to the same extent the signs of
               honour granted to him by God, will increase. Every joy which is not caused by
               excellence will at once stir emotions of desire in him that has found it. This is to
               be understood of all desires connected with the affections, not of the natural ones
               only.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
