<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 65</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 65, pp. 297-311.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="65">
            <head>LXV</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="443"/>Good advice giving instructions concerning watchfulness
               and directions concerning the way of discipline by which a man may acquire a high
               rank</p>
            <p>Repentance<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n297-1"/> is the mother of life. It opens to us its gate when we flee from
               all things. The grace which we have lost, after baptism, by a lax behaviour, is
               restored in us by repentance, through discrimination of mind. From water and spirit
               we have put on Christ, without perceiving His glory. By repentance we enter into His
               delight through the discriminating love which rises in us.</p>
            <p>He who is destitute of repentance, is destitute of future delight. He who is near to
               all, is far from repentance. He who is far from all, with discrimination, is the true
               repentant. As soon as a man withdraws from men and concentrates upon himself,
               impulses of repentance will show themselves in his mind. He receives the seed of life
               from grace and, as an embryo, the affection of discrimination moves in him, and in
               his heart is stirred the thought of eternal life in the future and the hope of
               resurrection and the thought of Judgment.</p>
            <p>Do not think that without divine grace suffering falls into the mind, which receives
               [it] secretly, as a gift through divine mercy, because of a sudden contrition and a
               longing after life. As also the blessed Euagrius says<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n297-1"/>: A purifying drug is
               the <pb type="external" n="444"/>hot contrition of the soul, which is given by the
               Lord through the angels to those who repent, that through diligence <pb n="298"
               />purification from the affections may be granted. Farther he says: The fire of a
               furnace is the hot contrition of the soul, which through the grace of Christ happens
               to the soul at the time of prayer so that the thoughts attain contemplation. Its lack
               is cured by living water.</p>
            <p>The beginning of repentance is humbleness without artifice. Splendid garments are a
               confusion of repentance. The way towards wisdom is the regulation of the limbs.
               Bodily effervences are a confusion of wisdom. True wisdom is looking towards God.
               Looking towards God is silence of the deliberations. Solitude of the mind is
               quietness with discrimination. The moisture of the senses is a fountain of
               deliberations. Apperception in God is the depth of humbleness.</p>
            <p>True contemplation is the mortification of the heart. The heart which is really dead
               to the world, is wholly astir in God. True mortification is the motion of life. It is
               better to smell life by desisting from all, than to build life by desisting from
               smelling. Better is he that builds his soul than he that builds the world. It is
               better to imbibe life than to distribute life. He whose outward limbs are dead, his
               inner emotions are alive. He whose outward limbs are alive, has killed the limbs of
               wisdom. Humbleness with discrimination is true knowledge. True knowledge is a
               fountain of humbleness. He that is humble in his heart, is humble in his body. He who
               is audacious in his body, is audacious in his heart. He who is <pb type="external"
                  n="445"/>perturbed in his body, is perturbed in his heart. He who is perturbed in
               his heart, is foolish in his mind. He who is foolish in his mind, his ways are evil.
               Whose way is evil, he is dead in life.</p>
            <p>If thou lovest humbleness, do not love finery. A man who loves finery cannot bear
               contempt. And to take to lonely works, is difficult to him. And he is ashamed of
               submitting to him that is inferior to himself.</p>
            <p>The servant of God does not adorn his body. Know that every man who loves bodily
               finery is sick in his inner being, though he performs beautiful [works]. And to every
               one who loves visible profit, it is impossible to acquire true love of any one. And
               every one who runs after honour, is a slave of this world. If those who do these
               things are disliked by thee, then restrain thyself from the same things.</p>
            <p>Humbleness and chastity are promoted by the same idea <pb n="299"/>of contempt. And
               from him that loves honour and finery thou requirest not the former properties in
               their truth. If thou lovest chastity, do not love distraction. Things which happen to
               thee through divagation do not allow thee to cling to chastity with caution. No one
               who loves distraction, is chaste. And do not believe that any one who converses with
               lay people, is humble. Every one who loves God loves a solitary life. That a man who
               is given to distraction should guard truth in his soul without a stain, is
               impossible.</p>
            <p>Many show the appearance of repentance; but only he <pb type="external" n="446"
               />possesses it in truth, that is grieved in heart. Many run to find the affection of
               the heart; but only he finds it in truth, that possesses continual silence. Every one
               who is a servant of God, loves grief.</p>
            <p>Every one who possesses profuse speech is certainly empty within, though he tells
               amazing things.</p>
            <p>Inward grief is a bridle of the senses.</p>
            <p>If thou lovest truth, thou must love silence. This will make thee illuminated in God
               like the sun and it will deliver thee from the idle thoughts of ignorance; silence
               will even unite thee with God.</p>
            <p>When thy kneeling gives thee delight, do not hasten to reach its end. Would that it
               never ended as long as thou art in this life. When thy mind is concentrated, do not
               cut off thy prayer. Do not count as idleness a long concentrated prayer, as against
               the long recitation of Psalms. Love kneeling during prayer better than the sound of
               the sentences. If it profits thee, then accomplish it instead of thy service.</p>
            <p>If the gift of tears be given thee during thy service, do not deem the delight which
               is in it as a pause in thy service. For the gift of tears is the accomplishment of
               prayer.</p>
            <p>Do not wonder if sometimes, while thou art kneeling in prayer, thy mind, being
               concentrated upon it, desist from praying. This thou wilt find during service as well
               as during recitation. When thy mind is distracted, it will rather adhere to
               recitation than to prayer. Thy method of recitation has to be parallel to the scope
               of thy discipline. Not all books are useful for the concentration of the mind. Most
               books containing <pb type="external" n="447"/>instruction are not useful for
               purification. Various books cause to thee distraction of mind. Know that not every
               book containing instruction concerning the fear of God, is also useful <pb n="300"
               />for the purification of the inner being and the concentration of the deliberations.
               Do not dispute about the exact significance of these things with him that does not
               know the truth.</p>
            <p>Love rest more than labours. Honour recitation, if possible, more than
               standing<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n300-1"/>; for it is a source of pure prayer. But there is no reason at all
               to despise standing. Beware of snares.</p>
            <p>Recitation of Psalms is the root of discipline. But know this, that the sentences
               [sung] with a distracted mind suit better bodily labour. Mental grief is better than
               bodily fatigue. At the time of weariness be accustomed to spur on thy zeal somewhat.
               For the heart greatly needs to be alert to render fervent the emotions of the soul.
               As against desire, so natural warmth is also helpful at the time of weariness; for it
               chases the cold from the soul. Usually weariness befalls us at two occasions: through
               a heavy stomach and through great weakness caused by labours.</p>
            <p>The regulation of service is the light of the mind. There is nothing like
               knowledge.</p>
            <p>Let every prayer which thou offerest during the night, be honoured in thy eyes above
               all labours of the day. Do not make heavy thy stomach, lest thy mind become confused
               and <pb type="external" n="448"/>thyself troubled by distraction while standing
               during the night; and thy limbs be lax and thyself filled wholly with relaxation; thy
               soul be dark and thy impulses troubled, and thyself absolutely unable to concentrate
               them upon the sentences on account of darkness; and the taste of everything become
               weak to thee; and the sentences of the Psalms sung keep not their sweetness to thee,
               sentences the discriminations of which the mind used to taste with delight on account
               of its swiftness and illumination.</p>
            <p>When the order of the night-service is troubled, then the mind will also be confused
               during the service of the day and proceed in darkness, without taking delight in
               recitation, as usually. For it is as if a cloud lies over the impulses, when they are
               in emotion in prayer or in meditation. The delight which during the day is lavished
               upon the ascetic is poured on the watchful mind on account of the light of the
               nightly service.</p>
            <p>From him who has not experienced solitude for a long time thou canst not expect to
               learn anything additional concerning <pb n="301"/>the goods of the ascetics even
               though he may be very wise and instructive and possess a range of habitual
               virtues.</p>
            <p>Be cautious not to weaken thy body too much, lest weariness overpower thee and thou
               shouldst make thy soul cold against the taste of its service. As in a scale man ought
               to weigh his discipline. When thou art satisfied, be somewhat cautious against free
               speech in thyself.</p>
            <p>Let thy sitting be in chastity, also at the time of bodily want. Especially chaste
               and cautious thou hast to be when going to sleep, not only thy deliberations, but
               also thy members being watchful. Be watchful against presumption when good
               states<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-1"/> come upon thee. Thy weakness and thy dullness <pb type="external"
                  n="449"/>in the face of its subtlety thou must communicate to our Lord in zealous
               prayer, lest evil things should be allowed to try thee. For fornication follows
               haughtiness, and aberration presumption.</p>
            <p>Use handiwork as far as thou needest it, especially as thou art shut up in solitude.
               Let not thy hope on Him that provides for thee, indulge in any weakness; God's
               provisions in behalf of His housemates are amazing; even in the desert without human
               hands He provides for those who inhabit it and hope on Him. If our Lord supplies thee
               with that which the body needs, though thou doest not labour but carest for the soul
               only, then some thought will arise by the trickery of the murderer<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-2"/> namely
               this, that there necessarily must be on thy part some cause for all this care. And
               with this deliberation, God's care will be withdrawn from thee. And at the same time
               myriads of temptations will arise and assail thee, having their origin either in the
               neglect of those who used to care for us, or in the recommencement of pains and
               illnesses that are caused<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n301-3"/> in our body. God does not give up His care on
               account of this emotion alone, but when the mind sticks to it. On account of <choice><sic>in</sic><corr>an</corr></choice>
               voluntary emotion God does not chastise and judge a man, not even when we give way to
               it for a short time; but at once pain pricks us and contrition comes to us. Our Lord
               will not seek retribution for such a fault; but only for such a one as the mind
               really clings to, in that we glance at it unconsciously as if there <pb n="302"/>were
               no harm in it and without thinking of anything wrong. Perpetually we have to pray to
               our Lord in this way: O <pb type="external" n="450"/>Christ, Thou summit of truth,
               let Thy truth dawn in our hearts, that we know to walk in Thy way according to Thy
               will.</p>
            <p>When for a short time or longer some evil deliberation shows itself often in thee,
               know then assuredly that Satan wishes to lay a snare for thee. And pay attention to
               it in due time. If it is however a right-hand and good one, know that the Lord wishes
               to give thee some share of life and that for this cause this deliberation is astir in
               thee so unusually often. If it is a dark deliberation and thou art in doubt
               concerning it because thou canst not make out clearly whether it is helpful or
               treacherously hidden in a scheme of beauty, then pay attention to it in keen prayer
               night and day, with long vigils. Do not push it from thee, neither deliver thyself
               unto it but pray diligently and fervently because of it. Do not cause crying to our
               Lord, and He will show himself manifestly, [so that thou knowest] whence it is.</p>
            <p>Love silence above all things. It brings thee near the fruit which the tongue is too
               weak to interpret. At first we compel ourselves to be silent. Then from our silence
               something is born which draws us towards silence. May God grant thee to perceive that
               which is born from silence. If thou beginnest with this discipline, I do not know how
               much light will dawn in thee through it. Concerning what is said about the <pb
                  type="external" n="451"/>admirable Arsenius: that Fathers and brethren came to see
               him, but that he sat with them in silence and dismissed them in silence — do not
               think, my brother, that this happened by the action of his will alone, though in the
               beginning he had to compel himself. After some time some delight is born in the heart
               from the exercise of this service and by force it draws the body towards remaining in
               silence.</p>
            <p>Many tears are born in us by this discipline, by the amazing sight of things which
               the heart perceives distinctly. Sometimes by suffering, sometimes on account of
               ecstasy the heart becomes small as a child; and as soon as it insists in prayer,
               tears will burst forth.</p>
            <p>Great is the man who, side by side with bodily endurance, possesses admirable customs
               in his soul.</p>
            <p>If thou placest all labours of this discipline<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n302-1"/> on one side <pb n="303"/>and
               silence on the other, silence will outweigh them. There are many warnings of the
               Fathers which need not be kept laboriously when a man approaches unto silence, and
               the practice of which becomes superfluous, because he is elevated above them, and is
               near the mark. Silence is also helpful for solitude.</p>
            <p>For it is impossible that, living in an inhabited place, we should not meet with any
               one. Even that angel of God, Arsenius, who loved solitude more than any one, could
               not wholly avoid meeting others. For in such a place we meet Fathers and brethren and
               innumerable other persons, and we have to visit the church. When that blessed man saw
               that it <pb type="external" n="452"/>was impossible to avoid this, so long as he was
               in the vicinity of an inhabited place (though his dwelling-place was at a distance of
               many miles from a human settlement, even from the solitaries who dwelt in those
               places), he learned from grace this means: continual silence. When sometimes it was
               necessary for him to open his door to some of them, they enjoyed his aspect only;
               conversation was superfluous.</p>
            <p>Many fathers have been led by this sight, to become careful also as to their own
               person that, their spiritual riches might increase, through the instruction they
               received from the aspect of the blessed one. They continually saw him silent, so that
               many of them put a stone in their mouth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n303-1"/>, others tied a rope to their inner
               wall for the sake of recollection, others wearied themselves by unusual fasting; when
               they had to go to meet other people they imposed the trial of hunger upon themselves.
               For hunger greatly helps those who try to acquire a greater concentration of the
               senses. And many used to do such things in order to acquire this self-control of
               beautiful aspect that imparts life.</p>
            <p>Many fathers I have found, o my brethren, great and admirable, who cared for the
               direction of the senses and the bodily attitude more than for other labours, because
               from them is <pb type="external" n="453"/>also born the direction of the
               deliberations. Many causes, independent of his will, meet a man and make him leave
               the domain of his freedom. And if he did not guard his senses through the regularity
               of custom which dominated his soul before, they would for long prevent him from
               recovering his mind, finding his former quiet.</p>
            <pb n="304"/>
            <p>The education of the heart is, to be occupied with its hope. The education of
               discipline is to free oneself from every thing. The recollection of death is a
               wholesome bond of the outward limbs. A hook [drawing] the soul towards life is the
               joy that rises in the heart on account of hope. A drink of knowledge are the
               perpetual temptations which the mind every day draws from within, through the two
               varying states. The budding of the heart is the conviction of the resurrection in
               faith, which hope receives from within.</p>
            <p>Deem me worthy, my Lord, to see in my soul Thy bounty, before I depart this would,
               that I may perceive in my self in that hour consolation, as have done those who in
               good hope have left this world. Open my heart, o God, through Thy grace and purify me
               from the communion with sin; and make level in my heart the way of repentance, my God
               and my Lord, my hope and my boast, my strong refuge, by whom my eyes receive light,
               and let me receive understanding by Thy truth.</p>
            <p>Deem me worthy, O my Lord, to taste the delightful gift of repentance by which the
               soul is made free from the bondage of sin and the whole will of flesh and blood.</p>
            <p>Deem me worthy, o Lord, to taste this affection in which reposes the gift of pure
               prayer. My saviour has reached the amazing passage through which the soul leaves the
               visible <pb type="external" n="454"/>world and in which begin new impulses for entry
               into the spiritual world, and experiences of new apperceptions.</p>
            <p>He that begins and accomplishes well, places his discipline upon this foundation,
               entreating God unceasingly that He may deem him worthy to perceive this apperception
               in which is sown the knowledge of the future order of things through imperishable
               hope, which through divine grace is preserved for man after the completion of this
               world.</p>
            <p>But he that begins pervertedly goes from above downwards: he begins with joy and he
               ends with weeping; and he becomes devoid of knowledge and hope, as a formless body
               which not attained to the reception of the soul, because it has not completed the
               state of preparation in the womb, but has reached the end of the life of
               form<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n304-1"/>.</p>
            <p>Contempt for intercourse with the world is the sign of a <pb n="305"/>soul that has
               perceived its hope. A hidden alertness implies drowsiness regarding visible
               tilings.</p>
            <p>The weapon of the heart is faith in Christ. Who by the desire of hope has withstood
               even death, death is esteemed as nothing in his eyes, and so are being exiled from
               his country, and the strife of the demons and alienation from men, and lack of the
               consolation of the world. What is the consolation of visible things and the being
               occupated with them, as compared with the delight of hope that is perceived in the
               heart? As he that has abandoned the body in the drunkenness of his joy, through the
               flaming faith which kindles his heart, so that <pb type="external" n="455"/>all
               visible things are hidden from him and he knows nothing in the creation through the
               heat of his body and the emotions of his soul, and as he that abides already in the
               kingdom, does he account [earthly things] because of the faith of his mind.</p>
            <p>Though sometimes we are subject to despondency because of loneliness — perhaps this
               is permitted in us by Providence — yet we also possess through our heart's faith the
               consolation of hope which is too great for words; and through this hope, troubles are
               accounted by us as nothing, even death. And well has one of those who are clad with
               God, said: Sufficient is the love of God, as a consolation for him that believes,
               even when he loses his self. How should troubles injure him who despises even the
               delights of comfort for the sake of future good?</p>
            <p>Also this I advise thee, o my brother, that in all thy discipline the scale of mercy
               be preponderant; through this thou wilt perceive God's mercy for the world. Our own
               state becomes to us a mirror in which we behold the true Prototype, in those things
               which naturally belong to that Essence.</p>
            <p>By these things and the like we become illuminated so as to be in motion unto God,
               with a clear mind. A heart wicked from of old, cannot become serene.</p>
            <p>A merciful man is the physician of his own soul; for he drives away from his inner
               being the dark mist, as by a strong wind. Mercy is a good investment with God,
               according <pb type="external" n="456"/>to the Gospel of life: Blessed is the
               merciful: for he shall obtain mercy<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n305-1"/>. Not only in the world to be,
               symbolically also here. What mercy is greater than this, that when a man is <pb
                  n="306"/>moved by mercy unto his <choice><sic>follow</sic><corr>fellow</corr></choice> man and becomes his partner in
               suffering, our Lord delivers his soul from gloomy darkness which is intelligible
               Hell, and brings it in contact with the light of life, for its comfort? The blessed
               Euagrius has well said: A clear way is founded upon mercy.</p>
            <p>Therefore, as I have said: Let a merciful heart preside over thy whole behaviour,
               then thou shalt find peace with God. Be careful, that no evil be ever done to any man
               through thy hands, not even to the evil one<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n306-1"/>. And when it is possible for
               thee to deliver the iniquitous from evil, do not omit it. Not that, if the matter be
               far from thee, thou shouldst go and mix thyself with such things — such a deed does
               not belong to thy duty — but if the matter is put in thy hands, and thou hast power
               over it, because it has been placed before thee accidentally as a trial, in that God
               wished to try thee by His admitting it, then be cautious regarding thyself lest thou
               become a participant in the blood of the <choice><sic>iniquious</sic><corr>iniquitous</corr></choice>, because thou doest
               not hasten to deliver him. But try with thy whole soul to save him, even if thou
               shouldst die for his sake. Then thou wilt really be a martyr and as one that has
               suffered death on the cross for sinners. And pray God, that this<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n306-2"/> may not
               happen through thee. But even if he be worthy of evil, let him receive the judgment
               of his deeds by the hands of <pb type="external" n="457"/>others. It does not become
               thee to regard the worth of his deeds. Let good [alone] happen to him by thy
               hands.</p>
            <p>Think of Him who bears all, the deeds of all men being placed before His eyes,
               clearer than the sun; and if He liked He could destroy all men by the breath of His
               mouth. Thou wert not appointed to pronounce [the judgment of] vengeance against deeds
               and their perpetrators, but it is thy duty to implore mercy on the world, to abide in
               vigil for the salvation of all, to share in the suffering of every man, righteous and
               sinners. And thou must know, that if he deserve it, justice will bind him within a
               short time, by the hands of others who are fit for this deed; and thou wilt save thy
               soul and become a living martyr. But even this thou hast not to ask or to care for,
               but to implore God's mercy upon him, that he may change and become as it is the will
               of God that he should <pb n="307"/>be and may depart life in righteousness and not
               [awaiting] the retribution of wickedness.</p>
            <p>Be instead of an avenger, a deliverer; instead of an accuser, a peace maker; instead
               of one who delivers, a martyr; instead of a plaintiff, a dependant. Beseech God in
               behalf of the sinners, that they may obtain grace. And pray for the righteous, that
               they may be preserved. Vanquish the evil ones by this kindness, and make the zealous
               wonder at thy bounty. Those who love justice, make them ashamed by thy mercy. With
               the afflicted be afflicted in thy mind. Love all men. And be far <pb type="external"
                  n="458"/>from all men. Recollect death, and prepare thyself for thy entrance into
               it. Embellish thy course. Remember that the sins of all men go before them to the
               court of justice.</p>
            <p>Be not dejected because of trespasses. I do not say that thou shouldst not suffer;
               but thou must not account them as being incurable. Better broken than dead. For one
               who is broken, there is the physician, who on the cross has implored mercy for those
               who crucified Him, who asked forgiveness for His murderers while He hung on the
               cross. 'All manner of sin and blasphemy shall be forgiven unto men'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-1"/>, namely
               on account of repentance. When Simon who had denied Him, had wept a short time, He
               forgave him. And after His resurrection, He appointed him as the head of His flock.
               Three times He asked him: Lovest thou me?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-2"/>, even as three times he had denied
               Him, in order to confirm His pardon. Christ came on behalf of the sinners, in order
               to heal the broken in heart, and to bind up their wounds<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-3"/>. 'The Spirit of the
               Lord is upon me; therefore He has anointed me, to preach good tidings unto the meek;
               He hath sent me to bind up the brokenhearted, to proclaim liberty to the captives,
               and sight to the blind, and healing to those who are broken, by forgiveness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-4"/>.
               And the Apostle says in his epistle: Jesus Christ came to the world to save
               sinners<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-5"/>. And his Lord witnesses: For I am not come to call the righteous;
               for they that are whole have no need of the physician, but they that are
               sick<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n307-6"/>. There were two debtors to a certain creditor; and because they had
               nothing to pay with, he forgave both of them; namely: when they had beseeched
               him.</p>
            <pb n="308"/>
            <p>Our frail nature would not be strong enough if God's justice <pb type="external"
                  n="459"/>should proceed to take vengeance. Therefore He uses mercy so that we at
               all times are bound by our debt.</p>
            <p>Do not sin, o man, in hope of repentance, and do not indulge in weakness, confiding
               in forgiveness. Remember, that death will not be postponed. Do not contrive to
               approach to the delight of sin, with a cunning mind. God is not mocked<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n308-1"/>. His
               knowledge precedes thy deliberation: trouble will come upon thee suddenly, and thou
               wilt cry, but He will not answer thee.</p>
            <p>When thou approachest thy bed, because the time for sleep has come, say: O bed,
               perhaps thou wilt become my grave this night and I not know it. Perhaps in stead of
               temporary sleep, eternal sleep will fall on me this night, while I thought of
               preparing for days and months, which I did not see.</p>
            <p>As long as thou hast feet, run after the service of righteousness, before they be
               caught by a bond which it is impossible to sever. As long as thou hast hands, stretch
               them towards heaven in prayer, before thy arms fall from their joints and thou desire
               to raise them, and it is impossible for thee. As long as thou hast fingers, raise
               them unto God in supplication. For there will come a time when the splendid strength
               of their joints is weakened. As long as thou hast eyes, fill them with tears during
               prayer, weeping for thy sins, <pb type="external" n="460"/>before the moment when
               sand will cover the black [clothes] and the eyes will become feeble, staring
               senseless in one direction, without thy knowing it. As long as the heart, the
               fountain of the deliberations, is ordered by a distinguishing power, bethink of those
               things which are helpful to thy life, before the soul be hastened on to departure
               from it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n308-2"/> and become a house devoid of its inhabitants.</p>
            <p>O thou who art wise, let no deliberation flatter thee with the hope of a long life.
               As a flower withers by the blowing of the sirocco, so against thee will blow one of
               the elements which are within thee and without thy expecting it, suddenly thy knees
               will relax. And while thou thinkest that it is nothing and that thou art curing the
               illness, suddenly the cunning one will approach, who laughs at the wise.</p>
            <pb n="309"/>
            <p>O, for the wretchedness of our nature! how are we entangled in its love, though God
               does not desire to leave us in this state. Set thy heart to prepare for departure, o
               man. As a sage thou must expect departure every hour, thinking every day: the
               messenger of him that comes after me, has reached the gate; why should I remain
               sitting? It is a departure for ever, I cannot return hither. Go asleep with these
               thoughts every night; and meditate upon this deliberation every day. And when [the
               time of departure] comes, go joyfully to meet it, saying: Come in peace. I knew that
               thou wouldst come and I have not neglected anything that could serve me on the
               way.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="461"/>Take provisions for thy long way, o sage. Drive away the
               heaviness of sleep from thy heart, o companion. Order thy things for departure, thou
               who dwellest as a sedentary. Morningtime is near, o traveller, why art thou sleeping?
               Come, prepare thyself, thou sailor who art about to sail off, prepare the utensils of
               thy ship; for thou doest not know when the wind will begin to blow.</p>
            <p>Be ready and prepared before he comes that will destroy thy forms. For Sheol shall
               make wither their form<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n309-1"/>, and they shall be bereft of the beautiful glory of
               nature and their bodies will be left in the wilderness. Remember always that
               destruction of deplorable appearance, that formless scattering of thy senses, that
               ruin of the building of thy body, that pure mixture that will become mud in Sheol.
               <choice><sic>Bleased</sic><corr>Blessed</corr></choice> is he that with joy meets the recollection of that destruction!
               Blessed is he that with good hope awaits that event full of mystery, in which the
               wonder of the Creator's great power is hidden! Spiritual meditation is, to be
               continually occupied with the hope of [things which will be] after the
               resurrection.</p>
            <p>The beginning of this impulse in the mind lies in the domain of repentance. That
               which induces the soul to embrace repentance, is the constant thought of future
               things. Who has been moved by repentance, his hope has turned to the future world.
               Who has forgotten this, his mind abides in this world.</p>
            <p>Who loves intercourse with Christ, loves to be alone. Who loves to remain in the
               company of many others, he is a friend of this world.</p>
            <pb n="310"/>
            <p><pb type="external" n="462"/>Repentance<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n310-1"/> is the constant sorrow of the heart
               at the meditation of that inexplicable statute: how shall I reach that unspeakable
               entrance? If thou lovest repentance, then love also solitude. For without this,
               repentance cannot be completed. If there is any one who disputes this, do not dispute
               with him, for he does not know what he says. If he did know what repentance is, he
               also would know its place, and that it is not to be disturbed by trouble. If thou
               lovest solitude, the father of repentance, then love also to accept gladly the small
               deficiencies of the body, and the blame that arises from them. Without this
               preparation it will be impossible for thee to live in solitude, freely, without
               trouble. If thou despisest those things, thou wilt acquire solitude, according to
               God's will. If thou art wronged or robbed or laughed at or the like, thou wilt not be
               moved, because of thy love of solitude.</p>
            <p>Love of solitude is the constant expectation of death. He that without this
               meditation enters solitude, having other thoughts, cannot bear those things which,
               for the sake of solitude, he must bear from all sides: to die for the sake of God,
               and to live in God. The accomplishment of life is meditation upon death for the sake
               of God. This brings our mind near to union with God, says Euagrius.</p>
            <p>Also this thou must know, o <choice><sic>discrimiating</sic><corr>discriminating</corr></choice> reader, that lonely
               dwelling and solitude and reclusion are not chosen by us in order to perform an
               excellent canonical labour. For it <pb type="external" n="463"/>is known that
               communion with many others gives a better opportunity, because the body preserves its
               strength better. But if reclusion were not necessary, the pious men that were the
               holy Fathers, would not have abandoned intercourse with many people. Some of them
               dwelt in graves, others chose reclusion in a lonely cell, which is greatly relaxing
               to the body and which does not promote the accomplishment of the canonical rules. And
               all bodily weakness and misery, and severe illnesses which struck them, they bore
               gladly during their whole life, even when they were not able to stand on their feet
               or to offer the usual prayer, or to praise God with their mouth, or to recite a
               psalm, or to perform any of the [works] which are performed through the body. And
               bodily weakness alone and solitude with them took the place of all canonical
               rules.</p>
            <pb n="311"/>
            <p>And this was their occupation all the days of their life. And during all this so
               called idleness, none of them longed to leave his cell or to wander abroad ceasing
               from canonical labours, or to enjoy the sound of the glorifications of others in a
               congregation.</p>
            <p>Better is he that perceives his sins, than he that is profitable to the world by his
               appearance. Better is he that one time has sighed by himself, than he that quickens
               the dead by his prayer and dwells among many others. Better is he that has been
               deemed worthy of seeing himself, than he that has been deemed worthy of seeing the
               angels. The latter <pb type="external" n="464"/>partakes of the eyes of the body, the
               former of the eye of the soul. Better is he that clings to Christ mournfully in
               solitude, than he that praises Him in a congregation. No one should adduce the words
               of Paul: For I could wish that myself were accursed by Christ for my
               brethren<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n311-1"/>. He that has received the power of Paul, he has also the permission
               to do so. Paul was behaving as he did because a divine order had been given to him to
               be profitable to the world. As he witnesses to it, that he did not this by his own
               will: for necessity is laid upon me, woe is unto me, if I preach not the
               gospel<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n311-2"/>. Moreover, the election of Paul was not because of repentance, but
               that he should preach to humanity he received even greater power.</p>
            <p>So we must love solitude, o my brother, that this world may die from our heart and we
               may think of death continually. And by this meditation we shall approach unto God in
               heart; and we shall despise the emptiness of the world; and its desires shall be
               despicable in our eyes. Let us joyfully bear, with a sorry body, the continual
               idleness of solitude, my brother, in order that we may be deemed worthy of delight
               with those that in the caverns and the clefts of the earth are waiting for the
               glorious revelation of our Lord from heaven. To Him and to His father and to the Holy
               Ghost be glory and praise for ever and ever.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n297-1">Cf. Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n300-1"> in prayer or in vigils</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-1">ܫܘܚ̈ܠܦܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-2">Satan</note>
            <note xml:id="n301-3">lit. stirring</note>
            <note xml:id="n302-1"> solitary life</note>
            <note xml:id="n303-1">Ghazālī tells this about Abū Bakr</note>
            <note xml:id="n304-1">ܚܝ̈ܐ ܕܨܠܡܢܘܬܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n305-1">Matthew 5,7</note>
            <note xml:id="n306-1">Cf., p. 14, 79 etc.</note>
            <note xml:id="n306-2">viz.. the punishment of the iniquitous</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-1">Matthew 12,31</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-2">John 21,16</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-3">cf. Psalm 147,3</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-4">Luke 4,15</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-5">1 Timothy 1,15</note>
            <note xml:id="n307-6">Mark 2,17</note>
            <note xml:id="n308-1">Galatians 6,7</note>
            <note xml:id="n308-2">the heart</note>
            <note xml:id="n309-1">Cf. Job 14,20: Thou changest his countenance and sendest him
               away.</note>
            <note xml:id="n310-1"> Cf. Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n311-1">Romans 9,3</note>
            <note xml:id="n311-2">Romans 9,16</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
