<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 34</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 34, pp. 149-152.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="34">
            <head>XXXIV</head>
            <head>On the natural children of virtues and the like</head>
            <p>Asceticism is the mother of saintliness; from it is born the taste of the first
               apperception of the divine mysteries and it is called the first period of spiritual
               knowledge. That no one deceive himself and become a false prophet. For the impure
               soul does not ascend to the pure kingdom, neither in the symbolical nor in the common
               sense, and it cannot mingle with the holy spirits. But when the elements have mingled
               with their relatives, the distinction of the natural unity being <pb n="150"
               />preserved, that miserable [soul] will be preserved for the great future
               judgment.</p>
            <p>Keep pure, o brother, the beauties of thy chastity, by tears and fasting and sitting
               alone by thyself. When the right course of the natural sphere has been finished and
               [the soul] has reached that great luminary, which supports the spheres of the stars
               multitudinous in their personal distinctions, as <persName>Paul</persName> says in order to prove the
               future resurrection, and when it has mingled with its rays — I do not mean in the
               natural sense — then the vehicle of the will shall be bound with the bonds of
               unconsciousness and the two exuberant fountains will dry up in their basins. And then
               the priests will leave the sanctuary on <pb type="external" n="222"/>account of the
               cloud of God's majesty<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n150-1"/>. At that time the king of <placeName>Israel</placeName> will be <persName>Solomon</persName>,
               viz. that peace which is born from humility; he will build a house for the Lord and
               completely provide it with all the sacred vessels.</p>
            <p>A little trouble for God's sake is more excellent in God's eyes than much service
               without suffering. Because trouble borne from free will is a manifestation of love.
               Service in comfort, however, rises from inward satiety. Therefore by troubles, not by
               service with satiety the saints were tested concerning the love of Christ. Service
               without labour is the righteousness of lay people who wish to be justified on account
               of what they possess, but do not acquire excellency in their person.</p>
            <p>Thou, however, who art victorious, taste the suffering of Christ in thy person, that
               thou also mayest be deemed worthy of tasting His glory. For if we suffer with Him, we
               shall also be glorified with Him. The mind cannot be glorified with <persName>Jesus</persName>, if the
               body does not suffer for <persName>Jesus</persName>. He who despises glory will receive glory at the same
               time. He will be glorified in his body as well as in his soul. The glory of the body
               is humble subjection before God. The glory of the mind is true contemplation
               concerning God. Right subjection is twofold; it follows from labour and from disdain;
               so that when the body suffers, the heart also suffers with it.</p>
            <p>If thou doest not know God, it is not possible that His love should be excited in
               thee. It is not possible for thee to love God, if thou hast not seen God. Thou seest
               Him as soon as <pb type="external" n="223"/>thou knowest Him. Sight is not prior to
               knowledge. Make me <pb n="151"/>worthy of knowing Thee, my Lord, then I shall love
               Thee too. [I do not desire] that knowledge which arises amidst distractions of the
               mind, in the training of instruction. But make me worthy of that knowledge by which
               the mind, while gazing at Thee, will be glorifying thy nature; gazing with that gaze
               which banishes from the mind the apperception of the world. Make me worthy of
               becoming exalted above arbitrary sight from which come phantastic thoughts, so that I
               gaze at Thee by the compulsion of the bonds of the cross, the latter half of which is
               the crucifixion of the mind whose position of freedom is annihilated by the service
               of the impulses, with that gaze which nature gives not, but is constantly directed
               towards Thee. Place in me the pure metal of Thy love, so that, following Thee, I
               become alienated from the world. Move in me the understanding of Thy humility by
               which Thou hast lived in the world clad with the cover taken from our limbs, that by
               the constant and never weakening remembrance of it I may accept with delight the
               humiliation of my nature.</p>
            <p>Two are the parts of the ascension on the cross. One is the crucifixion of the body.
               The second is the ascension unto contemplation; but the former is a matter of
               freedom; the latter of influence. [m]</p>
            <p>The mind will not be subjected, if the body is not subjected. The reign of the mind
               is the crucifixion of the body. The mind is not subjected unto God, if freedom has
               not been subjected to reason.</p>
            <p>It is hard to trust an elevated matter to boyish rank. For woe to thee, O town, when
               thy king is a child<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n150-1"/>.</p>
            <p>He who subjects himself, nearly all will be subjected unto him. He who knows himself,
               the knowledge of all things will <pb type="external" n="224"/>be given him. The word
               'know thyself' means the accomplishment of all knowledge. As all is encompassed in
               thy being, so in the knowledge of thy being all knowledge is encompassed, and in the
               subjection of thy being, the subjection of all the world. At the time when humility
               dominates thy behaviour, thy being will be subjected to thee, and with it everything,
               because in the heart a divine peace will be born. As this has not yet happened to
               thee, thou art perpetually persecuted not only by the affections, but also by
               accidents. Verily,</p>
            <pb n="152"/>
            <p>O Lord, if we do not humble ourselves, thou ceasest not to humble us. True humility
               is the offspring of knowledge; right knowledge the offspring of temptations.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n150-1">Allusion to 1 Kings 8,11</note>
            <note xml:id="n151-1">Ecclesiastes 10,16.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
