<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 69</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 69, pp. 321-323.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="69">
            <head>LXIX</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="479"/>How the intelligent have to dwell in solitude</p>
            <p>Listen, my beloved, to what our love says to thee.</p>
            <p>If thou desirest that thy labours shall not be empty and thy days idle and thyself
               destitute of the profit which the intelligent expect from the discipline of quiet,
               let then thy entering into solitude take place with discrimination, not in a kind of
               groove, as it is with many. But let there be an aim towards which thy mind directs
               the labours of its behaviour[#n321-1]. And interrogate those who have solid
               knowledge, through experience, not through reading only. And exercise thyself in all
               the wonderful and liberal distinctions of solitude, without taking rest before thou
               art trained in all the ways of its service. And at every step thou takest, examine
               whether thou art walking in the way, or thou hast erred away from it on one of the
               ways leading to the desert.</p>
            <p>Thou must not believe that the true discipline of solitude is accomplished by visible
               labours alone. If thou desirest to reach by personal experience that which our
               Fathers have found, thou must secretly have signs and tokens in thy soul, at every
               step thou takest, by which thou canst recognise the truth of our Fathers or the error
               of Satan. A few of them, written in order that thou mayest become wise in thy way are
               as follows.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="480"/>When thou seest, in solitude, that thy mind is able to
               use freely its righthand impulses and that there is no compulsion in its rule over
               any of them, then know that thy solitude is right. And if, while thou art performing
               thy service with discrimination, without distraction as much as possible, the words
               are suddenly cut off from thy mouth, and the bonds of <pb n="322"/>compulsory silence
               are placed on thy soul and this phenomenon is constantly repeated, then know that
               thou art making progress in thy solitude and that its simple beginnings are taking
               increase.</p>
            <p>For simple solitude is rejected by justice. And every simple [act of] discipline,
               among discriminate sages is accounted as a lonely, helpless member.</p>
            <p>And if thou seest that at every deliberation which stirs in thy soul, at every
               recollection and vision happening during solitude, the surroundings of thy eyes are
               filled with tears and thy cheeks are moistened by them, without compulsion, then know
               that before thee, in the opposing camp, there begins to grow a breach.</p>
            <p>And if thou findest that thy spirit, from time to time, descends within them without
               unusual efforts, and abides there some time, whatever that time be and afterwards
               thou seest thy members as it were in great weakness, while peace reigns over all thy
               deliberations, but [the weakness] remains continually the same, then know that the
               cloud has begun to cover the tabernacle.</p>
            <p>If, during thy abiding in solitude, thou findest that harsh <pb type="external"
                  n="481"/>deliberations reign over thy soul, and that it is tyrannised by them
               every moment, and that at all times the mind is attracted by those things which were
               administered before, namely, when it is desirous of vain investigations — then know
               that thou art fatiguing thyself with solitude in vain and that thy soul is corrupted
               by distraction, and that there are outward causes, or inward neglect of duties,
               especially of vigils and recitation. Then direct and fix thy will. But if thou doest
               not find peace from the assaults of the affections as soon as these days begin, then
               be not astonished.</p>
            <p>Now[#n322-1], if the bosom of the earth when the sunrays have ceased, preserves their
               heat for a long time, and if an aromatic smell and the odour of perfumes which spread
               through the air, remain a long time before they are dissipated and become effaced —
               how much more certain is it, that the affections, like dogs accustomed to lap up
               blood at the butcher's, will stand at the door barking, when the usual food is
               withheld from them, till their old force has abated.</p>
            <pb n="323"/>
            <p>When neglect begins to penetrate into thy soul secretly and to spread gloom, and the
               house is near to being filled with darkness, then thou wilt secretly perceive in
               thyself these signs which will soon appear: Thy faith will be weakened. Visible
               things will arouse thy covetousness. Thy confidence will diminish. Thy neighbour thou
               wilt wrong. And thy whole person, thy <choice><sic>month</sic><corr>mouth</corr></choice> and thy heart, will be full of
               vituperation against every <pb type="external" n="482"/>man and thing and against
               that which thy deliberations and senses meet, and even against the most High. And
               thou wilt be terrified by the frailty of the body which has rendered thee
               pusillanimous at all times. And from time to time thy soul will be shaken by fear, so
               that thou shalt be frightened and terrorised as it were by thy shadow.</p>
            <p>For by faith I do not understand that which is the foundation of the common
               confession, but the intelligible force that by the light of the mind supports the
               heart, and by inward testimony stirs in the soul great confidence in God; so that the
               soul does not provide for itself, but casts all its cares on the Lord without
               thinking of any of them.</p>
            <p>Then, when thou art making intelligible progress, thou wilt soon perceive in thy soul
               these dim signs. By hope thou shalt become strong, and by prayer rich. And
               continually abundant profit will be the part of thy mind in all that thou meetest,
               and thou wilt perceive the weakness of human nature. On the one hand thou must beware
               of haughtiness; on the other hand let injury against thy neighbour be despicable in
               thy eyes. Departing the body has become desirable to thee because of the desire to be
               near those things in which we are going to live. And as for all the afflicting
               accidents which happen to thee manifestly and secretly thou wilt soon find that all
               of them happen to thee justly, in all sincerity which is far from <pb type="external"
                  n="483"/>presumption. And concerning all these thou shalt make confession.</p>
            <p>These are signs for the watchful and for those who constantly dwell in solitude and
               wish to reach veraciousness of behaviour. Those who are relaxed, do not want subtle
               signs indicating hidden traps. For they are also far from hidden virtues.</p>
            <p>As soon as one of these begins to show itself in thy soul, then at once try to
               understand towards which side it begins to incline; then thou shalt know at the same
               time to which category it belongs.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n321-1">Book of the Dove, p. 1 9</note>
            <note xml:id="n322-1">Introduction</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
