<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 30</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 30, pp. 141-145.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="30">
            <pb n="141"/>
            <head>XXX</head>
            <p>On the power and the evil action of sin and concerning those in whom it maintains
               itself and those in whom it is annihilated</p>
            <p>A man is not freed from the allurements of sin in his heart until he hates from [the
               depth of] his heart and sincerely the cause of sin. This causes the vehemence of the
               struggle which opposes man in the blood and in which his freedom is testified to
               through the purity of his love of virtues.</p>
            <p>This is the power which is called seduction, by the scent of which the weak soul is
               defeated because of its mighty attraction. This is the strong power of sin by which
               it troubles the <pb type="external" n="209"/>serenity of the chaste and overpowers
               the pure emotions by things the knowledge of which they have never experienced. Here
               we have to show our endurance, my beloved.</p>
            <p>This is the time of the unseen martyrdom in which the order of the solitaries is said
               to excel at all times. By the shock of this war the mind of the steadfast is troubled
               and upset, if it is not extremely watchful. Our Lord, who possessest almighty power,
               fountain of all help, support Thou in these times of martyrdom the souls who joyfully
               have betrothed themselves to thee, heavenly bridegroom, and who have given thee the
               promise of sanctity, in entire purity of emotions without an afterthought. Fill them
               with the force which subdues the resistance of fortresses and of heights that raise
               themselves against sanctity, lest they be driven away from their proposed aim by the
               unbearable compulsion of this time in which the struggle in the blood rages.</p>
            <p>Not always does this severe strife take place in the struggle of chastity. Remittance
               may occur that a test may be applied. Woe to the weak who is put to the test in this
               decisive strife. It possesses great strength and maintains its customary force
               against those who have given themselves wholly, even though it be but once, to
               defeat, by submitting their deliberations to it.</p>
            <p>Be on your guard against idleness, my beloved; intelligible death is hidden in it.
               Without it it is impossible that the solitary should fall into the hands of those who
               wish to captivate <pb n="142"/>him. Not that God will judge us on that day on the
               basis of <pb type="external" n="210"/>the Psalms we have recited or whether we have
               passed in idleness the times of service occasionally; but by our neglecting them, the
               demons win access. And when they have found an opportunity to enter and have shut our
               rooms, they accomplish in us tyrannically things which will necessarily bring their
               perpetrators under divine judgment in view of the severe punishment allotted for
               them. So we become enslaved through negligence in small matters which by the prudent
               are treated in a painstaking way, for the sake of Christ. As it has been said:
               Whosoever does not subject his will to God, he becomes a slave to his foe. We have,
               therefore, to consider as walls against those who desire to captivate us, those
               things which are reputed to be of a humble nature and which are accomplished in the
               cell, things which by those who maintain the strict institutes of the church have
               been laid down in prudence in a spirit of revelation, for the preservation of our
               life, the neglect of which is deemed insignificant by the imprudent, the harm of
               which, however, they do not consider. The beginning and the middle of their path is
               untrained freedom, which is the mother of wrongs. To trouble oneself with the care of
               small things is better than to give opportunity for sin by remissness regarding them.
               This is freedom at the wrong time; the end of which is grinding slavery.</p>
            <p>As long as thy senses are alive to the shock of every accident, thy soul is to be
               deemed dead. For in that case the flames of sin will never be absent from thy limbs,
               whatever be thy states, and no peace will be able to settle in thy soul. If any of
               the solitaries promises in his heart to be watchful in <pb type="external" n="211"
               />such a state, he does not desire to be conscious of punishment.</p>
            <p>When a man deceives his companion he deserves the curse, such as is according to the
               law. When, however, a man deceives himself, he is not deserving those punishments;
               for while conscious he has made himself unconscious, because it is demanded from him
               that he shall eradicate the cause from his heart. But this is difficult in his eyes;
               and, for this reason, while conscious, he desires to be unconscious. O how sweet is
               the cause of affections. He will cut them off sometimes and be pleased to drive them
               away. Often he rejoices on account of their being <choice><sic>apeased</sic><corr>appeased</corr></choice>; to eradicate
               their cause he is, however, not able. Therefore we are put to the test, though it be
               against <pb n="143"/>our will, and are distressed by the affections although we like
               that their causes be strong in us.</p>
            <p>Sins we desire not; their conductors, however, we receive with delight; so secondary
               reasons become a mighty cause of primary ones. For he who desires the causes of the
               affections, is subject to them, though not of his will.</p>
            <p>Who hates his sins, abstains from them. He who confesses his faults, receives
               forgiveness. There is no abstaining from customary sins without acquiring hate, nor
               receiving of forgiveness without confession of faults. The latter is accompanied by
               true humility; the former by grief, through shame rising in the heart. So long as we
               have not advanced to the point of hating blameworthy things, it is not possible to
               perceive the foetid odour they spread when perpetrated, nor their stinking <pb
                  type="external" n="212"/>smell, bearing them, as we do, in ourselves. So long as
               thou hast not cast evil away, thou knowest not what shame thou wilt foster nor what
               chastisement will rise from it. If thou seest in others that with which thou art
               charged, then thou knowest the shame with which thou art clad. Remove thyself from
               evil, then thou wilt know. For thou inhalest the foetid odour as a sweet scent, and
               [considerest] the nakedness of thy shame as a glorious cover.</p>
            <p>Blessed is he that has removed himself from darkness and seen himself; so long as he
               is in it, sight and discernment are impossible. Blessed is he that has come forth
               from the dizziness of his wine and has seen in others the shamelessness of his
               drunkenness; then he will understand his own shame. As long as he himself is under
               the drunkenness of sins, all that he does is beautiful in his eyes. When nature has
               deviated from its order, it is all alike, to be drunk with wine or with desires; both
               [states] remove [a man] from what is becoming; both excite in their bearer, the body,
               the same heat; they are different as to their idea, but one in appearance; and one in
               madness. There is no equality in their causal ideas; but in their bearers there is no
               diversity.</p>
            <p>All rest is followed by vexation; and all vexation by rest. If all in this world is
               liable to change, nevertheless man undergoes it in an attitude of opposition, either
               here or there or at the time of departure. This is especially the case with rest <pb
                  type="external" n="213"/>from lasciviousness or vexation which precedes it, in the
               way of sanctity. This is administered by God with compassion, so <pb n="144"/>that
               man has to taste this torment either on his way or at its end; then he passes away.
               And on account of the richness of God's compassion He [uses] this as a means of
               remuneration, like a deposit; so that the wages of good do not diminish the capital;
               but the wages of evil do.</p>
            <p>As has been said: He who is chastised here, diminishes [his torments in] Hell.</p>
            <p>Beware of freedom preceding subjection, beware of consolation preceding strife.
               Beware of knowledge older than the shock of temptations; beware of it rather than of
               love preceding the accomplishment of repentance.</p>
            <p>If all of us are sinners, and none is exalted above their experience, then none among
               the virtues precedes repentance. Recollect that all delight is secondary to aversion
               and bitterness.</p>
            <p>Beware of joy also, to which is not joined variation without cause. Concerning all
               things provided from above thou wilt find the cause of their variation unattainable
               to knowledge. Fear that which is reputed to be joined with equality; it is said to
               lie besides the way which is trodden. He who knows to steer the ship of the world
               with prudence, has connected variation with all that belongs to Him. Different from
               this is likeness.</p>
            <p>Distraction of the thoughts is connected with the rest of the limbs; dejection with
               immoderate labour; distraction with dejection. Distraction differs from distraction.
               The former is <pb type="external" n="214"/>accompanied by the strife of wantonness;
               the latter by the inclination to leave the cell and to [inhabit] various places.
               Moderate labour connected with constancy is priceless; where it fails, there is
               exuberant desire; where it prevails, there is room for trouble.</p>
            <p>Bear the folly of nature prevailing in thy body, o brother, because thou art destined
               to possess that wisdom which possesses the everlasting crown of government. Be not
               troubled by the disturbance of the body, [the inheritance] of Adam, which is destined
               as soon as it is clad with that heavenly image which is the king of peace, to dwell
               in that delight of which the knowledge would overpower in this world the minds of
               those who are clad with flesh.</p>
            <p>Be not troubled on account of the wild variations of nature. For the short duration
               of the labour caused by them is, to him who endures, as a delightful gift. They are
               hounds accustomed <pb n="145"/>to the butcher<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n145-1"/>; a sound from the mouth is
               sufficient to make them flee. But if thou shouldst condescend to have connections
               with them, thou wouldst make them strong lions.</p>
            <p>Despise mean pleasures, lest thou become subjected to the force of their
               heat<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n145-2"/>. A little patience regarding small things repels the danger of the
               approach of large ones. It is not possible to overcome great evils without a small
               victory over trifling ones.</p>
            <p>Recollect the kind of way thou wilt go, o brother; there is no longer life there
               sustained by chemicals driving mortality; nor warmth of temperament exciting the
               young nature by the allurement of its pleasure. Bear the labour of the struggle into
               which [He] has introduced thee in order to put thee to the <pb type="external"
                  n="215"/>test; then thou wilt take the crown and pass; for after a little time
               thou wilt have rest from this world. Think of that rest without end, of that life
               without allurements, of that state of perfect manhood, of that course of life without
               shocks, of that compulsory force of divine love reigning over nature.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n145-1">viz. the butcher's shop</note>
            <note xml:id="n145-2">when it has grown strong</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
