<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 12</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 12, pp. 82-84.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="12">
            <head>XII</head>
            <head>That it is not beautiful for the servant of God who had renunciation the world and
               has gone forth to seek event he truth, out of fear that he shall not find the truth
               to desist from seeking it or from the fervour which is born from the desire of divine
               things, or from the inquiry after their mystic secrets which are described
               mysteriously. That, by this seeking, the mind may desist from evil distraction and
               recollections of the affections</head>
            <p>There are three degrees which constitute the whole course of man. The degree of
               novitiate, the middle one, and that of perfection.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="122"/>And although the mind of the first degree looks with all
               its occupations and recollections towards excellence, yet it is connected with the
               affections.</p>
            <p>The second degree, the middle one, lies between the affectable and the spiritual
               state. Righthand and lefthand deliberations are stirred equally in it. And neither
               the fountain of light nor that of darkness ever cease to flow on its side, as it has
               been said. If the [solitary] cease for even a short time from meditating restlessly
               on spiritual writings, or from thinking of divine things, such as enflame him as fire
               by their tending towards the truth, in union with outward needfulness as strict <pb
                  n="83"/>as possible which includes inward cautiousness and sufficient works — then
               he is swept away towards the side of the affections.</p>
            <p>But if he heighten his natural warmth in the way mentioned, without desisting from
               seeking and inquiring, and if he follow these things from afar without seeing them,
               except their designation in the scriptures, and if he multiply his deliberations and
               dominate them by those which do not decline unto the left side, and receive not any
               seed of phantasies coming from the demons instead of from truth, but be desirous on
               the contrary, long and guard himself and beseech God in passionate, enduring prayer —
               then, as soon as it will please God to give it, He will open His gate before him.
               Especially on account of his humility, for to the humble the mysteries are
               revealed.</p>
            <p>If he dies, however, in that expectation, without having seen that country at a short
               distance, I think that his heritage will be with the ancient righteous, who have
               expected perfection, according to the word of the Apostle, but have not seen
               it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n83-1"/>, <pb type="external" n="123"/>yet have worked in expectation of it all
               their lifetime and have departed. But what shall we say, if any one does not reach
               [the degree which enables him] to enter the promised land which is the stage of the
               perfect and to find truth eye to eye in so far as nature is capable of this? Shall he
               then resign this [and remain] on that low stage which is wholly connected with that
               of the left side? And because he has not found the whole truth, shall he remain in
               this low state which does not even know to desire these things, or shall he elevate
               himself unto the middle stage mentioned, even though he does not look as it were in a
               mirror, but expects it from afar, and in that expectation will be gathered unto his
               fathers?</p>
            <p>Even though he is not deemed worthy of the fulness of that grace here, yet he shall
               occupy his mind through intercourse with it at a distance and by its stimulating
               influence during his lifetime he shall eliminate and fly from bad deliberations. And
               in this hope, his heart being full of God, he shall depart this world.</p>
            <p>All that takes place in humility, is beautiful. The uncorporeal thoughts of the mind
               inclining towards the love of God [engendered] by the understanding of the
               scriptures, are a <pb n="84"/>fence for the gates of the soul against foreign
               deliberations. They guard the spirit by ardent recollections of future things,
               against its being distracted through idleness to the recollection of [worldly]
               things; this would quench the ardour of its emotion and it would fall into
               desires.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n83-1">Cf. 1 Peter 1,10-12</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
