<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 44</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 44, pp. 212-214.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="44">
            <head>XLIV</head>
            <head>Concerning how many degrees knowledge has and concerning the degrees of faith</head>
            <p>There is a knowledge which is anterior to faith and there is a knowledge which is
               born from faith. The knowledge anterior to faith, is natural knowledge; that which is
               born from faith, is spiritual knowledge.</p>
            <p>What is natural knowledge? Knowledge which distinguisheth good from evil and which is
               also called natural distinction. God has implanted in rational nature to know good
               from evil, naturally, without instruction, yet this knowledge increases through
               instruction. There is no one in whom this [knowledge] is not active and this is the
               force of the knowledge of the rational <pb n="213"/>soul by nature, namely the
               distinction between good and evil is stirring in it naturally, without ceasing. Those
               who are defective in this respect are beneath the rank of reason. Those in whom this
               is found, stand upright in psychic nature, and <pb type="external" n="319"/>there has
               not been destroyed in them that which was given by God unto psychic nature, to the
               honour of His reason.</p>
            <p>Those who have destroyed this knowledge which distinguishes between good and evil,
               are scorned by the prophet: man has no insight in his own honour<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-1"/>. The honour
               of rational nature is the faculty to distinguish between good and evil. Rightly the
               prophet compares those who have destroyed this faculty with the brutes who possess no
               distinguishing and rational soul. On account of this faculty we are naturally able to
               find the way of God, and this is the natural knowledge which is anterior to faith and
               this is the way unto God. On account of the fact that a man knows how to distinguish
               between good and evil, he receives faith. Witness is the force of nature to the fact
               that it is beautiful for a man to believe in Him that has created all these things
               and that he acknowledge the words of His commandments and performs them.</p>
            <p>From the fact that he believes this, is born the fear of God. When man clings to the
               service of the fear of God, and by service proceeds to some extent in it, the
               spiritual knowledge is born of which we have said that it is born from faith. Not
               that it is simply born from faith. From simple faith only spiritual knowledge is not
               born, but from faith fear of God is born. And when we begin with the service of the
               fear of God, from the service of the fear of God spiritual knowledge is born,
               according to the word of the blessed commentator<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-2"/>: When a man possesses the
               will to cling to the fear of God and an upright mind he will easily receive the
               revelation of hidden <pb type="external" n="320"/>things. The revelation of hidden
               things he calls spiritual knowledge. Not that the fear of God brings this forth, it
               is not possible to bring forth that which is not implied in nature. But knowledge is
               to given gratuitously for the service of the fear of God.</p>
            <p>When<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n213-3"/> thou inquirest well thou wilt find that the service of the fear of God
               is repentance. And spiritual knowledge is, as we have said, that of which we have
               received the pledge <pb n="214"/>in baptism and which we receive really by
               repentance. The gift of which we have said<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n214-1"/> that we receive it by repentance,
               is spiritual knowledge, which is given gratuitously for the service of the fear of
               God. Spiritual knowledge is apperception of the things which are hidden. When a man
               perceives the things which are unseen but most profitable, after which spiritual
               knowledge is called, by this apperception is born a different faith. Not that it is
               contrary to the old faith, nay it even corroborates it. It is called the faith of
               sight. Hitherto there was hearing; now there is sight. Sight is more true than
               hearing.</p>
            <p>All these things are born from that knowledge which distinguishes between good and
               evil and which is stirring in nature. And this is the seed of excellence, as it has
               been called. But when we conceal this by our will which loves desire, we lose all
               this good.</p>
            <p>With this knowledge are connected a perpetual stabbing of the heart; distress and
               grief; fear of God; shame before nature; grief at the transitory things which
               [occupied the mind] before; <pb type="external" n="321"/>zeal for that which is
               becoming; perpetual remembrance of death, torturing thoughts of that transition and
               care for its provisions; passionate beseeching of God that we enter well that gate
               through which all nature has to pass; contempt of the world and noble strife for the
               sake of excellence. All these things are found in this natural knowledge. Man has to
               examine his discipline in view of these and when he is in accord with them, he goes
               in the way of nature. When he climbs higher and reaches love, he leaves the domain of
               nature and strife, fear and fatigue leave him alone.</p>
            <p>In accordance with what has been said man has to measure his things [in order to
               know] in which way he is walking; in that which is beneath nature, in nature, or
               above nature. Through these distinctions which have been clearly expounded, a man may
               easily understand what the discipline of his whole life has to be. When thou art not
               in the things of nature which have been described here, nor in the things above
               nature it is clear that thou dwellest beneath nature.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n213-1">Cf. Psalms 49,12,20</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-2">Theodore of Mopsuestia</note>
            <note xml:id="n213-3">Cf. Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n214-1">p. 315</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
