<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 3</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 3, pp. 14-28</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="3">
            <head>III</head>
            <p>The soul whose nature is not greatly solicitous for the gathering of possessions,
               does not require great diligence in order to find within itself impulses of wisdom
               unto God. For freedom from connection with the world will naturally set in motion
               flashes of intuition from which it can exalt itself unto God and remain in
               ecstasy.</p>
            <p>When the waters from without do not enter the fountain of the soul, its natural
               waters will arise, viz. the wonderful intuitions which are moving towards God at all
               time.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="21"/>As often as the soul is found not to be in this state, it
               has either found a starting point in foreign recollections, or the senses have caused
               it to be troubled by the touch of [outward] things, when the senses are fenced in by
               solitude without a break and recollections have grown dim by its helpful influence —
               then thou wilt see what the nature of the deliberations of the soul, and what the
               nature of the soul is, and what treasures are collected in it. These treasures are
               incorporeal intuitions which arise from the soul without care or labour being spent
               on them. Nay, a man does not even know that such deliberations could arise in human
               nature, nor does he know who was his teacher, or how he has found that which he
               cannot describe to his companion, or who has been his guide towards that which he has
               not learned from another<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14-1"/>.</p>
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>This is the nature of the soul. So the affections are additions, entering the soul on
               account of [certain] causes. But naturally the soul is not affectable.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-1"/></p>
            <p>When thou findest psychic or corporeal affections here or there in the scriptures,
               such things are said concerning those causes. But the soul naturally has no
               affections.</p>
            <p>But the philosophers who are without do not believe this; neither do those who are
               their followers. But we believe that God has not made His image affectable. With His
               image I do <pb type="external" n="22"/>not mean the body but the soul which is
               invisible.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-1"/> Every image is a copy in which the prototype is depicted. And a
               visible image cannot be the copy of something invisible. So we believe that the
               affections of the soul are not natural as they say. If any one likes to dispute
               concerning this point we will ask him: What is natural to the soul? To be without
               affections, full of light, or moved by the affections and dark? Now if the nature of
               the soul is to be clear and a receptacle of the blessed light, it will be found in
               this condition when it returns unto its original state. But when it is moved by the
               affections, all the members of the church confess it to have abandoned its nature.
               Consequently the affections are later accessions to the nature of the soul. And it is
               not at all becoming to think the affections to be psychic. If the soul be moved by
               them, nevertheless it is clear that it is moved by something outside it, not by what
               is its own. And if these [affections] are thought to be natural, because the soul is
               moved by them through the intermediary cause of the body, then hunger, thirst and
               sleep would also be natural to the soul because it is affected and brought to rest by
               them along with the body. And this would also be true for the amputation of limbs,
               fever, pains, illnesses and so on, by which the body is affected because of its
               connection with the soul and the soul because of its connection with the body, being
               affected with joy because of bodily experiences, and receiving distress, along with
               the torments of the body.</p>
            <p>What is natural to the soul; what is external to and what is above its
               nature<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15-2"/>.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="23"/>Natural to the soul is the understanding of all created
               things, <pb n="16"/>sensible and intelligible. Above its nature its being moved by
               divine contemplation; external to its nature its being excited emotionally by the
               affections. Also the light of the world, the victorious <persName>Basilius</persName>, says thus: when the
               soul is in its natural order, it is found above; When it has abandoned its nature, it
               is found beneath and on the earth. There are no affections above, where also the
               place of the soul is said to be. But when its nature abandons its order, it becomes
               affectable. Where then are the affections of the soul, now that it appears that they
               do not belong to its nature?</p>
            <p>It is clear that the soul is moved by the reprehensible affections which are in the
               body, as also it is moved by hunger and thirst on account of the body. But because
               there are no laws concerning these, the soul is not reprehensible on account of them.
               Just as, sometimes, a man is ordered by God to do those things which are blameworthy
               and he receives, instead of blame and reprehension, good reward, as <persName>Hosea</persName> the prophet
               who contracted an unlawful marriage and as <persName>Elijah</persName> who committed slaughter in his zeal
               for God and as those, who on <persName>Moses</persName>' order, stabbed with swords their kindred.</p>
            <p>But it is said that, apart from what belongs to the nature of the body, the soul has
               also that which belongs to its nature, viz. anger and choler; and these are its
               passions.</p>
            <p>Second question. We ask: when the desire of the soul is kindled to a flame by divine
               things, does this belong to its <pb type="external" n="24"/>nature, or rather when it
               is set upon earthly and bodily things? And when it is said that the nature of the
               soul is on fire for the sake of those things which excite its zeal, is then this
               passion natural when it goes hand in hand with bodily desire, envy, glory and so on,
               or when it goes in the direction opposite to them? We shall answer the disputed
               question and we too shall enquire into it.</p>
            <p>The holy writ says many things allegorically<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-1"/>; and often it uses
               metaphorical<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16-2"/> terms. Many times it applies to the soul that which belongs to
               the body and to the body that which belongs to the soul without distinguishing
               between the two, for the sake of succinctness. Now the intelligent understand what
               they read, viz. the aim of scripture. In the things related to the divinity of our
               Lord for instance, in a high and elevated <pb n="17"/>way, applies to His humanity
               that which does not suit human nature and to His divinity what does not suit it. And
               many who do not understand the aim of the language of scripture have stumbled here so
               that they never could rise again. — So it is also with the things which concern soul
               and body.</p>
            <p>If excellence is the natural health of the soul, the affections however ailments
               accustomed to oppress it and to bereave it of its health, it is clear that health is
               prior in nature to accidental illnesses. And if this be so (as it is indeed true)
               then excellence necessarily must be natural to the soul and the accidental external
               to its nature. For it is not possible that what is prior should not be natural.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="25"/>Third question. The affections of the body are they
               naturally inherent in it or of a secondary nature? And those which affect the soul,
               by the intermediary of the body, are they secondary or natural? To call those of the
               body not natural, is impossible. As to the soul — because it is known and universally
               confessed that purity belongs to its nature — no one will venture in view of this
               fact to maintain that it is primarily affectable; for it is generally conceded that
               ailment is secondary to health and it is not possible that one and the same things
               should be a good and an evil nature. One of the two, in any case, must be the prior
               of the other; and that which is the older one, is also the natural. Whatever is
               accidental, cannot be said to be natural and essential; but it is an irruption from
               without. And all accident and obtrusion is connected, whenever it be, with variation
               and change. Nature, however, does not change or vary.</p>
            <p>All<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17-1"/> existing affections are given to be a help to each of the natures to
               which they naturally belong and for the growth of which they were given by God. The
               bodily affections are placed by God in the body for the sake of profit and growth of
               the body, and the psychic affections, i.e. the psychic powers, for the sake of the
               growth and profit of the soul. And when the body is compelled to desist from its
               affectable nature, by withdrawing from the affections, and to follow the nature of
               the soul, it is injured. And when the soul leaves its own nature and follows that of
               the body, it is injured. Because, according to the word of the Apostle, the spirit
               desires that which harms <pb n="18"/><pb type="external" n="26"/>the body and the
               body desires that which harms the spirit<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18-1"/>. And these two are naturally
               opposites to one another. Therefore no one shall abuse God because He has implanted
               in our nature affections and sins. For, when He set in order each nature, He
               implanted in it that which gives it growth. But if one connects itself with the
               other, it is no longer in its own domain, but in a foreign one.</p>
            <p>If these affections naturally belonged to the soul, why then should the soul be
               injured when using them? For that which is the property of nature, does not injure
               it. And how is it, that the accomplishment of the bodily affections is profitable and
               helpful to the body, whereas those of the soul injure the soul, if they belong to it?
               And why should, if this be true, excellence torment the body, but be beneficial unto
               the soul? Thou seest how what is external to their nature injures everyone of these
               natures. For every one of these natures exults when it is near to what is its own. If
               thou art desirous to know what are the properties of every one of these natures, thou
               must observe that its properties are those things by the use of which it profits. And
               if it is tormented by [the use of] any of these things, then know that it is
               influenced by what is not its property. We conclude: If it is known, that the
               affections of every one of these natures are each other's opposites, then,
               consequently, all that gives profit and rest to the body when used by the soul has
               not to be reckoned as belonging to the soul. Because what is natural to the soul is
               fatal to the body, except those things which are connected with the soul in some
               secondary way. Because of the <pb type="external" n="27"/>weakness of the flesh the
               soul can absolutely not be freed from them, as long as it is clad with the flesh. For
               its nature is connected with the troubles of the flesh because of the union of its
               impulses with the carnal senses, with which they are interwoven by the inscrutable
               wisdom. And, though intermingled in this way, nevertheless impulses are distinguished
               from impulses, and will from will, viz. the carnal from the spiritual one. And nature
               is not at all composite nor does it disavow what is its property. And though man
               renders the impulses in a high degree equal to each other, by sin or by excellence,
               at certain times every one exerts its will and shows its power.</p>
            <pb n="19"/>
            <p>But when bodily thoughts have to some extent been lifted up, then their impulses
               manifest themselves wholly in the spiritual sphere, swimming in the heart of heaven
               with incomprehensible things. But even then the body cannot remain without some
               memory of what its own is, even as, when the impulses are in the domain of sin, the
               beautiful emotions of the soul are not brought to silence in the mind.</p>
            <p>What is purity of mind? Not that one who does not know evil things, is pure of mind —
               that were to be a brute. Nor do we call pure of mind those whom nature has placed in
               the age of boyhood that were to postulate that man should not belong to the class of
               created beings. But purity of mind consists in being captivated by divine things, [a
               state] that is only reached when many virtues have been practised.</p>
            <p>We do not venture to say that he that has reached it, has acquired it without the
               experience of contrary deliberations. Else he would not be clad with a body. For we
               do not think <pb type="external" n="28"/>that before the world-to-be nature can be
               purged from contrary [inclinations]. The temptation of the deliberations is not, in
               my opinion this, that one surrenders to them, but the beginning of the struggle
               within the deliberations which begins in the mind on account of the four kinds of
               bases which are the root of movement to all kinds of affections. So that in this life
               there is not found anyone exalted above earthly recollections, even if he belong to
               the masters of the battle and, like <persName>Paul</persName>, be reputed perfect.</p>
            <p>But while the body by means of its impulses, in accordance with the order of nature,
               and the world by its natures through the intermediation of the senses, and the soul
               by deliberations, recollections and powers of deviation, and the demons by the
               co-operating forces of the things mentioned — while<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19-1"/> the power of these
               fourfold affections is experienced by him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19-2"/>, he will be troubled to a small
               degree only<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19-3"/> and be drawn towards the excellent things which are seen by
               intuition. Decide thou, whether it is possible that one of these four be annihilated
               before the annihilation of the world, or by the transition that takes places at
               death; or whether the body can elevate itself wholly above its needs, without
               nature's urging it to seek any <pb n="20"/>of the worldly things. If now this is
               deemed absurd, so long as these [four powers] exist, it is necessary that also the
               affections move themselves in all beings clad with a body, and consequently caution
               must be practised by every one. By the affections I do not understand one or two, but
               all the different ones which [occur in] those clad with flesh. But if a man should
                  <pb type="external" n="29"/>venture [to say that he experiences only] weak
               impulses and harmless strife, we would say that, whoever such people may be, they do
               not require works but great watchfulness.</p>
            <p>What is the difference between purity of mind<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-1"/> and purity of heart.</p>
            <p>Purity of mind is something other than purity of heart, just as there is a difference
               between one of the members of the whole body and the whole body. The mind is one of
               the senses of the soul. The heart is the central organ<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-2"/> of the inward senses;
               this means the sense of senses, because it is the root<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20-3"/>. And if the root is
               holy, so also are all the branches. But this is not so if it is holy in one of the
               branches only. Now with but little acquaintance with the scriptures and a little
               exercise in fasting and solitude, the mind forgets its former occupation and is
               cleansed, while it refrains from foreign habits. But is also easily defiled.</p>
            <p>The heart is purified through great trouble and by being deprived of all association
               with the world, together with a complete mortification in every point. And when it
               has been purified, its purity is not defiled by the touch of insignificant [worldly]
               things; this means: it has no fear even before severe struggles. For it possesses a
               sound stomach that easily digests all sorts of food which are difficult for others
               who are sick in their interior. For the physicians say: All meat which is difficult
               of digestion, increases the forces of the sound body, because it is taken up by a
               strong stomach. In the same way every <pb type="external" n="30"/>purification that
               is brought about easily, in a short time and by small labours, is easily defiled
               again. But the purity that is acquired through great troubles and after a long time
               by the highest part of the soul, is not endangered by insignificant touches of the
               [worldly] things.</p>
            <p>Quiet senses give birth to peace in the soul, because they do not allow it to
               experience strife. But since the soul has no <pb n="21"/>sensation of any thing, it
               is a victory without struggle. But when it becomes negligent, it is not able to
               remain steadfast, and when it strives to get rid of apprehension after the latter has
               got accession, the soul destroys its previous properties, viz. serenity and natural
               perfection. For the majority of men, and possibly the whole world, leave their first
               state on account of this cause<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-1"/>. Only one out of many returns to his first
               place when he has once adopted the second habit. Much better is simplicity than the
               different kinds of forgiveness.</p>
            <p>Human nature needs fear in order to guard against the borders of the commandments
               being crossed, [it needs] love to excite the desire of good things, for the sake of
               which man hastens to perform beautiful things.</p>
            <p>Spiritual knowledge is posterior to the performance of excellence. Prior to both are
               love and fear. And fear is prior to love. Every one who ventures to acquire the
               latter things before the former, undoubtedly lays a perishable foundation in his
               soul. For they are placed by God in such an order, that these proceed from those. Do
               not interchange the love of thy neighbour with the love of [worldly] things, for that
               which is precious above all things, is hidden in it.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="31"/>A material object which is a mark for the eyes of the
               flesh, is also of such a nature as to affect the hidden visual powers; and the
               affections which cloud the second natural contemplation, acts in the same manner for
               the natural steadfastness. They are related to one another in the same way, up to
               where ceases the current of all kinds of contemplation. When the mind<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21-2"/> is in a
               state of natural steadfastness, it is in angelic contemplation, which is the first
               and natural contemplation which is also named naked mind. When the mind is in the
               second state of natural knowledge, it sucks and is sustained by the milk from the
               corporeal breasts; this state is called the last garment of the afore-mentioned
               state; it is placed after [the state of] purity, which the mind enters first. It is
               prior in being, for it is the first stage of knowledge, although posterior in honour.
               On this account, therefore, it is also called the second one, as also on account of
               the indications of some of the tokens by which the mind is purified and trained for
               the ascent to a second order, which is the perfection of the intellectual <pb n="22"
               />impulses, and the stage which is near divine contemplation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-1"/>.</p>
            <p>The last garment of the mind are the senses. Its state of nakedness is its being
               moved by kinds of non-material contemplation. Leave the small things in order to find
               the honoured ones.</p>
            <p>Be dead in life, then thou wilt not live in death. Let thyself die in integrity, but
               not live in guiltiness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22-2"/>. Not only those who suffer death for the sake of the
               faith in Christ are martyrs, but also those who die for the sake of keeping his
               commandments.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="32"/>Be not inept in thy petitions, lest thou grieve God by
               thy ignorance.</p>
            <p>Learn to pray with prudence, that thou mayest be esteemed worthy of glorious
               things.</p>
            <p>Seek well-esteemed things from Him, who does not withhold; then thou wilt receive
               honour from Him, because of the choice of thy wise will.</p>
            <p><persName>Solomon</persName> sought wisdom and he received, apart from it, the earthly kingdom, because he
               knew how to ask wisely viz. great things from the King.</p>
            <p><persName>Elisha</persName> sought one or two parts of the spirit that was upon his master and his request
               was not withheld from him.</p>
            <p>The honour of the King is lessened by him who seeks contemptible things.</p>
            <p>Israel sought despicable things; it gained the anger of God. It neglected to wonder
               at the workings and terrible effects of His deeds and it sought the desires of its
               belly. And while their food was still in their mouth, the anger of God reached them.
               Present thy requests unto God in accordance with His glorious being, in order that
               thy honour be great in His eyes and He rejoice in thee.</p>
            <p>When a man seeks from a king a measure full of dung he will not only be despised on
               account of his despicable request, <pb n="23"/>exposing thus his ignorance, but he
               also insults the king by his insipid demand: such also is he who in prayer asks
               corporeal things from God.</p>
            <p>Lo, the angels and the archangels which are the chiefs of the angels look at thee in
               the time of prayer, [in order to know] which prayer thou wilt present unto their
               Lord. And they wonder at thee when they see the corporeal one leaving his dunghill
               and asking heavenly things.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="33"/>Do not seek from God that which He is anxious to give us
               even if we do not beg for it, which He withholds not from his housemates and not even
               from those who are wholly foreign to the knowledge of Him, nay who do not even know
               that He is.</p>
            <p>Use not vain repetitions, as the heathen do<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23-1"/>. What is this "as the heathen"?
               The corporeal things are sought by the peoples of the earth; but give ye no thought
               saying what shall we eat, or what shall we drink or wherewithall shall we be clothed?
               For your Father knoweth that ye also have need of all these things<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23-2"/>.</p>
            <p>A son does not ask bread from his father, but makes supplication concerning the great
               portions in store for him in the house of his father. That which our Lord has
               commanded concerning daily bread, namely that we pray for it, is a petition which he
               handed down to the common people, because of the weakness of their minds. Regard that
               which he commands to those who are perfect in knowledge and sound of soul, viz.: ye
               shall not take thought of food or raiment. If your Father bestows care upon the fowls
               that have no soul, how much more upon you. But ask from God the Kingdom and
               righteousness, then he will add these things too.</p>
            <p>If He is slow in granting thy request, when thou askest without receiving promptly,
               then be not distressed. For thou art not wiser than God. When thou remainest as thou
               art<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23-3"/>, [it is] either because thy behaviour does not agree with thy request or
               because the ways of thy heart diverge from the aim of thy prayer; or because thy
               inner state is childish in comparison with the greatness of the thing.</p>
            <p>It is not becoming that great things should fall into our <pb type="external" n="34"
               />hands easily; lest the gift of God should be thought to be mean because of its
               being acquired without difficulty.</p>
            <pb n="24"/>
            <p>All that is acquired with labour, is guarded with caution.</p>
            <p>Thirst after <persName>Jesus</persName>; then he will satisfy thee with his love. Shut thy eyes to the
               precious things of the world; then thou wilt be deemed worthy of a peace given by God
               to reign in thy heart.</p>
            <p>Restrain thyself from the allurements that are shining for the eyes; then thou wilt
               be deemed worthy of spiritual joy.</p>
            <p>If thy behaviour is not worthy of God, do not ask from Him praised things, lest thou
               appear as a man who tries God.</p>
            <p>Prayer accords strictly with behaviour.</p>
            <p>No man desires heavenly things as long as he is bound with ties [impeding] his will,
               on account of the body. And no man asks divine things while he is occupied with
               earthly things. The desire of every man is known from his works; and that which he
               cares for, he will be anxious to seek in prayer. And he will be zealous in showing by
               his outward deeds that which he asks for in his prayer.</p>
            <p>He who desires great things, has no intercourse with mean ones.</p>
            <p>Be free even while thou art bound in the body and show submission in thy freedom for
               the sake of Christ; and be wise in thy innocence, lest thou be beguiled.</p>
            <p>Love humility in thy dealings, that thou mayest be freed from the imperceivable
               snares which are continually to be found by the side of the paths on which the humble
               walk.</p>
            <p>Do not reject the troubles, by means of which thou art led towards knowledge.</p>
            <p>Do not fear temptations by means of which thou wilt find precious things.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="35"/>Pray that thou mayest not be led into temptations of the
               soul. To those of the body thou shalt prepare thyself with all thy force and with all
               thy limbs thou shalt swim in them. For without them it is impossible for thee to
               approach unto God. For beyond them lies divine rest.</p>
            <p>Who flees from temptations, flees from excellence; not from the temptations of
               desires, but from [those of] troubles.</p>
            <p>How does the sentence "pray, that ye enter not into temptation"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-1"/> concord with
               "strive to enter in at the strait gate"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-2"/> and "fear not them which kill the
               body"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-3"/> and "he that loseth his life for my sake shall find it"?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24-4"/></p>
            <pb n="25"/>
            <p>In all these places our Lord recommends to us temptations; but in that he orders us
               to pray that we enter not into temptation. What kind of excellence can be
               accomplished without temptations? Or what kind of temptation is stronger than the
               which he orders us to undergo for His sake? And "he that taketh not his cross and
               followeth after me, is not worthy of me"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-1"/>. "Pray that ye enter not into
               temptation", but entering into temptations occurs everywhere in his teachings. And he
               has said: without temptations the Kingdom of heaven is not found.</p>
            <p>O how strait is the way of thy teachings, our Lord! And he who does not discriminate
               with knowledge, as he reads, will always remain without it, as far as his insight is
               concerned.</p>
            <p>When the sons of <persName>Zebedee</persName> and their mother desired of him to sit with him in the
               Kingdom, he postulated this: Are ye able to suffer gladly the cup of temptations? Are
               ye able to <pb type="external" n="36"/>drink of the cup that I shall drink of and to
               be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25-2"/>? And how orderest Thou
               here, O our Lord: pray that ye enter not?</p>
            <p>Which are the temptations into which we shall pray not to enter.</p>
            <p>Pray that thou enterest not into temptation concerning thy belief.</p>
            <p>Pray that thou enterest not into temptation through mental presumtion, with the demon
               of abuse and haughtiness.</p>
            <p>Pray that thou enterest not, under [God's] admission, into the manifest temptations
               of the senses, which <persName>Satan</persName> is able to instill unto thee with God's permission, on
               account of the foolish thoughts thou hast cherished.</p>
            <p>Pray that the witness of chastity be not taken away from thee lest thou be tempted in
               the flames of sin without him.</p>
            <p>Pray that thou enterest not into the temptation of abusing anything.</p>
            <p>Pray therefore, that thou enterest not into psychic temptations, namely those which
               lead the soul into struggle, doubt and allurements. But prepare for the bodily ones
               with thy whole body and swim in them with all thy limbs, thy eyes full of tears, that
               thou be found amidst of them with thy guardian. For without temptations God's care
               cannot be perceived and familiarity of speech with Him cannot be acquired and <pb
                  n="26"/>spiritual wisdom cannot be learnt and the love of God cannot be implanted
               in the soul.</p>
            <p>Before [having experienced] temptations, man prays unto God as a stranger. But when
               he has entered into troubles for the sake of his love, without being changed, then,
               as one that has laid upon God [the obligation of paying] a certain loan, he is
               reckoned as His housemate and His friend, who has fought, for the sake of His will,
               against the host of His enemies. This <pb type="external" n="37"/>is [the meaning
               of]: Pray that ye enter not into temptation.</p>
            <p>And further: pray that thou enterest not into temptations for the sake of thy
               self-exaltation, but for the sake of thy love of God, that His power may be
               conspicuous in thee. Pray that thou enterest not into such on account of the folly of
               thy thoughts and deeds, but in order that thou provest to be a friend of God and His
               power be glorified in thy endurance.</p>
            <p>On the mercy of our Lord in this matter, who measures his word in accordance with
               human weakness.</p>
            <p>Further he deals [with us] in this matter compassionately. If thou considerest bodily
               things [it appears that God], also in this point has remembered the weakness of
               nature; it was possible that, on account of the wretchedness of the body, we should
               not find fortitude against the power of the temptations whenever it should present
               itself, and consequently we should even leave [the path of] truth, being overcome by
               troubles. Therefore he orders us that, as much as possible, we should avoid entering
               wilfully into temptation. And not only this, but [he even says]: Pray that you be not
               found in it without just cause, if it be possible to please God without
               temptation.</p>
            <p>But if very great excellence is desired, when temptations assail and that most
               terribly, and if that excellence cannot be accomplished without a man's bearing them,
               in that case it is not becoming to spare ourselves or anyone. Even on account of fear
               thou shalt not shrink from that great thing upon which the life of thy soul depends,
               putting forward as an apology <pb type="external" n="38"/>for thy laxness: Pray that
               ye enter not into temptation. For such are those, concerning whom it is said that
               they sin secretly by [fulfilling] the commandments.</p>
            <p>If one of the divine commandments comes to be dissociated from a man, be it the state
               of chastity, or the habit of holiness, or the confession of faith, or the testimony
               concerning the word <pb n="27"/>of God, or the cautiously guarding of the other
               prescriptions of the Law — it is impossible that he should not fall if he be afraid
               of temptations. Therefore he has to despise the body with complete confidence, and to
               entrust God with its soul and to proceed in the name of the Lord. And He that was
               with <persName>Joseph</persName> in the land of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and who was the witness of his chastity, and who was
               with <persName>Daniel</persName> in the pit of lions, and with <persName>Hananja</persName> and his companions in the furnace,
               and with <persName>Jeremia</persName> in the pit of mire and who saved him and made him an object of
               compassion in the midst of the camp of the Chaldaeans; who was with <persName>Peter</persName> in the
               prison and brought him out of it through shut gates; and with <persName>Paul</persName> in the synagogues
               of the Jews; in short, He who in all generations was with His servants always and
               everywhere and showed in them His power and made them victorious and guarded them
               miraculously so that they saw His salvation manifestly at the time of their troubles,
               He will strengthen and guard him in the midst of the storms which surround him.
               Therefore he shall arm himself against the invisible foe and his hosts with the zeal
               of the Maccabees and of the other holy prophets, apostles, martyrs, confessors and
               recluses who have maintained the divine laws and the spiritual commandments in
               frightful places and <pb type="external" n="39"/>among difficult and fearful
               temptations and who have thrown the world and the body behind them and clung to the
               truth in them without giving way to the constraint pressing both body and soul and
               endured as heroes; in short, whose names are written in the book of life until the
               coming of our Lord. And their deeds are preserved in the book by God's decree for our
               instruction and encouragement according to the testimony of the blessed Apostle, so
               that we may get insight from them and learn the way of God, placing their stories
               before our mental eyes as living images, that we may resemble them and conform the
               ways of our behaviour unto theirs, after the pattern of the Ancients.</p>
            <p>To the soul endowed with mind the words of God are delightful as oily food which
               makes fat the body, to the palate of those who are healthy.</p>
            <p>The stories of the just are as desirable to the ear of the perfect, as a constant
               watering to young plantations.</p>
            <p>Listening to God's providential leading of the Ancients be estimated by thee as
               precious drugs for weak eyes. And let <pb n="28"/>the recollection of it be kept with
               thee at all times of the clay. Meditate and think of it and learn wisdom from it,
               that thou be able to receive in thy soul with honour the recollection of God's
               greatness and find for thyself everlasting-life in <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, the mediator of God
               and mankind, who was one in his two natures[a]. Though the legions of the angels are
               not able to look upon the glory surrounding His majestic throne, yet for thy sake He
               has appeared before the world the most contemptible and humble of man; without form
               or comeliness; <pb type="external" n="40"/>and while His invisible nature was not
               within the reach of the apprehension of created beings, He accomplished His
               providential dealings by [covering Himself] with a veil [made of the stuff] of our
               limbs, in order to save the life of all. [b]</p>
            <p>This is he through whom He has purified many peoples<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-1"/> and on whom the Lord has
               laid the sin of us all<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-2"/>, as <persName>Jesaja</persName> says. It pleased the Lord to humble him and
               to put him to grief<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-3"/>. [c]</p>
            <p>Sin has been placed in him who knew no sin<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28-4"/>. To whom, for his providential
               dealings in all generations for our sake, be glory and praise and thanksgiving and
               adoration from all, now and at all time and for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n14-1">The passage reminds in a remarkable way of Plotinus' description of
               the spontaneous character of the illumination. Zeller, Phil. d. Griechen⁴, III, 2, p.
               672 describes it thus: ohne Vermittlung und Vorbereitung, durch eine plötzliche
               Erleuchtung geht es in der Seele auf, sie kann nicht sagen woher es kommt, ob von
               innen oder von aussen, ja es kommt streng genommen, gar nicht, sondern es ist
               unmittelbar da.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-1">Cf. Introduction.</note>
            <note xml:id="n15-2">This terminology occurs in Stoic writings. Cf. Zeller. Philosophie
               der Griechen⁴, III, 1, p. 264.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-1">ܕܠܦܘܬ ܡܕܡ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16-2">ܫܐܝ̈ܠܐ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n17-1"> Cf. Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n18-1">Cf. Galatians 5, 17.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19-1">I have retained the anakoluthic character of the original.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19-2">The mystic.</note>
            <note xml:id="n19-3">Other Mss: he will perceive this to a small extent only.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-1">ܪܥܝܢܐ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-2">ܐܚܝܕ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20-3">Cf. Introduction.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-1">Negligence.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21-2">ܗܘܢܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-1">The above passage betrays its relation with Philonean thought at
               once by the term "naked mind" which often occurs in Philo (I 76 sq., 98, 179, 270).
               There is further concordance, but also difference between the two authors. Both of
               them distinguishes three kinds of nakedness. According to Isaac, they are: the
               puerile state, the state of natural purity, and the purified state. According to
               Philo (I 76 sq.) they are: the puerile slate; the state of Noah's drunkenness in
               which the sold has lost its faculties: the state of purity in which the soul has
               abandoned all earthly things.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22-2"> Cf. Porphyrius, Sententiae, IX: ὁ γοῦν θάνατος διπλοῦς· ὁ μὲν
               συνεγνωσμένος λυομένου τοῦ σώματος ἀπὸ ψυχῆς· ὁ δὲ τῶν Φιλοσόφων, λυομένης τῆς ψυχῆς
               ἀπὸ τοῦ σώματος. And the Pythagorean sentence in Stobaeus (p. 158): τεθνάναι πολλῷ
               κρεῖττον ἢ δι’ ἀκρασίαν τὴν ψυχὴν ἀμαυρῶσαι.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23-1">Matthew 6,7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23-2"> Matthew 6,31 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n23-3"> The prayer not being heard.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-1"> Matthew 26,41.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-2"> Luke 13,24.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-3"> Matthew 10,28.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24-4"> Matthew 10,39.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-1">Matthew 10,38.</note>
            <note xml:id="n25-2"> Matthew 20,22.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-1">Jesaja 52,15 in the Peshho.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-2">Jes. 53,6.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-3">Jcs. 53,10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28-4">2 Cor. 5,21.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
