<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 68</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 68, pp. 318-321.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="68">
            <head>LXVIII</head>
            <head>Short sections</head>
            <p>You must know, my brethren, that the sensual eye through its visual power alone
               (which is administered unto it from the brains as it were through a channel), without
               partaking of other light, is not able to receive [the images] of the different
               things. All natural apperceptions are placed on the same level as the intelligible
               things as regards spiritual behaviour in this respect; and [as for] the natural force
               of the intellect, which is also called psychic knowledge — it is impossible for the
               soul to participate in truth by contemplation, without receiving divine light. This
               is based upon excellence of behaviour, which is acquired when the affectible part of
               the soul is built upon natural health. For many have endeavoured [to acquire this]
               while being entangled in psychic and bodily affections, by philosophical training,
               being supported by the latter alone but they have lost even the truth which they
               possessed and have ruined their usual visual power. And just as eyes which see in the
               air fantastic images because of their weak sight which cannot reach the humid matter
               in them, so every one of them <pb type="external" n="475"/>considers as truth one
               image which presents itself to him. And when all the images of all of them are
               united, then, in stead of one truth, there appears a variety of images. And this
               happens to them because they have not asked for the rays of grace which shines so as
               to purify the soul. Truth is the apperception concerning God which a man personally
               tastes by the perceptive power of the spiritual senses of the mind.</p>
            <p>The flower of spiritual knowledge is divine love, which has its origin in radiant
               insights which are found by the spirit during prayer. Love is the fruit of prayer,
               which, on account <pb n="319"/>of contemplation originating in it, draws the mind
               towards a predilection which never becomes satisfied; the mind clings to this
               predilection for prayer without growing dejected, be it that it prays apperceptibly,
               with the body, or by the silent motion of the mind, fervently and eagerly. Prayer is:
               the impulses of the will being dead regarding fleshly life. For it is alike when a
               man prays veraciously and when he dies from the world; this means that he denies
               himself, and this means continually being in prayer.</p>
            <p>It is known to those who know the scriptures what beseeching in veracious prayer is.
               And it is known that those who have devoted themselves to this lonely state in order
               to acquire lonely prayer through their demands, thwarting their desire, do not follow
               their nature when they arouse trouble against their soul because of the contrary
               affections which they stir <pb type="external" n="476"/>in their soul after
               prayer.</p>
            <p>So the love of God is found in selfdenial. As from the seeds of the sweat of fasting
               the blade of chastity grows up, so does lasciviousness grow up from satiety and
               impudence from repletion. Against a hungry stomach wanton deliberations never direct
               themselves. Every food which we receive within us is added to the humours of the
               natural seed which is collected in our body. And when the organic limbs are filled
               with the influx which is gathered there from the whole body, and when it happens that
               the bodily [eye] sees [something], or when some involuntary recollection is awakened
               in the heart, then at once, together with the thought a sensation of delight is astir
               and spreads through the whole body, so that, even if the mind is very strong and
               chaste and cautious in its emotions, still, by this apperception of the limbs, the
               discriminating power of the mind is troubled at once, and is, as it were, cast down
               from the height where it stood, and the holiness of its deliberations is
               perverted.</p>
            <p>And its pure chastity is defiled by the confusion which is caused by the affection
               that is astir in the heart on account of the burning of the limbs; and at once half
               of its force is lost, so to say, and the former scope of its hope is forgotten; and
               though it has not entered into the struggle, it is defeated without strife or labour
               on the part of its fiend, and vanquished by the subduing will of the body.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="477"/>To such an extent does copious food and constant satiety
                  <pb n="320"/>compel a man's good will that, although he is moving steadily in the
               harbour of chastity, he stoops to comply with that which he never would have stooped
               to think of. And when he lies down to sleep, alone, a host of thoughts clad in
               impudent images surrounds him. And his chaste bed is made by them a theatre and a
               brothel, where he deals and speaks with his thoughts in drunkenness and defiles his
               holy limbs, though no woman is near to him.</p>
            <p>What sea is so disturbed by storms as the steady mind is stirred by the vehemence of
               the waves assailing it in the sea of the body, through a full stomach? O chastity,
               how is thy beauty made splendid by sleeping on the ground, by the suffering of
               hunger, when sleep flies from thee on account of the leanness of the body and the
               emptiness of the stomach, which is made a deep pit for the intestines between the
               ribs by abstinence from food. But by indulgence in food and comfort, evil
               representations and impure images are formed and come into existence. Then they
               proceed and show themselves to us in the hidden place of our mind, inciting us to
               mingle with them secretly by impudent actions.</p>
            <p>Emptiness of the stomach makes free room for the mind which is devoid of
               deliberations and all tumult of thoughts. But when the stomach is replenished and
               satisfied it is made thereby a place of sights and a theatre, even if we are in <pb
                  type="external" n="478"/>the wilderness and alone. For he that is satisfied
               desires many things.</p>
            <p>Thou understandest that thou hast been deemed worthy of psychic apathy therein not,
               that no evil deliberations pass through thee — that is [the absence of] the movement
               of the impulses which are in the body, <choice><sic>the</sic><corr>that</corr></choice> which is impossible — nor that
               thou vanquishest them easily, the thought not having been defiled or disturbed at
               all, however exalted this may be; but that, through the intellect being totally
               occupied, the mind is not even permitted to combat with or to crush them, but that as
               soon as deliberations elevate their head, it is dragged away from them by some
               involuntary force, which by custom or grace, begins to ferment in the heart which is
               the house of the intellect. The struggling mind is different from the rank of
               priesthood. The mind which, by heavenly mercy, is dead to the world, to it things
               cause simple deliberations only, without the strife of battle, though from the motion
               of the <pb n="321"/>limbs an apperceptive power without equal [is born]. Perfection
               which is joined with flesh and blood rules over that which originates in flesh and
               blood, but it does not annihilate the peculiarities of nature while vital impulses
               still move in elementary life, and the foundation of existence, on account of the
               four humours, is subject to various emotions.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
