<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 6</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 6, pp. 55-67</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="6">
            <head>VI</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="81"/>The fact that a man may fall into accidental faults,
               proves the weakness of his nature, namely that our nature necessarily is liable to
               such things. It has not seemed good unto God that it would be profitable for him that
               he should be wholly exalted above this [weakness], before his nature arrived at the
               second creation. The fact of his being subject to chance, is profitable for the
               subjugation of the mind. But the constant [falling into faults] causes audacity.</p>
            <p>There are three modes by which every rational soul may approach unto God: by the
               fervour of faith; by fear; by punishment from God. For it cannot approach unto the
               rank of love by its own power; but only if it is based on one of these modes.</p>
            <p>As from a disordered[#n55-1] belly confusion of thought is born, so, from wantonness
               in speech and confusion of habits, ignorance and folly of mind.</p>
            <p>The care of practical things confuses the soul, and the distraction of work disturbs
               the mind and makes it lose its quietness and drives away from it its peacefulness. It
               is becoming for the solitary who has devoted himself to heavenly work, that his mind
               be constantly free from care so that, when he examines his soul and deliberates, he
               may not see in it any thing belonging to this world, nor desire of any visible
               object, <pb type="external" n="82"/>but that, on account of his complete absorption
               from temporary <pb n="56"/>things, he may be able to meditate upon the law of the
               Lord night and day, without any distraction.</p>
            <p>Bodily works without mental beauty are like a barren womb and dry breasts; they do
               not bring any nearer unto the knowledge of God. They have no care for a body
               labouring to eradicate passions from the mind; so they do not reap anything.</p>
            <p>As a man who sows on thorns and is not able to reap, so is he whose mind is injured
               by care and wrath and desire of gathering treasures, and who sighs on his bed on
               account of the frequency of his vigils and abstinence. Witness is the scripture that
               says: As a nation that did righteousness and forsook not the ordinance of their God:
               they ask of me the ordinances of justice; they take delight in coming near unto God.
               Wherefore have we fasted and thou seest not? Have we afflicted our soul and thou
               takest no knowledge? Behold, in the day of your fast ye find pleasure and sacrifice
               unto all your idols[#n56-1].</p>
            <p>This means: the evil designs and the evil thoughts hold you in yourself in stead of
               God and sacrifice to them your liberty, a thing esteemed at all times; the sacrifice
               which is honoured above all things and which you ought not to omit, consists of your
               good works and pious inner being. A good land which makes its lord rejoice by
               yielding an hundredfold, is the soul <pb type="external" n="83"/>that is made
               excellent by meditation on God, in vigil day and night. The Lord will build upon its
               foundations and around it, a cloud for shade during the day and a shining flame of
               fire during the night. From within its darkness, light will dawn.</p>
            <p>As a cloud obscures the rays of the moon, so the vapour of the stomach obscures the
               divine wisdom so that the soul does not see it[#n56-2]. As a hearth burning with dry
               wood, so is bodily desire in a full stomach. As oily matter excites the fierceness of
               a flame, so does the humidity of food the carnal passion in the body.</p>
            <p>The knowledge of God does not dwell in a body that loves comfort.</p>
            <p>A man who loves his body will not be deemed worthy of divine gifts.</p>
            <p>As from the travail a fruit is born that gladdens the woman, so from labours there is
               born in the soul the knowledge of God's mysteries. To the pusillanimous and those who
               love <pb n="57"/>comfort, a fruit is born that causes shame. As a father shows mercy
               unto his son, so Christ shows mercy unto the body that performs labours, and He is
               near its mouth at all times. The labour of wisdom is priceless.</p>
            <p>A stranger is he who is strange is his spirit unto every habit of this world. A
               mourner[#n57-1] is he, who spends all the days of this life in hunger, thirst and
               mourning, for the sake of the expectation of heavenly hope. A recluse is he who, <pb
                  type="external" n="84"/>removing his abode from the sight of the world, and
               looking beyond, has only one demand in prayer: the desire of the world to be. The
               riches of the solitary are in his heart[#n57-2]. The riches of the solitary are
               either consolation granted him from the midst of mourning, or gladness that dawns
               from faith, the treasury of his spirit. The compassionate is he, whose spirit does
               not distinguish, when practising compassion, any of the classes of men. Virginity is
               this, that a man not only guards his body from the corruptions of revelling, but that
               he also guards his chastity against his soul even when he is alone. It thou desirest
               chastity, restrain the course of impure deliberations, by occupying thyself with
               recitation and constant beseechings unto God. Then thou wilt be armed also in thy
               inner being against the things that spring from nature. Without those, man is able to
               see purity in himself.</p>
            <p>If thou art desirous to acquire compassion, first train thyself to acquire contempt
               for [outward] things, lest their importance draw the mind away from the aim which it
               has set before itself. The purity of compassion is known from patience in bearing
               wrong, and the perfection of humility from idle oppression borne gladly. If thou art
               really compassionate, thou wilt not be angry within thyself, when thou art bereft of
               thy possessions iniquitously and with injustice; and thou wilt not show thy suffering
               openly unto others, but let the sin of thy injustice be effaced by <pb
                  type="external" n="85"/>passionate compassion, as the headiness of wine is abated
               by [mixing it with] much water. But show thou the mark of purity that arises from
               great mercy, by adding there-unto other things and do well to those who do thee
               wrong, with gladness, as also the blessed Elisha did unto his enemies, which were
               come to take him prisoner who, by praying and by blinding their eyes <pb n="58"/>by
               visions, made manifest the power at his disposal. And if he had wished this, they
               would have been annihilated before him; but by providing them with food and drink and
               letting them go away, he made manifest the mercy he possessed within himself.</p>
            <p>If thou art truly humble, be not troubled if thou art oppressed. And do not excuse
               thyself in any point, but actually take upon thee the wrong laid to thy charge,
               without being anxious to persuade people that the matter is otherwise. On the
               contrary, pray that thou mayest obtain forgiveness. Some have taken upon them the
               evil name of fornication and others have taken upon them deeds of adultery for which
               they were too pious, and the fruit of a sin which they had not committed they made
               appear serious by bewailing it as if it were their own. And they implored forgiveness
               for sins which they had not committed from their oppressor with tears, while their
               soul was crowned with the full purity of chastity. Others, lest they should be
               praised on account of wonderful deeds performed in secret, have assumed the habits of
               lunatics, though they were in the full possession of their wits and their serenity;
               so that <pb type="external" n="86"/>the holy angels, in admiration of these deeds,
               became spectators of the greatness of such men. Thou, however, hast assumed humility
               where those others have given witness against themselves; thou art not even able to
               keep silence if thou art accused, and yet thou deemest thyself to be humbler If thou
               art [really] humble, try thyself by these things, whether or not thou art
               troubled.</p>
            <p>The many mansions in the house of the Father denote the spiritual degrees of the
               inhabitants of that place. This means: the different gifts and the spiritual ranks in
               which they rejoice spiritually, and the variety of the classes of gifts. It is not to
               be understood in such a manner, that every person has really his defined portion in
               the various local habitations, so that [these differences] manifest themselves openly
               in the variety of particular mansions <choice><sic>apponited</sic><corr>appointed</corr></choice> for every one; but they
               are to be compared with the personal advantage every one of us obtains by the
               personal yet common use of this apperceptive sun in accordance with the purity of his
               visual power. Thus as the eyelid regulates the effusion of the quality of light, and
               as a lamp[#n58-1], in one and the same house, distributes the use of <pb n="59"/>its
               light in a varied fashion, although the lamp itself is not bereft of the simplicity
               of its light, so as to become many with its varied aspects, so, those who have been
               deemed worthy of that place, although dwelling in one mansion, indivisible as it is
               into parts, attract, at a fixed time, from one and the same intelligible sun, every
               one according to the rank of his <pb type="external" n="87"/>behaviour, the own
               delight, in one air and one place and one abode and with one sight and one mode. The
               high degree of his neighbour's rank is not seen by him who is inferior, namely not as
               if it arose from the many gifts of his neighbour and from the scarcity of his own
               gifts, so that it should be to him a cause of grief and spiritual torment, absit! To
               think such things in the place of delights were impossible. Every one rejoices within
               himself at the gift he has been deemed worthy of, and at the height of his rank. But
               the outward aspect of them all, is one; and the place is one. And what is still
               truer, they dwell as in encampments of angels, in one aereal abode, in equality of
               actual vision, with secret consciousness of their [different] ranks, in contemplative
               revelations that vary according to their degree.</p>
            <p>If real personal beings possess, apart from working apperceptive power, also
               spiritual impulses, no one will venture, even in the world to be, to proclaim in
               words an order of things deviating from this one: that [that the only differentiation
               is with regard to] the intellect and further [spiritual] powers, even though [this
               differentiation] be very manifest on account of the perfection of nature. True,
               therefore, is the word spoken by the Fathers: on the one hand there is ignorance for
               an undetermined time; on the other hand there is a limited time for the manifestation
               of its abrogation, together with [the revelation of] other peculiar mysteries that
               are defined in silence by the [supreme] being. For there is no mean between <pb
                  type="external" n="88"/>complete elevation and absolute abasement, in the future
               separation. Either one belongs wholly to the high ones or wholly to the low ones. But
               within this and the other [state] there are varying modes of retribution.</p>
            <p>And if this be true, as it is true, what then is the folly of some, who say: I do not
               desire to be in the kingdom; if I only could strive after salvation from hell. Being
               saved from hell is the kingdom. And being without the kingdom is hell. For the
               scriptures do not teach three places [in the world to <pb n="60"/>be]. What do they
               teach? When the son of man shall come in his glory, he shall set the sheep on his
               right hand, but the goats on the left[#n60-1]. Here the scriptures do not mention
               three classes, but two: those of the right hand and those of the left. The difference
               between the dwelling place is given distinctly. And these, it says, shall shine forth
               as the sun in the kingdom of the father[#n60-2], and those [will depart] into
               everlasting fire[#n60-3]. Further: They shall come from the east and west, and shall
               sit down with Abraham in the kingdom[#n60-4]. And the children of the promise that
               have not been obedient shall go into the darkness outside the kingdom. There will be
               psychic weeping and grinding of teeth, which is a grief more hard than the fire. Now
               thou understandest that to remain far from that elevation means torturing hell.</p>
            <p>It is beautiful for a man to admonish mankind unto beautiful <pb type="external"
                  n="89"/>things and to bring them, by his constant care, from error to the
               knowledge of life. And this is the stage of our Lord and the apostles, and it is very
               elevated. But if he perceives within himself, that by familiar and constant
               intercourse, his inner being becomes injured by the sight of [worldly] things, and
               his serenity is disturbed so as to lose its discernment, and is darkened, since his
               spirit still acquires cautiousness and stricter submission of the senses. For he is
               sick as long as his senses are not yet healed: and wishing to heal others, he loses
               his own partial health of soul and quits the chaste freedom of his will for a
               troubled mind. Such a one has to recall the word of the apostle who says: Strong meat
               belongeth to the healthy[#n60-5], and he shall turn back, lest he hear from them,
               symbolically: How art thou a physician for others, yet full of wounds thyself?
               Accordingly he shall keep to himself and guard his own health only. Then instead of
               audible words he shall care[#n60-6] for a beautiful behaviour, and others will profit
               not by his spoken words, but by the health in which he holds himself, if possible.
               Thus by his health they will be healed, even though he be absent, [that is to say] by
               the zeal of his excellent deeds, which is a more excellent thing than to serve them
               merely with words, while sick himself, and in need of healing more than they
               themselves.</p>
            <pb n="61"/>
            <p>For if the blind lead the blind, both shall fall into the ditch[#n61-1]. <pb
                  type="external" n="90"/>For strong meat belongeth to the healthy and to those
               whose senses have been trained and strengthened so as to receive all kinds of food,
               that is [those that are strengthened] against all sensual shocks, because the heart
               is healthy on account of its training in perfection.</p>
            <p>But when Satan desires to defile the chaste spirit by thoughts of fornication, he
               first tempts its endurance by vain glory, since the beginning of such a thought does
               not resemble that of the affections. This he does with the guarded spirit into which
               he cannot easily instill a thought which is purely evil. But when he that was strong,
               by meditating on old thoughts has left his fortress and when he is at some distance
               from it, Satan causes him to be assailed by full opportunity of fornication, by
               associating the spirit with lascivious things.</p>
            <p>At first the spirit feels a sudden terror when it meets them, because of the chastity
               of the deliberations that meet the [worldly] things, for the mind, their governor,
               has refrained from looking at them before. But it falls from the height of its
               original thought, even though it be not defiled. And it does not turn and regains
               quickly the former deliberations which are the cause of the secondary ones, then,
               when it meets often with these things, custom will blind the discernment of the soul
               through frequency of meeting. So in accordance with the quantity and the character of
               the first affection, is the submission to the second.</p>
            <p>To avoid the affections by the recollection of virtues is easier and more beautiful
               than to vanquish them in strife. For when the affections leave their place and are in
               motion so as <pb type="external" n="91"/>to show themselves at strife, then they also
               print on the spirit forms and images. [People of] this rank[#n61-2] possess a great
               valiance, so that they draw strength from the spirit; but the mind is greatly
               disturbed and troubled. By the former way of proceeding mentioned, even the traces of
               affections are not known in the spirit when they have departed.</p>
            <p>Bodily labours and meditating upon the scriptures preserve purity. And labours are
               made firm by hope and fear. Hope and fear are established in the spirit by seclusion
               from the <pb n="62"/>children of man and by constant prayer[#n62-1]. Until man has
               received the Comforter, he needs written documents[#n62-2], in order to fix in his
               heart, by images, profitable recollections. And by constant meditation upon them, he
               will renew the attractions of excellence and see in himself caution against the
               narrow paths of sin; for he does not yet possess the dominating force of spirit which
               reduces to oblivion those powers which bereave man of profitable recollections and
               adduce in him languor by distraction of mind.</p>
            <p>But when spiritual force enters and dwells in the intelligible forces of the
               operative soul, then there are fixed in the heart in stead of written laws spiritual
               commandments, which the heart learns secretly from the spirit, which does not need
               the help of sensible material[#n62-3] by the medium of the senses.</p>
            <p>Whenever the mind learns from matter this instruction is followed by error and
               forgetfulness. But whenever it draws instruction from incorruptible things, its
               recollection will also be incorruptible, founded on their intelligible nature.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="92"/>There are good deliberations and there is a good will.
               There are evil deliberations and there is an evil heart. The former, without the
               latter are of little account for remuneration. The latter are impulses which blow
               over the mind, as the winds that blow over the sea causing waves to arise. But the
               latter are the roots. And in accordance with the fundamental direction is also the
               good or the bad remuneration; not in accordance with the motion of the deliberations.
               For the soul does not cease from setting into motion varying deliberations, and if
               thou calculatest a remuneration for all these even though they have no root beneath,
               thou wilt be near to changing thy remuneration and thy retributions thousand times
               every day.</p>
            <p>A young bird without wings is the mind that has lately left the bonds of the
               affections, by means of the works of repentance. At the time of prayer it strives to
               exalt itself above earthly things, but it cannot. For it creeps still on the surface
               of the earth, where also the serpent crawls. But it concentrates its deliberations by
               recitation and works and fear and care for excellent qualities. For beyond these it
               does not yet know anything. And these keep the mind pure for a short time. But <pb
                  n="63"/>then recollections will return, troubling and defiling the heart. For he
               does not yet perceive the air of peace and liberty, which concentrates the mind for a
               long time, [keeping it] quiet without any recollection of [worldly] things. For it
               has still <pb type="external" n="93"/>wings of flesh, viz. bodily virtues which are
               exercised openly. But <choice><sic>is</sic><corr>it</corr></choice> does not yet see and perceive the theoretical
               significance of the virtues exercised, which consists in wings of the mind by which
               it approaches unto heavenly things and is removed far from the earth.</p>
            <p>As long as man serves God in a way that can be perceived by the senses and in
               [outward] things, the prints of things will be delineated in his deliberations and
               his mind will think of divine things in bodily forms. But when he perceives that
               which is within things, then, according to the measure of its apperceptive power, the
               mind will also be exalted above the forms of things in due time. The eyes of the Lord
               are upon the humble and His ears are willing to hear them[#n63-1]. The prayer of the
               humble [goes] as it were from his mouth unto [God's] ear: O Lord, my God, let my
               darkness be enlightened. When thou art [occupied] in solitude with the beautiful work
               of humility, when thy soul is near unto coming forth from under the darkness, this
               will be thy sign: thy heart will burn and glow as with fire, night and day, so that
               thou wilt esteem all earthly things as ash and dung. This means that it will not even
               please thee to touch food, on account of the pleasure of the new, fervent
               deliberations, which move continually within thee. Then, of a sudden, the fountain of
               tears will be given thee, so that they flow from thy eyes, as the waters of brooks,
               without compulsion, mingling themselves with all thy work, viz. with thy recitation
               and with thy prayer, with thy service and with thy meditation, with thy food and with
               thy drink, with all that thou doest tears will stream. If thou observest this in <pb
                  type="external" n="94"/>thyself, take heart, thou hast passed through the sea.
               Continue thy labours, keep thy cautiousness sound that thy grace may augment from day
               to day. As long as thou hast not yet met with these things, thy way has not yet
               finally reached the mountain of God.</p>
            <p>If this state vanishes after thou hast found it and if this fervour abates, without
               thy proceeding to take another thing <pb n="64"/>as its substitute, woe to thee, what
               hast thou lost! Either thou hast become haughty, or thou art lax. What is it that is
               situated after tears, and what a man meets after having passed beyond them, and what
               there is further after this latter state, we will describe beneath, in those chapters
               which deal with the course of behaviour, as a thing concerning which we are
               enlightened by the scriptures and by the Fathers who were entrusted such
               mysteries.</p>
            <p>If thou hast no works thou shalt not speak about excellence. Dearer to God are trials
               for righteousness' sake, than all vows and sacrifices. And dearer is the odour of the
               sweat of the fatigue they cause, than all the drugs of sweet scent and exquisite
               perfumes.</p>
            <p>All excellence, which does not vex the body, must be deemed by thee a miscarriage
               without a soul. The sacrifices of the righteous are the tears of their eyes, and
               their acceptable offerings are the sighs of their vigils. The saints lament because
               of the dulness of the body and they sigh and send their prayers unto God with
               suffering. And at the voice of their lamentations the <pb type="external" n="95"
               />holy hosts assemble to them in order to give them heart through hope and to console
               them. The holy angels are their partners during the temptations and sufferings of the
               saints, because they are near to them.</p>
            <p>Labours and humility make man a God on the earth. Faith and compassion give a speedy
               advance to clearness. Fervour and a broken heart cannot dwell in one soul; neither do
               those that are drunk know control of their mind. When fervour has been given, sorrow
               and mourning are taken away. Wine has been given for gladness, and fervour for the
               joy of the soul. The former warms the heart, the word of God the mind. Those who are
               kindled by fervour, are transported to the world to be in their deliberations by
               meditations of hope. As to those who are drunk with wine, various hallucinations
               present themselves, so he, who is drunk and is ablaze does not know trouble, nor the
               world nor anything in it. These things happen to those who are simple of heart and
               fervent with hope.</p>
            <p>The many things which will happen unto those who go the traditional course of
               behaviour after long labours of purification are tasted by them, in the beginning of
               the way, by faith of soul only. All that the Lord wills, He does.</p>
            <p>Blessed are those who, in the sea of troubles, keep themselves <pb n="65"/>simple and
               avoid investigation, in fervour to God, without turning their back, for they will
               quickly be safe in the harbour of the promises and rest in the mansions attained by
               all who labour well. There they are consoled for their toiling, exulting <pb
                  type="external" n="96"/>with the joy of their hope.</p>
            <p>Those who proceed with hope, are not liable to see the injuries on the way; neither
               are they able to investigate the like. But when they have gone ashore they appear
               unto them, and they praise God [thinking of] how they have been guarded amidst all
               those storms and the many cliffs of which they were unconscious, because they were
               not anxious to look at such things. But those who cherish serious thoughts and wish
               to deal very prudently, and give themselves up to evolving deliberations and to bear
               and make many preparations, and wish to see and to deliberate the causes of injuries
               and thoughts of relaxation, such are usually constantly found at the door of their
               houses. For the slothful man saith, There is a lion without, I shall be slain in the
               streets[#n65-1]. And as those who said: And there we saw the giants, and we were in
               our own sight as grasshoppers[#n65-2]. And the cities are strong and walled up to
               heaven[#n65-3]. These are the people who at the time of death are found at the
               beginning of their way. They are those who constantly wish to act prudently, but
               never to begin. But the simple swims and passes with his first ardour. He does not
               think of the body nor of the possibility that his commerce will not prosper.</p>
            <p>Let not the greatness of thy wisdom be a stumbling-block for thyself and a snare
               before thee, preventing thee from beginning manly and quickly, in the hope in God,
               thy course <pb type="external" n="97"/>cleansed with blood, lest thou be constantly
               needy and devoid of the knowledge of God.</p>
            <p>He who looks at the winds will not sow. Better for us is death in the war for [the
               sake of] God, than a life of shame and baseness[#n65-4]. If thou wilt begin with one
               of the works of God, make thy testament beforehand as one who has no further life in
               this world and as one prepared for death. Draw near to it without hope, as one whose
               end will be reached in that action and as if it will be the end of thy days without
               thy seeing any more. Let this be truly decided in thy mind, lest victory <pb n="66"
               />be taken from thee through hope of life, being a cause of spiritual laxity.</p>
            <p>Therefore let not wisdom reign wholly over thy actions. Give quickly room also to
               faith in thy spirit. Remember constantly the days after death and let laxity never
               enter thy soul, according to the word of the sage who has said: A thousand years in
               this world are not like one day in the world of the righteous[#n66-1].</p>
            <p>Begin manly with every work of excellence; do not approach it with a double heart. Do
               not doubt in thy heart, on the way of thy course, of the hope of God's grace, lest
               thy toiling become in vain and the work of thy service become heavy for thee. But
               believe in thy heart that God is merciful and saves grace to those who seek Him, not
               in accordance with our service but in accordance with the love of our soul and with
               our faith in Him. For as thou hast believed, so it will happen unto thee.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="98"/>Some are occupied by knocking their head the whole day in
               stead of by their services; and with some, perpetual kneelings take the place of the
               number of their prayers. Some are occupied by the course of their tears in stead of
               by their canonical [duties] without seeking any thing besides, because it is better
               to them than all other things. Some fulfill the laws prescribed to them by their zeal
               for their spiritual meditations, by their suffering from hunger which eats away their
               flesh. Some are withheld from accomplishing their work, by the torments which torture
               their stomach. Some do not make a break in their reciting of Psalms on account of
               their spiritual fervour. The heart of some is set aflame by written words; some are
               captivated by the understanding thereof. And there are some whose lips are withheld
               from their ordinary course by the stupor caused by the contents of their recitation.
               Some taste all these things and are satisfied and turn away and desist. Some taste a
               little from them only, and become puffed up and insolent and forget.</p>
            <p>Some are held back from them by the severe suffering from their plagues; some by all
               kinds of allurements; some by power, some by glory among men, others by passion for
               [worldly] things; some by wanton occupations. Some however advance <pb n="67"/>well
               and making up their mind, they do not turn their back before they have taken
               possession ot the pearl.</p>
            <p>Begin every work for the sake of God joyfully. And if thou art pure from affections
               and from doubt of heart, God will <pb type="external" n="99"/>remunerate thee and
               help thee and give thee wisdom, and according to His will and in a wonderful way He
               will bring thee to perfection. To whom be glory and power and adoration and
               exaltation for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
            <p>Completed are the six treatises on the behaviour of excellence.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n55-1">Cf. Thomas a Kempis' inordinatus.</note>
            <note xml:id="n56-1"> Is. 58,2 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n56-2"> Cf. Book of the Dove p. 27 note 3.</note>
            <note xml:id="n57-1">ܐܒܝܠܐ, also a word for monk.</note>
            <note xml:id="n57-2">Supplied from London Mss.</note>
            <note xml:id="n58-1">The same comparison is used by Ghazālī, Iḥyā, III, p. 4.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-1">Matthew 25,32.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-2">Matthew 13,43.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-3">Matthew 25.41.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-4">Matthew 8,11.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-5">Hebrews 5,14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n60-6">Read ܢܫܡܫ</note>
            <note xml:id="n61-1">Matthew 15,14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n61-2">Namely those who vanquish the affections.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-1">ܒܥܘܬܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-2"><choice><sic>Litt.</sic><corr>Lit.</corr></choice>: impressions in ink.</note>
            <note xml:id="n62-3">ܡܠܘ̈ܐܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n63-1">Cf. Ps. 34,15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-1"> Proverbs 22,13</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-2"> Numbers 13,33</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-3"> Deut. 1,28</note>
            <note xml:id="n65-4"> Cf. p. 31</note>
            <note xml:id="n66-1">Cf. Ps. 84,11</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
