<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 82</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 82, pp. 384-389.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="82">
            <head>LXXXII</head>
            <head>How much honour humility possesses and how high its rank is</head>
            <p>I <choice><sic>dessire</sic><corr>desire</corr></choice> to open my month, my brethren, to speak on the elevated place of
               humility; but I am filled with fear, as a man who is conscious of the fact, that he
               will speak concerning God in a tale of his own speech. For humility is the garment of
               divinity; for the word which became man, put it on and spoke in it with us, through
               our body. And every one who puts it on in truth, by humility takes the likeness of
               Him that has descended from His height and concealed the splendour of His majesty and
               hidden His glory, lest the creation should perish by the sight of Him. For the
               creation was not able to see Him without His being united to a part of it which He
               should assume and speak with them through it, then the creation was able to hear the
               word of His mouth, face to face.</p>
            <p>The children of Israel were not able to listen to His voice, while He spoke with them
               from within the cloud; then should the creation be able to bear the sight of Him
               openly? For the children of Israel were so troubled that they said to Moses: Let us
               speak with thee, and listen thou to His words for us; <pb type="external" n="575"
               />but let Him not speak with us, lest we die<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n384-2"/>. And so terrible was the sight,
               that even the intermediary said: I fear and tremble. For on mount Sinai the splendour
               of His glory revealed itself, and the whole mountain smoked and was shaken from <pb
                  n="385"/>fear of His revelation that took place on it, so that even the beasts
               which approached the foot of the mountain, died. And all the children of Israel, on
               the order of Moses, prepared themselves, every one purifying himself for three days
               in order to be worthy of listening to the sound of God's speech and of seeing His
               revelation. And when the moment came, they were not able to bear the sight of His
               light, and the vehemence of the sound of His thunder.</p>
            <p>But now that He has poured out His grace on the world by His coming, not in
               earthquake nor in fire, nor with a terrible and vehement sound — but descending as
               the rain upon the lamb's fleece, and as the soft dew drops which softly descend upon
               the earth — it has pleased Him to speak with us in a different way, concealing His
               majesty in the cover of flesh, speaking to us while being in us, in the garment which
               Providence had woven from the womb of the virgin, so that we, seeing Him speak with
               us as one of our race, should not be terrified by the sight of Him. Therefore, every
               one who puts on the garment in which our Creator appeared, by means of a body full of
               holiness, puts on Christ. For with the likeness in which He appeared to His creation
               and in which He dealt <pb type="external" n="576"/>with us, He desired to clad His
               inner man and in it He desired to appear to His fellow men, and with it [He desired]
               to be adorned in stead of with the garment of honour and outward glory. And therefore
               the creatures prostrate themselves as to a lord before every one whom they see being
               clad with this likeness, silent or speaking, on account of the honour of their Lord
               with which they saw Him clad and in which He wandered about.</p>
            <p>Which of the creatures should not be intimidated by the sight of the humble? Yet
               before the glory of humility revealed itself to all, this sight full of holiness was
               despised by them. But now that He has caused its majesty to dawn before the eye of
               the worlds, every man honours this likeness, wheresoever it shows itself. For through
               the mediation of it, the creation became worthy of receiving the sight of its
               Creator. And therefore [humility] is not despised even by the enemies of truth. And
               though he that has acquired it, should be a beggar in comparison with all creatures,
               yet he that has learned it, is honoured on account of it as if he were clad with
               crown and purple. No one will ever hate the humble nor assail him <pb n="386"/>with a
               word, nor despise him. And because his Lord loves him, he is beloved by every one.
               Every one loves him, every one cherishes him. And wherever he comes, he is looked
               upon as an angel of light and distinguished by [signs of] honour. When the sage and
               the learned speak, they are ordered to be silent in order to give the humble an
               opportunity to speak. The eyes of everyone look on his mouth [in order to know] which
               word will come forth from it. Every one awaits his <pb type="external" n="577"
               />words, as words from God. The sense of his few words is investigated as the words
               of a philosopher. Sweet are his words to the ear of the sages, more than honeycomb is
               to the palate of those who taste it. And by everyone he is reckoned as a God, though
               he be simple in his words and of mean aspect. He that speaks of the humble in a
               despising way, is not reckoned as one living, but as one who opens his mouth against
               God. And the more despicable he is in his own eyes, the more honour is shown to him
               on the part of the creatures.</p>
            <p>The humble approaches the beasts of prey and as soon as their eye rests on him, their
               wildness is tamed and they come to him and accompany him as their master, wagging
               their tails and licking his hands and his feet. For they smell from him the smell
               which spread from Adam before his transgression, when the beasts gathered near him
               and he gave them names, in Paradise — the smell which was taken from us and given
               back to us anew by Christ through His advent, which made the smell of the human race
               sweet.</p>
            <p>And when the humble approaches the deadly reptiles, as soon as the touch of his hands
               attains to their bodies, the virulence of their deadly poison is cooled and with his
               hands he crushes them as if they were locusts<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n386-1"/>.</p>
            <p>And when he approaches the children of man they look upon him as upon their lord. Why
               do I mention the children <pb type="external" n="578"/>of man? Because,
               notwithstanding all the evil and stubbornness of the demons and all the pride of
               their own mind, as soon as they meet the humble, they become as dust: all their
               hardness becomes weak, their tricks become craftless, their cunnings idle.</p>
            <p>Now that we have shown in how great honour humility <pb n="387"/>stands with God and
               how great a power is hidden in it, we will clearly show what humility is, and when a
               man will be deemed worthy of receiving it in its fulness, as it is. And we shall make
               a distinction between him who is humble in some respects and him that has been deemed
               worthy of veracious humility.</p>
            <p>Humility is a mysterious power, which the perfect saints receive when they have
               reached accomplishment of behaviour. And this power is not granted except to those
               who, by the power of Grace, have personally accomplished the whole of excellence, in
               so far as nature in its domain is able to do this. For humility is all-comprehending
               excellence. And therefore we cannot deem every man humble, without discrimination,
               but only those who have been deemed worthy of the rank mentioned. Not every one who
               in his nature is peaceful or quiet or discrete or without blame, has reached the rank
               of humility.</p>
            <p>But a humble one in truth is he that, possessing inwardly something worthy of being
               proud of, does not extol himself, but is as dust in his own thoughts. Nor do we call
               humble him that humbles himself on account of the recollection of his low
               characteristics or trespasses, which he remembers in order that his heart may become
               contrite and his mind <pb type="external" n="579"/>withdrawn from impulses of
               haughtiness, however praiseworthy this may be. For he still possesses deliberations
               of haughtiness. Humility however he does not possess, but, by various means, he seeks
               to draw it towards himself. And however praiseworthy this may be, as I have said, he
               does not yet possess humility; he asks for it, but it is not his.</p>
            <p>A perfectly humble one is he that does not need to find out a cause which should make
               his mind humble. But he has fulfilled all these, and possesses humility as something
               natural, without bestowing any labour upon it; so that, even though he has received
               within him the great gift of which all creatures are not worthy — namely his [humble]
               nature — yet he is deemed a sinner and a simple man in his own eyes. And though he
               has penetrated into the mysteries of all spiritual kinds [of beings], and possesses
               great wisdom concerning all the creatures, he knows with perfect certainty that he
               knows nothing. And this he is not by any intermediary; but without compulsion he is
               so in his heart.</p>
            <pb n="388"/>
            <p>Can it be possible that man should be so, that nature can thus change him? No. But do
               not doubt for this reason. For this mysterious strength which he has received, which
               makes him perfect in all excellence, without labour, is the strength which the
               blessed Apostles received under the aspect of fire. And on account of it our Saviour
               ordered them that they should not leave Jerusalem before having received the strength
               from on high, namely the Comforter which is the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And this is the spirit of visions. And this is what is said concerning them in the
               Scripture: To the humble the mysteries are revealed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n388-1"/>. This means that the
               humble are deemed worthy <pb type="external" n="580"/>of receiving within them this
               spirit of revelations which explains the mysteries. And therefore it has been said by
               holy men, that humbleness makes the soul perfect by divine revelations. Therefore, no
               one should venture to think concerning himself that he has personally reached the
               rank of humility, on account of a single thought of contrition which has once risen
               [in his heart], or on account of a few tears which he has shed, or on account of one
               beautiful attribute which he possesses by nature or which he has acquired by
               compulsion; for he would in that case have acquired that which is the summit of all
               mysteries and the sum of all excellence in the domain of small labours and reckon
               these as the whole gift. But if a man has vanquished all contrary spirits, and if
               none of all the works of excellence fails him, for which he has not laboured in order
               to possess them, and if he has vanquished and subdued all <choice><sic>forteresses</sic><corr>fortresses</corr></choice>
               of resistance, and if he then perceives with his spirit that his soul has received
               the gift, while the Spirit witnesses to his spirit according to the word of the
               Apostle, then this is the summit of humility. Blessed is he that has acquired it, for
               he at all times embraces Jesus' bosom.</p>
            <p>But if a man asks: What shall I do? How can I acquire it? By what means shall I
               become worthy of receiving it? For, if I compel myself and think that I have acquired
               it, I see that unperceivecl contrary impulses err through my mind, and, consequently,
               I fall into despair.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="581"/>He that asks this, is to be answered thus: It is
               expedient for the disciple to be as his master, and for the slave as his lord. Look
               at Him who has commanded this and who grants <pb n="389"/>the gift, how He acquired
               it; and strive thou to become like Him; then thou canst do it. For He has said: The
               prince of this world cometh, and hath nothing in me<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n389-1"/>. Doest thou see how
               humility is to be acquired by the accomplishment of all excellence? So that we have
               to imitate Him that has commanded it. 'The foxes have holes and the birds of the air
               have nests, but the son of man hath not where to lay his head'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n389-2"/>. To whom be
               glory from all those who have become perfect and have been sanctified and become
               accomplished, in all generations, with the Father who sent Him and the Holy Ghost,
               now and always and for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n384-2">Exodus 20,29</note>
            <note xml:id="n386-1">With this passage is to be compared the Book of the Dove, p.
               80</note>
            <note xml:id="n388-1">Cf. Ps. 25,9</note>
            <note xml:id="n389-1">John 14, 30</note>
            <note xml:id="n389-2">Matt. 8, 20</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
