<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 22</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 22, pp. 111-118.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="22">
            <head>XXII</head>
            <head>On various [experiences] during prayer and on the limits of the power of the mind.
               And in how far it has the power to move its arbitrary impulses by the various habits
               of prayer. And what is the limit prescribed to nature during prayer, the limit which
               prayer is not allowed to surpass. And how when it has passed it and has proceeded
               farther, it is no longer prayer, even though what happens is called by the name of
               prayer</head>
            <p>Glory to Him whose gift has been poured out upon mankind, in that He has ordained
               that they, although of the flesh, should serve on the earth the class of immaterial
               beings and has deemed worthy the nature of mortals to speak about such <pb
                  type="external" n="164"/>mysteries, especially sinners as we are, who are not even
               worthy of hearing speech concerning such things. In His bounty He has opened our
               blind heart to understand, by the contemplation of the scriptures and the instruction
               of the great Fathers even although I have not been deemed worthy of experiencing for
               personal zeal one thousandth of what I have written with my hands, especially in this
               tract, which we have ventured to write for the illumination and exhortation of our
               soul and of those who come across it, that perhaps, on account of its desire, it may
               be incited to approach unto practice.</p>
            <p>How then? Delight during prayer is different from sight during prayer. The latter is
               more excellent than the former, as an adult man is superior to a little boy. It will
               happen <pb n="112"/>that the words become sweet in the mouth and that one word of
               prayer is repeated infinitely so that no feeling of satiety with it causes thee to
               proceed and to pass over to a second. Sometimes from prayer a certain contemplation
               is born which also makes prayer vanish from the lips. And he to whom this
               contemplation happens becomes as a corpse without soul, in ecstasy. This we call
               sight during prayer and not an image or form forged by phantasy, as fools say. Also
               in this contemplation during prayer there are degrees and differences in gifts. But
               till this point there is still prayer. For thought has not yet passed into the state
               where there is no prayer, but a <pb type="external" n="165"/>state superior to it.
               For the motions of the tongue and the heart during prayer, are keys. What comes after
               them is the entering into the treasury. Here then all mouths and tongues are silent,
               and the heart, the treasurer of the thoughts, the mind, the governor of the senses,
               the daring spirit, that swift bird, and all their means and powers and the beseeching
               persuasions have to stand still there: for the master of the house has come.</p>
            <p>For like as the whole force of the laws and the commandments which God has laid down
               for mankind, have their term in the purity of the heart, according to the word of the
               Fathers, so all kinds and habits of prayer with which mankind prays unto God, have
               their term in pure prayer. Lamentations and selfhumiliations and beseechings and
               inner supplications and sweet tears and all other habits which prayer possesses, — as
               I have <choice><sic>haid</sic><corr>said</corr></choice>: their boundary and the domain within which they are set into
               motion, is pure prayer.</p>
            <p>As soon as the spirit has crossed the boundary of pure prayer and proceeded onwards,
               there is neither prayer, nor emotions, nor tears, nor authority, nor freedom, nor
               beseechings, nor desire, nor longing after any of those things which are hoped for in
               this world or in the world to be.</p>
            <p>Therefore there is no prayer beyond pure prayer, and all its emotions and habits by
               their authority with freedom conduct <pb type="external" n="166"/>the spirit thus far
               and there is struggle in it; but beyond this limit it passes into ecstasy and is no
               longer prayer. From here onwards the spirit desists from prayer; there is sight, but
               the spirit does not pray.</p>
            <p>Every kind of prayer which exists is set into motion by the impulses of the soul. But
               when the mind has entered the emotions of spirituality, then it can no longer
               pray.</p>
            <pb n="113"/>
            <p>Prayer is different from contemplation during prayer, though they are caused by each
               other. One is the seed; the other the load [of harvest] borne by the hands, while the
               reaper is astonished by the <choice><sic>undescribable</sic><corr>indescribable</corr></choice> sight of how from the mean
               and bare grains of seed glorious ears suddenly grow up before him. And during sight
               he remains without motion.</p>
            <p>Every prayer which exists, is demand and request, or praise or thanksgiving. But
               judge whether there exists any of these modes, or demand of anything, when the mind
               has passed into this domain and has entered this place.</p>
            <p>I ask this of those who know the truth. It is not given to every one to enquire into
               these distinctions, but only to those who have been personally witness and ministers
               of this matter or have been brought up in the presence of the spiritual
               authors<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n113-1"/> of such experiences and have received the truth from their mouth and
               have passed their days with such occupations, asking and answering concerning matters
               of truth. As among ten thousand men there is scarcely to be found a single one <pb
                  type="external" n="167"/>who has fulfilled the commandments and the laws to any
               extent and who has been deemed worthy of serenity of soul, so there is rarely to be
               found one among many, who on account of strenuous vigilance has been deemed worthy of
               pure prayer and who has made his way into this domain and been deemed worthy of this
               mystery. Not many are deemed worthy of pure prayer, only a few. But as to that
               mystery which lies beyond, there is scarcely to be found a single man in every
               generation who has drawn near to this knowledge of God's grace.</p>
            <p>Prayer is a beseeching for, a caring for, a longing for some thing, either liberation
               from the evil things here or [in the world] to come, or a desire for promised things,
               or a demand for something by which man wishes to be brought nearer unto God. In these
               emotions are included all habits of prayer. But its being pure or not depends upon
               the following circumstances. If, when the spirit is prepared to offer one of the
               emotions which we have enumerated, any foreign deliberation or distraction mingles
               itself with it, prayer is called non-pure, because it has brought upon the altar of
               the Lord an animal which it is not allowed [to offer], the altar which is an upright,
               intelligible heart.</p>
            <pb n="114"/>
            <p>But when the spirit gives itself with longing to one of these emotions, in accordance
               to the necessity of the case, at the time of beseeching, and when on account of its
               alacrity the gaze of the emotion is directed by the eye of faith beyond the curtain
               of the heart, the entrances of the soul are closed thereby against the foreign
               deliberations which are called <pb type="external" n="168"/>strangers<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n114-1"/>, whom
               the law does not allow to enter the tabernacle. This is called the accepted offering
               of the heart and pure prayer. Its boundaries are to this point. What lies beyond
               cannot be called prayer.</p>
            <p>If any one should mention what by the Fathers is called spiritual prayer, without
               understanding the force of the words of the Fathers, saying: This belongs also to the
               domain of prayer, I think that, if he should reach true insight, it would prove a
               blasphemy if there should be found any of the creatures who should say that spiritual
               prayer can be prayed at all. For all prayer that can be prayed, lies on this side of
               spirituality. And all that is spiritual, is in kind free from emotion and prayer.</p>
            <p>Now if man is hardly able to pray pure prayer what must be said of spiritual prayer?
               The holy Fathers are accustomed to designate all profitable emotions and all
               spiritual working by the name of prayer. And the blessed commentator<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n114-2"/> even
               counts beautiful deeds as prayer; though it is clear that prayer is different from
               deeds which are things done. But sometimes they designate by spiritual prayer that
               which they sometimes call contemplation and sometimes knowledge and sometimes
               revelations of intelligible things. Doest thou see, how the Fathers <pb
                  type="external" n="169"/>change their designations of spiritual things? This is
               because accurate designations can only be established concerning earthly things. The
               things of the world-to-be do not possess a true name, but only simple cognition,
               which is exalted above all names and signs and forms and colours and habits and
               composite denominations. When, therefore, the knowledge of the soul exalts itself
               above this circle of visible things, the Fathers use concerning this
               <choice><sic>knowlegde</sic><corr>knowledge</corr></choice> any designations they like, though no one does know the real
               names in order that the psychic deliberations may be based on them. We use
               denominations and riddles, according to the word of the holy <persName>Dionysius</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n114-3"/> who
                  <pb n="115"/>says: We use signs and syllables, conventional names and words in
               behalf of the senses. But when by spiritual working our soul is moved unto divine
               things, then the senses and their workings are superfluous to us, as also the
               spiritual forces of the soul are superfluous as soon as our soul becomes the image of
               the godhead through unification with the incomprehensible and radiant in the rays of
               the sublime, by those impulses which are not for the eyes[h].</p>
            <p>Therefore, my brother, of this thou mayest be sure: that the power of the mind to use
               the emotions with discernment has its limit in purity during prayer. When the mind
               has reached this point, it will either turn backwards, or it will desist from prayer;
               so prayer is, as it were, a mediator between the psychic and the spiritual state. As
               long, however, as <pb type="external" n="170"/>it is in emotion, it is in the psychic
               state. But as soon as it has passed this limit, prayer ceases.</p>
            <p>As the saints, in the world to come do not pray, when the mind has been engulfed by
               the [divine] spirit, but they dwell in ecstasy in that delightful glory, so the mind,
               when it has been made worthy of perceiving the future blessedness, will forget itself
               and all that is here, and it will not be moved any longer by the thought of
               anything<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n115-1"/>.</p>
            <p>Man, therefore, may freely go so far as to say: all excellence whatever and all
               orders of prayer whatever, in body or in spirit, are in the realm of free will, as
               well as the mind that dominates the senses. But when the influence of the spirit
               reigns over the mind that regulates the senses and the deliberations, freedom is
               taken away from nature which no longer governs but is governed. And how could there
               be prayer at that time, when nature does not possess power over its self, but is
               conducted by an outward force without knowing whither. Nature then does not direct
               the emotions of the spirit according to its will, but captivity reigns over nature in
               that hour and conducts it there where sensual apperception ceases; because nature
               even has no will at that time, even to this extent that it does not know whether it
               is in or without the body, as scripture testifies. Has therefore such a one prayer
               who is a captive to this degree and who even does not know himself? So no one should
               say with blasphemy that there is anyone <pb n="116"/>who could venture to say that it
               is possible to pray spiritual <pb type="external" n="171"/>prayer. This audaciousness
               the <persName>Meṣalleyānē</persName> vindicate for themselves, those haughty ignorants who proclaim
               concerning themselves that they are able to pray spiritual prayer when they like. But
               those who are humble and have insight and are inclined to learn from the Fathers and
               know the limits of nature, do not abandon their deliberations to this
               audaciousness.</p>
            <p>And therefore, when there is no prayer, can then this unspeakable gift be designated
               by the name of prayer? The cause, as we say, is therein, that at the time of prayer
               [this gift] is granted unto those who are worthy. And in prayer it has its
               starting-point, because this glorious gift cannot be granted excepted at this time,
               according to the testimony of the Fathers. Therefore it is called by the name of
               prayer, because from prayer the mind is conducted towards this blessed state, and
               because prayer is its starting-point and it does not occur on any other occasion,
               according to the testimony of <persName>Mar Euagrius</persName> and others. And we see also that the
               majority of the saints say that during prayer their mind was snatched<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n116-1"/>.</p>
            <p>If any one asks: How is it that at this time only these great and unspeakable gifts
               are granted? we answer: Because at this time, more than in any other hour, man is
               concentrated and prepared to look unto God and to desire and to expect compassion
               from Him. In short: it is the time that the demand of him who is at the gate of the
               king and asks <pb type="external" n="172"/>desiringly and beseechingly, is likely to
               be heard. And what time is there when man is so cautious and fit and prepared, as the
               time when he prays? Or should it be becoming that he should be deemed worthy of this
               at the time when he sleeps or settles any affair or is distracted of mind? However,
               the saints do not even know a time of idleness, because at all times they are
               occupied by spiritual things, for when they are not standing in preparation for
               prayer, they often meditate upon some stories of the scriptures, or their mind
               meditates in contemplation of the created things, or [their mind is occupied] with
               other things meditation of which is profitable.</p>
            <p>At the time of prayer the gaze of the spirit is exclusively fixed on God and the
               tendency of its emotion is wholly directed towards Him, and it offers to Him the
               beseechings of the <pb n="117"/>heart with the necessary zeal, with fervour and
               ardour. Therefore it is becoming that at this time, when a single thought dominates
               the soul, divine mercy should well forth from Him. For we see also that when we offer
               the visible sacrifice, while every one is prepared and standing in prayer,
               supplicating and beseeching, the mind being concentrated upon God, the gift of the
               spirit descends upon the bread and wine which we lay on the altar. To <persName>Zechariah</persName> also
               the angel appeared at the time of prayer and announced to him the conception of <persName>John</persName>.
               And <pb type="external" n="173"/>to <persName>Peter</persName> appeared, while he was praying on the roof
               the prayer of the sixth hour, the revelation that made him acquainted with the
               accession of the gentiles, by the cloth that descended from heaven and by the animals
               that were on it. And to <persName>Cornelius</persName> appeared, when he prayed, that which is written
               concerning him. And God spoke with <persName>Joshua</persName> the son of Nun while he was prostrated in
               prayer. And over the ark was placed a plate, from which the priest was taught by
               divine revelation what was required, at the time when the high priest, once in a
               year, entered the inner sanctuary at the dreadful time of prayer while all the tribes
               of the children of <placeName>Israel</placeName> were gathered and stood in trembling and fear in the outer
               tabernacle in prayer. And while the high priest was prostrated the voice of God was
               heard from the plate over the ark, in a dreadful, unspeakable revelation. How
               dreadful was the mystery that was ministered in this ceremony! So all the revelations
               and visions that happened unto the saints, happened at the time of prayer.</p>
            <p>What time is so holy and fit for sanctification and the receiving of gifts as the
               time of prayer, in which man speaks with God? At this time man utters his desires
               unto God, beseeching Him and speaking with Him and his whole emotion and thought are
               concentrated from all sides upon Him with <pb type="external" n="174"/>compulsion; of
               God alone he thinks and Him alone he supplicates; his whole thought is absorbed in
               discourse with Him and his heart is full of Him. It is in this state, therefore, that
               the Holy Ghost joins with the things which man prays, some unattainable insights,
               which it stirs in him in accordance with his aptitude of being moved so that by these
               insights the emotion of prayer ceases, the mind is absorbed in ecstasy and the
               desired object of prayer is forgotten. The impulses are drowned in a heavy
               drunkenness and man is no longer in this world. Then <pb n="118"/>there is no longer
               discrimination of body or of soul, nor recollection of anything, as <persName>Euagrius</persName>
               says.</p>
            <p>Prayer namely is steadfastness of mind, which is terminated only by the light of the
               holy Trinity through ecstasy. Thou seest, how prayer is terminated when those
               insights which are born in the spirit from prayer, pass into ecstasy, as I have said
               in the beginning of this treatise and in several places further on.</p>
            <p>Further he<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n118-1"/> says: Steadfastness of mind is highness of intelligible
               apperceptions<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n118-2"/>, which resembles the colour of the sky over which rises, at
               the time of prayer, the light of the holy Trinity. When is a man deemed worthy of the
               whole of this grace such that during prayer he is exalted unto this height? He says:
               When the mind puts off the old man and puts on <pb type="external" n="175"/>the new
               one by grace, then it also sees its steadfastness at the time of prayer, resembling
               sapphire or the colour of heaven, as the place of God was called by the elders of
               <placeName>Israel</placeName>, to whom it appeared on the mountain<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n118-3"/>.</p>
            <p>So, as I have said, this gift is not to be called spiritual prayer, but what then?
               The fruit of pure prayer, which is engulfed in the spirit. The mind has ascended here
               above prayer. And, having found what is more excellent, it desists from prayer. And
               further there is no longer prayer, but the gaze in ecstasy at the unattainable things
               which do not belong to the world of mortals, and peace without knowledge of any
               earthly thing. This is the well known ignorance<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n118-4"/> concerning which <placeName>Euagrius</placeName>
               says: Blessed is he who has reached, during prayer, unconsciousness which is not to
               be surpassed.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n113-1">literally: the Fathers</note>
            <note xml:id="n114-1">ܓܝܘܖ̈ܐ proselytes</note>
            <note xml:id="n114-2">Theodore of Mopsuestia</note>
            <note xml:id="n114-3">Areopagita</note>
            <note xml:id="n115-1">Cf. Plotinus's description of the mind's delight when it has
               forgotten matter VI, 7 § 34.</note>
            <note xml:id="n116-1">ܡܬܚܛܦ</note>
            <note xml:id="n118-1">evidently Euagrius</note>
            <note xml:id="n118-2">literally: things</note>
            <note xml:id="n118-3">Exodus 24,9-1</note>
            <note xml:id="n118-4">Cf. Dionysius Areopagita p. 274¹⁰</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
