<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 63</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 63, pp. 293-295.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="63">
            <head>LXIII</head>
            <head>Why it is that people who are in the psychic state of knowledge consider spiritual
               things in accordance with their [bodily] grossness and how it is possible that the
               mind be elevated above this and what is the cause why we are not freed from it and
               when and how it is possible for the mind to remain without images at the time of
               prayer</head>
            <p>He whose majesty is blessed, will open the gate before us, so that we have no single
               wish than desire of Him. When <pb type="external" n="438"/>we so abandon everything,
               and our mind goes out to seek Him alone, there will be no thought in it of anything
               which screens its face from the aspect of the Lord of the Universe. The more the mind
               abandons the thought of visible things, o my beloved, and the more it thinks of the
               future hope, in accordance with the degree of elevation above bodily thoughts and
               intercourse with them, to the same extent it will be <choice><sic>subtilised</sic><corr>subtilized</corr></choice> and
               become clear during prayer.</p>
            <p>To the same extent as the body, the mind is made free from the bonds of [worldly]
               things; and to the same extent as it is made free from the ties of thoughts, does it
               become <choice><sic>cerene</sic><corr>serene</corr></choice>; and to the same extent as it becomes serene, is it also
               subtilized; and to the same extent as it is subtilized, is it lifted up above the
               emotions of this world which bears the stamp of grossness. And it knows that it shall
               look on God as He is, not as we are.</p>
            <pb n="294"/>
            <p>If a man has not been deemed worthy of revelation before, it is not possible that he
               should know this. And if he does not attain purity, his emotions are not made clear
               so as to look at the hidden things. And until through his [spiritual] riches he be
               freed from all that is seen, he is not freed from emotions for those things, and he
               does not become devoid of deliberations that cause darkness. And even as darkness and
               enchaining thoughts, so the affections are there.</p>
            <p>If a man is not made free from all those things which I have mentioned and from their
               causes, he cannot consider the hidden things of the mind. Therefore our Lord has
               ordered us to practise renunciation before any other thing, and flight from the
               troubles of the world, and freedom from common human thought. Who does not forsake
               his whole human state and all that he possesses, and deny even himself, he cannot be
               a disciple to Me<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n294-1"/>; lest the mind be injured by anything: <pb type="external"
                  n="439"/>by sight, by hearing, by care of [worldly] things, their loss or their
               increase, or by man. And thereby that He has bound our mind by hope of Himself alone,
               He has caused the whole care of our deliberations to look towards Himself. And in
               Himself He has bound the whole care of our mind, after having freed it from all other
               things, that thence we may long after intercourse with Himself, because of our care
               being continually directed towards Himself.</p>
            <p>Prayer further requires also training, that through long practice the mind may become
               wise. For after renunciation which frees our impulses from bonds, prayer requires
               constancy that through constancy and time the mind may acquire training so as to know
               how to restrain its deliberations and to learn through experience many things which
               it cannot receive from others. Any [state of] discipline is prepared<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n294-2"/> by the
               preceding one; and the preceding one is necessary for the existence of the
               following.</p>
            <p>Prayer is preceded by reclusion; reclusion [is practised] with a view to prayer;
               prayer in order to acquire love of God; for in prayer are found causes for loving
               God.</p>
            <p>Also this we must know, my beloved ones, that any hidden intercourse, or any
               meditation upon spiritual things, is to be denoted by prayer or comprehended under
               the name of prayer <pb n="295"/>or included within this denomination: be it
               recitation with <pb type="external" n="440"/>discrimination, or songs in praise of
               God, or painstaking thought of our Lord, or prostration of the body, or psalms of
               glorification, and so on. For from them is received instruction concerning veracious
               prayer; and from the latter love of God is born. And love is through prayer; and
               prayer through dwelling alone. And loneliness serves the purpose, that we should have
               a place where we can converse with God in solitude. Loneliness is preceded by
               abandonment of the world.</p>
            <p>If a man forsake not the world first and renunciate all that he possesses, he cannot
               attain to loneliness. So abandonment of the world in its turn is preceded by
               patience, and patience by hatred of the world; hatred of the world by fear and love.
               For if the mind is not terrified by the fear of Hell and incited by the love of
               [future] good, the hatred of this world will not arise in him. And if the mind does
               not hate the world, it cannot forego its intercourse and comfort. And if the mind has
               not acquired patience before, it cannot choose dwelling in solitude without
               companions. And if it does not choose a lonely life, it cannot abide in prayer. And
               if it is not constantly in intercourse with God and cling to those impulses which are
               interwoven with prayer and to those kinds of instruction which are in prayer, as we
               have said, it cannot perceive love.</p>
            <p>So the love of God proceeds from intercourse with Him; the intercourse of prayer from
               solitude; solitude from renunciation; renunciation in its turn from patience;
               patience from <pb type="external" n="441"/>hatred of desires; hatred of desires from
               fear of Hell and the expectation of the [future] good. Desires are hated by him that
               knows the fruits thereof, namely what they prepare for him and from what good he is
               deprived for their sake.</p>
            <p>So every discipline is connected with that which precedes it, takes increase from it
               and proceeds unto others which are higher. And if one of the middle links should
               fail, the following could not maintain itself and it would appear that all were
               loosened and lost.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n294-1"> Cf. Luke 14,33</note>
            <note xml:id="n294-2"> literally: educated</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
