<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 9</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 9, pp. 74-77</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="9">
            <head>IX</head>
            <head>On sins [committed] intentionally and with evil will and on those [committed]
               accidentally</head>
            <p>There are sins in which a man is entangled through weakness and accidentally. And
               there are sins the source of which is the will; others [spring] from an uncultivated
               mind. Some are committed occasionally, others continually; others are customary. And
               all these classes and kinds of sins, though bound by the common verdict of
               reprehension, have a different character and their punishment may be greater or
               smaller.</p>
            <p>Some sins are reprehended severely; others are near to mercy. God has also shown unto
               Adam, Eve and the serpent, though not one of them was exempted from receiving the
               retribution of his fault, a great variety in the curse which was directed <pb n="75"
               />against each one of them; and so He did in the curses directed against their
               offspring. In accordance with the propensity and inclination of each unto sin, is
               judgment made more heavy.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="111"/>If any one be not inclined to follow sin, but he be
               drawn towards it on account of neglect regarding righteousness, although he be not
               zealous for it, his judgment will be severe even if the connection with sin be
               difficult for him. But if he be diligent and temptations rise, mercy is near to
               purify him, without doubt. For it is another thing that a man who is careful
               regarding excellence and constant in its works, meditating on it even in the night,
               should fail in any of its duties; while by day he is loaded with its burden and goes
               around with it, all his thoughts concentrated upon justness — it is a different thing
               that, while he is occupied with such things, through ignorance or the compulsion of
               opposition on the way of excellence and the mighty waves that arise every moment in
               his limbs, and the propensity towards aberration which is implanted in him as a test
               of freedom, the indicator of his scale should point somewhat to the left, and through
               the sickness of the flesh he should be entangled in any kind of sin and suffer and be
               sorry on account of it and bewail himself passionately because of his miserable
               weakness in the face of what overtakes him now and then.</p>
            <p>It is a very different thing, that one being lax in the works of righteousness or
               wholly neglectful of the way, should run like a slave in complete obedience to all
               the delights of sin, and try to find the means of its accomplishment; and that like
                  <pb type="external" n="112"/>a slave he should purpose zealously to perform the
               will of his adversary, his limbs serving him as weapons on behalf of Satan in
               complete obedience and that he should not even think of repentance so as to draw
               nearer unto excellence and end his path of shortcomings.</p>
            <p>Different are the trespasses and the stumbling-blocks laid on the way of virtue and
               in the course of righteousness. As the Fathers say: On the way of excellence there
               are stumbling-blocks, there are varying states, there is compulsion, and the
               like.</p>
            <p>A different thing is death of the soul and complete destruction and total
               abandonment. This is known thereby that, although one falls, he does not forget the
               love of his Father; and although he is loaded with trespasses of every kind, his zeal
               for the service of good is not held back, nor does he <pb n="76"/>desist from his
               course, nor abhor to stand in struggle against these things anew and with the same
               chance of being vanquished, nor cease from demolishing every day his building and
               beginning a [new] foundation.</p>
            <p>And the word of the prophet is in his mouth: Till the hour of my departure from this
               world, rejoice not against me, O mine enemy: when I fall, I shall arise; when I sit
               in darkness, the Lord shall be a light unto me<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-1"/>. And he will not cease to
               struggle till death. He will not allow himself to be vanquished, as long as there is
               breath in his nostrils. And though his ship is wrecked every day and the sweat of his
               commerce becomes a prey to the depths, he does not cease to borrow and fit out ships
               and navigate with good hope; till the Lord, seeing his zeal, has mercy for his
               shipwrecks and inclines unto <pb type="external" n="113"/>him in compassion and gives
               him strong impulses towards patience and towards braving the burning arrows of the
               Evil one. This is wisdom from God and whoever is sick in this way, is wise.</p>
            <p>To abandon hope profits not. It is more expedient for us to be judged on account of
               special [sins] than on account of complete abandonment. Therefore the blessed
               commentator<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n76-2"/> warns us against becoming weary in face of the many struggles and
               the frequent various kinds of strife to be met on the way of righteousness lest we
               should turn back and give our adversary the opportunity of a complete victory in any
               kind of evil. And so the blessed commentator says, arranging the strugglers as it
               were in classes: If you are truly zealous to look towards excellence and anxious for
               serenity of mind unto God, and to practise those things which are agreeable unto Him,
               you must necessarily bear for the sake of these things, all the struggles which will
               arise continually against you on account of the natural affections and the
               attractions of this world and the evil of the demons, without relaxing in spite of
               the constant and never ceasing strife, without fear of the tenacious vehemence of
               war, without dread of the hosts of enemies, and without dejection if it happen that
               you trespass somewhere and sin, but receiving on your faces the blows and wounds such
               as are [to be expected] in so great a war. On account of these things, therefore, you
               must not let yourself be moved <pb n="77"/>even from your will's decision on the
               contrary you must maintain the choice of your behaviour, deeming it a beloved and <pb
                  type="external" n="114"/>glorious thing to show yourselves in the war besmeared
               with the blood of your blows, without pausing in the slightest degree from strife
               against the enemies. These are the warnings of the blessed commentator.</p>
            <p>Thus, it is not becoming in us to relax because of these things. Woe to the solitary
               who is unfaithful to his covenant and, treading down his conscience, gives Satan
               entrance into him, in small and great matters of sin, so that he does not find
               strength to defend against the enemies the breach [Satan] has made in his soul. And
               with what countenance will he behold the chaste, his companions, when they are
               brought together from whom he has separated his way to go the way of destruction, and
               the freedom of speech with God which the pious possess, and the prayer which arises
               from the chaste heart towards God and uplifts itself and even passes the hosts of the
               angels and stops not until it reaches God's majesty, holding the keys in its hands
               ceasing not until it has acquired its demand, returning unto the mouth that has sent
               it, with gladness. [And with what countenance will he look upon] what is harder than
               all these things, viz. that, as he has separated his way from them here, so Christ
               will separate him from them on that day. When the brilliant clouds will bear on their
               backs<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-1"/> the bodies that have become splendid by purification and that enter the
               great gate of heaven. Therefore the ungodly shall not stand in the judgment<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-2"/>,
               because their work is already judgment, nor sinners in the congregation of the
               righteous<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n77-2"/>, in the resurrection before the judgment, nor the impure in the
               ranks of the saints.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n76-1"> Micah 7,8</note>
            <note xml:id="n76-2"> Theodore of Mopsuestia</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-1">Literally: hips</note>
            <note xml:id="n77-2">Ps. 1,5</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
