<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 18</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 18, pp. 95-105</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="18">
            <head>XVIII</head>
            <p>Things which I have heard from old men and stories of holy people, their pious words
               and wonderful behaviour. May God preserve us by their prayers amen</p>
            <p>One day I went to the cell of a holy brother and lay down <pb type="external" n="140"
               />in a corner as I was ill, expecting that he would visit me for God's sake. There
               was nobody in that country [whom I knew]. I had seen this brother several times at
               night, as he stood, a long time ago. He usually woke for the service earlier than any
               of the brethren. Then he would begin with Psalms and would recite them diligently.
               Then, of a sudden, he would leave the service, fall on his face, and beat, so to
               speak, a hundred times, with his head on the earth violently and quickly, on<pb
                  n="96"/>account of the fervour which grace had kindled in his heart. Thereupon he
               would rise and salute the cross. Then again he prostrated himself, rose, saluted the
               cross and again fell down on his face. This he repeated so many times that I was not
               able to count them. Who could have counted the many kneelings which that brother
               performed these nights?</p>
            <p>He would also approach the cross and kiss it twenty times, full of reverence and of
               fervour, in love mingled with fear; thereafter he continued his reciting of Psalms.
               From time to time, when he was no longer able to bear that flame of joy, he was
               suddenly overwhelmed by frequent currents of deliberations, which kindled him with
               their fervour; and he would elevate his voice because he could not restrain
               himself.</p>
            <p>And I was astonished at the grace which was with that brother and I wondered at his
               zeal and alacrity in the works of God.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="141"/>After the morning service, when he sat down for
               recitation, he was like one in the state of rapture. At every verse he recited he
               would fall on his face several times; and at many of the words he would stretch his
               hands towards heaven and utter the glorification several times.</p>
            <p>He was a man of middle age, nearly forty years old. He ate but little; his
               temperament was dry and hot. And because he compelled himself, when his body could
               not bear it, he looked like a shadow from time to time, so that one pitied him on
               account of his thin face, which was vanishing and becoming as small as two fingers.
               Several times I said to him: moderate this strict rule of behaviour, my brother, and
               this beautiful way which thou treadest and do not disorder nor break thy rule as a
               spiritual chain, out of desire to add a small quantity of works with the result that
               thy whole course will be brought to a close. Eat moderately, but eat regularly. And
               make not thy way too long for thy strength, lest thou shouldst have to desist from it
               wholly.</p>
            <p>Further he was compassionate and very bashful, he was glad to show compassion. He was
               honest by nature and easily persuaded, and prudent in God. Because of his honesty and
               joyous disposition he was liked by every one and they all loved him. He worked with
               all the brethren in clay in their cells, when <pb type="external" n="142"/>they had
               any, now for three, now for four days every evening he returned to his own cell, till
               the work of the brother was finished. He was very well skilled in this work.</p>
            <pb n="97"/>
            <p>If he possessed any thing, and one of the brethren begged him to give it him, he gave
               it him even though he was in great need of it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n97-1"/>. He was very sensitive before
               all sorts of persons and was not able to say: I have not, or: I want it myself. And
               that he regularly left his cell to work with the brethren, was because of his
               sensitiveness before others; so he compelled himself, although not inclined to go
               out. And several times he spoke to me about his aversion to leave his cell. This was
               the divine behaviour of that wonderful brother.</p>
            <p>Concerning another solitary<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n97-2"/>. Once I went to the cell of an old solitary, an
               excellent man who loved me greatly. He was somewhat quaint in his words, but
               illuminated in his thoughts and profound. And what he <choice><sic>choose</sic><corr>chose</corr></choice> to tell, he
               spoke with a certain goodheartedness. He scarcely left his cell, except for the holy
               mysteries<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n97-3"/>. He was constantly concentrated and in solitude.</p>
            <p>Once I said to him: Father, I <choice><sic>purpose</sic><corr>propose</corr></choice> going on Sunday and sitting down in
               the <choice><sic>galery</sic><corr>gallery</corr></choice> of the church and to eat early in the morning. Then every
               visitor will see and despise me. The solitary said to me: It is written: He who
               offends the lay people, will not see light. Nobody knows thee in these regions,
               neither do people know what thy fame is. So they will say: The solitaries eat early
               in the morning. There is a <pb type="external" n="143"/>greater reason. There are
               novices of weak deliberations, many of whom will be edified by thee now; but if they
               see thee [eating], they will turn back. The ancient Fathers could do such things,
               because of the signs and the forces which were wrought through them and because of
               the great name and fame they possessed. These things they practised, each of them in
               order to be despised and blamed, and to obscure the fame of his behaviour and to keep
               far from him the cause of haughtiness. But what is the necessity for thee to act in
               this way? Doest thou not know that even for the behaviour [of solitaries] moderation
               is necessary and a fixed time for every one of their works? But what necessity is
               there for thee regarding such things? Thou doest not follow a distinct discipline,
               nor art thou famous. Thou hast the same discipline as the other brethren. Therefore,
               thou doest not gain profit for thyself by doing so, but thou art harmful for
               others.</p>
            <pb n="98"/>
            <p>And this behaviour<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n98-1"/>, is not profitable for all men, but for the great and
               perfect only, because it involves relaxation of the senses. For the novices and those
               of the middle state however it is very harmful. For they, on the contrary, need
               watchfulness and subduing of the senses. For the trained solitaries have passed [the
               period of] watchfulness, as has been said, and mix with what they like, yet know to
               gain profit. A simple merchant will lose greatly in great affairs; in small ones he
               often easily comes forward. Therefore, as I have said, <pb type="external" n="144"
               />in all work moderation is necessary; and every discipline has its fixed time. Every
               one who, before its time, begins with what is above his rank, will be injured and
               gain no profit.</p>
            <p>If thou desirest this, first suffer that disdain which Providence sends thee without
               thy willing it, gladly, without being troubled thereat and without hating those who
               disdain thee.</p>
            <p>Concerning another solitary. Once I was in intercourse with the virtuous one that had
               tasted from the tree of life in the sweat of his soul, from the morning of youth
               until the evening of old age. And after much conversation in which he taught me
               concerning excellence, he also said this to me: Every prayer, in which the body does
               not participate and by which the heart is not affected, is to be reckoned as an
               abortion without a soul.</p>
            <p>Further he said to me: Have not the slightest intercourse with any man who strives
               after victory in his words, and is astute in spirit and of keen senses, lest thou
               destroy the serenity thou hast acquired by works and thy heart become full of
               darkness and trouble. —</p>
            <p>Once I went to the cell of one of the Fathers. This saintly man scarcely ever opened
               to any one. When he saw from his window that it was I, he said: Thou wishest to
               enter? I said to him: Ay. When I had entered and we had prayed and sat down and he
               had spoken with me concerning many things, I asked him at last: What shall I do, my
               lord? There are persons who constantly visit me, without my profiting by their
                  inter<pb type="external" n="145"/>course. To forbid them to enter would be painful
               to me. They often hinder me even in my usual service. But I am not able to say so to
               them openly. So I am much troubled by this matter.</p>
            <pb n="99"/>
            <p>This blessed man said to me: When such people visit thee, people who like to be lazy
               and who spread<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n99-1"/> idle words, and when they have sat down a little time, assume
               the air that thou desirest to stand for service. And say to [thy visitor], whosoever
               he be, with an obeisance: My brother, we will perform the service. For the time of my
               service is come and I may not overlook it. For it would be hard for me to combine it
               with the next prayer; that would cause me trouble; and I may not omit any service
               without [the plea of] necessity. At present there is no necessity to let the time
               pass. — This shalt thou urge till he stand up with thee for the service. And if he
               say: Perform thou thy service, now I will go away — make an obeisance before him and
               say: Be kind to me and perform with me this single service, that I may be helped by
               thy prayer. Then, when he agrees and you are standing, make thy service longer than
               usually. So thou shalt do with them as often as they enter. And when they see that
               thou art not of their kind and that thou doest not love idleness, then they will no
               more come where they hear that thou art. Behold, thou shalt be no respecter of
               persons and neglect none of the works of God.</p>
            <p>If, however, [thy visitor] be one of the Fathers, or a foreign <pb type="external"
                  n="146"/>brother who is fatigued, then deem it an important service to remain in
               intercourse with him. But if this stranger also should be one of those who love idle
               words, content him as much as thou canst and dispatch him quickly.</p>
            <p>Once one of the saints said to me: When I hear, that there are people who perform
               work in their cell and also accomplish the rules of the cell without failure, I
               wonder how it is possible that they are not troubled.</p>
            <p>He also said a wonderful thing: verily, I say that even when I go to make water, this
               troubles my constancy [of mind] because practice turns away from me the complete
               discernment which I have mastered.</p>
            <p>A solitary asked a brother: What shall I do? Often I desire a thing and am in need of
               it on account of illness, or work, or some other reason, so that by its aid I would
               nigh well be able to lead a life of solitude. But if I see anyone who needs this
               thing as I do, then compassion causes me to give it him.</p>
            <pb n="100"/>
            <p>Or if any one asks me for this thing, I am pressed by love and by command so that I
               give it him. But afterwards I require this thing. And my need causes me care and
               disturbance and troubled thoughts, and it takes away my concentration of spirit and
               my care for the usual service of solitude. So that I am <pb type="external" n="147"
               />compelled many times to leave my solitude and go and ask for this thing. And when I
               restrain myself from going out, I am in great need and perturbance of mind. On
               account of this thing I am constantly shaken and disturbed without knowing which of
               the two I shall choose: that which destroys and disturbs my peace for the sake of the
               peace of my neighbours; or to abandon this, so as to remain in solitude and
               renunciation, and to care for the small things of my self only, without any
               inclination to think many thoughts or to care for others.</p>
            <p>I beg to learn, in answer to this, what is good and worthy of recommendation. The
               solitary answered saying: All compassion is either love, or alms, or a gift. And
               every becoming thing, and every deed reckoned as being godly which destroys thy
               solitude and bereaves thee of thy freedom regarding the world, and causes thee care
               and troubles thy thoughts concerning divine things, and breaks the order of thy
               prayers and brings about troubled deliberations and takes from thee the concentrated
               occupation with recitation and freedom from distraction, and destroys thy
               watchfulness and makes thee instead of a prisoner one who walks where he likes and
               [changes] thee from a solitary into one who mingles [with other people] and awakens
               in thee buried passions and relaxes the asceticism of thy senses and quickens thee
               again who wert dead to the world and casts thee out of thy angelic service which is
               concentrated solitary thought, and sets thy part with the service of the laity — this
               [sort of] righteousness may perish. To accomplish alms of love to thy neighbour,
               consisting in bodily <pb type="external" n="148"/>comfort, belongs to the service of
               lay-people, or of those solitaries who are inferior to service in solitude or
               practice a mingled solitude in the company of one another and through constant
               visits<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n100-1"/>. — But those solitaries who have earnestly chosen to be free from the
               world in body and in spirit in order to establish in their mind the prayer of
               solitude which is the being dead to the things that perish and to all thought <pb
                  n="101"/>of practice and seeing and recollecting [worldly] things, they do not
               serve Christ by any service in these bodily things or with a righteousness founded
               upon manifest deeds with the intermediation of persons in order to be justified
               thereby, but [they serve Him] by mortifying their members which are upon the
               earth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n101-1"/>, according to the word of the Apostle, offering at all times the pure
               sacrifices of their thoughts as the first fruits of their service and their bodily
               affections through patience in trouble for the sake of that which they expect. The
               behaviour of the solitaries is like that of the angels. So it is not just to neglect
               the service of heavenly things and to gather righteousness by [practising] earthly
               things.</p>
            <p>A brother was blamed because he provided the wants of the poor from his own
               possessions. He answered proudly: Solitaries are near to alms. He that blamed him
               said: Well known is the solitary who is not near to alms; who without shame can say
               to our Lord, as has been said: Behold, we have forsaken all, and followed
               thee<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n101-2"/>. This is he that does not possess any<pb type="external" n="149"/>thing
               on the earth, nor does he perform bodily labour for earthly things, his thoughts do
               not turn to any of the visible things in the world, nor does he expect to acquire
               anything. If any one offers anything to him, he only accepts according to his want;
               he never looks at aught else. But he is in his dealings like a bird, the which does
               not think of giving alms; for he has a service more excellent than alms.</p>
            <p>How can he give others from that of which he is liberated? But as long as a man works
               with his hands and receives from others, he is also obliged to give alms. To neglect
               this would be a manifest transgression of God's commandment. But if he does not make
               progress with God in hidden things, and does not know to serve God in spirit and
               despise the manifest things which lie within his power, what further hope has he to
               acquire life? Be he anathema.</p>
            <p>Admonition of one of the fathers concerning the right solitude</p>
            <p>I wonder at those who trouble themselves in their course of solitude because they
               desire to comfort others by bodily things.</p>
            <pb n="102"/>
            <p>He also said: It is not becoming to mingle with the service of solitude the thought
               of any thing in the world, <choice><sic>safe</sic><corr>save</corr></choice> only those which it is possible to perform in
               solitude. And we have to honour every solitary performance in its place, lest we
               become <choice><sic>confuse</sic><corr>confused</corr></choice> in our solitary course. For he who cares about <pb
                  type="external" n="150"/>many things, is a slave of many persons. He who lets go
               all and cares for the steadfastness of his soul, is a friend of God. Behold, those
               who practise alms and completely show their love of neighbours by bodily things, are
               many in the world. But those who beautifully serve in solitude and have intercourse
               with God are scarcely to be found. Or who are, among those who practise righteousness
               and gain it by earthly things, those from whom we may receive one of the gifts which
               those who work in solitude receive from God?</p>
            <p>The same has further said: If thou art a lay man, practise the behaviour which suits
               lay people. But if thou art a solitary, gain profit by the labours by which the
               solitaries gain profit. If, however, thou wilt practise both, thou wilt fall short in
               both. The work of solitaries is this: to become liberated from sensible things and to
               be constantly with God in the thoughts of the heart and through fatiguing the body by
               prayer. Judge thou thyself whether it be possible to despise these things and to fill
               their place with worldly excellence. Or should a solitary be able to practise in
               solitude two kinds of behaviour, the outward and the inward one viz. meditation on
               God and burdening his heart with the care of others? I say even this that he who has
               honestly willed to lead a life with God, and leaves all, fixing his attention solely
               upon matters of behaviour — that even he will not be able to accomplish without
               shortcomings <pb type="external" n="151"/>all the duties of the practice of solitude.
               He is found wanting in the bearing of his load, though he desists absolutely from the
               use and the care of the world — not to mention the case of his being occupied by many
               other thoughts.</p>
            <p>To our Lord are given<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n102-1"/> those who administer and visit His servants and His
               sons. He has also chosen those who minister before Himself.</p>
            <p>We do not only see, in the affairs of earthly kings, that those who are constantly
               with the king and participate of his secrets are more glorious and elevated in their
               ranks than those <pb n="103"/>who accomplish their outward affairs with love, but,
               also in divine affairs, it is easy to see what a freedom of speech those possess who,
               in intercourse with Him possess the mysteries of prayer at all times and over what
               riches of heaven and earth they reign, and how apparent is their mastership over all
               created natures, which, without dispute, obey their words as those of God. They are
               stamped with the manifest sign of His image, with a glory greater than that of all
               rational and irrational<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n103-1"/> beings, greater than that of those who serve God
               with possessions and earthly things and seek to content Him in [the company of] their
               companions. This may be very beautiful, but as to us, we have not to take as examples
               those who stand at a low degree in the service of God, but those who are athletes in
               our path<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n103-2"/> and the saints who go our course, and those who once for all have
               given up and turned their back on the earth and have taken hold of the vault of
               heaven.</p>
            <p>Whereby have the ancient saints pleased God, those who <pb type="external" n="152"
               />have trodden the way of our behaviour and have excelled: the holy John of Thebaïs,
               that treasury of excellence and fountain of prophecy? Did he comfort his companions
               with bodily things, in his reclusion, or did he please God by prayer? I confess that
               there have been [solitaries] who also in these things pleased [God] and gained
               profit. But they are less in number than those who pleased God by prayer and by
               renouncing all things. What their help to their <choice><sic>follow</sic><corr>fellow</corr></choice> brethren who live in
               solitude is, is well known. It consists in helping them as often as they are in want
               of a profitable word or [in helping them] by offering prayer <choice><sic>in</sic><corr>on</corr></choice> behalf of them.
               Apart from these things, it is not wise for him who dwells in solitude to give place
               in his heart to recollections or thoughts concerning any one as far as bodily things
               are concerned. 'Render unto Caesar the things which are Caesar's; and unto God the
               things that are God's<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n103-3"/> and what belongs to a neighbour is his, and what
               belongs to God is His' does not apply to those who dwell in solitude, but to those
               who walk without. It is not the duty of him who performs the service of the angels
               with the thoughts of the soul, to please in earthly things; namely to have thought
                  <pb n="104"/>for manual work or to taking from others and giving to others. His
               service is in heaven.</p>
            <p>It is not becoming for the solitary to allow the thought of anything to move and
               drive away his spirit from before God. If, however, anyone dare to adduce the example
               of Paul, who <pb type="external" n="153"/>also performed [manual] work and also gave
               alms, we reply to him: Paul was unique and a master in all things. We know not that
               another Paul has ever existed who was a master in all things like him. Show it me, if
               thou art found to be another Paul, and I will believe thee. Do not, therefore,
               compare the matters of government with the inner practice. For the work of the
               heralds is different from that of solitude.</p>
            <p>But if thou wilt master solitude, be like a Cherub who has no care for earthly
               things. And think that there is no other man in the created world, excepted thee
               alone, and God about whom thou thinkest, as thy Fathers who have gone the way before
               thee, have taught thee. Unless a man harden his heart and restrain his compassion
               forcibly so as to be far from the thought of any man, should it be for the sake of
               God or of any bodily being — but he shall only be in prayer, at the times appointed
               to him, lest love or care of anyone enter his heart — it is not possible for him to
               be freed from the trouble of thought or to be in solitude. So much is certain. But
               when a deliberation is awake in thee, urging thee to the thought of anyone under the
               pretext of excellence, the purpose of which is to drive away from thee the peace that
               was becoming customary to thy heart through the recollection of God, then say to it:
               it is beautiful to lead a life of love and compassion for the sake of God, but I do
               not seek it, even for the sake of God, so it only remains to me to drive thee away
               for the sake of God. Thus the solitary will speak. Then the deliberation <pb
                  type="external" n="154"/>will say to him: And I flee from thee for the sake of
               God.</p>
            <p>Aba Arsenius, for the sake of God, did not open his mouth to speak, neither
               profitable nor gratuitous words. Another, however, for the sake of God, spoke the
               whole day and received all the strangers that visited that place. The former, in
               stead of this, chose silence and solitude.</p>
            <p>Thus he voyaged with the spirit of God on the ocean of this world in the ship of
               solitude, in exalted peace, as is shown in revelation to the athletes who investigate
               this thing.</p>
            <p>This is another denomination of solitude: rest from all <pb n="105"/>things<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n105-1"/>.
               If thou art full of trouble even in solitude, because thy body is troubled by manual
               service and various affairs, and because thy soul is troubled by the thought of
               others, what peace doest thou possess then to care for many things and to please God?
               Judge thyself. It appears to me ridiculous to talk about mastering the course of
               solitude without abandoning all things and the care of all things.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n97-1">Translation according to the London Mss.</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-2">ܣܒܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n97-3">The Eucharist</note>
            <note xml:id="n98-1">Assuming the habits of sin</note>
            <note xml:id="n99-1">ܡܦܖ̈ܩܝ</note>
            <note xml:id="n100-1">literally: entering and departing</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-1"> Colossians 3,5</note>
            <note xml:id="n101-2"> Matthew 19,27</note>
            <note xml:id="n102-1">ܫܒܝܩܝܢ</note>
            <note xml:id="n103-1">Literally: speaking and mute</note>
            <note xml:id="n103-2">In the sense of: mystic course, <!--  Add Arabic  --></note>
            <note xml:id="n103-3">Matthew 22,21</note>
            <note xml:id="n105-1">ܫܠܝܘܬܐ ܕܡܢ ܟܠ</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
