<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 36</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 36, pp. 180-188.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="36">
            <head>XXXVI</head>
            <head>On the various ways in which Satan wars against those who tread the narrow way which
               is above the world</head>
            <p>Our enemy Satan has also other methods, when he cunningly proposes to attack those
               who engage themselves in this strife. His way of warfare varies according to their
               character and in relation to their personal tendencies.</p>
            <pb n="181"/>
            <p>As to those whom he sees to be of a weak will and of feeble thought he
               <choice><sic>combates</sic><corr>combats</corr></choice> them vehemently from the beginning by submitting them to heavy
               and terrible temptations, in order to make them taste the nature of his evil from the
               very beginning of the way. In this way he intends to instill into them a horror of
               the first battle so that this way shall appear to them difficult to walk. And if the
               beginning is very <pb type="external" n="270"/>difficult, who could endure to the
               end, facing all the battles which are ranged in the middle? Thus they will not again
               venture to withstand him or to look for other help, on account of their being totally
               occupied with the thought of his attacks. And when he has pressed them a little
               vehemently they take to flight. Or better: God lets him oppress them, without helping
               them in any way because they have engaged in the battle of the Lord, with a cold
               heart and hesitatingly. Cursed is everyone who performs the work of the Lord without
               diligence, retaining his hand from bloodshed. But also: His help is near those who
               fear Him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n181-1"/>; and He commands that we should not meet the foe with a cold and
               fearful heart. Begin to destroy him and to wage war with him and I will begin to put
               the dread of thee and the fear of thee upon the nations that are under the whole
               heaven<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n181-2"/>.</p>
            <p>If thou doest not voluntarily die to the senses for the sake of the love of God, thou
               wilt die intellectually away from God, against thy will. That which belongs to thy
               lot thou shalt not refuse to take upon thee willingly, though it is connected with
               temporary suffering; afterwards thou shalt enter the glory of God. If thou perishest
               bodily in the strife of the Lord, the Lord will even crown thee; and to thy
               <choice><sic>thriumphant</sic><corr>triumphant</corr></choice> limbs He will attribute the honour of the martyrs.</p>
            <p>So, as I have said above, if they have not girded themselves up from the beginning
               and strengthened themselves and vowed themselves to death, then they will appear to
               be inferior in all battles, especially because God overlooks their
               relaxation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n181-3"/> in that they <choice><sic>trie</sic><corr>tried</corr></choice> to accomplish the work of the Lord in
                  <pb type="external" n="271"/>a frivolous and tentative way. And even Satan knows
               them from the beginning, examining what their thoughts are: pusillanimous, loving
               themselves, even sparing their body. So he persecutes them like a
               <choice><sic>hurrycane</sic><corr>hurricane</corr></choice>, because he does not find in <pb n="182"/>them the
               intelligible power which he usually finds in the triumphant. As a man's will tends
               towards God, for whose sake he loves labours, so God will send him His help and show
               him His care. For it is not possible for Satan to approach unto anyone or to bring
               forward his temptations, except by permission of the godhead; or else that his will
               has become relaxed and he has given himself to impure thoughts and to distraction; or
               because doubt has taken hold of him. Concerning such persons Satan does not ask
               [permission] to try them as in the case of those who are perfect and great; as to the
               latter he knows that they are not given over into his hand. For he knows that it is
               not possible that the power of God's care be withdrawn from them. Except because of
               one of the causes mentioned.</p>
            <p>This is one way in which the foe makes war. As to those whose will he sees to be
               vigorous and who reckon death as nothing and who have begun with keen zeal giving
               themselves over to every temptation and to death, and who trample upon life and the
               world and the body with its temptations — <choice><sic>thees</sic><corr>these</corr></choice> <pb type="external" n="272"
               />he does not meet at the outset, nor does he usually show himself to them. But he
               withdraws himself and gives way to them. He neither encounters them with his
               principal force nor does he enter into battle with them. For he knows that the
               beginning of battles is usually hot and the antagonist is zealous and zealous
               champions are seldom vanquished.</p>
            <p>This method he follows, not because he is afraid of them, but of that divine power
               which sets them ablaze through the forces working in them till they begin to emit it
               through their own will in full confidence. But he leaves them for some time till
               their zeal is abating and their attention is withdrawn from the exercise of the
               weapon for which they had trained themselves and with which they had armed their
               mind, viz. different divine words and profitable and strengthening recollections; and
               thus awaits the time of negligence. And when the first thoughts have abated somewhat,
               how often will they find within themselves occasions of defeat on account of
               allurements that have their origin in the mind. They dig a ditch in themselves
               through the distraction of thoughts that arise in their mind through tediousness,
               through which a chill overpowers them.</p>
            <p>It is not spontaneous when Satan acts thus, delaying the time of battle; for neither
               when he spares them nor when he <pb n="183"/>withdraws himself from them, does he
               account them nothing. But I think that a certain power surrounds those who are
               blazing with fervour unto God and who have begun in a youthful way, without
               forethought, confiding in Him on account <pb type="external" n="273"/>of their faith,
               without knowing however against whom they have to fight. Therefore he conceals his
               evil nature from them, approaching not near. For his nature is checked by the
               guardian which he sees with them continually. Now if they do not cast away the causes
               of profit: beseeching, labours and humbleness, the helper will never withdraw Himself
               from them. The love of comfort is a cause of [God's] withdrawal. But if they adhere
               to these [works] sedulously, they will never be destitute of help and the foe will
               not be allowed to approach them. And if [God] <choice><sic>witdraws</sic><corr>withdraws</corr></choice> himself from time
               to time, this is for the sake of training. For while the holy force governs and
               accompanies them, they do not fear seducers; the mind is full of courage and
               therefore it despises them. But He trains them as a man who teaches swimming to a
               little boy; as soon as he begins to sink, the teacher lifts him up, for the boy swims
               upon the hands of his teacher. And when the courage of the boy begins to diminish,
               from fear that he will be drowned, the man who supports him with his hands, cries: be
               not afraid, I support thee. Or, as a mother who teaches her little child to walk,
               places him at a distance from her and calls him; but when the boy will go to his
               mother on those little tottering feet of his, they tremble on account of their
               weakness. Then when the boy is about to fall, the mother will run and take him <pb
                  type="external" n="274"/>in her arms. So God's grace will bear up and train the
               children of man, namely those who trust themselves clearly and simply to the hands of
               Him that created them and who with their whole heart turn from the world and follow
               Him.</p>
            <p>And thou, O man, who hast begun to follow God, recollect perpetually during thy whole
               struggle the beginning and that first zeal at the outset of the way and the fervent
               thoughts with which thou didst leave thy former life and range thyself in the order
               of battle. And examine thyself every day [in order to state] whether the fervour of
               thy soul has abated in comparison with the zeal with which thou wert blazing. Or
               whether thou lackest any weapon with which thou wert girded at the beginning of thy
               struggle. And elevate constantly thy voice in the camp and encourage those of the
               right hand with familiar <pb n="184"/>thoughts. And show the opposite party that thou
               art awake. And if thou meetest impetuosity in the beginning, because the temptator
               will frighten thee, do not then relax. Perhaps this will be profitable to thee.</p>
            <p>It is not without reason that thy saviour permits anything unto thee but only when He
               has foreseen it and ordered it to thy profit. Show thou no relaxation from the
               beginning; for if thou shouldst show relaxation here, thou wouldst not be able to
               withstand what follows: hunger, sickness, fearful sights and so on. Do not turn into
               its opposite the intention of Him that commands thee to fight, which serves to thy
               profit, lest <pb type="external" n="275"/>thy foe find thee as he hopes to find thee.
               But cry unto God unceasingly and weep before His grace and weary thyself out with
               beseeching, till He sends thee a helper. And if thou once seest the saviour who is
               with thee, thou wilt no more be vanquished by thy foe who is standing before
               thee.</p>
            <p>Thus far these two kinds of strife.</p>
            <p>Another way in which Satan makes war against those who are girded.</p>
            <p>When after all this Satan is still opposed by a man without being able to overpower
               him in battle, or rather his helper, for whose sake man resists him, and who helps
               and strengthens him to such an extent that he who is compact flesh and body
               vanquishes him that is spiritual and unbodily — when Satan sees all the help which
               that man receives from God so that his outward senses are not vanquished by sights
               and sounds nor his thoughts weakened by excitations and allurements, nay he even
               despises the blows they give him, then he seeks for a means to separate that man from
               the angel that helps him, or rather he purposes to blind the mind of him that is
               helped so that he is left without support.</p>
            <p>So he stirs that man's thoughts of presumption namely those of [imaginary] strength,
               so that he thinks his mind the cause of all this vigour and of the glorious wealth
               which he possesses in his soul. His preservation from all these obstacles, sad, <pb
                  type="external" n="276"/>unspeakable, and bloodthirsty, he sometimes ascribes to
               accident, sometimes to their being weak. I do not mention other things the bare
               recollection of which makes the soul shiver on account of their blasphemous
               nature.</p>
            <p>It also happens that he advances his betrayal insidiously under the appearance of
               divine revelations. During sleep he <pb n="185"/>imparts information and in the state
               of waking he assumes the likeness of an angel of light. And all this [is of such a
               nature] that, should a man surrender to it even to a small extent, he will become its
               victim. But if a man be wise and keep his thoughts under control, or rather if God
               helps him and he fixes the gaze of his heart on heaven in order to turn away from
               incantators, then the foe plans another kind of war. This is the only one left to him
               now; and because it has some affinity to nature he expects the more that man will be
               entangled in it. What is it? He contrives in all manner of ways to set man in contact
               with those things through which he usually becomes guilty on account of his nature.
               The mind of the warrior namely becomes blinded by sight of and contact with [worldly]
               things, and it is easily vanquished in battle when it is near them, especially when
               they are ranged before his eyes. The clever one knows this cunning thoroughly on
               account of his experience with many valiant champions who were <pb type="external"
                  n="277"/>vanquished through it. Therefore he prepares this means cunningly. And
               when it is not of a nature to be practised because of the [warrior's] utter solitude
               and his dwelling far from things that cause [sin], then he contrives to bring it near
               him through phantasy. So he shows him fallacious images in the habit of reality, in
               order that by these visions he be rendered desirous and incited to conceive impure
               thoughts and become guilty and to alienate Him that helps him. For Satan knows that
               the solitary's victory and defeat, his treasure and his help and all that belongs to
               him, depends upon deliberation, and that, if deliberation be moved from its place,
               one short moment is able to throw him down from the nest of life on to the earth, if
               his will be pointed in this direction for even a moment only. Thus it has happened to
               many of the saints that he showed them the image of a beautiful woman.</p>
            <p>Those who dwelt at a distance of one or two or even ten parasangs from the inhabited
               world he did indeed contrive to bring in contact with a woman. But to those, to whom
               he could not do this on account of their distant dwellingplace being too far off, he
               showed the images of womanly beauty by appearing to them, now in splendid dress and
               finery and in a seducing aspect, now even in the form of a naked woman. Some of the
               solitaries he overpowered by these means and the like, some by real seduction, some
               by things of the<pb n="186"/>imagination which brought about their fall<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186-1"/>
               through the relaxation of their deliberations; so they fell down into the abyss of
               despondency and turned unto the world, cutting themselves off from heavenly hope.</p>
            <p>Others however who were steadfast and illuminated by grace, <pb type="external"
                  n="278"/>have vanquished him and his fantastic representations and trampled upon
               bodily pleasures; and they have been found to be elected by the love of God.</p>
            <p>Often also he represents to them images of gold and precious things as treasures that
               were hidden somewhere. It even happens that he shows them these things in reality,
               expecting that by one of these various [artifices] it will be possible to impede some
               one of the solitaries so as to bar his course through his being entangled in one of
               the snares of his nets. Lead me not, o Lord, into these temptations; for even the
               strong and the elect scarcely pass this gate victorious.</p>
            <p>The seducer is allowed to make war upon the saints in all these ways of temptation,
               in order that the love of God which is in them may be proved under these
               circumstances; namely, whether they are friends of God and whether they adhere to His
               love because [worldly] things are at a distance, far off and absent; or whether they
               love God really, so as to make war on and to despise these things even when present,
               without being vanquished and without giving up their love of God through the
               allurements of those temptations. This does not happen that they may be known to God
               through these [temptations], but to the Devil, who is very desirous of recognizing
               them, if possible. As he also said concerning Job, asking God about him: Doth Job
               fear God for nought<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n186-2"/>? If then a little negligence creeps in, the temptator
               approaches with authority in accordance with the power he has over them. Then the
               unjust appears in the desire which these things excite in him. <pb type="external"
                  n="279"/>And through these things those are proved who are strong in their love of
               Him, those who despise all these things, which in their eyes are counted as nothing
               in comparison with the love of God. In this they are humble, ascribing merits only to
               Him who strengthens all and who is the cause of their victory and into His hands they
               entrust the battle. For Thou art the <pb n="187"/>powerful, and the battle is Thine.
               Fight, o Lord, and be victorious on our behalf.</p>
            <p>Then they are tested by these things as gold in the furnace. But those who are
               untrustworthy are recognized there through those trials, and thrown out as refuse.
               They give way to their foe and have to leave the battle, defeated through the
               relaxation of their mind, or perhaps through their haughtiness which has made them
               unworthy of that strong power which is always ready to help the saints.</p>
            <p>For never to be defeated is the power of Him that helps us, the omnipotent, the
               almighty, the victorious at all times whenever He descends into the body of mortals
               to fight for them. But it is manifest that those who are defeated, are defeated
               without Him. They are those whose will is stripped of Him because of their
               injustrice, who are not worthy of that power which is the support of the victorious.
               They also perceive at the time of battle that they lack the usual strength, which
               they found in themselves in all hot and difficult battles. How do they perceive this?
               They see in themselves that their defeat gives them comfort and that the hardships of
               strife are <pb type="external" n="280"/>difficult for them to bear, hardships under
               which at all times they were wonted to win a clear victory. And the emotions of zeal
               which at such times used to stir nature vigorously and which were strengthened by a
               fiery heat — they do not find them in themselves.</p>
            <p>Now those who are shaken from their foundation are terrified not only by these and
               the like struggles, but even by the sound of the leaves of the trees<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n187-1"/>, and
               give way and renounce and turn their back under light trouble, for hunger or slight
               illness. The true and elect, however, do not even satisfy their hunger with herbs and
               vegetables. But, feeding upon drugs and dry stubble, even then they are not to be
               persuaded to open their mouth for food, before the fixed time. Lying on the earth,
               with an emaciated body and eyes blinded<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n187-2"/> on account of bodily weakness, their
               soul near their mouth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n187-3"/> through tribulation, even then they do not give way so
               as to be vanquished and give up their firm will. For it is more delightful for them
               to be troubled for the sake of love, with <pb n="188"/>labours for excellency, than
               to possess temporal life and all its comforts. So, when adversities approach them,
               they rejoice; for they know that these will lead them to perfection. And not only
               have they no doubt of the love of Christ in spite of the bodily tortures they have to
               suffer, but it would be delightful <pb type="external" n="281"/>even to bear for His
               sake loss of life; even then they would not separate themselves from Him.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n181-1">Ps. 145,19</note>
            <note xml:id="n181-2">Deut. 2,25</note>
            <note xml:id="n181-3">ܠܡܬܪܦܝܘ as the London Mss. have</note>
            <note xml:id="n186-1"><choice><sic>litt.</sic><corr>lit.</corr></choice> derision</note>
            <note xml:id="n186-2">Job 1,9</note>
            <note xml:id="n187-1">Cf. Lev. 26,36</note>
            <note xml:id="n187-2">Isaac himself is said to have become blinded</note>
            <note xml:id="n187-3">i. e. on the point of leaving the body</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
