<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 67</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 67, pp. 316-318.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="67">
            <head>LXVII</head>
            <p>An elucidation with examples concerning the distinctions between intelligible things
               [showing] which use there is in each of them</p>
            <p>Intellect<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n316-2"/> is a spiritual sense which is made a recipient of the visual
               power, as the pupil of the fleshly eyes into which perceptible light is poured.</p>
            <pb n="317"/>
            <p>Intelligible sight is natural knowledge which by power has been mixed with the order
               of nature, and which is called natural light.</p>
            <p>A holy power is grace, the sun of distinction for those things, which hold a middle
               position between light and sight. Species<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n317-1"/> are those things which are
               intermediary and distinguished by light so as to become sight. The affections are as
               it were some dense entities, which, placed between light and sight, hinder the
               distinction of things.</p>
            <p>Purity is the clearness of the intelligible air, through the mediation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n317-2"/> of
               which spiritual nature circulates in us.</p>
            <p>The reverse way: If the intellect is not of a sound nature, knowledge does not
               influence it. If the fleshly sense is harmed by some cause, sight is taken from it.
               If the intellect is sound, but there is no knowledge, the intellect cannot have any
               distinct influence upon spiritual things without it; just as an eye which is sound in
               all those things which are its own, <pb type="external" n="473"/>and yet, often its
               visual power is dull. So, if all these [spiritual] things are preserved in their
               proper state, but grace is not near, they remain, all of them, destitute of the
               service of their different functions; as it is also during nighttime, when all these
               things, because of the absence of the sun, remain without function, though they are
               true and perfect in themselves. I mean eye, sight and things, not those which are
               distinguishing or distinguished. This is what has been said: In Thy light we see
               light<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n317-3"/>. Now, even when grace, the intelligible sun, is near and inciting and
               flattering and working and exhortating, but there is no purity through which (as
               through the air purified from the density of the clouds and from the matter of
               darkness) the sunrays attain to us easily, so that we enjoy by their light a sight
               which is wholly spiritual — then sight is impeded in its discriminating power, nature
               looses its active force, the soul is hindered from perceiving the second sun which
               dawns over the world, because of the screen of the body in which the rays of truth
               are hidden so that they cannot reach us.</p>
            <p>Therefore, all that has been said is strictly necessary. And because all these things
               are hardly to be found without <pb n="318"/>deficiency any one, not many are found
               who reach a partial completeness in spiritual knowledge. Such a deficiency has its
               origin in impotence of the intellect, or in neglect of the aim, <pb type="external"
                  n="474"/>or in the unpreparedness of the will, or in lack of purity, or in want of
               guides, or in the impediments of grace (for riches do not suit the fool, nor is a
               slave entitled to rule over many things) — or in the hindrances of time, place and
               mode.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n316-2">ܡܕܥܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n317-1">ܟܝ̈ܢܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n317-2">lit. bosom</note>
            <note xml:id="n317-3">Ps. 36,9</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
