<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 17</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 17, pp. 91-95</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="17">
            <head>XVII</head>
            <head><pb type="external" n="134"/>On the short paths towards God which are revealed to one
               from the sweet works in vigils and that those who are given to vigils are supported
               by honey their wholy lifetime</head>
            <p>Do not think, O man, that among all the works of ascetics there is any one greater
               and more profitable than that of vigils. In truth, my brethren, if during the day the
               ascetic is not distracted by corporeal things and temporal care, but cuts himself off
               somewhat from the world, and is watchful to even a low degree during vigils, then I
               do not object to declare unto you in truth, that soon his spirit will fly as with
               wings and ascend unto God to be in delight. And he will easily look at that glory,
               and in that knowledge which is higher than <pb n="92"/>human spirit he will quickly
               swim. The solitary who during his vigils abides by the discernment of the mind, will
               no longer seem to be clad with flesh. Verily, this work belongs to the class of the
               angels. And it is impossible that those who applicate themselves to this behaviour,
               should be left without great divine gifts, on account of the vigilance and serenity
               of their heart, and because their deliberations tend to Him only.</p>
            <p>The soul, therefore, which applies itself in its labours to the duty of vigils,
               becomes trained, and acquires Cherubs' eyes in the swiftness and acuteness of their
               gaze, so that at all times it gazes on heavenly contemplations.</p>
            <p>I am of the opinion that he who on account of <choice><sic>vaste</sic><corr>vast</corr></choice> <pb type="external"
                  n="135"/>knowledge and with discernment has chosen for himself this great and
               divine work, and is wholly devoted to bear the load of the glorious part he has
               chosen, will necessarily be zealous to guard himself also during the day against the
               trouble of occupations and of care for [worldly] things, and that he consequently
               will not be devoid of wonderful fruits and the great delight he will gather from
               them. And I may say deliberately, without lying, that he who despises this, does not
               even know for what purpose he performs all this toil: the loss of sleep, the many
               repetitions, the fatigue of the tongue, the standing on his feet during the whole
               night, while his mind is not there where he recites his Psalms and prayers; but he
               performs these works as a matter of custom, as something which is devoid of
               discernment. And if this were not as I say, how could he suffer to be bereft of and
               to remain without reaping profitable fruits from the constant occupation with his
               work? But he strives towards these [results] through the holy occupation of the
               recitation of the scriptures, which is a fortification of the mind and, principally,
               a cause<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n92-1"/> of prayer, a helper and a companion of vigils, a light of the mind, a
               guide on the way and the seed<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n92-2"/> of manifold contemplation during prayer. It is
               a check against the distraction of the spirit and against its occupying itself with
               idle things. It sows in the soul constant recollection of God and [of] the ways of
               the saints who have pleased Him. And it causes the mind to acquire wisdom and
               subtlety.</p>
            <p>Wherefore then, O zealous man, doest thou order thy <pb n="93"/><pb type="external"
                  n="136"/>occupations in this way, without discernment? For thou showest care for
               thyself in that thou standest upon thy feet during the whole night, fatiguing thyself
               with glorifications and Psalms and prayers. It would be easy for thee, by little
               watchfulness during the day, to be made worthy of the divine grace for thy strenuous
               efforts in other duties. Wherefore doest thou fatigue thyself and sow in the night,
               whereas during the day thou renderest useless thy works so as to lose the fruits,
               dissipating this vigilance and fervour which thou wouldst acquire by vigils, through
               the distraction of intercourse with men and through different occupations, and
               destroying thy profit by wandering idleness?</p>
            <p>If thou wouldst associate to thy nightly meditation, o man, service during the day
               without breaking in twain the fervour of the occupations of the heart, thou wouldst
               quickly embrace Jesus' bosom.</p>
            <p>And from this thou seest that thou sufferest for lack of discernment. For thou doest
               not perceive why vigils are necessary for the ascetic. Thou thinkest it is for the
               sake of toiling only, and not in respect of another thing which is expected to be
               born from it.</p>
            <p>But he that by grace has almost been made worthy of understanding that for which the
               sages hope in combating sleep and compelling nature to such a degree that during the
               whole night, awake bodily and mentally, they offer prayers — also knows the strength
               given by watchfulness during the day and the profit it grants the spirit in its
               nightly solitude while <pb type="external" n="137"/>at its vigils with discernment,
               and the power it supplies over the deliberations and the purity<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n93-1"/> and
               concentration with which it endows the mind, so that without compulsion and strife
               the spirit gazes at the greatness of the words [recited] .</p>
            <p>I say this also, that though the body may fall short in the work of fasting on
               account of its great weakness, yet vigils, by their lonely character, afford the mind
               steadfastness in prayer, and enable the heart to recognize spiritual powers by means
               of insight. This can only take place if it is not assailed by any disturbance through
               relaxation caused by things met during the day.</p>
            <p>Therefore I admonish thee, o man of insight who wishest to acquire vigilance of mind
               in God and knowledge of the <pb n="94"/>new life, that during thy lifetime thou
               mayest not despise this duty<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n94-1"/> of vigils, by which thy eyes will be opened so
               as to see the whole glory of ascetic work and the power of the way of
               righteousness.</p>
            <p>And if it should happen — unfortunately — that a thought of relaxation should make
               its nest in thee, and thou shouldst think, on account of [previous] experience, that
               thy usual helper is training thee and making thee prudent by means of varying states,
               such as coldness and heat, or by variety of chance and occasion, or on account of thy
               body being ill or weak; and if this should induce thee to forego sleep in the
               evening, though thou shouldst not be willing to fatigue thy body — then I beseech
               thee with love to desist from all this zealous labour, the reciting of Psalms, the
               performing of the service, the <pb type="external" n="138"/>frequent kneelings during
               regular praying. I <choice><sic>advice</sic><corr>advise</corr></choice> thee to sit in solitude, awake, if thou art able
               to do this, without recitation of Psalms and without prostrations. And if thou art
               able to do so, pray with thy heart only. But do not sleep. And by all means pass thy
               night, sitting, in the usual beautiful meditation. Only — do not make thy heart
               heavy<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n94-2"/> and dark by sleep. Then the old swiftness and force and fervour will be
               given thee by grace and thou wilt rejoice and exult and thank God. For such heaviness
               and coldness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n94-3"/> are admitted unto man in order to test him.</p>
            <p>If a man rouse himself fervently and shake off and cast away [despondency],
               compelling himself somewhat, suddenly grace will approach as before. And another
               force will impart itself to him, in which ten thousand [gifts of] grace and
               profitable states are hidden. And man will be astonished while thinking of the former
               heaviness and the swiftness and strength following it, and of how such a state of a
               sudden has overcome him.</p>
            <p>Therefore he will be prudent henceforth, so that, when this heaviness comes again at
               other times, he will recognize it. But if he had not been daring on former occasions,
               he would not have acquired this knowledge.</p>
            <p>Thou seest how prudent a man becomes if he rouse himself a little and if he be
               valiant at the time of struggle. But when <pb n="95"/>his nature really subsists only
               and no longer struggle but sickness or natural weakness, it is useless to resist. If
               a man compel himself in other points, strength in all things will be given him.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="139"/>Constant solitude, with recitation and moderate food,
               easily arouse in the spirit a state of ecstasy<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n95-1"/>, if perpetual solitude be not
               broken or any cause. Insight brought about by works performed in solitude, will of
               itself, automatically and suddenly, impart to these two eyes a kind of baptism, by
               tears which but forth and moisten the cheeks by their profuseness.</p>
            <p>If thou perceivest in thy body, humbled by the asceticism of watchful solitude, the
               vehement passion of fornication, — not the usual dark impulse of nature, — know then
               that thou art tempted in thy spirit by haughtiness. Mix thy food with ashes, press
               thy belly against the dust and scrutinize what thou hast thought. And recognize the
               varying states of thy nature and thy service which is above thy nature. Perhaps God
               will have mercy upon thee and send thee light so that thou wilt know how to be
               humble, lest thy evil become greater.</p>
            <p>So we will not desist from carefulness, till repentance dawns in our heart, and we
               find humility and our heart finds rest in God.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n92-1">ܫܩܝܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n92-2">literally: the sower</note>
            <note xml:id="n93-1">Reading of some Mss.</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-1">ܕܘܒܪܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-2">Literally: thick</note>
            <note xml:id="n94-3">Reading ܩܪܝܪܘܬܐ with the London Ms</note>
            <note xml:id="n95-1">ܬܗܪܐ ܕܥܠ ܨܒܘ̈ܬܐ amazing attitude regarding things</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
