<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 71</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 71, pp. 328-331.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="71">
            <pb n="328"/>
            <head>LXXI</head>
            <head><pb type="external" n="489"/>On the influences proceeding from grace</head>
            <p>Thou must perpetually place a token in thy soul, and pay attention to it. And when
               thou perceivest that divine care begins to reveal itself to the soul, then understand
               that thou art near the harbour of purity. As soon as man begins to be lifted up above
               the affections, this holy force will cling to the soul, without leaving it, day or
               night, showing it God's providence. And even the particulars of what is and comes to
               pass, of yes and no, what happens to a man secretly and manifestly and the facts
               relating to the creation of this world, are revealed to the soul by that force which
               clings to it and which reveals to it the creative power of God and shows it divine
               providence which, without a break, follows and visits this whole creation. And it
               shows the soul how this providence follows man at all times, and, though he does not
               perceive it and does not know it, preserves him against adversities at all times and
               directs him towards what serves for the salvation and the rest of his soul and body
               and to gain life.</p>
            <p>Now this divine force, which works all these, shows itself secretly to man, by
               intelligible revelation to his spiritual nature, which is intellect. When man has
               been deemed worthy to receive this power within his soul, he abides only in ecstasy
               and silence and tears which always flow as water, so that he desists from <pb
                  type="external" n="490"/>all work.</p>
            <p>And thou must gaze at all times at this sight of God's continual care for the work of
               His hands: the mind absorbed in ecstasy, the senses at rest, weak man prostrated on
               his face in prayer, [<choice><sic>in astate</sic><corr>a state</corr></choice>] in which no tongue can speak and in which
               no heart can pray, but by astonishment at these things even prayer is cut off.</p>
            <p>This is the idleness which is more profitable than work, when a man is purely at
               rest, with his senses and his impulses, being continually prostrated before his Lord.
               And even his bones in silence send up a glorification to God, in this so called
               idleness as the prophet says: All my bones shall say:</p>
            <pb n="329"/>
            <p>Lord, who is like unto Thee?<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n329-1"/> At this time, above all affections, thou
               findest the demon of haughtiness bound and thrown at the feet of the soul. By this
               gift, as it is said, man becomes worthy of the love of God and of complete
               humility.</p>
            <p>This first gift is tasted through solitude. And those who, in service and observance,
               have abided within absolute solitude, must necessarily know it. But when a man leaves
               solitude and begins to be lax, it is withdrawn from him. And when he enters again and
               cares for himself and clings diligently to the usual service, he is again supplied
               with it, and it shows its force to the soul. Then, when man has become wholly
               perfect, this force will cling to him inwardly and outwardly and <pb type="external"
                  n="491"/>not one hour will he be without sighs and tears and the rest, if he does
               not neglect<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n329-2"/> the pure order of his service. Even now there are men who have
               been deemed worthy of this partly. And the peculiarities of the degree of perfection
               they recognize from that which they possess partially. For, when a man has tasted a
               small quantity<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n329-3"/> of wine from a large skin, he knows how all the rest is, even
               when others drink a part or all the remainder.</p>
            <p>A man who possesses [this gift] in perfection, will not soon be found, nay hardly at
               all. For this power is a gift of the observance of solitude; and because in this our
               enervated generation there is none who keeps perfect solitude and complete
               observance, we are also destitute of its gifts<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n329-4"/>. He who possesses these signs
               in writing of ink, but their practice is not found in him by experience, resembles a
               man who bears in his arms a cither adorned and provided with strong strings, but his
               fingers do not know, because they are not trained, to play thereon and to bring forth
               different melodies for his own delight. For he only possesses the cither, but not the
               required art. And he needs others to play on it before him and give him
               enjoyment.</p>
            <p>Do not rejoice when thou art rich in the knowledge of many things; but rejoice when
               that which thou knowest is found with thee practically. The former without the latter
               will retire gradually and even end in haughtiness, through idleness. When thou art
               zealous in the latter, thou wilt necessarily be illuminated <pb n="330"/>by it
               without instruction. The eye of knowledge is experience; its growth is brought about
               by continual service.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="492"/>This will be to thee a luminous token of the serenity of
               thy soul: when thou, examining thyself, findest thyself full of mercy for all
               mankind, and when thy heart is afflicted by pity for them and burns as with fire
               without personal discrimination. While by these things the image of the Father in
               heaven is continually seen in thee, thou canst recognize the degree of thy behaviour,
               not by the discrimination of the labours, but by the varying states to which thy
               intellect is subject. The body is then wont to swim in tears, as the mind gazes at
               spiritual things, while it is as if from the eyes there flowed brooks which moisten
               the cheeks, without compulsion, spontaneously.</p>
            <p>Now,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n330-1"/> I know one who even during his sleep was overwhelmed by ecstasy in God
               through the contemplation of something which he had read in the evening. And while
               his soul was amazed at this contemplative meditation, he perceived, as it were, that
               he had meditated for long in the motion of sleep and examined the ecstatic vision. It
               was in the depth of the night, and suddenly he awoke from his sleep while his tears
               dropped as water and fell upon his breast; and his mouth was full of glorification
               and his heart meditated in contemplation for a long time, with a delight which did
               not come to an end. And through the many tears that, without measure, were shed by
               his eyes, and through the stupefaction of his soul by which all the members of his
               body were relaxed, and of his heart in which some delight <pb type="external" n="493"
               />was astir, he was not even able to accomplish his usual nightservice, except some
               psalm at break of dawn, so overwhelmed was he by the many tears which as a fountain
               broke forth from his eyes spontaneously, and by the other spiritual things.</p>
            <p>Let us also be zealous, my brethren. And before we go to sleep, let us many times
               meditate upon glorifications and recited psalm and passages of the holy scriptures,
               guarding ourselves against evil recollections and from bad thought. And let us
               provide<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n330-2"/> our treasury with every beautiful thing. Then sleep will overtake us
               while we are full of the recollection of God, while our soul is flowing with great
               desire for the things that <pb n="331"/>are good, through the grace of God which
               surrounds us in our sleep and spends upon us its gifts while we are sleeping,
               examining us, whether our body is free from any kind of impurity, and the impulses of
               our heart pure from evil. And through grace it will be impossible for the sons of the
               prince of darkness to approach us because the sword and lance of grace surround us.
               But when they find us as they like to find us, when grace has withdrawn from us
               because it disliked us and has removed us from itself as corpses void of life, then
               they approach us, with all their evil, and try us by all sordid and fearful impulses,
               according to the desire of their evil will.</p>
            <p>And when such a thing happens to us in our sleep, let us understand at once and
               recollect and perceive, that in that night God's inspiration<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n331-1"/> was far from
               us. And how is it that the <pb type="external" n="494"/>demons have not devoured us?
               Because the divine will in whose hand the soul of all flesh is placed, only allows
               [them] to approach us, that we should arouse and look at ourselves. It is not
               possible for them to approach us when [inspiration] is near.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n329-1">Ps. 35,10</note>
            <note xml:id="n329-2">ܡܙܘܪ, meaning uncertain</note>
            <note xml:id="n329-3">ܡܢܩܝܬܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n329-4">cf. Book of the Dove, Introduction, p. XVI</note>
            <note xml:id="n330-1">Cf. Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n330-2">Reading ܢܐܣܢ instead of ܢܣܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n331-1">ܡܓܢܢܘܬܐ</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
