<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 43</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 43, pp. 210-212.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="43">
            <head>XLIII</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="315"/>Profitable words full of spiritual wisdom</p>
            <p>Faith is the gate of the mysteries. What the bodily eye is for the things of the
               senses, the same is faith in connection with the treasures hidden to the eyes of the
               mind.</p>
            <p>We possess two psychic eyes, as the Fathers say, just as we possess two bodily eyes.
               But both have not the same purpose as to sight.</p>
            <p>With one we see the hidden glory of God which is concealed in the things of nature,
               His power and His wisdom, and His eternal care for us which by His peculiar
               providence is directed unto us. With the same eye we also see the spiritual classes
               of our fellow-beings.</p>
            <p>With the other we see the glory of His holy nature. When our Lord desires to give us
               initiation to the spiritual mysteries, He opens in our mind the ocean of faith.</p>
            <p>As a grace beyond a grace has repentance been given to man. Repentance is being born
               anew in God. That of which we have received the pledge by baptism, we receive as a
               gift by repentance. Repentance is the gate of mercy which is opened to all who seek
               it. Through this gate we go in to divine mercy. Apart from this entrance it is not
               possible to find <pb n="211"/>mercy. Because all have sinned, according to the words
               of scripture, and are justified freely by grace[#n211-1]. Repentance is a second
               grace; it is born in the heart from faith and fear. Fear is the paternal rod which
               guides us up to the spiritual Eden. <pb type="external" n="316"/>When we have arrived
               there, it leaves us and returns. Eden is the divine love wherein is the paradise of
               all goods, where the blessed Paul was sustained by supernatural food. When he had
               eaten from the tree of life which is there, he exclaimed: eye has not seen, nor ear
               heard neither have entered into the heart of man the things which God hath prepared
               for them that love him[#n211-2]. Adam was bereft of this tree by the promise of the
               Devil. The tree of life is the divine love which Adam lost by his fall, after which
               he worked and wearied himself. Those who are bereft of divine love are still eating
               the bread that is won by the sweat of their labour, even though they work
               righteousness, as was commanded to the head of our race when he lost it by his fall.
               Until we find love, we work in the earth with her thorns. Among thorns we sow and
               reap, even if we sow the seed of righteousness. Perpetually we are pricked by them,
               even if we are justified, and live with sweat on our faces.</p>
            <p>When, however, we have found love, we eat the heavenly bread and we are sustained
               without labour and without weariness. Heavenly bread is that which has descended from
               heaven and which gives the world life; this is the food of angels. He that has found
               love eats Christ at all times and becomes immortal from thence onwards. For whoever
               eats of this bread shall not taste death in eternity. Blessed is he that <pb
                  type="external" n="317"/>has eaten from the bread of love which is Jesus. Whoever
               is fed with love is fed with Christ, who is the allgoverning God. Witness is John who
               says: God is Love[#n211-3]. Thus he smells life from God, that lives with love in
               this creation. He breathes here of the air of resurrection. In this air the righteous
               will delight at resurrection. Love is the kingdom of which our Lord spoke when He
               symbolically promised the disciples that they would eat in His kingdom: 'you shall
               eat and drink at the table of my kingdom'. What should they eat, if not love? Love is
               sufficient to feed man in stead of food and drink. This is the wine that gladdens the
               heart of man. Blessed is he <pb n="212"/>who has drunk from this wine. This is the
               wine from which the lascivious have drunk and they became chaste, the sinners and
               they forgot the ways of offence, the drunkards and they became fasters; the rich and
               they became desirous of poverty, the poor and they became rich in hope; the sick and
               they became valiant; the fools and they became wise.</p>
            <p>As it is not possible to cross the ocean without a boat or a ship, so no one can
               cross towards love, without fear. This foetid sea, which lies between us and the
               intelligible paradise, we cross in the boat of repentance, which has fear for a
               rudder. If the rudder of fear does not govern this ship of repentance, in which we
               cross the sea of this world towards God, we shall be drowned in the foetid sea.
               Repentance is the ship, fear is her governor, love is the divine port.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="318"/>Fear places us in the ship of repentance and makes us
               cross the foetid sea of the world and brings us in the divine port which is love,
               towards which look all those who are weary and crushed by repentance.</p>
            <p>When we have reached love, we have reached God and our way is ended and we have
               passed unto the island which lieth beyond the world, where is the Father and the Son
               and the Holy Ghost; to whom be glory and dominion. That He make us worthy to fear Him
               and to love Him. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n211-1">Cf. Rom. 3,23 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n211-2">1 Cor. 2,9</note>
            <note xml:id="n211-3">1 John 4,16</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
