<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 8</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 8, pp. 70-74</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="8">
            <head>VIII</head>
            <head>What it is that helps a man to come near unto God with his heart and why it is that
               help comes near unto him secretly and what it is that causes a man to come near unto
               humility</head>
            <p>Blessed is the man who knows his weakness. This knowledge becomes for him the
               foundation and the beginning [of his coming] unto all good and beautiful things. When
               a man <pb n="71"/>knows and perceives that he really and in truth is weak, then he
               restrains his soul from profuseness which is dissipation of knowledge and he will
               augment the watchfulness of his soul.</p>
            <p>Unless a man has been remiss in some small thing and a slight negligence has appeared
               in him and tempters have surrounded him either with temptations that arouse bodily
               affections or with temptations which stir the affectable power of the soul, he cannot
               perceive his own weakness. Then, however, he recognizes the greatness of God's help
               by comparing it with his own weakness.</p>
            <p>Thus if he sees that his heart does not rest from fear, even though he be provident
               and very cautious, withdrawing and <pb type="external" n="105"/>hiding his soul in
               innumerable apartments and providing his soul with causes of trust, then he
               understands and knows that this whole impulse of his heart denotes some other thing
               which is lacking and which is very necessary to him, viz. that he needs other help.
               For the heart testifies to [this] within, by the fear that moves in it, denoting the
               lack of something. And therefore he cannot remain in confidence. For the help of God
               is necessary for deliverance.</p>
            <p>When he knows that he needs divine help, he will frequently pray. And by much
               beseeching the heart becomes humble, for there is no man who is needy and asking,
               without being humble. And God will not despise a broken and contrite heart<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n71-1"/>.
               Until the heart has become humble, it will not rest from distraction. Humility
               restrains the heart. And as soon as man has become humble, mercy will surround and
               envelop him. And when mercy draws near, the heart will perceive help at once, because
               some confidence and force will also move in it. When it perceives that divine help
               approach unto it and that He is its support and its helper, then the heart will be
               filled with faith at once. Then it will see and understand that prayer is the port of
               help, the fountain of salvation, the treasure of confidence, the sheet-anchor amidst
               the storms, the light in the darkness, the stick of the weak, the shelter at the time
               of temptations, the medicine at the time of illness, the shield of protection in the
               battle, the sharp arrow against the enemies.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="106"/>And because by prayer he has found the entrance unto all
               this good, he will delight in prayer of faith for ever more, <pb n="72"/>while his
               heart exults in confidence, not blindly and with words only, as it had been till
               then.</p>
            <p>When he knows this, he possesses prayer as a treasure within his soul. And from joy
               he changes the tenor of prayer into sounds of thanksgiving. And the following word
               has been said by the sage among the saints, Mar Euagrius, who did every thing which
               he did with a purpose: Prayer is a joy that gives place to thanksgivings. Concerning
               this prayer, which takes place after receiving the knowledge of God, he says: This
               prayer that gives place [to thanksgiving], in which a man does not pray nor act as in
               the other passionate prayers which he prayed, perceiving grace, consists therein that
               in the heart, which is filled with joy and ecstasy, frequently emotions of
               thanksgivings and gratitude stir themselves, in the silence of kneelings. Then, on
               account of the inner ardour, which is set in motion by wonder at the understanding of
               God's bounties, he will of a sudden raise up his voice and praise without being
               wearied, while the inner ardour gives place to thanksgivings also of the tongue and
               so he will give utterance [to his feelings] long and wonderfully. Who has experienced
               these things clearly, not dimly, and has noted them with intelligence, will
               understand when I say that it occurs without variation, for it has been experienced
               many times. And furthermore [such a man] <pb type="external" n="107"/>will leave idle
               things and be constantly with God, without a break, in constant prayer, fearing that
               he will be bereft of the current of its helping forces.</p>
            <p>All these beautiful things are born from a man's perceiving his own weakness. For
               from this, because of his longing for help, he turns to God with beseechings. And as
               he brings near his spirit unto God, He comes nigh unto him with His gifts. And He
               does not take away from him His inspiration, because of his great humility. For as a
               widow unto the judge, he cries at all times: avenge me on my adversary. Therefore
               God, the merciful, necessarily will delay his petitions, that he have the better
               reason to approach unto Him. And because of his need he will constantly remain at the
               fountain of help, while God grants some of his demands quickly, others not: [He
               grants] those concerning which He knows that they are necessary for life, the rest He
               delays. And in some cases He withholds from him the ardour of his enemies, and in
               others He gives an opening to temptations, that this, as I have said, <pb n="73"
               />should be a cause for approaching unto God, and that he should become prudent by
               temptations. And this is what is said in the scripture: The Lord left many peoples
               and He did not destroy them at once, nor did He give them into the hand of Joshua, in
               order to test Israel by them so that the generations of the children of Israel should
               learn war<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n73-1"/>.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="108"/>As for the righteous who is not acquainted with his
               weakness, all his affairs are in peril. He is not far from falling, the destroying
               lion is not removed from him nor the demon of haughtiness. Who lacks knowledge of his
               weakness, lacks humility. Who lacks humility, lacks perfection. Who lacks perfection
               is still in a state of peril. And the enemy can attack him at every quarter, because
               his town is not fortified with iron bolts nor with a brazen lintel.</p>
            <p>Neither is humility to be acquired except through the causes which bring about a
               continually broken heart and destroy the deliberations of presumption. Without
               humility the service of man cannot be sealed: the seal of the spirit has not yet been
               placed on the charter of his freedom, he is still a slave and his service cannot be
               established without his being made humble, neither can he acquire wisdom without
               temptations, neither can he reach humility without wisdom. Therefore God necessarily
               sends the saints things which cause humility and brokenness of heart and passionate
               prayer without distraction. Sometimes he afflicts them by accidents that arise from
               the natural affections or by transgressions arising from impure deliberations;
               sometimes by disdain or by idle oppressions which they have to endure from men, or by
               bodily pains; sometimes by poverty or need of necessary things; sometimes by vehement
               affections <pb type="external" n="109"/>of fear in the open war of the demons which
               He allows in order to keep them continually in motion, or by terrible varying states
               of which one is still more strong and sorrowful and hard than the other.</p>
            <p>All these things happen, that man should have a reason for being humble, lest he
               should sleep in neglect either of things present from which the struggler suffers, or
               of fear of things to be. Therefore temptations will necessarily be profitable unto
               men. Now I do not say, that, in order to have a cause of humility, he ought to let
               loose his will unto evil <pb n="74"/>things, with the purpose of humbling himself by
               the recollection of them, or that he should hasten unto other temptations. But it is
               beautiful for him that, apart from his performing good works, he should constantly
               spur himself and remember that he is a creature and naturally prone to be seduced.
               And whosoever is a creature, requires an external power, viz. to help him. And he who
               requires external help, the deficiency of his own nature is manifest. And every one
               who knows that he is deficient, to him humility is becoming in order to receive what
               he needs from Him who is able to give it.</p>
            <p>If he knows all these things from the beginning and looks to them at all times, he
               will not sleep. And if he does not sleep, he will not be delivered into the hand of
               the powers which endanger his vigilance. Therefore it is becoming for him <pb
                  type="external" n="110"/>that goes the way of God, that he confess and reproach
               and rebuke his soul for all [evils] that overtake him, knowing that either because of
               his negligence it is excited by the tempter by order of the Governor, or because he
               has exalted himself. Therefore he shall not leap up nor be shaken, but keep his soul
               quiet without accusation [of God], lest his evil be doubled. For there is not
               iniquity with God, on the contrary, He is the fountain of justice.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n71-1">Ps. 51,17</note>
            <note xml:id="n73-1">Cf. Judges 3,1 sq.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
