<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 19</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 19, pp. 105-109</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="19">
            <head>XIX</head>
            <p>On the revelations and powers which happen to saints in images</p>
            <p>The degree of revelation is not the same as that a man deepen his emotions by the
               study of wisdom and by intellectual labour so as to arrive at some understanding and
               contemplation <pb type="external" n="155"/>of anything by mental investigation. For
               it is said: Revelation is silence of intellect. And by zealous efforts and human
               thoughts no one can imagine that he has found knowledge; this happens by spiritual
               power so that he to whom the revelation is imparted, at that time is not aware of any
               thought of his soul nor of those things which present themselves to his senses;
               neither does he use them nor is he acquainted with them.</p>
            <p>This we do not assert on our own authority, but it can be proved sufficiently from
               the writings of the prophets, who, when revelations happened to them, did not
               perceive any of the usual things nor could they use their thoughts at will nor had
               they any sensual apperceptions, because they were in ecstasy. Their mind was wholly
               concentrated upon those things which appeared to them during the revelation. As it
               happened to the blessed Peter when he was hungry and ascended unto the roof in order
               to pray: when the revelation began, he did not perceive his hunger. Even the
               recollection of food was effaced from his mind, because he was in ecstasy, as
               scripture says<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n105-2"/>.</p>
            <p>Concerning all these things one may be well instructed in particulars from the
               writings of the blessed bishop Theodore, the light of the whole world<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n105-3"/>. For
               he speaks about the kind <pb n="106"/>and the rank of revelations, especially in the
               three volumes on <pb type="external" n="156"/>Genesis and in the two volumes on Job
               and in the last one about the Twelve Prophets, and in the commentaries on the Acts
               and the Gospel of Matthew.</p>
            <p>Scripture mentions six kinds of revelations. The first: that by the senses. The
               second: by psychic sight. The third: by rapture<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n106-1"/> of the spirit. The fourth:
               by the rank of prophecy. The fifth: in some intellectual way. The sixth: as it were
               by a dream.</p>
            <p>Revelations by the senses are divided into two different kinds: those which take
               place by means of the elements and those which take place without matter. Examples of
               the former kind are the revelation in the thornbush, in the cloud, in the tables and
               so on, things which were also seen by the people; also those wondrous things which
               every day happen in the whole world and the causes and details of which are gained by
               the saints in revelations; and also the works and deeds and things which are hidden
               or far away, yet are revealed unto some at the time of their actual occurence.</p>
            <p>Without matter: as for instance the men that appeared unto Abraham, the ladder of
               Jacob, the revelation about the tabernacle (try only to look at and to act with the
               likeness that appeared unto thee on the mountain, and so on), the divine light of
               exalted rays that shone for Paul on the way and blinded his eyes. It is well known
               that, though a revelation, it was visible and perceptible by the senses, so that also
               those who were with him saw and heard it; yet it was not a material revelation, nor a
               natural and elementary light, as the <pb type="external" n="157"/>blessed commentator
               denotes in his commentary on the story in the Acts: And those who went on the way
               with Paul, stood in amazement while they heard the voice, yet did not see anyone. He
               comments on the words, in amazement thus: In silence without [uttering] a word, also
               seized with doubt, because they had caught the voice that had spoken to him and, as
               far as it was possible for them, had seen the light that appeared unto him. Lest it
               should be surmised later that Saul had invented what had happened and that which had
               been wrought unto him, while none of those who were with him had heard or seen it.
               But they did not see anyone. For <pb n="107"/>they did not see Jesus, because, as I
               have said, that which appeared was even no sensible light, but an incomprehensible
               apperception which in an immaterial way was given him by divine action in the
               likeness of a vision of light, so that he thought that the heavens were opened and so
               on. — These are the revelations which have taken place through the medium of the
               bodily senses. They are exalted above any commixture with the elements or any of the
               sensible and human events.</p>
            <p>But those who receive these revelations are not enveloped in ecstasy of mind, as in
               the case of the revelation that takes place through the eyes of the soul in the
               vision of the soul, as: I saw the Lord sitting on a high throne and Seraphs each with
               six wings round it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n107-1"/>, and as in the revelation unto Ezekiel, in the revelation
               of the wheels and the amazing images, and the sound from the wheels resembling the
               sound of the <pb type="external" n="158"/>sea, and the glorifications heard from the
               Cherubs with many eyes, which say: Blessed is the majesty of the Lord in His place.
               How much subtler these revelations are than those of the first mentioned class, is
               known to the illuminated. [To the second class also belongs] for instance the vessel
               that appeared to Peter and the animals in it, with the other things described. And he
               who wishes, may recognize these things from the scriptures.</p>
            <p>Rapture of the spirit, as for instance when he was taken up unto the third heaven,
               and whether this was in the body or without, I do not know. But he was taken to
               Paradise and heard unspeakable words, which it is not lawful for a man to
               utter<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n107-2"/>.</p>
            <p>Prophecy, as for instance the things that happened unto the Prophets, who foretold
               future events, many ages before they took place, as it was also given unto Balaam the
               sorcerer to foretell many things through the spirit of prophecy, things even more
               numerous than what prophets had prophesied.</p>
            <p>In some intellectual way. As for instance the blessed Paul says: I pray that you may
               be filled with the knowledge of God in all wisdom and spiritual
               understanding<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n107-3"/>. And: May the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of
               glory, give unto you the spirit of wisdom and revelation in the knowledge <pb n="108"
               />of Him: the eyes of your hearts being enlightened; that ye may know what is the
               hope of His calling, and the riches of His glory in the saints, and the exceeding
               greatness of His power in us who believe<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108-1"/> and the other things which were
               given to the Apostle in a revelation of knowledge concerning <pb type="external"
                  n="159"/>the things of the world to be, and the order of resurrection and the
               alteration of human bodies and so on. And as for the degree of exalted understanding
               and the knowledge of the divine nature, as for instance that [man] is the likeness of
               the invisible God and that with His hand He has made the worlds, God has given us
               revelation by His spirit. Again we know in part and we understand in part<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108-2"/>;
               and: In the beginning was the word<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108-3"/>; and: Thou art the Christ, the son of the
               living God<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108-4"/>; and so on. Again, unsearchable are His judgments, and His ways
               past finding out<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108-5"/>; and: He who worketh all after the counsel of His own
               will<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108-6"/>; and: God hath concluded them all in unbelief, that He might have mercy
               upon all<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108-7"/> and so on.</p>
            <p>These are designations of the insight which was given unto them that they sought to
               know and understand through the Spirit the divine nature.</p>
            <p>By dreams, as for instance happened to Abimelek and Joseph and Pharao and
               Nebukednesar; and when the angel of the Lord appeared in a dream to Joseph the
               husband of Mary, and so on.</p>
            <p>Also this it is necessary to know: that all revelations, which God has granted for
               the sake of teaching mankind and instructing them concerning things, take place by
               means of images, especially revelations unto those who are of simple understanding
               and of small insight in the truth. But those which are destined to comfort and to
               instruct some person, and to console to <pb type="external" n="160"/>some extent and
               to instruct a single person, take place without images and by intelligible
               apperception. This is clearly proved by the blessed commentator<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n108-8"/> in the
               second volume on Job. For how much greater, as compared with other revelations, are
               the things which are given in a revelation for the intellect and the understanding
               through an intellectual medium and how much higher are the mysteries which serve to
               instruct all concerning God. This is perfection of knowledge.</p>
            <pb n="109"/>
            <p>And also this it is becoming to know: Revelation and [divine] action are different
               from truth and knowledge in so far as revelation is not the exact truth, but only
               shows indications and signs corresponding to human strength. Neither may the action
               and the wondrous things in those revelations be called knowledge and truth. They are
               called inspiration caused by [divine] action. So that it is impossible to gain from
               them instruction concerning God's foreknowledge or His incomprehensible nature or His
               different qualities or the understanding of the mysteries of His will concerning
               mankind and the other things which are to be attained by sound knowledge concerning
               Him. Therefore: the mysteries which are attained by the intellect through insight
               into the divine nature is different from the action by which the mind is inspired
               during a certain time. Therefore it is not absolutely necessary that every one to
               whom a revelation is imparted or who is influenced by a consoling action, must know
               the truth and the exact knowledge <pb type="external" n="161"/>concerning God. For
               many are those to whom such things were imparted, yet knew God as children only.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n105-2">Acts 10,10</note>
            <note xml:id="n105-3">Theodore bishop of Mopsuestia</note>
            <note xml:id="n106-1">ܚܛܘܦܝܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n107-1">Isaiah 6,1</note>
            <note xml:id="n107-2">2 Cor. 12,2-4</note>
            <note xml:id="n107-3">Colossians 1,9</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-1">Ephesians 1,17-19</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-2">1 Corinthians 13,12</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-3">John 1,1</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-4">Matthew 16,16</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-5">Romans 11,33</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-6">Ephesians 1,11</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-7">Romans 11,32</note>
            <note xml:id="n108-8">Theodore</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
