<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 70</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 70, pp. 324-327.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="70">
            <pb n="324"/>
            <head>LXX</head>
            <p>That we can understand the degree of our behaviour by the varying states of our mind
               without childishly judging by the many distinctions of our labours only that we
               should recognise the degree of our soul as sages by the joy which day by day is
               secretly perceived in it. The subtle order of initiated knowledge</p>
            <p>Examine thyself constantly, my beloved, and pay attention to the steadiness of thy
               labours, and the troubles assailing thee, thy lonely dwellingplace, the subtlety of
               thy mind and the keenness of thy knowledge, the long period of thy solitude, and the
               frequent drogues of temptations that are continually administered by the true
               physician in order to heal the inner man; sometimes however by the demons. Sometimes
               they come through illnesses and bodily sufferings, sometimes through the terrors of
               the emotions of thy soul when it thinks of the woes which will come in the end.
               Sometimes through <pb type="external" n="484"/>the tenderness and fostering of grace
               there will arise warmth and sweet tears and spiritual joy and all the other things,
               to be short.</p>
            <p>Doest thou see with certainty through all these that thy wounds are going to be
               healed, that is — that the affections begin to grow weak? Put up a mark and enter
               into thyself continually and see which of the affections have become weak before
               thee; which of them have reached their end and are altogether finished; which of them
               are beginning to become silent in the health of thy soul, and not by the departure of
               emotional influences; through the maturity of the mind and not for lack of
               causes.</p>
            <p>Doest thou now see perfectly — as thou observest that living flesh, which is peace of
               the soul, is going to cover thy open wound — which of the affections continually
               trouble thee, and which from time to time; and which are bodily, which are psychic,
               and which of a mixed nature; and whether they stir darkly, as being ill by
               recollections, or they assail the <pb n="325"/>soul vehemently; whether they
               consequently behave stealthily or imperiously; and how king mind, the governor of the
               senses, looks at them when they knock at the door; whether it combates and vanquishes
               them by its force, or even does not look at them or think of them; and which of them
               are the remnants of old ones, and which have been newly formed; and whether the
               affections stir through representations, or by apperception without any
               representation; whether there is recollection without affections, and emotion without
               allurements.</p>
            <p>By these [symptoms] it is possible to recognize the degree which the soul occupies.
               If the first mentioned alternative is to be affirmed (though it does not prevail),
               this shows that <pb type="external" n="485"/>there is still strife in the soul though
               it is strong against [the contrary powers]. If the second mentioned alternative is to
               be affirmed, it almost proves that, as scripture says, David sat in his house and the
               Lord had given him rest round about from all his [enemies]<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n325-1"/>.</p>
            <p>These things are not to be connected with one affection, but with the natural
               affections of desire and love also, as also with the affection of love of glory,
               which forms images and phantasies and allurements. And the affection of the love of
               money — when the soul participates of it secretly, though it is not persuaded to
               commit any action thereby — forms in the mind images of things connected with the
               love of money in the examples of wealth-gathering, and it induces the soul to think
               of them and it excites the desire of possessing them, and so on.</p>
            <p>Not all affections combat man by allurements. For some of them burden the soul with
               troubles only. Dejection and despondency and distress do not bring allurements nor
               comfort, but only burden the soul with heaviness. The readiness of the soul is
               demonstrated by a victory fought against those forces which make use of allurements
               in the struggle.</p>
            <p>For a man ought to possess all these, namely subtle knowledge and signs, in order
               that he may perceive, at every step he takes, how far he is gone and in which country
               his soul has begun to walk, in the land of Kanaan or beyond the Jordan.</p>
            <p>Consider also this: whether the soul, through its illumination, possesses sufficient
               knowledge for these distinctions; or distinguishes them dimly, or is wholly destitute
               of such distinctive <pb n="326"/><pb type="external" n="486"/>faculties. Doest thou
               find with absolute certainty, that the deliberations have begun to become clear? Does
               distraction desist from the intellect at the time of prayer? Which affection troubles
               thee when the mind approaches unto prayer? Doest thou perceive that the power of
               solitude envelops the soul with the quiet and the unusual peace which it engenders in
               the mind? Is the mind continually snatched away spontaneously, by immaterial
               emotions, towards those things which it is not allowed to interpret to the senses?
               Does there suddenly blaze in them joy which makes the tongue silent by its
               incomparable delight? Does there constantly flow from the heart some enjoyment which
               envelops the whole being in rapture, without thy perceiving it? Is sometimes thy
               whole body possessed by some delight and joy, which no fleshly tongue can express, so
               that thou esteemest all earthly things as ashes and dung, even when thou recollectest
               them?</p>
            <p>The first happens sometimes at the time of prayer, sometimes during the recitation;
               sometimes when through constant and prolonged meditation the spirit has become
               meditative and the mind fervent.</p>
            <p>The second usually happens without these. Often during fortuitous works, usually
               however during the night and on purpose, between sleeping and waking, sleeping though
               not sleeping and waking though not waking. And the delight which flows through the
               whole body is esteemed so high at that time, that it seems as if the kingdom of
               heaven were nothing else but this.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="487"/>And further consider this: if the soul possesses the
               strength to reject recollections of apperceptible things by the strength of the hope
               which reigns over the heart and makes strong the inner senses by an unfathomable
               conviction; and if the heart has acquired, without forethought, the habit of being
               captured so that it does no longer [perceive] earthly things, through continual
               intercourse with our Saviour, and thou possessest knowledge so as to distinguish the
               different designations of this intercourse, when thou nearest them — solitude
               cultivated without interruption will make it easy to the soul to acquire the taste of
               these.</p>
            <p>They disappear however, after having been present, through the neglect of those who
               have received them, and for a long time they do not reappear.</p>
            <pb n="327"/>
            <p>On account of these, man ventures to adduce with confidence the testimony of his own
               mind; so the blessed Paul says: For I am persuaded that neither death, nor life, nor
               things present, nor things to come, nor any other thing shall be able to separate me
               from the love of Christ<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n327-1"/>. Then should bodily and psychic trouble, or
               persecution or hunger, or nakedness or loneliness, or captivity or danger or the
               sword? No, not even the angels of Satan, nor his powers with their evil cunning; nor
               glory which makes efforts by its alluring flatteries; nor oppressions and scorn by
               their vain blows.</p>
            <p>If these things, my brother, to a larger or lesser extent have not begun to show
               themselves in thy soul, thy labours and troubles and all thy solitude are vain
               efforts. And even <pb type="external" n="488"/>if miracles were wrought by thy hands
               and thou shouldst quicken the dead, this would be, nothing in comparison with the
               absence of these. And it is becoming that thou arousest thy self and with tears
               beseechest the Saviour of the world that He may take away the veil from the heart,
               and disperse from the inner firmament the darkness of the clouds of the affections;
               and that thou mayest be deemed worthy of seeing the rays of daylight.</p>
            <p>Then thou wilt not dwell in darkness as one who is dead for ever. Continual vigils
               with recitation and frequent kneelings performed between, will not fail one day to
               give this good to him that is diligent. For those that have found them, have found
               them through these works. And those who will find them, will be able to do so through
               these works.</p>
            <p>And while we are constantly abiding in solitude, performing these works, and the mind
               is not bound by any thing or any man without the soul, then by the works of inward
               excellence we shall soon find in ourselves a partial, but veracious apperception of
               them and we shall acquire certainty also concerning the rest. Those who, while
               abiding in solitude, have experienced God's lovingkindness, do not need much
               persuasion. Nor is their soul sick by the affection of unbelief as those who doubt
               the truth. The witness of their mind is for them sufficient persuasion, more than
               myriads of words not founded on experience.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n325-1">2 Sam. 7,1</note>
            <note xml:id="n327-1">Cf. Rom. 8,38</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
