<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 64</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 64, pp. 296-297.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="64">
            <pb n="296"/>
            <head>LXIV</head>
            <p>On the many varying states which cling to the mind and are purified by prayer</p>
            <p>To choose what is good, is the part of the good will of him that desires this. To
               accomplish the choice of the excellent will, this belongs to God and it requires much
               help on His part. Therefore we have to combine the good desire which is awakened in
               us, with continual prayer. Not only in order to ask from Him help, but also to
               discriminate whether it concords with His will or not. Not every beautiful desire
               falls into the heart by divine action, but [only] that which is profitable. There are
               beautiful things which man may desire though they do not help him. Such desires may
               even be sent by Satan, even though they be esteemed to be helpful. How many times
               does the thing desired not fit his measure; and <pb type="external" n="442"/>Satan
               has contrived it to his detriment, compelling him to ask it, though he has not yet
               reached this [stage of] discipline or though he is a stranger to the rank of its
               scheme; or the time is not fit in which Satan incites him to accomplish these things;
               or he is not able to perform them, either through [lack of] knowledge, or through
               bodily weakness, or through the time not being favorable. At any rate, though it does
               seem beautiful, it either troubles him, or it causes him bodily harm, or it places a
               hidden snare in his mind.</p>
            <p>So, as I have said, we have to combine continual and diligent prayer with
               <choice><sic>theseemingly</sic><corr>the seemingly</corr></choice> good desire which is awakened in us, saying, every one
               of us: May it be Thy will regarding me, to accomplish in fact this good which I have
               <choice><sic>choosen</sic><corr>chosen</corr></choice> and which I desire to practise, if it concords with Thy will. To
               fix my will on it, is easy to me; to practise it, is however not possible for me
               without a gift on Thy part. Though in truth both are thine, to will and to
               do[#n296-1]. For it is not without Thy grace that I have surrendered to or been
               shaken before that which stirred in me. It is the custom of him that desires any good
               thing with discrimination of mind, to work for it in <pb n="297"/>prayer continually;
               and the force [he acquires] thereby, he will use as an aid for his service. And then
               wisdom which distinguishes truth from falsehood through much prayer and labour and
               watchfulness and beautiful longing without break, will come to light, in continual
               tears, humbleness and heavenly help, especially when its opponents are deliberations
               of haughtiness which remove from us God's help, and which we can annihilate by
               prayer.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n296-1">Cf. Philippians 2, 13</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
