<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 40</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 40, pp. 202-204.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="40">
            <head>XL</head>
            <p>Exposition concerning the degrees of the path, namely concerning the power of
               ministration of each of them</p>
            <p>Bodily discipline in solitude purifies the body from the material elements in it.
               Mental discipline makes the soul humble and purifies it from the material impulses
               that tend towards decaying things, by changing their affectible nature into motions
               of contemplation. And this will bring the soul near to the nakedness of the mind that
               is called immaterial contemplation; this is spiritual discipline. It elevates the
               intellect above earthly things and brings it near to primordial spiritual
               contemplation; it directs the intellect towards God by the sight of unspeakable glory
               and it delights spiritually in the hope of future things, [thinking of] what and how
               each of them will be<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n202-1"/>.</p>
            <p>Bodily labours are called bodily discipline unto God. For <pb type="external" n="304"
               />they serve for the purification of the body through the service of excellence which
               is manifest personal works, by which man is purified from the pus of the flesh.
               Mental discipline is labour of the heart. It is the thinking, without cessation, of
               the great coming judgment, in constant prayer of the heart, and of God's providence
               and care for this world in its individuals and in its <pb n="203"/>species. This is
               also the regarding of the domain of the inner affections, lest any of them pass into
               the hidden and spiritual place. This is the labour of the heart which is called
               mental discipline.</p>
            <p>By this labour of discipline, which is called psychic service, the heart is
               subtilized and torn away from participation in decay, viz. in the praeternatural
               affections; from here onwards the heart begins to be often set in emotion by insight
               into the things of the senses which were created to the purpose of the education of
               the body and which administer strength to the four elements which are in the
               body.</p>
            <p>Spiritual discipline is service without the senses; this is what has been written by
               the Fathers, that when the mind of the saints was gifted with personal contemplation,
               then the heaviness of body was taken away. And further on sight will be spiritual
               sight.</p>
            <p>Personal contemplation he uses in the sense of contemplation concerning the
               primordial creation of nature. From there one is easily moved onwards toward what is
               called solitary knowledge which is, according to a clear interpretation, ecstasy in
               God, this is the order of that high future state which will be given in freedom that
               lives in immortality, in that way of life <pb type="external" n="305"/>which will be
               after the resurrection. It will consist therein, that from that point onwards human
               nature will not be cut off from constant ecstasy in God, to mingle itself with any
               created being. If there were any other thing equal to Him, nature would sometimes
               follow Him, sometimes His equals. When, however, the beauty of all which exists in
               that future order of things, is inferior to His beauties, how should it be possible
               for the mind not to fix its gaze exclusively on Him? What then? Should mortality
               trouble it, or the heaviness of the flesh, or the remembrance of kindred, or natural
               wants, or the adversities which overtake it; or the distraction of ignorance, or the
               deficiency of nature, or the distraction caused by the elements, or intercourse with
               one another, or the influence of dejection, or the weariness of the flesh? If now in
               this world — while all these things are thus — the veil of the affections is
               sometimes withdrawn from before the eyes of the spirit so that it gazes at the glory,
               and the mind is drawn away in ecstasy — then, without doubt, if God had not limited
               the duration of these moments in this life, man would not come back from that <pb
                  n="204"/>state<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n204-1"/> his whole life, if he were allowed. Now when all these
               [earthly] things exist no longer and that endless order [has been established], and
               when we personally and practically abide in the habitations of the kingdom — if our
               behaviour be worthy — how then should the spirit find a way to remove itself from the
               wondrous sight of God and to dwell with any other? Woe <pb type="external" n="306"
               />to us, who do not know for what state we are destined, reckoning as something this
               life of sickness and this animal state, and the world with its troubles and evils and
               pleasures.</p>
            <p>O Christ, who art the only strong one, blessed is the man whom thou supportest and in
               whose heart are the steps towards thee. Turn thou, o Lord, our face away from the
               world by desire of Thee, so that we see it as it is, without taking shadows for
               truth. Throw, o Lord, zeal into our heart before death comes, that at the time of our
               departure we may know for what purpose our entrance in and our departure from this
               world have served. Then, fulfilling the work to which we were called in accordance
               with thy aim in placing us in this life first, we shall hope, with a mind full of
               confidence, to receive the great things which, according to the promises of the
               scriptures, in the second creation are prepared by Thy love, things the recollection
               of which we preserve with mystic faith.</p>
            <p>Bodily purity is to be clean from filth. Psychic purity is to be free from hidden
               affections in the spirit. Purity of mind is to be purified by revelations from any
               emotion unto things which, in view of their material nature, lie in the domain of the
               senses. Children are pure in body and as to their soul they can be without
               affections. Yet no one will call them pure in mind. Purity of mind is perfection
               through training in <pb type="external" n="307"/>heavenly contemplation, so that the
               mind without the senses receives impulses from the spiritual powers of those worlds
               above, powers which are amazing, surpassing number, distinguished in demeanour,
               mingled in invisible service, subject to many variations at all times, on account of
               the motion of the divine revelations.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n202-1"> The Greek translation has the right division of the text
               here</note>
            <note xml:id="n204-1"><choice><sic>Litt.</sic><corr>Lit.</corr></choice> from there. Cf. Plotinus, Enneades, VI, 9 § 9</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
