<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 72</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 72, pp. 332-337.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="72">
            <pb n="332"/>
            <head>LXXII</head>
            <head>On true knowledge and on temptations and that it is becoming to know exactly that not
               only weak and insignificant and uneducated people but also those who have been deemed
               worthy of temporary apathy and have reached perfection of mind and have approached
               partial purity as far as this is compatible with mortality and have gained exaltation
               above affections — in so far as in this world it is allowed by God in combination
               with life in affectible flesh — have to struggle and are injured by the affections
               because of the body and that to them also are continually permitted [temptations] in
               mercy because of the danger of haughtiness in some degree and that many times they
               transgress and heal themselves by repentance grace accepting them again</head>
            <p>That every rational nature is liable to deviation without distinction and that
               varying states pass through all men at all times, the discriminate is able to
               understand from many [symptoms]; moreover the experiences of each day are wholly
               sufficient to make him prudent if he is cautious and keeps to what is his domain.
               [They also show him] how many varying <pb type="external" n="495"/>states of rest and
               unrest work upon the mind every day, so that it suddenly passes from peace to
               perturbation without any reason from anywhere and falls into unspeakable danger. Even
               this is clearly described by the blessed <persName>Macarius</persName>, with great care and devotion, in
               order to remind and <choice><sic>instinct</sic><corr>instruct</corr></choice> the brethren, lest those who stand in the
               degree of purity give way to despair at the time of contrary states, when there
               happens to them an accidental [state] like [a change in] air, provided that this is
               not due to neglect and relaxation, but that these circumstances contrary to the scope
               of their mind, happen to them while they are walking in their path.</p>
            <pb n="333"/>
            <p>And also the blessed <persName>Euagrius</persName> witnessing to this through real experience, has
               committed it to writing, for the sake of ampler confirmation, as it were lest any one
               should think that the blessed <persName>Macarius</persName> wrote this in his letter fortuitously without
               having examined his words carefully. Thus then by reason of two veracious witnesses
               like these, the mind may accept, without doubt, its consolation at the time of
               need.</p>
            <p>What then? Varying states happen to every man, like [changes of] the air. Understand
               it: to every man; for nature is one. Do not think that he is speaking to
               insignificant men only and that the perfect should be exempt from varying states and
               that they stay in one class, without liability of deviation and without the impulse
               of the affections, as the Meṣalleyānē say. Therefore he says: unto every man.</p>
            <p>How is this, o blessed man? He says: there are states of <pb type="external" n="496"
               />cold, and soon after states of heat; and perhaps of hail, and soon there-after of
               serenity. It is thus for our instruction: strife, then the help of grace. And
               sometimes the soul runs into a storm and heavy billows assail it; then there comes a
               different state and it is visited by grace; then joy fills the heart and peace from
               God and chaste, peaceful deliberations. Grace makes dawn here chaste deliberations on
               the bestiality and impurity of those whom it had ordered away.</p>
            <p>Therefore he warns, saying that after these chaste and peaceful deliberations,
               accidents will befall the mind, that we should not be sorry or despair; or at the
               time of rest caused by grace, be puffed up, but that, at the time of joy, we should
               look at trouble. He says that we should not be sorry when accidents happen; not that
               we should not resist them, nor that the mind should accept them joyfully as something
               natural belonging to us, but that thou shouldst not despair even as the man who
               expected what is exalted above strife, and perfect rest without varying states and
               without struggles and blows, and freedom from the impulse of any adversity — the
               which it has not pleased our Lord God to give to our nature in this world so that we
               should entirely desist from labours and in consequence of this thought thou shouldst
               be relaxed by despondency and desist from thy course.</p>
            <p>But know that all the saints have to face this labour as long as we are in this
               world, though we have ample <pb type="external" n="497"/>consolation for it in
               secret. For every day and at all times it is <pb n="334"/>demanded of us that we give
               proof of our love unto God by the struggle against temptations. And therefore we
               should not be sorry; namely, we should not be dejected in our struggle but thus is
               our way prepared. 'For he that deviates from this method, becomes a prey of the
               wolves'. Admirable is that saint, who with a small word confirmed this section that
               is loaded with significance and absolutely took doubt away from the mind of the
               reader. 'For he that deviates from this method, becomes a prey of the wolves'. This
               means that he, that possesses this intention and is minded to walk out of the way,
               wishing to go in loneliness a way that has not been trodden by the Fathers, is
               through this in danger of becoming the prey of old wolves who are clad in lambs'
               clothes in order stealthily to turn back foolish souls to their evil under the
               pretence of truth. That at the time of joy we should look at trouble, means: when by
               the influence of grace, suddenly mighty emotions and amazement of the intellectual
               vision of what is above nature, fall on the soul; as the holy <persName>Euagrius</persName> says: when the
               holy angels approach us filling us with spiritual sight, and all those who were in
               opposition to us vanish, and there comes peace and unspeakable stupefaction; when
               thou art in this state; when grace envelops thee, and the holy angels are near and
               around thee and, therefore, all those who tried thee, have withdrawn from thee, then
               do not <pb type="external" n="498"/>extol thyself and do not think that thou hast
               reached now the undisturbable harbour and the unchangeable air and that thou art
               altogether exalted above this bay and the contrary storms and that there is no fiend
               and no evil accidents. For there were many who have thought thus and have fallen into
               danger, as <persName>Euagrius</persName> says, namely: the danger of thinking that thou art greater than
               many others, and that thou deservest these [spiritual distinctions] and that others,
               on account of their insufficient knowledge, are destitute of the like; but I possess
               [those distinctions] duly, and therefore I have reached perfect chastity and the
               degree of spirituality, and definite renovation.</p>
            <p>On the other hand recollect the impure deliberations and the unclear images which
               printed themselves in thy mind in the winterperiod, and the
               <choice><sic>disturbancies</sic><corr>disturbances</corr></choice> and the disordered deliberations which assailed thee
               shortly before, during that gloomy darkness; and how easily thou deviatedst towards
               the <pb n="335"/>affections and hadst intercourse with them, when thy mind was
               troubled, without being ashamed before the divine sight and on account of the gifts
               and presents thou hadst received.</p>
            <p>And know that all this was brought upon thee, in order to humble thee, by the care of
               God, which provides for every one of us as is profitable to him. But when thou
               exaltest thyself on account of its gifts, it leaves thee, and thou wilt wholly
               relapse into the practice of those things by which thou wert tried in thy
               thoughts.</p>
            <p>Know, therefore, that the fact that thou art standing, is not due to thee nor to thy
               excellence; but that it is grace which <pb type="external" n="499"/>bears thee on its
               handpalms so that thou art not moved.</p>
            <p>These things thou hast to recollect at the time of joy, when thy deliberation exalts
               itself, says our holy Father, and then thou hast to weep and shed tears. And humble
               thyself at the recollection of thy transgressions committed when [temptations were]
               admitted to thee; perhaps thou wilt be saved by acquiring humility through them. Be
               not, however, dejected, but expiate thy sins by deliberations of humility. Humility,
               even without labours, expiates many sins. Labours without humility on the contrary,
               are not only destitute of profit, but cause us many evils. Therefore, expiate thy
               sins, by humility, as I have said. As salt is to all kinds of meat, so is humility to
               all virtues. The force of many sins is able to break this. Therefore it is necessary
               for the mind to suffer continually by humiliation and by pain borne with discernment.
               If we possess this, it makes us a son of God; even without service, it allows us to
               stand before God rich in virtues. Without it, every service and every virtue and all
               labours are vain.</p>
            <p>Therefore God demands the alteration of the mind. By the mind we acquire improvement
               and by the mind we become despicable. So this alone is sufficient, without [any
               further] help, to stand before God and to speak in our behalf.</p>
            <p>Thank God without break on account of the fact that, notwithstanding thy so weak and
               easily deviating nature, from time to time thou art lifted up by the aid of grace to
               such a height and to such gifts and remember in which sphere <pb type="external"
                  n="500"/>thou then art — above thy nature, and how when [temptations] are admitted
               to thee, thou art brought low and possessest a brutish mind. And recollect the
               wretchedness of thy <pb n="336"/>nature and how easily thou becomest subject to
               varying states, as also one of the saintly Fathers has said: When thou art assailed
               by the deliberation of haughtiness which desires to enumerate thy virtues, then say:
               Father, look at thy fornication. He means the fornication by which the deliberations
               are tried at the time of the admittance [of temptations] and with which man is
               provided by grace, be it as a means of strife or as a means of help, according to the
               degree in which grace helps us. Seest thou how clearly this admirable Father explains
               the matter? 'When thou art approached by the deliberation of haughtiness, because of
               the elevation of thy behaviour, then say: Father, look at thy fornication!' It is
               manifest that this Father was speaking to a great one, because it is impossible that
               deliberations of haughtiness should assail other people than those who occupy a high
               degree and are behaving in a praiseworthy way. For this affection attacks the soul
               when virtue has been exercised, in order to bereave it of its performance.</p>
            <p>Also from one of the letters of <persName>Macarius</persName> thou canst learn, if thou desirest, which
               degrees those saints occupy unto whom temptations are admitted. That letter was
               written by <persName>Macarius</persName> to all his beloved sons, showing clearly how struggles and the
               help of grace are provided by God, through which it has pleased His wisdom to train
               them as long as they abide in <pb type="external" n="501"/>this life, struggling
               against sin, in behalf of excellence. This He does in order that at all times their
               looks may be fixed upon Him and that, by continually looking at Him, His holy love
               may be augmented in them. So that, when they seek continually refuge with Him against
               the ardour of the affections and the fear of deviations, they are confirmed in faith,
               hope and love.</p>
            <p>So these things are not said to those who continually are in contact with men and
               wander about everywhere, participating in impure actions and passions [and living] in
               a state of relaxation. Nor are they said to those who perform righteousness in works
               which have nothing to do with solitude and who at every moment are captured by the
               senses, and who at all times are in danger of falling on account of the compulsion
               exercised on them by the things which happen to them involuntarily, through
               circumstances which they have not foreseen, so that they are unable to guard
               completely not <pb n="337"/>only their deliberation but even their senses. But they
               are destined for those who by the great watchfulness with which they guard their
               bodies and their deliberations, keep altogether aloof from the perturbations and
               conversations of men, and who by having given up all, even their soul, are able to
               guard their mind in prayer and to receive various provisions from grace, in perfect
               solitude. And under the arm of the knowledge of the Lord they are brought up and
               secretly made wise by the spirit, while they have rest from works and the sight of
               things and possess a mind dead to the world. The affections do not die; but
               intercourse [with them] dies, because they keep aloof from things and because they
               are helped by grace.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
