<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 59</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 59, pp. 278-281.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="59">
            <pb n="278"/>
            <head>LIX</head>
            <head>A profitable discourse</head>
            <p>True is the word of our Lord who has said that no one can possess love of God side by
               side with love of the world; nor mingle with the world and with God, nor care for the
               world and care for God. Apart from all that is connected with vain glory, many of us
               generally deviate because of bodily want, we who have promised to serve the kingdom
               of heaven but who do not remember the promise of our Lord who has said: If ye bestow
               all your care upon the <pb type="external" n="415"/>kingdom of heaven, I shall not
               leave you in want of the needs of sensible nature; but these things will come to you
               spontaneously before ye think of their use at the time of want, although I do not
               even let you want because of care for them.</p>
            <p>Upon the soulless fowls which have been created in your behalf, God bestows care; and
               should He neglect you that care for righteousness? To him that cares for spiritual
               things, even partially, bodily things are prepared even when he does not provide for
               them, in accordance with their necessity and in their time.</p>
            <p>He that shows care for the last named things more than is becoming, will fall from
               God, even involuntarily. While we bestow care upon things connected with the name of
               our Lord, He will provide us with both kinds, in accordance with the measure of our
               care and the importance of the want of each of them. We should however not ask God's
               care in these bodily things for ourselves as a remuneration for our labours, but we
               should direct our whole service towards the future hope. For he that once has given
               himself to excellence with the love of his soul and longs after its service with his
               whole being, does not think of looking after bodily things, whether they are or are
               not. How many times does God allow the friends of excellence to be tempted by such
               things! And not only this; but He even allows many evil things to assail them from
               all sides; and He smites their body, as in the case of <pb type="external" n="416"
               /><persName>Job</persName>, and gives poverty entrance to them <choice><sic>an</sic><corr>and</corr></choice> lets them be deprived of their
               human state, and smites them in all that <pb n="279"/>they possess, with this
               restriction only, that the plague should not attain to their life.</p>
            <p>It is not possible that we should walk in the way of righteousness and that no
               troubles should hurt us, nor that the body should not suffer illness and pains, nor
               that we should remain without varying states, if we really desire to live in
               excellence. That however a man should wilfully kill or injure himself or harm himself
               in any way, is a cause of damnation. If he walks in the way of righteousness and
               follows his course towards God, together with many of his fellows, and one of these
               things should hurt him on his way, it is not becoming for him to deviate; but he
               shall accept them joyfully without scrutiny, thanking God because He has given him
               His gift, God for whose sake he has been deemed worthy to be entangled in temptations
               so as to become associated with the sufferings of prophets and apostles and the other
               saints who have endured troubles on behalf of the way of God; [thanking God] because
               He has deemed him worthy to bear afflictions for the way of excellence, even though
               they should happen through men, or through the demons or through the body.</p>
            <p>These things are not permitted without the divine will, but they happen in order that
               thou mayest have a cause of righteousness. For it is not possible that God should
               give the opportunity of becoming excellent to him that desires to be with Him,
               otherwise than by bringing him into contact with temptations for the sake of
               truth.</p>
            <p>That a man himself is not able to become worthy of such <pb type="external" n="417"
               />a greatness that he should be led into temptations in behalf of these divine things
               with joy, but only by a gift from Christ, is witnessed by the blessed apostle. For so
               great is this thing, that he openly calls it a gift that a man for the sake of the
               hope in God should be prepared to suffer by faith, saying: For unto you it is given
               from God, not only to believe in Christ, but also to suffer for his
               sake<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n279-1"/>.</p>
            <p>Then thank without a break Him that has delivered you from the dominion of the
               darkness of the world and has brought you near the kingdom of His son, and has made
               you fellows of all the children of light who have suffered for the sake of God, in
               order that you may gain the part that has fallen to <pb n="280"/>the lot of the
               saints in the light. And this is what <persName>Peter</persName> writes in his epistle: But if ye suffer
               for righteousness' sake, happy are ye<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n280-1"/>. For you will have a share in Christ's
               suffering. Therefore, when thou art free from affliction, do not leap up with joy,
               nor when circumstances assail thee cover thy face with sadness, reckoning this as
               something foreign to the way of God.</p>
            <p>Behold, for years and generations, the way of God has been leveled by the cross and
               by death. How is this with thee, that thou seest the afflictions of the way as if
               they were out of the way? Doest not thou wish to follow the steps of the saints? Or
               doest thou wish to go a way which is especially <pb type="external" n="418"/>for
               thee, without suffering? The way unto God is a daily cross. No one can ascend unto
               heaven with comfort, we know where the way of comfort leads.</p>
            <p>If any one trusts himself with his whole heart to God, God never wishes to take care
               away from him, namely care for the sake of truth. But thereby he knows that he is
               guided by God, when He continually sends him afflictions. But those who are guided
               under afflictions, are never allowed by divine care to fall into the hands of the
               demons, especially when they kiss the feet of the brethren and hide and cover their
               shortcomings as if they were their own.</p>
            <p>He that wishes to be without care in the world yet guided by excellence, loathes this
               way. As the blessed commentator says in his interpretation of <persName>Matthew</persName>: For those who
               long after excellence, it is not possible to flee from afflictions. For afflictions
               will necessarily increase to the same measure as the soul fights against contrary
               powers. But when afflictions leave it, the soul in the first place leaves what
               belongs to it.</p>
            <p>He that says that he is without care, yet is guided by excellence, does not even know
               whence excellence is born in the soul. For we know what are the governors of
               excellence. By temptations the gate of heaven is opened before the soul. Our Fathers
               have guided us in this way. God who gives unto His saints victory in strife so that
               their deliberations are not turned away from the future hope, will guard and help us
               by their prayers. Amen.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="419"/>The righteous not only excel in beautiful works by their
               will but even in involuntary temptations they excel greatly by <pb n="281"/>their
               tried patience, because they valiantly endure all earthly troubles, expecting the
               amazing wages of the world to be. The soul which clings to the fear of God does not
               fear before anything which harms the body.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n279-1">Philippians 1,29</note>
            <note xml:id="n280-1">1 Peter 3,14</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
