<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 39</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 39, pp. 197-202.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="39">
            <head>XXXIX</head>
            <p>Helpful advice based on love</p>
            <p>Hardships for the sake of the good are loved as the good itself. Nobody can acquire
               real renunciation save him that is determined in his mind to bear troubles with
               pleasure. Nobody can bear trouble save him that believes that there is something more
               excellent than bodily consolation which he shall acquire in reward for trouble. Every
               one that has devoted himself to renunciation, will first perceive the love of trouble
               stir within himself; thereupon the thought of renunciating all worldly things will
               take shape in him. Every one who comes near unto trouble will at first be confirmed
               in faith; then he will come near unto trouble. He that renunciates [worldly] things
               without renunciating the senses, sight and hearing, he prepares twofold trouble for
               himself and he will find tribulation <pb n="198"/>in a twofold measure. Or rather:
               while he refrains from the use of things, he delights in them through the senses and
               by the affections which they cause he experiences the same from <pb type="external"
                  n="297"/>them that he had to endure in reality before; because the recollection of
               their customs is not effaced from the mind. If then imaginary representations
               existing in the mind alone can torture man, apart from the things corresponding to
               them in reality, what shall we say when the real things are close at hand?</p>
            <p>Beautiful therefore is solitary life and very helpful, because it silences the
               deliberations with force and gives us strength to train ourselves in endurance; and
               teaches a man patience by the exercise given by cruel troubles, which accompany the
               life of the solitary necessarily.</p>
            <p>Do not seek the advice of him that is not thy fellow in behaviour, though he be very
               prudent. A layman who has experienced things is more to be trusted than a sage who
               speaks on the basis of theoretical knowledge but without experience.</p>
            <p>What is experience? Experience is not this that a man goes and touches things,
               without acquiring knowledge concerning their advantages and their defects and without
               remaining with them during a certain time. How often the faces of things give the
               impression of defect, whereas within them is found matter full of advantages. In the
               same way are to be judged things of the opposite aspect.</p>
            <p>Many are those who from profitable things gather defects. Neither is the testimony of
               these concerning their knowledge to be trusted. This is only the case with him that
               has learned to examine things with patient distinction. Not all man's advice,
               therefore, is to be trusted; but [only] that of him who has behaved well before, who
               has knowledge founded upon experience in all things, who does not love himself, or
               who does not shun disdain.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="298"/>As often as thou findest thy course in peace, without
               variations, then be suspicious. For thou art deviating from the divine ways trodden
               by the weary footsteps of the saints. The more thou proceedest on the way towards the
               city of the kingdom and approachest its neighbourhood, this will be the sign: that
               thou meetest hard temptations. And the more thou approachest, the more thou wilt find
               difficulties.</p>
            <pb n="199"/>
            <p>So, as often as thy soul on its way perceives varying states which cause difficulty
               thou must know that thy soul has secretly been advanced to a higher state and that it
               has acquired a gift of increase in comparison with the degree it occupied before.</p>
            <p>The hard temptations into which God brings the soul are in accordance with the
               greatness of His gifts. If there is a weak soul which is not able to bear a very hard
               temptation and God deals <choice><sic>meakly</sic><corr>weakly</corr></choice> with it, then know with certainty that, as
               it is not capable of bearing a hard temptation, so it is not worthy of a large gift.
               As great temptations have been withdrawn from it, so large gifts are also withdrawn
               from it. God never gives a large gift and small temptations. So temptations are to be
               classed in accordance with gifts. Thus from the hardships to which thou hast been
               subjected thou mayest understand the measure of the greatness which thy soul has
               reached. In accordance with affection is consolation.</p>
            <p>What then? Temptation, then gifts; or gifts and afterwards temptation? Temptation
               does not come if the soul has not received secretly greatness above its previous
               rank, as well as <pb type="external" n="299"/>the spirit of adoption as
               sons<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n199-1"/>. We have a proof of it in the temptation of our Lord and of the
               Apostles; for they were not allowed to be tempted before they had received the
               Comforter. Those who partake of good have also to bear temptations. Along with good
               are the oppressions [in behalf of it]. So it has pleased God, who is wise in all
               things.</p>
            <p>Thus is the state of things; and accordingly, the apperception of temptations is
               anterior to the apperception of gifts, in order to test freedom. Grace never reaches
               a man before he has tasted temptations. In reality it is anterior; to the
               apperception it is posterior.</p>
            <p>It is true therefore, that there are with thee at those times two opposite feelings,
               not resembling one another. What are they? Joy and fear. Joy, because thou findest
               thyself as appears from the sign of the temptations going the way that has been
               trodden by the saints, nay even by the saviour of the world. Fear, lest thou be
               tempted by these temptations through haughtiness. But the humble are gifted with
               prudence by grace, so as to be able to recognize the distinctions of these things,
               namely [to distinguish] between the temptations that arise from <pb n="200"
               />haughtiness, and cheeks that burn from love. For the temptations that serve to
               improve behaviour are to be distinguished from those temptations which are permitted
               [by God] with the purpose of overcoming the presumption of the heart.</p>
            <p>The temptations which take place under paternal control and serve to educate the
               soul, to train and to try it, so that it becomes illustrious, are: dejection, bodily
               weariness, relaxation <pb type="external" n="300"/>of the limbs, despondency,
               confusion of mind, bodily pains, temporary despair, darkness of deliberations,
               deprivation of human help<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n200-1"/>, want of bodily provisions and so on. For by these
               man acquires a solitary soul and humbleness and a mortified heart; and these things
               try him by the love of the creator and the governor administers them to those to whom
               they are sent, in accordance with the force necessary to bear them. In them are
               mingled consolations and distress, light and darkness, struggles and help. In short:
               they make narrow and they enlarge, which is the sign of the increase of help. The
               temptations which happen by permission unto those who venture to puff themselves up
               in their mind before the bounty of the author of our boons so as to become
               injuriously haughty regarding His boons — are the following: the manifest temptations
               of demons which lie without the domain of the psychic forces, so that [those who are
               tempted] are destitute of the force which imparts to them prudence; a vivid sensation
               of the impulses of fornication which are let loose in order to suppress their
               presumption; a being led easily to anger; the setting up of the will; love of victory
               in dispute; rashness; a heart inclined towards contempt; complete aberration of the
               mind; abuse of Him whose honour be blessed; foolish thoughts full of jest, or rather
               weeping; contempt as to men; [endangering] personal honour by impudence;
               ridiculousness through many contrivances of the demons, secretly and manifestly; love
               of mingling and intercourse with the world; frequent evasions <pb type="external"
                  n="301"/>of foolish words; novel individual inventions and false prophecies;
               frequent promises above one's power in the bodily sphere; a continually hard involved
               fate most difficult of solution; perpetual meetings with evil and ungodly persons;
               falling into the hands of evil persons; perpetual emotions of the heart, caused by
               sudden fear without reason; repeated heavy falls <pb n="201"/>from rocks and high
               places and the like, such as destroys the body; the inability of the heart to lean on
               God's care and to confide as is becoming to faith; in short: all unbearable forces
               which it is above one's power to withstand, such as are let loose against the
               solitary and his surroundings.</p>
            <p>All that I have expounded belongs to the temptations of haughtiness; the beginning of
               them shows itself in a man as soon as he becomes wise in his own eyes. He gets into
               all these evils according as he gives way to this deliberation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n201-1"/>. So by
               distinguishing between thy temptations thou wilt gain insight into the narrow paths
               of thy mind. If thou lookest on and observest some [of these temptations] on thy
               mind's paths, thou must know that the quantity of temptation is in accordance with
               the defiling working of presumption.</p>
            <p>Hear also another consideration. All hardships and troubles which are not borne with
               patience, cause twofold torture. A man's patience throws off his distress. Want of
               courage is the source of tortures. Patience is the source of consolations, a <pb
                  type="external" n="302"/>certain strength born from courage of the heart. It is
               difficult for a man to find in his own soul in troubles, if it be not given him by
               God, that which is found through supplication and the pouring out of tears.</p>
            <p>If God decrees that a man shall be troubled in a larger measure, He gives him into
               the hand of faintheartedness. And this will give birth to great despondency which
               gives the feeling of psychic suffocation; all these things taste after Hell.
               Thereupon the spirit of confusion is let loose against [the solitary], and from it
               rise innumerable temptations: perturbance, anger, abuse, vituperation, oscillating
               deliberations, moving from place to place, and the like. If thou sayest: Who is the
               cause of all these? I say: thou; because thou didst not care to find out the means to
               heal them. There is one remedy for all these and by it a man will at once find
               consolation within himself. What is this then? Humility of heart. Without it, it is
               not possible for a man to demolish the fence of these evil things, for he would find
               them far too strong. Be not angry with me for telling thee the truth: thou never hast
               sought this within thy soul. If thou wilt, follow it, then thou shalt see how it
               causes the destruction of thy evils.</p>
            <pb n="202"/>
            <p>In accordance with thy humility will be given thee endurance in thy distress; and in
               accordance with thy endurance its weight will be lightened from thy soul which will
               be <pb type="external" n="303"/>consoled in its troubles; and in accordance with the
               consolation of thy soul, thy love in God will increase; and in accordance with thy
               love thy spiritual joy will increase. When our compassionate Father is of the will to
               relieve those who are real sons in their temptations, He does not take them away from
               them, but He imparts to them endurance under temptations, and all that good which
               they receive through it, to the perfection of their souls. May Christ in His grace
               make us worthy of bearing evils for the sake of His love, with thanksgivings of the
               heart. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n199-1">Cf. Rom. 8,15</note>
            <note xml:id="n200-1"> This enumeration has been taken over by Bar Hebraeus, Book of the
               Dove, p. 528</note>
            <note xml:id="n201-1">viz. the deliberation of haughtiness</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
