<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 16</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 16, pp. 89-91.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="16">
            <pb n="89"/>
            <head>XVI</head>
            <head>How profitable it is for the soul while in solitude to be free from works and how
               intercourse harms the mind of the novice which has but lately begun to have insight
               for itself and how it is clear that bodily works necessarily bring about in the
               solitary a deficiency in divine works</head>
            <p>That a man who is beset with care, should be quiet and in a slate of peace, is
               impossible. For the necessary things which cohere with those things upon which he
               expends his labour, cannot but have the effect that he be shaken; and they will
               bereave him of his rest and quiet. For the only opportunity for Satan to enter the
               soul is distraction. Therefore it is becoming for the solitary to place himself
               constantly before God's face and to look for His will<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n89-1"/>, if it be his intention
               to keep his mind in watchfulness and if it be his will grasp quickly the small
               deviations as soon as they begin to stir in him, and, in peace of spirit, learn to
               recognise what passes in him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n89-2"/>.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="131"/>Frequent oscillations are a sign of the solitary's
               relaxation as to the preparation of Christ's service, and they are signs of
               deficiency in divine things.</p>
            <p>Without being free [from cares] thou canst not demand lucidity from thy soul; nor
               rest and quiet if the senses are set free; nor concentration of the senses when the
               oscillations of practice [are frequent].</p>
            <p>Keep thy self free from accidents; then thou wilt find no trouble in thy mind.</p>
            <p>Without constant beseechings it is not possible to be near to God. And to think of
               other things at the same time with the work of beseechings, is distraction of the
               heart.</p>
            <p>If fervent emotions befall thee sometimes when thou tastest God in the hot fire of
               divine things, but when thou seekest them again thou findest them to have become
               insipid and cold <pb n="90"/>within thyself, [this is because] the distraction of
               intercourse with men has assailed thee somewhere, or because thou hast estimated
               bodily work above them, and on account thereof the fervour of thy deliberations has
               become cold. Tears, however, and beating the head [on the ground] during prayer, and
               fervent self-humiliations quicken again their warm sweetness in the heart. And in
               lauded madness the heart will fly after God, crying:<quote> My soul thirsteth for thee, the
               living God: when shall I come and see thy face</quote><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n90-1"/>? He that has tasted this wine
               and has been bereft of it, he only knows in what a torment he has been left and what
               has been taken from him on account of his relaxation.</p>
            <p>O, how evil is the sight of men and intercourse with them <pb type="external" n="132"
               />for him that lives in solitude, especially him that is relaxed and left
               alone<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n90-2"/>. Verily, my brethren, as a strong blast of cold, that suddenly hits the
               buds of the trees and nips their small heads germinating from the twigs, so
               intercourse with men, even though it be short and in a congregation with a good
               purpose, withers the sprouts of the virtues which have but lately shown their heads
               because of the good air<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n90-3"/> of solitude, and which beset with their humidity the
               tree of the soul, planted by the brooks of repentance. And as the sharpness of the
               cold strikes the new sprouts of the roots, destroying and pushing back their heads
               into the earth, so intercourse with men destroys the root of the mind which but
               begins to grow green by reason of the herbs of virtues, thrusting them back to their
               original place and destroying their tenderness. And if intercourse with those who are
               nearly master of themselves is so obnoxious to the soul, be it only on account of
               their hindering the customary service, this must happen to a larger extent if a man
               speaks with and sees stupid and uncultivated men or even lay people, which has the
               effect of fire upon small wood. And as the humility of an honourable and estimable
               man, who forgets himself frequently by drinking wine, is troubled and his honour
               stained and his chastity shaken by the foreign deliberations which dominate his
               spirit on account of the force of the wine, so the chastity of the soul is shaken by
               intercourse <pb type="external" n="133"/>with and sight of men; and it forgets the
               aim of its watchfulness and is bereft of the whole intention of its will; and <pb
                  n="91"/>intercourse and recreation and the use of luxury eradicate from its depth
               the whole foundation of laudable behaviour.</p>
            <p>And even if a man be silent and only in the presence of such men in person, hearing
               and seeing, the mere fact that the doors of his eyes and his ears let in [what is
               seen and heard], is able to turn his spirit from divine things and to trouble it
               greatly.</p>
            <p>If thus the mere sight of men and the bare hearing of their speech for only a small
               time is able to cause so much harm to the solitary who is watchful, what then shall
               we say about regular meetings or about those of a longer duration?</p>
            <p>The vapour rising from the stomach obscures<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n91-1"/> the knowledge of divine things,
               as the inhalations rising from the damp earth obscure the face of the
               sun<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n91-2"/>.</p>
            <p>Haughtiness does not understand that it proceeds in darkness without knowing insight
               and wisdom. In its own thoughts it is elevated above all things, but it is poorer and
               lower than any thing. It is unable to know the ways of God, and the Lord will hide
               His will from it, because it does not like to go in the way of the humble.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n89-1">ܪܡܙܗ</note>
            <note xml:id="n89-2">Literally: those who go in and out.</note>
            <note xml:id="n90-1">Ps. 42,2</note>
            <note xml:id="n90-2">viz. by grace</note>
            <note xml:id="n90-3">literally: the mixture of the air</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-1"> In one Ms. only</note>
            <note xml:id="n91-2"> See p. 83</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
