<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 50</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 50, pp. 230-241.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="50">
            <head>L</head>
            <p>Short sections containing various considerations in which is shown the injury caused
               by foolish zeal under the pretext of fear of God and the profit originating in
               quietness; together with other subjects</p>
            <p>A zealous man will never reach peace of mind. And he that is destitute of peace is
               also destitute of gladness. Peace of mind is called complete health, zeal is the
               contrary of peace. He, therefore, that is moved by zeal suffers from a severe
               illness. Before thou art deemed, o man, to move thy zeal against the illness of
               others, thou has driven away health from thyself. Thou hast rather to bestow care
               upon the healing of thyself. If thou desirest however to heal the sick, know that
               those who are sick, are in want of nursing more than in want of vituperation. So,
               whilst thou doest not help others, thou vexest thyself by a severe illness. Zeal is
               not counted <pb type="external" n="344"/>among man as a form of wisdom, but as one of
               the illnesses of the soul, namely a narrowmindedness and a great ignorance. The
               principle of divine wisdom is quietness acquired by magnanimity, and the endurance of
               human weaknesses. Ye, therefore, that are strong, bear the loads of the sick, and
               direct the transgressor in a meek spirit. The Apostle counts among the fruits of the
               Holy Spirit peace and patience<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n230-1"/>.</p>
            <p>A heart full of suffering on account of its insufficiency regarding manifest bodily
               labours, is the acme of all bodily labours.</p>
            <p>Bodily labours, without mental suffering, are as a body without a soul.</p>
            <p>He that suffers in his heart and is lax regarding his senses, <pb n="231"/>is as a
               sick man whose body is aching and whose mouth indulges in all obnoxious kinds of
               food. He that suffers in his heart and is lax regarding his senses, is as a man who
               has an only son and slays him with his own hands limb by limb.</p>
            <p>Suffering of the mind is an honourable gift from God; and he that bears it together
               with the duties it imposes, is as a man who bears holiness in his limbs. A man who is
               dominated by his tongue in all things, good and evil, is not deemed worthy of this
               gift.</p>
            <p>Repentance along with intercourse is as a pierced jar.</p>
            <p>Blame along with a gift is a knife concealed in honey.</p>
            <p>Chastity and intercourse with women are as a lioness and a lamb in one house.</p>
            <p>Labours and depravity before God are as a man who slaughters a son before his father.
               He that is sick in his soul <pb type="external" n="345"/>and directs his comrades, is
               as a blind man that shows the way.</p>
            <p>Compassion and justice in one soul are as a man adoring God and idols in one house.
               Everywhere compassion is the enemy of justice.</p>
            <p>Justice is the equality of the even scale which gives to every man as he deserves
               without deviation to any side and without any consideration of a reward for
               it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n231-1"/>.</p>
            <p>Compassion is an affection which is stirred by bounty and which goes out to every one
               for their support. It does not repay him that has deserved evil. To him that has
               deserved good, it gives a double portion. If the former stands on the side of
               righteousness, then the latter is on the side of evil. As stubbles and fire cannot
               remain together in one room, so justice and compassion cannot in one soul.</p>
            <p>As a grain of sand does not balance a load of gold, so the effect of God's justice
               does not counterbalance His compassion.</p>
            <p>As a handful of sand thrown into the ocean, so are the sins of all flesh as compared
               with God's mind.</p>
            <p>As a fountain that flows abundantly is not dammed by a handful of earth so the mercy
               of the Creator is not vanquished by the wickedness of the creatures.</p>
            <p>As one that sows in the sea and expects that he shall reap, so is he that prays while
               preserving rancour.</p>
            <p>As the flames of the fire cannot be checked from going <pb n="232"/>upwards, so the
               prayers of the merciful cannot be checked from ascending towards heaven.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="346"/>As the violence of water in a narrow place, so is the
               force of anger when it has found a place in our mind.</p>
            <p>He that has humility in his heart, has become dead to the world. He that is dead to
               the world, is dead to affections. To him that is dead in his heart regarding his
               relatives, Satan is dead. He that has found envy has also found him that found it for
               the first time<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n232-1"/>.</p>
            <p>There is a humility that has its origin in the fear of God and there is a humility
               that arises through the love of God. Some people are made humble by their fear,
               others by their joy in Him. The former live with limbs subdued and ordered senses and
               in perpetual contrition of heart; the latter in full exuberance and with an exulting
               heart which is never checked. Love does not know bashfulness; these, therefore, do
               not know how to regulate or to order their limbs. Love naturally possesses frankness
               and oblivion of measure.</p>
            <p>Blessed is he that has found Thee, thou harbour of all joys.</p>
            <p>Beloved of God is the congregation of the humble, as the congregation of the
               seraphs.</p>
            <p>A chaste body is dearer to God than a pure offering. Both, however, prepare a
               dwelling-place for the Trinity in the soul. Walk with thy friends in a reserved
               attitude; in doing so thou wilt be of profit unto thyself and unto them. For usually
               under the pretext of friendship the soul casts off the reins of watchfulness.</p>
            <p>Be cautious regarding intercourse; it is not always profitable.</p>
            <p>In the congregation honour silence; for it prevents many wrongs.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="347"/>Be not so cautious regarding the belly, as regarding
               sight. Inner war is in any respect easier.</p>
            <p>Do not believe, o brother, that inner deliberations can be regulated without the
               regulation of the body.</p>
            <p>Fear customs rather than enemies. He that fosters a custom is as one fostering fire.
               Both display their vigour when they have acquired free play. When custom, however,
               has been repelled the first time it demands access, thou wilt find it weaker, a
               second time. But if thou fulfillest its desire the first time, thou wilt find it
               stronger when it demands access unto <pb n="233"/>thee the second time. Under all
               circumstances this recollection will strengthen thee.</p>
            <p>Help proceeding from watchfulness is better than help proceeding from labours.</p>
            <p>Be not friends with one that loves laughter and derision; for he will drag thee
               towards lax customs. Be not joyous with him whose behaviour is lax; but be cautious
               against hating him. If he desires to remain standing, try to help him; and care for
               his existence, until death. If thou art yet ill, thou hast not to play the physician;
               stretch the end of thy staff toward him, and so on.</p>
            <p>Speak with watchfulness before a boaster and one who is sick with envy. For while
               thou speakest he gives in his heart thy words the explanation he desires. He seizes
               the opportunity to make others stumble, even through beautiful things in thee.</p>
            <p>And thy words will be changed in his mind into opportunities of illnesses.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="348"/>Frown upon him that begins to speak to thee concerning
               his brothers. Doing so thou wilt be found cautious by God and by him.</p>
            <p>If thou givest something to one who is poor, let gladness of face and kind words and
               encouragement for his suffering precede thy gift. When thou doest this, by thy gift
               the delight of his mind will be greater than the want of his body.</p>
            <p>On the day that thou openest thy mouth to speak against a man, deem thy soul as dead
               to God and void of all thy labours, even if it is thought that thou art moved to
               speak by [the desire to] direct and to build. Wherefore should a man demolish his own
               building and order that of his neighbour?</p>
            <p>On the day that thou sufferest on behalf of a man in any way, be it on behalf of the
               good or on behalf of the wicked, in body or in mind, deem thyself on that day to be a
               martyr and as one that has been deemed worthy of confessorship for the sake of
               Christ. Remember that Christ died for the wicked, according to the words of the
               scripture, not for the good. Behold how great a thing it is to suffer for the evil
               and to do good to the sinners, even greater than to do this for the righteous. The
               Apostle reminds thee of this as of an amazing thing.</p>
            <p>If thou art able to acquire righteousness within thyself, be not anxious to seek
               other righteousness.</p>
            <pb n="234"/>
            <p>Anterior to all thy deeds are chasteness of body and purity of heart. Without them
               every deed is vain before God.</p>
            <p>Any work which thou performest without deliberation and examination — know that thy
               labour upon it is vain even <pb type="external" n="349"/>though it be beautiful. God
               counts as righteousness every matter of discrimination, not fortuitous
               performances.</p>
            <p>A lamp in the sun — the righteous who is not wise.</p>
            <p>Seed on a rock — prayer of one harbouring rancour.</p>
            <p>A tree without fruits — an ascetic without compassion.</p>
            <p>A <choice><sic>venemous</sic><corr>venomous</corr></choice> arrow — vituperation that has its origin in envy.</p>
            <p>A hidden snare — the praise of the cunning.</p>
            <p>A foolish counsellor — a blind watchman.</p>
            <p>Sorrow of heart — sitting with sinners.</p>
            <p>A sweet fountain — intercourse with the wise.</p>
            <p>A wise counsellor — a wall to rely upon.</p>
            <p>A foolish friend — a treasure of deficiency.</p>
            <p>Better it is to see a mourning assembly than to see a wise man clinging to a
               fool.</p>
            <p>Better it is to dwell with the beasts than to dwell with people affected by envy.</p>
            <p>Better it is to dwell in a grave than to dwell with people who behave in a depraved
               way.</p>
            <p>Sit with vultures but not with those who are covetous.</p>
            <p>Associate with the murderer, but not with the quarrelsome.</p>
            <p>Have intercourse with the swine, but not with the loquacious.</p>
            <p>Better is the young of the swine than the mouth of the loquacious.</p>
            <p>Sit amidst lions, but not amidst the haughty.</p>
            <p>Be the persecuted, not the persecutor.</p>
            <p>Be the crucified, not the <choice><sic>crucifyer</sic><corr>crucifier</corr></choice>.</p>
            <p>Be treated unjustly rather than treat unjustly.</p>
            <p>Be the oppressed, not the oppressor.</p>
            <p>Be peaceful, not a zealot.</p>
            <p>Deal <choice><sic>beneficiently</sic><corr>beneficently</corr></choice>, not justly. Justice does not belong to the
               behaviour of Christianity and no mention is made of it in the doctrine of Christ.</p>
            <p>Rejoice with those who rejoice, and weep with those who weep; <pb type="external"
                  n="350"/>this is a sign of serenity. With the sick, be as if sick; with the
               sinners practise mourning and with the converted rejoice.</p>
            <p>Be a friend of all men, but a solitary in thy mind.</p>
            <pb n="235"/>
            <p>Join in the suffering of all men, but hold thy body far from all men.</p>
            <p>Do not vituperate any one and do not direct any one, not even those who are very evil
               in their behaviour.</p>
            <p>Spread thy mantle over the sinner and cover him.</p>
            <p>If thou art not able to take upon thee his transgressions and to receive chastisement
               in his stead, at least suffer exposure, in order not to expose him.</p>
            <p>Do not quarrel for the sake of the belly.</p>
            <p>Do not hate for the sake of honour.</p>
            <p>Do not love to be a judge.</p>
            <p>Thou must know, o my brother, that we stay indoors in order not to know the evil
               deeds of men. For when we consider all men as good, we shall reach purity in our
               mind. But if we also become vituperators and chastisers and judges and vindicators,
               <choice><sic>persecutators</sic><corr>persecutors</corr></choice> and critics, in what respect then is dwelling in the
               towns inferior to abiding in the desert?</p>
            <p>If thou art not quiet in thy heart, be quiet with thy tongue.</p>
            <p>If thou art not able to be a ruler of thy deliberations, be a ruler of thy
               senses.</p>
            <p>If thou art not a solitary in mind, be a solitary in body.</p>
            <p>If thou art not able to labour with thy body, suffer in thy mind.</p>
            <p>If thou art not able to watch on thy feet, watch on thy bed.</p>
            <p>If thou hast no sufficient power to fast during the night, fast at least in the
               evening. And if thou hast no force for fasting <pb type="external" n="351"/>in the
               evening, be on thy guard at least against satiety.</p>
            <p>If thou art no saint in thy heart, be a saint in thy body. If thou art no
               mourner<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n235-1"/> in thy heart, let at least thy face be clad with mourning.</p>
            <p>If thou art not able to justify thyself, then speak as a sinner.</p>
            <p>If thou art not a peacemaker, be at least not a disturber.</p>
            <p>If thou art not able to be valiant, be a humble man in thy mind.</p>
            <p>If thou art not a victor, be not wrath with the vanquished.</p>
            <p>If thou hast no sufficient power to shut the mouth of him that speaks against his
               neighbour, guard at least thyself, lest thou become his partner.</p>
            <p>Know that if fire goes out from thee and kindles others, the souls of all those to
               whom some of this fire has been <pb n="236"/>imparted, will be demanded at thy hands.
               And if thou doest not throw out fire, but doest agree with him that does, and
               compliest with his deed, thou wilt be his partner in judgment.</p>
            <p>If thou lovest peace, be peaceful. And if thou hast been deemed worthy of peace,
               rejoice at all times. Pray for insight, not for gold.</p>
            <p>Be clad with humility, not with byssus. Acquire peace, not a kingdom.</p>
            <p>No one has insight without being humble. He that is not humble, has no insight. No
               one is humble without having peace; he that has no peace is not humble either. No one
               has peace without rejoicing. While men walk in all the ways which there are in this
               world, they do not find peace, until they approach unto hope in God. The heart does
               not acquire peace from vexations and offences, until it approaches unto this place.
               But hope will give them peace and pour gladness <pb type="external" n="352"/>into
               their heart. This is what that adorable mouth, full of holiness, has said: come unto
               me, all ye that labour and are heavy laden and I will give you rest<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n236-1"/>. Draw
               near to the hope which is in me, and desist from the many ways, and ye will have rest
               from labours and from fear. Hope in God elevates the heart. Fear of Hell breaks
               it.</p>
            <p>The light of the mind gives birth to faith. Faith gives birth to the consolation of
               hope. Hope makes the heart strong. Faith is the revelation of insight. When the mind
               is dark, faith is hidden, and fear reigns in us and cuts off our hope. Faith through
               instruction does not free a man from presumption and doubts; only that faith which
               dawns by insight. It is called the revelation of truth.</p>
            <p>As long as faith understands God as God, through the revelation of insight, fear will
               not approach unto the heart. When we are left in darkness and we lose this insight
               that we may become humble, fear assails us which brings us near to humility and
               repentance.</p>
            <p>The son of God has borne the cross and sinners have acquired courage in
               repentance.</p>
            <p>If the habit of repentance has driven away the anger of the King, he will not now
               reject your sincere mind. If the habit of humility can drive away God's anger from
               him who knows <pb n="237"/>himself not to be true, how much more will this be the
               case with you who are suffering in truth for your trespasses. Sufficient is the
               suffering of the mind in place of all bodily labours, according to the word of the
               commentator<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n237-1"/>.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="353"/>A temple of grace is he that is mingled with God by
               constantly thinking of that which belongs to him. What is thinking of that which
               belongs to him? It is the constant hunting after his rest; suffering at all times;
               the toil of constant care concerning those things which always remain imperfect on
               account of the wretchedness of nature; the constant sorrow at these things which the
               mind bears under strong emotions and which it places before itself with humble
               contrition as an offering during prayer. As much as possible it despises the care of
               the body, according to its power. Such is he that bears in his soul the constant
               recollection of God, as the blessed Basil, the bishop, says.</p>
            <p>Prayer without distraction is that prayer which produces in the soul the constant
               thought of God. For also this is God's incarnation, that He dwells in us by our
               constant recollection of Him with painstaking care of the heart, seeking His
               pleasure. Involuntary evil deliberations have their origin in previous laxity.</p>
            <p>O men and brothers, ye that desire to give some rest to the body in the way of
               recreation, for the sake of the service of God, in order to acquire force and to
               return to your service — let us not weaken our perfect watchfulness during the few
               days of rest, giving our whole self to relaxation as if we were men who have not the
               intention to return unto their service.</p>
            <p>Those who in the time of peace are wounded by arrows, are the people who bear the
               cause of this in themselves, namely wilful freedom of speech. And the dirty clothes
               with which they see themselves clad in a holy place (namely at the <pb
                  type="external" n="354"/>time when God is astir in their soul) are those which
               they have woven in the time of relaxation. The things which put us to shame when, at
               the time of pure prayer, we wish to offer them, are those with which we have
               accustomed ourselves at the time when we esteemed our senses too low.</p>
            <p>Watchfulness helps a man more than labours; and relaxation injures him more than
               rest. In rest there arise internal wars <pb n="238"/>which a man is able to overcome
               vexing though they may be to him. For as soon as he gives up rest and returns to the
               place of labour, they are put to silence and flee from him. Not so it is with that
               which is born from relaxation, though relaxation is born from rest. For as long as
               man is in the place of his freedom, he is able to lay hand on himself and place
               himself under the order of his laws; he is still in the place of his freedom. But
               when he is relaxed, he has left the place of freedom. If a man does not throw away
               completely all his watchfulness, he is not compelled against his will to comply with
               those things which he does not like. And if he does not completely give up the domain
               of his freedom, he will not be assailed by accidents, which bind him so that he is
               not able to withstand necessity. Do not give up the place of freedom on account of
               any of thy senses, o man; else thou willst not be able to return thereto. Rest
               injures the novices only; <pb type="external" n="355"/>relaxation also the perfect
               and the aged. Those who let themselves be directed to the comfort of bad
               deliberations, may find the way back by watchfulness and gain the height of good
               behaviour. But as for those who, confiding in their labours, have neglected
               cautiousness, and have been captivated by the relaxations of life, after [they had
               walked on] the height of behaviour, some have been wounded in the country of the
               enemies and have died during the time of peace, others have set out for the sake of
               the merchandise of life, and have exposed their soul to offence.</p>
            <p>We have no difficulties when we trespass in a thing, but only when we persevere in
               it. Trespasses will sometimes happen even to the cautious.</p>
            <p>But clinging to them is utter death. Suffering which we endure for the sake of things
               in which we transgress fortuitously, are counted as pure service on our part, by the
               grace that sustains our life.</p>
            <p>He that sins a second time expecting [forgiveness] walks with God cunningly.
               Unexpectedly the rope of punishment will be thrown upon him and he will not reach the
               time for which he had hoped.</p>
            <p>If a man's senses are lax, his heart is also lax. The service of the heart is a bond
               of the outward members, if a man performs it with discrimination as the Fathers who
               were before us. This is known from other tokens which are seen in him: <pb n="239"
               />namely that he is not entangled in bodily profits, that he does <pb type="external"
                  n="356"/>not love money, and that he is wholly void of anger. Where on the
               contrary these three are found: the love of bodily profits to a small or to a large
               extent, and quick anger, and giving way to the belly (even in the case of the former
               saints), know that the relaxation in outward things originates in inward lack of
               patience, not in the baseness of the discriminating soul. How else could it be
               possible that such a one did not possess disregard of bodily things, and
               quietness?</p>
            <p>To expose oneself to disdain<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-1"/> discriminately is to be freed from all things,
               to disregard life and to love men.</p>
            <p>If thou endurest willingly injuries for the sake of God, thou art pure within.</p>
            <p>If thou doest not despise any one on account of his stains, thou art surely a free
               man.</p>
            <p>If thou doest not run to encounter those who honour thee, and if thou art not moved
               by meeting those who do not concord with thee, thou art really dead to this life.</p>
            <p>Watchfulness with discrimination is better than all kinds of behaviour to all kinds
               of men.</p>
            <p>Do not hate the sinner<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n239-2"/>; we are all worthy of condemnation. If thou art moved
               for the sake of God, weep over him. Why shouldst thou hate him? Thou meanst to hate
               his sins? Pray on his behalf, that thou mayest resemble Christ, who was not angry
               with sinners but prayed on their behalf. Hast thou not seen how He wept for
               Jerusalem? In many things we are made mock of by Satan. Why should we hate them that
               are made mock of like ourselves by the same one that makes mock of <pb
                  type="external" n="357"/>us? Why hatest thou the sinner, o man? Perhaps because he
               is not righteous as thou art? And how art thou righteous, that hast no love? And if
               thou hast love, why doest thou not weep for him, instead of persecuting him? It is
               through ignorance that some people, reputed to be discriminating, are moved by the
               deeds of sinners.</p>
            <p>Be a herald of God's goodness, because He provides for thee who art not worthy of it.
               And though thou art guilty of many things, it is not known that he is desirous of
               revenge. And for the few things in which thou showest [good] will, he remunerates
               thee with many. Do not call God just anymore, <pb n="240"/>for His justice is not
               known in His dealings with thee. Though David called Him just and righteous, still
               His son has made it clear to us that He is good and kind. For He is kind towards the
               evil and the miscreant. How callest thou God just when thou comest across the section
               on the hire of the workmen? Friend, I do thee no wrong. I will give unto this last,
               even as unto thee. Or is thy eye evil because I am good<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n240-1"/>? How can any one
               call God just if he come across the story of the prodigal son? When he had spent all
               in fornication, it was only on account of the contrition he showed that [the father]
               ran to throw himself at his neck and made him lord of all his possessions. No one
               else can say concerning Him that he doubts His goodness. His son testifies this
               concerning Him. How could there be justice in God, when Christ died <pb
                  type="external" n="358"/>for us who were sinners? If He is compassionate here, we
               believe that there will be no change in Him. Far be it from us that we should
               wickedly think that God could not possibly be compassionate. God's properties are not
               liable to variations as those of mortals. It is not possible that He sometimes should
               not possess a thing, and afterwards should possess it, or that what He possesses
               should diminish or increase as that which creatures possess. But that which God
               possesses is with Him from eternity, and it is with Him for ever, as also the blessed
               commentator<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n240-2"/> says in his exposition on the creation.</p>
            <p>Fear before His love, not before the reputation of harshness with which He has been
               charged. Love Him because it is our duty to love Him; not for those things which He
               will give, but also because of those which we have received. Even if He had made this
               world only for our sake, who could sufficiently tell His bounty? Where is the
               remuneration for Him in our deeds? Who has persuaded Him beforehand to bring us into
               existence? And who will intercede with Him for our sake when we shall be in a state
               of oblivion as if we were not? Who will stir our destruction into life? And from
               where will the impulse of knowledge be cast into [what is] dust? O the wonder of
               God's compassion. O the amazement of the bounty of our Creator. O the power of His
               almightiness. O His immeasurable kindness regarding our nature, that He also brings
               sinners into <pb n="241"/>existence! Who can sufficiently tell His praise, who
               quickens the sinner and abuser who had become dust without motion [so as to
               participate of] a laudable, recognizing and rational mode of existence; that changes
               scattered dust into a being exalted above perception; that makes scattered senses a
               rational nature with quick motion? If the sinner is not able to [understand] His
               quickening power, he can be content with His grace.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="359"/>Where is Hell which can make us suffer? And what is the
               torment which can overcome in us His fear, vanquish the joy at His love? And what is
               Hell as compared with the grace of resurrection, which will restore us to life after
               Sheol and make this corruptible to be clad with incorruptibility, and make rise in
               glory what was lying in the contempt of Sheol? Ye understanding, come and wonder. Who
               has an intellect wise enough to wonder? Come and let us wonder at the grace of our
               Creator. The retribution of the sinners is this, that He repays them with
               resurrection instead of with justice. And those that have trampled upon His laws are
               clad by Him with the glory of perfection instead of with the body. This grace after
               we had sinned is greater than that which brought our being<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n241-1"/> into existence
               when we were not yet.</p>
            <p>Glory to Thy immeasurable grace. Now the floods of Thy grace make me silent without
               any emotion remaining, not even thankfulness. With what mouth shall we thank Thee,
               good king who lovest our life? Glory to Thee in both the worlds which Thou hast
               created for our education and for our delight, from all those that Thou hast brought
               into existence to know Thy glory, now and at all times, world without end, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n230-1">Gal. 5,22</note>
            <note xml:id="n231-1">itself</note>
            <note xml:id="n232-1">I am not certain of the sense of these words</note>
            <note xml:id="n235-1">abila, also a monk</note>
            <note xml:id="n236-1">Matthew 11,28</note>
            <note xml:id="n237-1">Theodore</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-1">ܫܝܛܘܬܐ. Cf. Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n239-2">With this passage cf. p. 14, 79, 348, 350</note>
            <note xml:id="n240-1">Matt. 20,13-15</note>
            <note xml:id="n240-2">Theodore</note>
            <note xml:id="n241-1">ܬܘܩܢܢ</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
