<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 52</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 52, pp. 253-254.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="52">
            <head>LII</head>
            <head>Short sections on a different subject on the distinction of the impulses of
               knowledge</head>
            <p>When knowledge pursues visible things, concerning which instruction is acquired
               through the senses, it is called natural. When it pursues the intelligible forces
               behind the visible things in non-bodily species, it is called spiritual. For
               perception is <pb type="external" n="378"/>received by the spirit, not by the senses.
               And regarding both of these kinds the soul receives the recognizable materials from
               without. When however knowledge pursues the Essence it is called supernatural, or
               rather agnostic, because it is elevated above knowledge. As to this [latter kind],
               the soul does not acquire contemplation concerning it in materials lying without it,
               as is the case with the former kinds. But without materials, by a sudden working of
               grace within, unexpectedly, it is revealed in the soul. For the kingdom of God is
               within us<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n253-1"/>. And it will not come from the place from where it is expected,
               nor through observation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n253-2"/>, according to the word of our Lord. But within the
               hidden form of the intellect it is revealed without cause and without meditation upon
               it. For the intellect has no materials to meditate upon it.</p>
            <p>The first [kind of knowledge] is born from constant recitation and from zeal for
               teachings. The second kind from a steady <pb n="254"/>behaviour and faith of the
               intellect. The third kind is due to faith alone. For there knowledge ceases and works
               reach their end and senses will be superfluous.</p>
            <p>As long as knowledge is beneath this line, it is called knowledge. And the lower it
               is, the more honoured it becomes, so that when it reaches the earth and earthly
               things, knowledge is master of all, and without it all is cripple and idle. But when
               the soul elevates its gaze and directs the space and the <pb type="external" n="379"
               />time of its impulses towards heavenly things and becomes desirous after the things
               which are not to be seen with the bodily eye and over which the flesh has no power,
               then all things fall under the category of faith.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n253-1">cf. Luke 17. 21</note>
            <note xml:id="n253-2">Luke 17,20</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
