<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 48</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 48, pp. 227-228.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="48">
            <head>XLVIII</head>
            <head><pb type="external" n="339"/>On the varying states of light and darkness to which the
               soul is subject at all times and on the training it acquires in things of the right
               hand and of the left</head>
            <p>Let us look at ourselves at the time of service and prayer. If we possess
               contemplation regarding the words of the Psalms and of prayer, this has its origin in
               real solitude.</p>
            <p>Let us not be perturbed when we are in darkness; especially if we are not the cause
               of it ourselves. For it is brought about by divine care, for causes which are known
               only to it. Our soul is then suffocated and, as it were, in the midst of storms.
               Whether a man approach unto a book of service — to whatever he approaches, it is
               darkness upon darkness which he finds in it, so that he desists from all effort. How
               many a time is he not even allowed to approach. He is wholly unable to believe that a
               different state will come upon him so that he will be in peace again. This hour is
               full of despair and fear; and the hope in God and the consolation of faith are wholly
               effaced from the soul, which is totally filled with doubt and fear.</p>
            <p>Those who are tempted by the storm of this time, know by experience the varying state
               which will follow after it. Never will God leave the soul a whole day in this state;
               otherwise it would lose life and all Christian hope. But gradually — however strong
               this darkness may be — a turn unto life will appear from it. Unto thee, o man, I give
               the advice: if thou possessest no power to dominate thy soul and to fall upon <pb
                  type="external" n="340"/>thy face in prayer, envelop thy head in thy mantle and
               lie down till the hour of darkness has passed away from thee.</p>
            <pb n="228"/>
            <p>Leave not, however, thy cell. By this temptation are tried especially those who are
               willing to walk in mental discipline and who in their course are running toward the
               consolation which comes from faith.</p>
            <p>This dark hour, therefore, tortures them, more than by any thing else, by spiritual
               doubt. It is also accompanied by strong abuse; sometimes even by doubt of the
               resurrection and other points which it is not necessary to mention.</p>
            <p>All these things we have experienced many times and recorded for the consolation of
               many. Those who are occupied by bodily labours only are wholly removed from this
               struggle. They are attacked by dejection with which every man is acquainted and which
               differs from the state mentioned and similar ones. The healing of the latter — viz.
               its consolation — has its origin in solitude. By intercourse a man will never obtain
               the light of consolation, but in the course of time he will find alleviation.
               Afterwards, however, it will attack him vehemently. He needs an enlightened man,
               experienced in these things, by whom he may be illuminated and encouraged from time
               to time, though not constantly. Blessed is he that endures under these circumstances
               the abiding indoors, he that after these things reaches the large and strong
               apartment, as the Fathers say. Not at once, however, will this struggle cease;
               neither will grace come and dwell in the soul completely at once, but <pb
                  type="external" n="341"/>gradually. One, and the other: sometimes temptation,
               sometimes consolation. Some of it will remain, even till departure. Complete
               deliverance from it we do not expect here, nor complete consolation.</p>
            <p>Thus has it pleased God that our temporal life should be provided. And these things
               are for those that walk in the way.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
