<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 24</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 24, pp. 120-123.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="24">
            <head>XXIV</head>
            <p>On the things a brother is provided with in his cell</p>
            <p>It occurs many times in a day, that a brother, even if thou shouldst give him the
               kingdom of the world, would not consent at that hour to leave his cell or to [allow]
               any one to visit him. For the time of commerce<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n120-1"/> has presented itself, of a
               sudden. Such things happen on days such as are considered as days of relaxation.
               Often on such days and even on those wherein he has intercourse with others, grace of
               a sudden will visit him, in tears without measure, or a vivid affection moving <pb
                  type="external" n="178"/>the heart, or a certain gladness without cause, or the
               delight of kneelings.</p>
            <p>I know a brother who put the key in the door of his cell in order to shut it, for he
               was going out in order to be occupied with idle things as the scripture
               says<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n120-2"/>. And there grace visited him, so that he returned immediately. Nobody,
               therefore, shall blame a brother if, on the days on which he does not keep canonical
               solitude, he should happen to neglect the congregational service sometimes.
               Especially if he be not reputed base or given to inane occupations, and if he does
               not neglect it on account of bodily labour. You know, my brethren, that our work is
               not only that which is accomplished before the eyes of men; but we have also a
               service which is hidden from the eyes of men and which is not known to novices and
               lay people. For you are acquainted with the fact, that the solitary is under a rule
               and not his own master. Therefore if any of his brethren comes to visit him and he
               answers him not, he shall return immediately without blaming his brother. For he <pb
                  n="121"/>does not know that with which his brother is occupied at that time. The
               cell of a solitary is the cave of the rock in which God spoke with Moses, as the
               Fathers say. Those solitaries who have not been put to the test by the service which
               consists in the true taste of solitude, do not know these things. They despise their
               brethren and judge, claiming for themselves equality with them in all things.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="179"/>It also happens sometimes that a brother is suddenly set
               face to face with some necessary strife, and, with his hands laid on his heart, he is
               in danger of flying away. Being prostrated he beseeches God, not able to bear the
               voice of any one. These varying states are known to those who once have crossed this
               ocean and are acquainted with the winds blowing [there].</p>
            <p>It may also happen that the thought of repentance may rise in a man and that his past
               may suddenly be united with the memory of his death and present itself before him.
               And this brilliant sun will be darkened before his eyes and every recollection of the
               world will be effaced from his heart.</p>
            <p>It may also happen that suddenly billows may rise against him and his ship be
               engulfed in hidden abysses; things which are not known to every one, but which
               unexpectedly assail the solitary in his solitude owing to the violent struggles of
               Satan, so that the cell becomes a place of mourning.</p>
            <p>Numerous are the varying states of this ocean and who knows its labours and its
               multifarious connections, the wonderful pearls in its depth and the animals rising
               from it? Blessed is he who sleeps not during the whole of his course until the port
               of death.</p>
            <p>No one loves anything without multiplying his connections [with it].</p>
            <p>No one is able to occupy himself with divine things without having cast away and
               despised temporal ones; becoming a stranger to worldly honour and delights, following
               the disdain of the cross, drinking every day vinegar and gall on account of the
               affections, men, demons and poverty.</p>
            <p>Be alert, my brother, and be like a prudent merchant, <pb type="external" n="180"
               />bearing thy pearl and wandering through the world, anxious that its excellent
               beauty be not besmirched. Be careful, lest it be stolen from thee on account of thy
               laxity and thou go to Hell in distress.</p>
            <p><choice><sic>Persue</sic><corr>Pursue</corr></choice> the small consolation which is gained from labour in <pb n="122"
               />its time, that thou may be deemed worthy of that great consolation which liberates
               those who have found it, from torment in this place of distresses. Do not reject
               small things, lest thou be bereaved of the great ones. No one has ever seen a child
               which sucks milk putting meat into its mouth. By means of small things the gate unto
               great ones is opened. Thou disdainest God, o my brother who desirest that God shall
               govern thee without His rule. No one has been entrusted with great things, without
               having been first tried in small ones. Think of this, o my brother, and remember me
               in due time: every station which on the morrow thou attainest to in this way of
               excellence and knowledge of the truth, will be found by thee more glorious and
               excellent than that in which thou hast spent the night before. Thou departest,
               wondering at the beauty of the station which thou has entered to-day. But its beauty
               vanishes by the beauty of that which thou wilt reach to-morrow. Who can perceive the
               mind's varying states, full of delight? Pray only, that the gate may be opened before
               thee.</p>
            <p>Be on thy guard against dejectedness. Thou servest not under a tyrant; thy service is
               under a kind Lord, who has given thee all, without taking from thee anything and who,
               before thou didst exist at all, destined thee to <choice><sic>ocupy</sic><corr>occupy</corr></choice> thy present place.
               Who can do justice to His grace even as shown by His calling us into existence?</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="181"/>O, for His immeasurable grace! Who can sufficiently tell
               the glory of Him who has given us the knowledge of all things? Not only of those
               which are manifest, but also of those which are hidden, so that we know that, if
               there is anything that we know not, we must ask it of Him; who has taught thee, o
               mortal, to be moved by the desire of seeking that of which the knowledge is not in
               thy nature? Never seek a consolation that lies without the heart, which is the
               knowledge of discernment. Exalt thyself above all consolation administered by the
               senses, that thou may be worthy of that consolation which lies beyond. The solitary
               who has become alien to the consolation of the world, without expecting every day the
               consolation of Christ, is dead in his living state.</p>
            <p>For God is compassionate and prone to give; but He desires that we give the
               opportunity. For He rejoices when man offers a wise prayer.</p>
            <p>The mark of him who is recovering from illness is that he <pb n="123"/>is desirous of
               the hidden things. There is delay, however, if he beholds essential health. He who
               wearies of asking is the companion of him who wearies because of delay. Weariness
               declines to ask in prayer, viz. it is an impediment to asking. Dejectedness shortens
               prayer and bars its prolongation. Expectation gives patience and incites us to
               prolong prayer. Expectation makes light the weight of fatigue in the limbs. It also
               knows how to impart rest to the heart in its troubles. There is no load the weight of
               which is more agreeable than work with expectation; nor is there any comrade with
               whom <pb type="external" n="182"/>intercourse is more desired than with it. Prison is
               a pleasant habitation if it be there. Make it thy companion, o repentant brother,
               then thou wilt not perceive any of the labours of thy struggle. If thou art in thy
               cell, it will be with thee. If thou art found among men, fix thy mind on it. And if
               at any time thy heart errs after anything on the earth, this world and all that is in
               it will be found alien to thee. If thou sleep, make it thy bed-companion; and
               converse with it until thou art enfolded in sleep. Then no depraved deliberation will
               draw near thy heart, because thy occupation is of an immaterial kind and no object
               clad with matter, which by its appearance moves the spirit, is able to show itself
               there; and no demoniac deliberation knows how to show itself detached from material
               appearance.</p>
            <p>The fruit of life sprouts from endurance in prayer. And expectation is a helper
               during prayer to those who possess it. When thou prayest, remember the husbandman who
               sows in hope. And He who causes to return twofold the seed of the husbandman who sows
               in faith, and who has estimated the seeking of His kingdom and His righteousness
               higher than the temporal things, He will incline himself to our prayer to our
               demands, as He has promised. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n120-1">Often the image of spiritual things</note>
            <note xml:id="n120-2">Eccles. 1,14 etc.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
