<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 7</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 7, pp. 67-70</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="7">
            <head>VII</head>
            <p>On other subjects, chapter by chapter, in short sections on the character of trust in
               God and for whom it is becoming to trust in God. And further; when a man trusts, he
               will have power according to [the state of] his mind. And who trusts foolishly and
               without discernment</p>
            <p>There is a trust in God, with a faith of the heart, which is beautiful and which
               rises from the discernment of knowledge. And there is another trust which is insipid
               and rises from folly; and this is false trust.</p>
            <p>That a man who has absolutely no care for any of these passing things and whose soul
               is night and day given to the works of God, without thought of any work of this world
               because of his great zeal for excellence and because of his absorbing anxiety for the
               divine things, and who, therefore, neglects to prepare dress and food and to fix and
               to prepare a place for his shelter and the like, — that such a man trusts in God that
               He will prepare in its due season all he needs and that He will care for him — this
               is really true trust and a trust of wisdom. And in truth, for such a man it is also
                  <pb type="external" n="100"/>beautiful to confide in God, because he is His
               servant, and he is ladened with thoughts concerning Him and he bears the weight of
               His works without neglect. And so it is becoming <pb n="68"/>to Him to show care for
               him, which is distinguished from His care for the rest of mankind, because he has
               eminently maintained in his person the word of our Lord saying: seek the kingdom of
               God and His righteousness[#n68-1] and: Take no thought for your body[#n68-2]. And if
               ye care for this, the world will prepare all for you, like as a servant. And as unto
               a master it will be obedient unto your words without hesitation, without thwarting
               your will in anything.</p>
            <p>Therefore, because such a man does not desist on account of [worldly] causes from
               standing perpetually before Him, he will not surrender himself to those things which
               the body needs. For he does not care for other things either, but he abstains from
               them all equally, be they small or great, be they things of comfort or pleasure — an
               abstention based on fear of God. So he will find sustenance in a wondrous way, even
               though he does not touch any of these things, nor fatigues himself with them.</p>
            <p>Another however, whose heart is wholly buried in the earth and who constantly eats
               dust with the serpent without caring in any way for the things pleasant to God, who
               fatigues himself in every respect by the bodily things and is occupied by and
               constantly cares for intercourse and pleasure and luxury, and who has manifold
               worldly connections, — when such a man, given to such laxity and indifference
               regarding excellence, from time to time gets into trouble or want, or the fruits of
               sinfulness disturb him in any way, and [when he] says as follows: <pb type="external"
                  n="101"/>I trust in God, He will work for me without doubt and He will comfort me,
               — o fool, till now thou hast not recalled God but thou hast disdained Him by the
               laxity of thy works and His name was slandered among the nations, as the scripture
               says. And now thou sayest with a full mouth: I confide in Him who will help me and
               care for me. God has well said through the prophet, scorning such people: They seek
               me daily and delight to know my ways, as a nation that did righteousness and forsook
               not the ordinance of their God: they ask of me the ordinances of justice[#n68-3]. To
               them belongs the fool who does not even spiritually come near unto God, but, at a
               time when the darkness of troubles surrounds him, elevates his hands unto Him in
               confidence. That such become wise, requires that they <pb n="69"/>be branded several
               times. For, although they have no works such as could be a basis for trust in God,
               yet they have been thought worthy of chastisement and loaded with mercy, as it were
               from [the midst] of their evil works and their indifference regarding their duties.
               They should not mislead themselves and, forgetting the rank of their previous way of
               life, say: I trust in God. Such have to be chastised, lest they, though not
               possessing works of faith, stretch out their feet in idleness, saying: I believe that
               God will give me to eat, as if they were toiling in the works of God.</p>
            <p>Or it may come to pass that some one goes and falls into a pit through his own folly,
               and although he has never thought of God before, he says now: I trust in God, He will
                  <pb type="external" n="102"/>deliver me. Err not, thou fool. Trust in God has to
               be preceded by works for the sake of God and by the sweat of His service. If thou
               believest in God thou doest well. But also faith requires works; and confidence in
               Him requires the testimony of the heart which is born of the toils [for the sake] of
               excellence. Believe that God is He who cares for His creatures and who is clad with
               all power. But connect with this faith the works which suit it. Then He will answer
               thee. Take no wind in thy fist, viz. faith without deeds.</p>
            <p>If a man travel a road without being conscious of the fact that there are evil beasts
               or murderers on it, or the like, how many times will this universal care of God cause
               [the danger] to pass, by retaining him at the place where he is, for any cause, till
               the danger is over, or by some one meeting him and causing him to return. Or another
               time, a dangerous serpent lies on the way, which he has not noticed. If God will that
               he be not entangled in evil, the animal will at once make a sound or leave its place
               and disappear, or it will creep farther so that he sees it and is cautious. Thus God
               will save him, even if he be not worthy, for motives which God alone knows,
               especially for His mercy's sake. Or, another time a house or a wall or a rock is on
               the point of falling or slipping from its place and coming down instantly [at the
               place] where <pb type="external" n="103"/>some men are sitting. Thereupon God will
               order an angel and will hinder this accident and prevent it till those people have
               risen [and left] that place, for any reason whatsoever that makes them go away, so
               that none will remain under [the falling thing]. But as soon as they have left [the
               place], it will <pb n="70"/>fall. But if it happens that anyone be under it, he will
               not be damaged. By this God desires to show the greatness of His power.</p>
            <p>Such things and the like are [signs of] universal care. The righteous possesses this
               grace perpetually as an individual, not[#n70-1] as a member of the community. The
               rest, however, are ordered by God to govern themselves with insight and to mingle in
               their affairs intelligence with the care of God. But the righteous does not need this
               insight in order to govern with it his affairs. In stead of this insight he possesses
               faith by which he storms strong fortresses. And such things as we have enumerated he
               does not fear. As scripture says: the righteous is <choice><sic>bald</sic><corr>bold</corr></choice> as a lion[#n70-2] and
               he ventures all through his faith. Not as one who tempts God but as one who possesses
               confidence in Him and as one who is armed and strongly clad with the force of the
               spirit. And concerning His great perpetual care for him God has said thus: I will be
               with him in trouble; I will deliver him and honour him. With long life I will satisfy
               him, and shew him my salvation[#n70-3]. He who is <pb type="external" n="104"/>weak
               in his works and lax or negligent, or whose deeds are evil, it is impossible that
               this hope be his. But it will be for him that is constantly with God in all things
               and who is His relative by his beautiful works[f], who directs constantly the gaze of
               his heart towards God's grace, as David says: My eyes fail while I wait for the
               Lord[#n70-4].</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n68-1"> Matthew 6,33</note>
            <note xml:id="n68-2"> Matthew 6,25</note>
            <note xml:id="n68-3"> Jos. 58,2</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-1">Lacking in one of the London Mss.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-2">Proverbs 28,1</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-3">Ps. 91,15</note>
            <note xml:id="n70-4">Cf. Ps. 119,123</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
