<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 13</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 13, p. 84</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="13">
            <head>XIII</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="124"/>On the varying states which come to those who live in
               solitude, as is justly ordered by God concerning this [spiritual] way: now sadness
               and psychic suffocation, then, suddenly, gladness and joy and hot fervour and unusual
               strength. Praise to Him that has ordered our way amen</p>
            <p>To him who has determined to order his being in lonely dwelling and to pass the
               remainder of his days in service and in the ordering of the way of solitude, it will
               come to pass that, while he is as usual, in solitude, such as is justly prescribed by
               divine grace, his soul will be hidden in darkness. And just as the radiance of the
               sun is hidden from the earth by thick clouds, so, for a short time he is bereft from
               spiritual consolation and from the rays of grace, by the clouds of the affections;
               and some of the joy-giving force is withdrawn from him, while an unusual darkness
               falls upon his spirit; yet his mind is not troubled nor inclined towards dejection;
               but he remains patient, occupying himself with the writings of divine men and with
               prayers to which he forces himself, looking for help.</p>
            <p>Then of a sudden it will be given him unexpectedly[#n84-1]. For, as the face of the
               earth is gladdened by the rays of the sun when the dense atmosphere is torn asunder,
               so the words of prayer are able to tear away and to remove from the soul the <pb
                  type="external" n="125"/>dark cloud of the affections and to gladden and to
               illuminate the spirit by the rays of joy and consolation which is born in our
               deliberations.</p>
            <p>Especially when the soul is able to have recourse to the profit from the holy books
               and from vigils that make the mind pure. Constant meditation upon the holy scriptures
               will perpetually fill the soul with incomprehensible ecstasy and joy in God.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n84-1">Literally: though he does not know it.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
