<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 77</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 77, pp. 352-359.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="77">
            <head>LXXVII</head>
            <p>This chapter is full of life</p>
            <p>O thou wretched man, wishest thou to find life? Take faith and humility in order to
               find by them mercy and help and consolation from God, and protection secretly and
               openly. Desirest thou to acquire these, which are the fountain of life? Put on
               sincerity, from the beginning. In sincerity walk before God, and not in knowledge.
               Sincerity is combined with faith; subtlety and the reflections of knowledge, with
               presumptuous thoughts; presumptuous thoughts, with being removed from God.</p>
            <p>When thou liest before God in prayer, then be in thy consideration as <choice><sic>a an</sic><corr>an</corr></choice> ant
               and as the reptiles of the earth and as the beetle. And stammer as a villager and
               speak not before Him with knowledge. With a childlike mind approach unto God and walk
               before Him, that thou mayest be worthy of the paternal care which fathers entertain
               in behalf of their young children.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="525"/>It has been said: The Lord guards the children. A child
               may approach a serpent and take it at its neck; and the animal will not bite. A child
               may go naked during the whole winter. And while others are clad and covered — yet the
               cold penetrates all their members — he sits down naked in the day of frost and ice,
               without suffering, because the body of their childhood is covered by a different,
               invisible garment, by that hidden care which guards the frail members of childhood,
               lest injury from any side approach them. Doest thou now believe that there is a
               secret care in behalf of the tender body which is <choice><sic>expecially</sic><corr>especially</corr></choice> liable to
               all kinds of injuries on account of its tenderness and the weakness of its joints, so
               that it is guarded from obnoxious influences so that they do not cause suffering? For
               the Lord guards the child. Thou must not only apply this and believe it in the case
               of children, but also in the case of those who, being wise in the world, leave their
               knowledge, and relying upon that wisdom which is <pb n="353"/>all-sufficient become
               children by their own will. Then they learn wisdom, which is not to be learnt by
               labours of exercise.</p>
            <p>Also the blessed Apostle, who was wise in divine things, has beautifully said in an
               admonition: If any man seemeth to be wise in this world, let him become a fool, that
               he may be wise[#n353-1]. But beseech God, that He may grant thee to reach the degree
               of faith. If thou perceivest the delight of faith in thy soul, it is not difficult
               for me to say that there is nothing further which withholds it from Christ. And it is
               not difficult <pb type="external" n="526"/>for it to be always captivated and not to
               perceive earthly things but to forget this weak world and the recollection of its
               things. On behalf of this pray without dejection; and ask it with tears and beseech
               fervently; and supplicate with great earnestness, till thou hast received it. Further
               no fatigue will be necessary.</p>
            <p>Thou wilt be deemed worthy of this, if beforehand thou compellest thy soul to cast
               thy care on God, in faith, and so thou wilt change thy care for His care. Then, when
               He sees that in utter serenity of spirit thou art willed to believe God in things
               which concern thee and that thou compellest thy soul to confide in God more than in
               thyself, that power with which thou art not acquainted, will take hold of thee, so
               that thou wilt be affected in an apperceptive way by the power which works in thee,
               no room being left for doubt.</p>
            <p>By this power which they perceived, many went into the fire without fear, and walked
               on water without thinking of the possibility that they could be drowned in it,
               because faith strengthened the senses of their soul so that it felt an inward
               conviction that resolution could not be weakened nor look on terrible things except
               with a gaze exalted <choice><sic>bove</sic><corr>above</corr></choice> the senses.</p>
            <p>Take care not to think at all, that spiritual knowledge can be received by psychic
               knowledge. It is not only that spiritual knowledge cannot be received by psychic
               knowledge, but it is even impossible that those who zealously try to acquire training
               in psychic knowledge should be deemed worthy to <pb type="external" n="527"/>perceive
               spiritual knowledge. And if any of them should desire to approach unto spiritual
               knowledge, before having denied psychic knowledge and all its subtle orders and
               intricacies and before having reached childhood of spirit — it will not be <pb
                  n="354"/>possible for him to approach even a little way towards it. But its
               customs and perverted impulses become to him many hindrances, before he gradually
               forgets them.</p>
            <p>Spiritual knowledge is simple, not illuminated by psychic deliberations. Before the
               mind has been freed from manifold deliberations and has reached the unified
               simplicity of purity, it is not able to perceive spiritual things.</p>
            <p>This order of knowledge, consisting therein that man here already perceives the
               delight of the life of the world to be, rejects much deliberation. And psychic
               knowledge is not able, apart from the gatherings of many deliberations, to know
               anything which is received by serenity of spirit. And the word of our Lord is not
               denied: Except ye be converted and become as little children, ye shall not enter into
               the kingdom of heaven[#n354-1]. Indeed, many are those who do not reach this
               innocence; but on account of their beautiful works a portion is kept for them with
               our Lord in the kingdom of heaven, as can be recognized from the understanding of the
               blessings which He especially pronounced in His gospel. In these blessings He has
               touched a variety of ways of behaviour [from which it appears] that for every man who
               walks to Him, in whatever measure on whatever way, the gate of the kingdom of heaven
               is open. But the word 'Except ye be converted <pb type="external" n="528"/>and become
               as little children' means that here man perceives the delight of the kingdom. The
               kingdom of heaven is said to be spiritual contemplation. And this is not found by the
               labours of the deliberations, but it is tasted by grace. And before a man has become
               pure, he is not able even to hear. Because it is not acquired by learning. If thou
               reachest purity, my son, which is acquired through the faith of the heart and by
               reclusion from men, and thou forgettest the knowledge of this world and doest not
               perceive it, then [spiritual contemplation] suddenly is found within thee, without
               inquiring after it. Erect a pillar and pour oil upon it[#n354-2], and thou wilt find
               thy treasure within thee.</p>
            <p>If, however, thou art entangled in the snares of psychic knowledge, I have no
               objection to say that it will be easier to thee to escape from iron bonds than from
               it. And thou wilt never be far from the snares of seduction, and thou wilt <pb
                  n="355"/>never be able to find and to have freedom of speech and confidence unto
               our Lord. And at all times thou wilt walk on the edge of the sword and thou wilt not
               be able absolutely to be without suffering[#n355-1].</p>
            <p>Take refuge with weakness and sincereness, that thou mayest live beautifully before
               God, and that thou mayest be without fear. For as the shadow follows the bodies, so
               does mercy follow humility. Therefore, if thou wishest to be connected with these,
                  <pb type="external" n="529"/>do not give room any-how to weak deliberations. If
               all injuries and evils and dangers surround thee and make thee fear, do not care to
               look at them or to think of them. If once thou believest that God is able to guard
               and to govern thee, and if thou followest him, then do not further care for anything
               like these. But say to thyself: All-sufficient is He to whom thou hast once entrusted
               thyself. I am not near [to anything], but He knows it.</p>
            <p>Then thou wilt see indeed the wonders of God, namely how near His salvation always is
               to those who fear Him; and that His care surrounds them, though it is invisible. And
               though the guardian which is with thee is invisible to the bodily eyes, yet thou
               shalt not doubt his existence. Sometimes he reveals himself also to the bodily eyes,
               for the sake of thy confirmation. But when man has thrown away all visible help and
               human hope and clings to God in faith and with a clear heart, then at once grace will
               cling to him and reveal in him its force by various [acts of] help. At first it shows
               its help in manifest things, also in bodily ones, by its care of him, in order that
               by these things he may the better be able to perceive the power which is in God's
               care of him, and that by insight in manifest things he may become confirmed in hidden
               ones, as is becoming to his childlike mind and his lack of training. How then?</p>
            <p>It is to be compared with this, for instance, that a man's want is prepared for him
               without labour, without his bestowing care on it. So grace causes him to escape many
               accidents <pb type="external" n="530"/>which often come near him and which are full
               of danger. And while he has no anxiety before them because he does not perceive them,
               grace disposes of them in a very wonderful way, as also the other things which
               suddenly assail him, without his thinking how often injury to the soul and also to
               the <pb n="356"/>body may proceed from them. And it preserves him against them, as a
               nurse who gives him shade and spreads her wings over her sons, that no harm may
               approach unto them. And at the same time it causes him to perceive that which
               happened, showing him what threatened to destroy him, by the <choice><sic>yees</sic><corr>eyes</corr></choice> of the
               body, and the actual help of God, in a clear way; and the dissolution of his life
               which was near and from which God saved him.</p>
            <p>So [grace] instructs him, also in hidden things. And it reveals to him the ambushes
               of thoughts and of deliberations difficult to understand. So he will easily attain to
               their understanding and their mutual relation and seduction, which is related to
               which, and how one is born from the other and destroys the soul. And the whole ambush
               of the demons is laid open before him, and the cover of their deliberations, and what
               is related to every one of them.</p>
            <p>And [grace] provides him with insight, so that he understands what will happen. Then
               in his sincereness dawns a hidden light so that he perceives everything and the force
               of the emotions of subtle deliberations. It shows him as it were with its finger — if
               he did not know this — what is going to happen to him. And then this is born in him,
               that he asks from his governor, in prayer, all things small and great.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="531"/>And when grace, by all these things, has confirmed his
               mind in confidence on God, then it begins to introduce him gradually into
               temptations. And it admits unto him those temptations the difficulty of which his
               degree is able to bear. And by such a temptation it adduces unto him its help in an
               apperceptive way, in order to strengthen his courage, till, gradually, he acquires
               training and wisdom and despises his enemies through confidence in God.</p>
            <p>For it is impossible for a man, without these, to become prudent in spiritual
               struggles and to recognize his governor and to perceive his God, and to become
               secretly confirmed in his hope, by the force which he has received personally through
               experience. And as often as [grace] sees that the deliberation of presumption begins
               to move somewhat in him, and that he begins to think great things of himself, it
               allows the temptations to become strong and powerful against him, so that he
               recognizes his weakness and flees and seeks refuge with God in humility.</p>
            <p>By these things man reaches the degree of perfect man, through <pb n="357"/>faith and
               hope in the son of God to whom he is lifted up in love. For in a wonderful manner
               God's help unto man is recognized when he is surrounded by circumstances full of
               despair, and God shows there His power by delivering him from them. Never has man
               experienced the divine power in rest and comfort, and never has He shown His action
               in an apperceptive manner except in a lonely place or in the desert or in places not
               visited by men and free from the disturbance of their habitation.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="532"/>Be not astonished if, when thou beginnest [to practice]
               excellence, severe troubles rise against these from all sides. For excellence is not
               to be deemed to involve that its practice is not combined with difficulty and
               labours. Excellence has received its denomination from this, says the holy Euagrius.
               Usually difficulties make front against this alertness, and excellence is to be
               rejected when it is combined with comfort, says the blessed Marcus, the solitary.</p>
            <p>All excellence whatever, is called the cross, because it accomplishes the order of
               the spirit. For all those who desire in the fear of God to live in Jesus Christ, are
               assailed by troubles. If any man will come after me, let him deny himself, and take
               up his cross and follow me. Whoever would save his life in comfort, loses it; and who
               gives up his life for my sake, finds it[#n357-1]. Therefore our Lord has placed
               before thee the cross, that thou mightest pronounce death on thy soul and thereupon
               cause it to follow Him.</p>
            <p>There is nothing so strong as despair. It does not know how it can be defeated by
               anything belonging to those of the right or to those of the left hand. When a man in
               his mind has given up his life, none is more courageous than he is, and there is no
               enemy who is able to meet him, and there is no trouble the fame of which can weaken
               his mind. For any trouble whatever is inferior to death, and he has resolved to take
               death upon himself.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="533"/>If in every place and in every work and at all times
               concerning all things which thou art going to perform thou placest labour and pain as
               an example for the mind, thou wilt not only be found always courageous and undaunted
               to thwart all reputed difficulty, and by the vigour of the deliberations to put
               timidity to flight which usually rises therefrom that<pb n="358"/>deliberations look
               for comfort, but also all hard and difficult things which meet thee will seem to thee
               easy and light.</p>
            <p>How often thy will is thwarted by what thou expectest, though perhaps these things do
               not reach thee. For thou knowest that the expectation of comfort always withholds men
               from great profit and from excellent good, so that even those who live in the world
               with their fleshly dealings cannot accomplish their wish if they do not resolve in
               their mind to bear difficulties. And because experience is witness to this,
               persuasion with words is not necessary. And in all preceding generations till now
               there is nothing which makes men despair of victories and checks them from
               <choice><sic>exellent</sic><corr>excellent</corr></choice> practice and which makes them — to say it in one word — despise
               to enter into the kingdom, as the expectation of the small comfort which is near. And
               not only this, but many times this aspect is the cause of severe accidents and hard
               temptations to every man whose mind is directed towards it and whose deliberations
               move unto it; <pb type="external" n="534"/>because his governor is the will of
               desire. Who does not know that also the bird by the aspect of comfort draws near the
               snare? Perhaps our knowledge, as compared to that of a bird, is much inferior,
               concerning the hidden things and the accidents which are hidden in things and actions
               and places and various things. And also Satan, from the beginning, tries to ensnare
               us by promises and the prospect of comforts.</p>
            <p>Now that my mind is occupied with the subject of desire, by the words I have written,
               I have erred away from the scope which I had indicated above, viz. that at all times
               we must place the aspect of troubles before our mind, in all that we wish to begin in
               the path of our Lord, so that it reach its end duly.</p>
            <p>How many times, when a man wishes to begin some work for the Lord, he asks whether
               there is comfort in the thing, or whether it is possible to accomplish it easily,
               without labour, or whether there is any thing in it to trouble the body. Are not
               above and beneath names of comfort? What doest thou say, o man? Doest thou wish to
               ascend unto heaven and to receive the Kingdom which is there and communion with God
               and spiritual comforts and that blessedness and mingling with the angels, and
               immortal life? And doest thou ask whether there is trouble in this way? How
               astonishing are those who desire the things of this world and the riches which are to
               be destroyed and the dominion which will be dissolved. They <pb n="359"/>walk on the
               difficult waves of the sea; and they tread frightful ways; they bear a long course
               full of labours and troubles, <pb type="external" n="535"/>and other mournful things
               which men are wont to perform for the sake of their desire; and they do not
               deliberate at all whether there is labour in the matter or vexation in what they wish
               to do; whereas we always inquire after comforts.</p>
            <p>If we always in our mind take upon us the way of crucifixion and always comply with
               the crucifixion, what difficulty then should not be easier than it? Does there exist
               any one at all who is not acquainted with this, that no man has ever won a victory in
               battle and received a perishable crown, or has administered divine actions, or has
               succeeded in any of the glorious things of excellence, or has got the desire of his
               will even in things not laudable, without having undertaken first labours and
               troubles or without having pushed away alluring thoughts of comfort that gave birth
               to dejection and pusillanimity and caused relaxation in all things? But when the mind
               is zealous in behalf of excellence, the outward senses — smell, touch, hearing, sight
               and taste — do not know what it means to be vanquished by the severe shocks caused by
               foreign influences lying outside the course and dominion of the power of nature.</p>
            <p>When anger influences [a man] naturally, then bodily life appears more despicable
               than dung. When however the heart is spiritually zealous, the body does not suffer by
               troubles, nor does it shrink from terrible things. But the mind faces all temptations
               being like diamond in its endurance.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="536"/>Let us also be zealous with a spiritual zeal for the
               sake of the will of Jesus, then all dejection which causes relaxation in the mind
               will be driven away from us. For zeal causes courage and firmness of soul and
               soundness of body. What power is there in the demons when the soul moves its zeal
               against them with natural vigour?</p>
            <p>Resolution too is said to be the offspring of zeal. And all immoveable vigour which
               is born in the soul when it sets its powers to work, is implanted in it by zeal. Also
               the crowns of confessorship which the victorious martyrs receive on account of their
               endurance are born by this twofold influence of zeal and resolution which have their
               origin in the power of natural anger, [and thus the martyrs] become apathetic against
               the vehement suffering in vexations.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n353-1">1 Cor. 3,18</note>
            <note xml:id="n354-1">Matth. 18,3</note>
            <note xml:id="n354-2">Cf. Gen. 28,18</note>
            <note xml:id="n355-1">Affection?</note>
            <note xml:id="n357-1">Matth. 16,24</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
