<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 33</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 33, pp. 148-149.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="33">
            <pb n="148"/>
            <head>XXXIII</head>
            <p>On the action of divine love</p>
            <p>Now that we have written the above[#n148-1] about spiritual allurements, it is time
               to explain [this idea]. It is a dim power which arises from love in the heart, at
               first without sensible causes, for it sets in motion the temperament, without
               personal vision or practical understanding or reasoning. And therefore it is thought
               to be without cause, because the mind is still vague.</p>
            <pb type="external" n="219"/>
            <p>This is its impression on the untrained. To the perfect the cause is revealed later,
               in connection with examination of it; and then the [impression] is still stronger,
               for delight is moving in the heart. A part of it is reserved in the body by the
               recipient; and another part is sent to the psychic forces. For the heart is in the
               middle between psychic and bodily apperceptions; to the former it belongs
               organically, to the latter naturally. And the recipient directs the taste of its
               action towards both sides. Therefore the world is compelled to depart from it as it
               itself departs from the things of the world. We must necessarily inquire into the
               cause [of this phenomenon]. Love is something hot by nature. And when it alights on
               any one without measure, it renders that soul as it were mad. Therefore the heart
               that perceives it, cannot contain and bear it without unusual excessive variations
               becoming manifest in it. And these signs it publishes in an apperceptive way, openly:
               at once the face becomes reddy and joyous, the body grows hot; fear and bashfulness
               are thrown away and it becomes as it were wanton; the power of concentration flees;
               impetuosity and disturbance reign. His own life forthwith is estimated as nothing in
               comparison with his Friend. Therefore even death, which was more dreadful to him than
               any thing, is the same to him as pleasure. And with all this, the gaze of the mind is
               not free from fantastic thoughts on Him. Afar, he speaks with Him as with one who is
               near. His knowledge inquires into the hidden state of Him who is concealed from
               sight. His <pb n="149"/><pb type="external" n="220"/>gaze is natural and hostile to
               sensual apperception. In his actions, as in his sight, he is enflamed. He dwells in
               solitude, and deliberation entertains itself as it were with a partner and is
               stupefied.</p>
            <p>This passion has enebriated martyrs and, driven by it, apostles have travelled
               through the whole earth in trance, the saints have been tormented, have suffered
               derision and were erring in the wilderness. Composed, they have become deranged;
               wise, they have wilfully become foolish; bashful, they have become wanton with
               discernment; exempt from affections [they have walked] in the flesh. Constantly
               demanding, they have become quiet without compulsion. May we be worthy to reach their
               madness by the compassion of our adorable God. Amen[#n149-1].</p>
            <p>If thou considerest thyself as having peace from the assault of the affections,
               before thou hast entered the town of humility, do not trust this. There is some
               ambush prepared for thee. Expect, after this peace, great trouble from them. While
               passing along all the apartments of virtues, thou wilt not find rest <pb
                  type="external" n="221"/>from thy tribulations nor relief from thy persecutors,
               till thy course will have reached the apartment of humility.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n148-1">End of chapter XXXII</note>
            <note xml:id="n149-1">In the text there follows: "who has taken a mediator from our race
               and given us these things through his hand; who was in all points tempted like as we
               are, yet without sin (Hebrews 4, 15). On account of the equality of his natural flesh
               with ours, eternally without mixture, in the unity preserving the properties of the
               natures, He has made himself worthy of sitting to the right hand. Therefore praise
               and power and adoration to Him, now and in life without end for ever and ever''. The
               passage is lacking in the Greek translation and looks like a Nestorian
               addition.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
