<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 62</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 62, pp. 288-293.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="62">
            <pb n="288"/>
            <head>LXII</head>
            <head>That by the thoughts which stir in a man he knows to which degree he belongs and
               which thoughts follow</head>
            <p>As long as a man is negligent, he fears the hour of death; when, however, he comes
               near to God, the coming of Judgment. But when he proceeds firmly, both kinds of fear
               are taken away. How does this happen? While<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n288-1"/> his knowledge <pb
                  type="external" n="430"/>and his behaviour are of a bodily nature, he is
               frightened by death. But when his knowledge is of a psychic nature, and his behaviour
               is steadfast, his mind is moved by the thought of Judgment every moment. In the first
               state he belongs wholly to nature; in the psychic state he is moved and guided by his
               knowledge and by his discipline. And he is happy in the neighbourhood of God. But
               when he reaches true knowledge by the motion of the apperception of God's mysteries
               and becomes confirmed in future hope, he is consumed by love.[o]</p>
            <p>He that is bodily, fears as an animal fears being slaughtered; he who is rational
               fears the Judgment of God. He that has become a son, is pleasing to love, not to the
               staff of him who terrifies. 'I and my house, we will serve the Lord'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n288-1"/>. For
               love annihilates fear. It not only <choice><sic>felars</sic><corr>fears</corr></choice> not but it even longs after
               departure. Love is the dissolver of temporary life. He that has reached the love of
               God, does not desire to stay here any more.</p>
            <p>My beloved ones, because I was foolish, I could not bear to guard the secret in
               silence, but am become mad, for the sake of my brethren's profit. For true love is
               not able to cling to the cause of love apart from friends.</p>
            <p>Oft when I was writing these things, my fingers paused on the paper. They could not
               bear the delight which had fallen into the heart and which made the senses silent.
               Blessed is he that is in constant intercourse with God and has withdrawn himself from
               worldly things, being with Him only, in intercourse founded upon his knowledge. And
               if he has to be patient, it will not be long before he sees fruits.</p>
            <pb n="289"/>
            <p><pb type="external" n="431"/>Gladness in God is <choice><sic>tronger</sic><corr>stronger</corr></choice> than earthly
               life. He that has found it, is not only free from the trial of the affections, but he
               does not even turn towards his life any longer. Furthermore he has no other
               apperception, if he really has been deemed worthy of this.</p>
            <p>Love is sweeter than life. And understanding concerning God, from which love is born,
               is sweeter than honey and honeycomb. What is the sweetness of love which excels life?
               Love is not spiteful if it has to undergo a myriad of deaths for the sake of its
               friends.</p>
            <p>Love is the child of knowledge, knowledge the child of health of soul. Health of soul
               is a power born from patient endurance. And what is knowledge? The apperception of
               immortal life. What is immortal life? Apperception in God. Knowledge concerning God
               is the highest of all desirable things. And the heart that has received it, does not
               want the sweetness of anything on the earth. Because to the sweetness of the
               knowledge concerning God nothing is to be compared.</p>
            <p>O Lord, fill my heart with life everlasting. Life everlasting is consolation in God.
               He that has found consolation in God, to him the consolation of the world is
               superfluous. How is it perceived in a man that he has received wisdom from the
               Spirit? Thereby, that wisdom teaches him kinds of humbleness, internally and by his
               senses; then it is revealed to him in his intellect, how humbleness is acquired.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="432"/>How is it to be perceived that he has reached
               humbleness? Thereby that it is a vile thing to him to please this world by act or
               word, and thereby that the glory of this world is ugly in his eyes.</p>
            <p>What are the affections? The allurements that lie in the things and the stories of
               this world, evoking a bodily want, which never cease as long as the world exists. If
               a man however has been deemed worthy [to know] the divine intellect and to taste and
               perceive what is more profitable than those things, their allurements will not enter
               his heart, because their place has been taken by a desire which is better than those.
               Then the allurements of [worldly] things and those which are born from them, will no
               longer approach his heart. But they will stand outside idle. Not that the allurements
               of the affections do not exist any longer, but the heart which could <pb n="290"
               />receive them is dead to them and living to some other thing. Not that it desists
               from watchfulness and the labour of discrimination, but there is no longer any
               struggle in the mind, in as much as the inner being is satisfied by the delight of
               some other thing. So, when a man is satisfied with delicious and fat food, and his
               inner being with abundance and delight, and then he sees food which is unclean and
               steeped in its own filth, his inner being does not need care to check it from desire
               or to withhold it from gazing at it with lust; nay, the whole inner being is even
               shaken and troubled by the sight <pb type="external" n="433"/>of it. This does not
               happen on account of the uncleanness of the food, for possibly he had been accustomed
               to it before; but on account of the comparison with the excellence of that other food
               which had filled his inner being with every delight. So it is with the health of the
               soul. If the heart has really received the apperception of spiritual things and the
               contemplation of the world to be, its inner being will regard the affections in the
               way mentioned.</p>
            <p>And just as a man when he loses his riches and becomes poor and destitute of the
               glorious and excellent food in which he delighted in the royal palace, forgets its
               delicious taste, and those glorious dishes are no longer with him and his stomach is
               deprived of the delight of their abundance, and he has necessarily to turn towards
               food which is by far inferior — so it is with him that was deemed worthy of health of
               soul. If he is deprived of that divine delight because he neglects his duty and falls
               asleep and becomes neglectful he again turns towards that sordid food, that has been
               steeped in all filth and which is unclean; and his inner being does not examine,
               because the stomach of his soul is empty. For to the hungry soul even bitter things
               are sweet.</p>
            <p>And farther: no one to whom a treasure is entrusted will indulge in sleep. If he
               keeps the law of watchfulness and <pb type="external" n="434"/>clings to the labour
               of discernment, and through knowledge derived from these drinks in life, the struggle
               of the allurements of the affections will not approach his mind at all. And these
               allurements will not be held back with effort from entering the heart, but the
               satiety of the inner soul which is full of knowledge, and the desire of amazing
               visions which is found in it, restrain them from approaching to man with their
               intercourse. This does not happen, as I have said, while man <pb n="291"/>desists
               from watchfulness and from the labour of discrimination which are the guardians of
               true knowledge and of psychic light; but it happens without the mind being involved
               in struggle, for the reasons which have been expounded.</p>
            <p>The food of the poor is despicable to the rich and the nutriment of the sick to the
               healthy. But riches and health are established through watchfulness and diligence.
               This is witnessed to by nature. As long as a man lives he needs watchfulness and
               diligence and alertness in order to guard his treasure. But if he leaves his
               territory, he becomes ill and is robbed [of his possessions]. For a long time even he
               will possess strength through his previous health, but when this does not increase,
               he will become a prey to weakness and indigence. Does not even nature instruct us
               concerning these things? And is there any heavenly thing which cannot be discussed in
               a comparison which we find in our nature? Even our Lord used to confirm all spiritual
               things by examples from nature and in this way He used to establish their power in
               our souls; not only things relating to the shortliving earthly pawn, but also those
               belonging to the true body, and the <pb type="external" n="435"/>completion and the
               truth of our future. Do not wonder at what I have said. There is not only work to be
               done till the fruit shows itself, but even till the time of gathering the fruit there
               is still work to be done. By the time of gathering the fruit I mean the grave. It may
               occur that, when the fruit has become ripe, hail of a sudden will strike it.</p>
            <p>He that mingles with things and proceeds to have intercourse, cannot be certain that
               his health will stay with him. I say: using and seeing [are the same]. O <persName>Jesus</persName>
               Christ, king of the worlds, make me worthy of desire in Thee. The man who adheres to
               intercourse with God, and who has mingled his life with it, is greater than any other
               man on the earth and [greater] than any service performed by rational creatures. When
               thou prayest unto God, say to Him only this: O Lord make me worthy of becoming dead
               to the intercourse with this world, in truth. — So thou canst comprehend the whole
               prayer. And try diligently to accomplish this in thyself in reality. If prayer is
               followed by practice, thou surely art standing in the freedom of Christ.</p>
            <p>Being dead to the world is not only this that a man keeps himself far from mingling
               with [worldly] things. But this is <pb n="292"/>being dead to the world in truth:
               that a man in<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n292-1"/> his mind does not long after the goods of the world.</p>
            <p>If we are accustomed to beautiful meditation, we are <choice><sic>eshamed</sic><corr>ashamed</corr></choice> of the
               affections when we come in contact with them (this is known by those who have
               experienced it in their soul), and so we shall be ashamed to approach unto their
               causes.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="436"/>If thou desirest to cling to some work for the sake of
               the love of God, then set death as the limit of thy desire for it. So by practising
               it, thou wilt be elevated unto the degree of martyrdom through every suffering and
               injury which smites thee within the domain of death, if thou perseverest till the end
               without giving way. Meditating upon a feeble deliberation weakens the power of
               patience. But the confirmed mind imparts a strength which does not belong to nature,
               to him that adheres to its contemplation. O Lord, make me worthy of hating my life,
               for the sake of life in Thee.</p>
            <p>Dealings in this world resemble a copy of a book which is still in rough draft. What
               a man desires or whenever he wishes, something can be added to or taken from it, and
               so he may alter his writing. Future dealings resemble documents drawn up as bonds,
               provided with the seal of the king, to or from which it is not allowed to add or
               subtract anything. As long as we are in the place where altering is possible, let us
               observe ourselves; and while we have authority over our lifebook and our book is
               still between our hands, let us zealously add [acts of] beautiful behaviour, and let
               us scratch from it the loss of the old behaviour without freedom. We are allowed to
               scratch out faults, as long as we are here. And God will take into account every
               alteration we make in it. May we be deemed worthy of life everlasting before we
               appear before the king, and He puts His seal on the book<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n292-2"/>. As long as we are
               in this world, God will not put His seal <pb type="external" n="437"/>neither on our
               good works nor on our bad ones, before the hour of departure, when we have completed
               the service of our country and we prepare to strike camp.</p>
            <p>So it is becoming for us, as the blessed <persName>Mar Ephraim</persName> says, that we make our soul
               resemble at all times a ship that is prepared [for sea]. When the wind [required] for
               her will blow, <pb n="293"/>she does not know. And the army does not know when the
               trumpet will give the sign to start; and to the tenant it is not known when the
               landlord will give the command to depart. Now if these are thus prepared for the sake
               of a short absence, as they will soon turn perhaps and come back, how much more is it
               becoming for us to be prepared and ready before the long absence of the day of death.
               May Christ, the mediator of our life, grant us to reach that long bridge and the gate
               of the new world, in a state of preparation. To whom be glory for ever and ever.
               Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n288-1">Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n288-2">Joshua 24,15</note>
            <note xml:id="n292-1">The text has: in the intercourse or occupation of his mind</note>
            <note xml:id="n292-2">Cf. the Muslim doctrine of the <foreign xml:lang="ar">خواتيم</foreign></note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
