<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 53</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="53">
            <head>LIII</head>
            <head>On prayer and other things which are necessarily to be sought<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n254-1"/> in constant
               recollection and which it is very profitable for a man to recite with discrimination
               and to retain</head>
            <p>That a man have trust in the petition of his prayer through trust in God, is the
               chief part of the gift of faith. The assurance of faith in God is not a correct
               confession, though this is the mother of faith, but a soul that looks on the truth of
               God by the power of behaviour. When thou findest faith and what is related to it, in
               the holy scriptures mingled with behaviour, do not consider it in the sense of true
               confession. Faith which gives the conviction of trust is never demanded by the
               imperfect, or by those whose mind is perverted so that it cannot attain truth. The
               assurance of truth reveals itself in the soul — in accordance with the elevation that
               is the result of behaviour — in an attitude which tends toward the legislation of our
               Lord.</p>
            <p>The light of the soul consists in constant meditation upon the scriptures. For they
               trace in the intellect profitable recollections with regard to watchfulness against
               the affections and for perpetual abiding with God, in love and in purity of
               prayer.</p>
            <pb n="255"/>
            <p>They trace before us the way which is made peaceful by <pb type="external" n="380"
               />the steps of the saints. Yet do not confide in the signs of the words when they are
               not accompanied by great alertness and perpetual affectability through constant
               prayers. Accept without doubt words that are spoken from experience, even if they are
               uttered by a simple man. Even the great treasury of earthly kings does not abhor to
               take increase from the money of the mendicant. And from small sources the large
               streams of the rivers increase.</p>
            <p>If the recollection of the excellent renews in us the desire of excellence when we
               commune with them mentally, the recollection of the impudent also renews in our mind
               impure desire when we are reminded of them. This is because the recollection of all
               these develops in our mind the distinct lines of their deeds. And with their finger
               as it were they show us their evil deeds or the elevation of their behaviour, in
               accord with their belonging to one or to the other kind. And the recollection with
               its stings — be they right or left ones — spurns us to meditate upon the baseness of
               our mind (while the images of their noble behaviour are depicted in our imaginations)
               and to look upon them zealously.</p>
            <p>So not only the meditation upon evil injures those who are captured by it, but also
               the sight and the recollection of those who perform evil. And not only is the
               performing of excellent things greatly profitable to those who accomplish them, but
               also the imaginative representation formed by the recollection of the persons who
               perform those things. And on account of <pb type="external" n="381"/>this it can be
               understood that those who are near to reaching the stage of purity, are deemed worthy
               of seeing perpetually holy men in nightly visions. And during the whole day the
               images of the saints which are printed in their soul are to them a source of joy by
               their intellectual intercourse with them. And on account of this they turn with
               renewed fervour towards the performance of good works and an intense fire of love
               unto excellence is kindled in them.</p>
            <p>It is said that the holy angels assume the appearance of honoured and excellent men
               and show themselves to the soul in visions during sleep when the emotions are
               distracted, for the sake of joy and higher incitement. And during the day they set
               [the solitary] astir by the recollection of the visions, and so they are fired anew
               to their labour by their joy at <pb n="256"/>those holy men. And so the latter are
               promoters of the former's course. In the same way, at the time of the heat of battle,
               those who are accustomed to evil intercourse, are visited by the demons in this
               likeness. They assume a likeness in which they show themselves to the soul, namely
               visions highly exciting amidst the recollections of the day to those who converse
               with these. Sometimes also they do this by frightful visions which terrify the soul
               and weaken it, and which accentuate the difficulty of behaviour in solitude and
               reclusion, and the like.</p>
            <p>We ought therefore, o my brethren, to use discrimination regarding recollections, in
               our meditation, [choosing] which of them we should cherish and which we should dispel
               hastily as soon as they approach our mind, according to whether they <pb
                  type="external" n="382"/>proceed from the activity of the demons who provide the
               affections with matter, or from desire or anger, or from the holy angels such as give
               indications that cause joy and knowledge and profit by the deliberations which they
               excite through their offerings to us, or by the recollection and perception of former
               deeds some of which stir in the soul deliberations that are useful in any
               direction.</p>
            <p>Experience concerning the two we must acquire by discriminating knowledge, as also
               experience concerning their aspect, their intercourse, even concerning their way of
               working. Each of the two has at once to be met with a distinct prayer.</p>
            <p>Love which is maintained by [outward] things is to be compared with a small flame
               whose light subsists by the sustenance of oil; and with a stream subsisting through
               rain, and whose flow ceases as soon as the supply which maintains it becomes
               deficient. Love of which God is the cause, is as a source welling from the depth,
               whose current will never cease. For He alone is the source of love whose supply does
               not fail.</p>
            <p>Thou desirest to perform the recitation of Psalms during thy service with delight,
               and thou wishest to perceive the spiritual words which thou recitest? Abandon the
               performance of a certain quantity and ignore the measures of service; and say the
               words in the way of prayer, and leave the usual iteration. Understand what I say. As
               to those sections which bear the character of a history, let thy spirit consider
               their repetition as the recitation of some providential act of God, in order that by
               the deep significance which is in them the soul be <pb type="external" n="383"
               />awakened unto amazement at Providence; and from here it <pb n="257"/>may be stirred
               to praises or to profitable affection. The passages which are prayers, take them unto
               thyself. When thy mind has become established in them, confusion has given way and
               disappeared. For in the service of bondage there is no peace of mind, nor is there
               trouble of confusion in the liberty of the children. For confusion is wont to suck
               away the taste of insights and to rob them of their intellect, as the leech which
               with the blood of the limbs sucks the vitality of the body. For it is possible, to
               say of confusion that it is the mount of Satan even. Satan, as a chariot-driver, is
               wont to ride on it constantly, taking with him a multitude of affections. Thus he
               invades the poor soul making use of the darkness of its confusion.</p>
            <p>And this thou hast to understand clearly, lest in the sentences of thy recited Psalms
               and of thy prayer thou becomest a conductor of words as if they came from a strange
               person. For thou shouldst not think that thou art sedulously promoting the work of
               the apostles if thou art wholly devoid of the passion and the joy which is in it. But
               thou shouldst say the words beseechingly, as originating in thyself, with
               intelligence and with passionate discrimination, as one who is aware of his being
               occupied with ritual of his own. Dejection is caused by distraction of mind;
               distraction by neglect of labours and recitation and by intercourse left to
               chance.</p>
            <p>Not to use conversation with those who speak to us, but <pb type="external" n="384"
               />to cut off their speech entreatingly, is a sign of a mind that has found wisdom and
               power by grace. For its true knowledge frees it from much labour; and by its treading
               short ways it cuts off the many windings of a long way. For we have not at all times
               the power to reduce to silence all contrary deliberations by arguments, and it may
               happen, when we receive a blow, that for a long time we shall not be healed.</p>
            <p>Against those who are six thousand years old thou wilt stand thy trial. But they also
               are provided with means which may destroy thee, being mightier than thy wisdom and
               thy learning. But even if thou vanquishest, the dirt of their deliberations will
               defile thy mind and their stinking odour will linger in thy smell. But by the former
               method<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n257-1"/> thou wilt be free from all these and from fear, because there is no
               helper like God.</p>
            <pb n="258"/>
            <p>Perpetual tears during prayer are a sign of divine mercy of which the soul is worthy
               because of its repentance which has been accepted; and with tears it begins to enter
               the plain of serenity. Unless the deliberations have been freed from the care of
               transitory things and have cast away the hope of the world and contempt for it has
               been established in them and they have begun to prepare provisions for the day of a
               man's departure, because the thought of things beyond earthly ones has been
               established<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n258-1"/> in the soul — it is not possible that the eyes shed <pb
                  type="external" n="385"/>tears. Tears originate from pure meditation without
               distraction and from perpetual meditations without deviation, and by some subtle
               recollection which falls into the mind and affects the heart by the anxiety it
               causes. Then tears become frequent.</p>
            <p>When thou turnest towards perpetual handiwork in thy solitude, do not make the
               commandment of the fathers a pretext for love of money. In order to avoid despondency
               thou must have some trifling occupation which does not trouble the mind. If however
               thou desirest to bestow more care upon it, for the sake of alms, know then that the
               order of prayer is more excellent than alms; if thou desirest to do so because of thy
               need, without being covetous, that which is sufficient to fulfill thy want is what
               our Lord provides thee with. He never has left His servants in want of transitory
               things. Seek ye first the kingdom of God and His righteousness, and all these things
               shall be added unto you, before ye ask, says our Lord<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n258-2"/>.</p>
            <p>One of the saints<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n258-3"/> has said: it is not the aim of thy discipline that thou
               shouldst appease the hungry and that thy cell <choice><sic>chould</sic><corr>should</corr></choice> become a place of
               congregation for strangers. For this behaviour is rather meet for those who are in
               the world, but <choice><sic>nor</sic><corr>not</corr></choice> for solitaries who are free from thoughts of visible things
               and who preserve their mind by prayer. If ever thou wilt be deemed worthy of the
               solitary state and avoid heavy <pb type="external" n="386"/>loads in the kingdom of
               its freedom, let not the customary thought of fear terrify thee with its many and
               varying deliberations. But as a man who believes that there is a guardian with him
               and who knows <choice><sic>occurately</sic><corr>accurately</corr></choice> through his wisdom that he and all creatures
               are under one Lord, and that one will moves them all and stops and governs them, and
               that no fellow is able to injure his comrade without the commandment <pb n="259"/>of
               the Governor, and that all is under His care — make up thy mind to be courageous. For
               though some of them have been given freedom, yet they have no freedom in all things,
               and neither the demons nor the beasts of prey, nor malicious men are able to injure
               any man according to their good pleasure, until the divine will has given the command
               and until material opportunity has been given. It is not granted by the divine will
               that all freedom should realize itself, otherwise no flesh could live. For the Lord
               does not allow the freedom of demons or man to approach his creatures that they use
               it according to their good pleasure.</p>
            <p>So thou hast to say to thyself: there is a guardian with me and there is no
               possibility for any of the creatures even to show themselves to me, if no permission
               from on high has been given. So if thou seest with thy eyes and hearest with thy ears
               their threatenings, even then thou must not believe that they will venture to act. If
               they had received an order <pb type="external" n="387"/>from the heavenly will, no
               speech and even not a word even would be necessary, but action would immediately
               follow will. And if this be the will of my Lord (so say to thyself), that the evil
               ones have power in his creation, then I must not resist this fact as if I were one
               taking pleasure in contradicting the will of his Lord. Thus, even in thy temptations,
               thou shalt be full of gladness, as one who knows and feels that his Lord is governor.
               Support therefore thy heart by confidence in the faith in the Lord without being
               afraid for the terror by night nor for the arrow that flies by day<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n259-1"/>. For the
               faith of the righteous in God makes the beasts of the field as lambs and
               goats<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n259-2"/>. It is namely impossible to be a righteous man confiding in God unless
               this be true of thee, that for the sake of the service of righteousness thou art gone
               into the desert with its many troubles and that for it thou art administering the
               will of God. So thou labourest in vain when thou takest upon thee these pains. For
               God does not wish the pains of mankind, but that thou offer to Him as a sacrifice of
               love thy personal affections. All those who love God show Him this distinctive [sign
               of love] that they are willing to bear troubles for the sake of His love. For all
               those who desire to live in the fear of God through Jesus Christ, bear troubles. And
               then He makes them rule over his hidden treasures.</p>
            <pb n="260"/>
            <p>One of the saints has said: There was an old, honoured solitary to whom I once went
               when I was shaken by <pb type="external" n="388"/>temptations. He was ill and had to
               lie down. When I had greeted him I sat down near him and said: Pray for me, Father,
               for I am very much shaken by the temptations of the demons. He opened his eyes and
               looked at me <choice><sic>benignanthy</sic><corr>benignantly</corr></choice>, saying. My son, thou art a boy; God will not
               admit the demons unto thee. I answered: If I am a boy I have to bear the temptations
               of strong men. Then he said to me: So God is trying to make thee wise. I said to him:
               How can I become wise, if I taste death every day? He said to me: God loves thee; be
               silent, God shall give thee His gift. Then he said to me: Thou must know, my son,
               that I have been making war upon the demons during thirty years, of which I have
               passed twenty without enjoying any help whatever. When twenty five years had elapsed,
               rest began to show itself. As it approached, it increased and when twenty eight years
               had passed it had grown considerably. And now that thirty years have been
               accomplished rest has increased to such a degree, that I know not how this can
               happen. — Further he said: When I desire to stand performing service, I am allowed to
               accomplish one marmita<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n260-1"/>. Further, even if I remain standing during three
               days, I am in ecstasy with God, without perceiving fatigue. — Behold how prolonged
               labours produce illimitable rest.</p>
            <p>One of the Fathers used to eat two times every week. He <pb type="external" n="389"
               />said to us: 'The day on which I speak with someone, I am not able to keep the usual
               rule of fasting, but I am compelled to break it'. So we understand that the keeping
               of the tongue not only does excite the mind unto God but that it also in secret
               grants considerable force for the accomplishment of the visible labours which are
               performed through the body. And on account of a hidden service the intellect will
               constantly be illuminated, as our Fathers say. For keeping the tongue excites the
               heart unto God, if we be silent with knowledge.</p>
            <p>This saint was much given to vigils saying: When of a night I stand till dawn and
               take rest after the recitation of Psalms, and then wake up from sleep, on that day I
               am as a man who is not in this world. No single earthly thought <pb n="261"/>rises in
               my heart, nor do I want definite regulations, but all day I am in ecstasy.</p>
            <p>On one day such as this in which I was wont to take food (and since four days I had
               not eaten), when I rose in order to perform the evening service and to eat
               afterwards, I stood in the room of my cell in full sunlight. I perceived only that I
               began with the marmita which is the beginning of the service; but till the next day
               when the sun rose before me and the clothes on my body became warm, I did not
               perceive where I was. As the sun troubled me by burning my face my mind came back to
               me and behold, I saw that it was a <pb type="external" n="390"/>new day. And I
               thanked God because of His pouring out His grace upon mankind and because of His
               deeming worthy of such a greatness those who seek Him.</p>
            <p>Here end the tales of holy men.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n254-1"> Bedjan's ܕܬܒܥܢܢ is a misprint for ܡܬܒܥܝܢ</note>
            <note xml:id="n257-1">viz. by cutting off discussions</note>
            <note xml:id="n258-1">Reading ܒܕܕܠܬ</note>
            <note xml:id="n258-2">Matthew 6,33</note>
            <note xml:id="n258-3">Perhaps Euagrius; cf. Book of the Dove, p. 30</note>
            <note xml:id="n259-1">Psalm 91,5</note>
            <note xml:id="n259-2">Cf. Book of the Dove, p. 80</note>
            <note xml:id="n260-1">a fifteenth part of the psalter.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
