<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 32</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 32, pp. 146-148.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="32">
            <head>XXXII</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="216"/>On the aim of guarding the heart and on subtle
               speculation that looks into the apartment</p>
            <p>Let there not be hidden to thy knowledge the power that lies in spiritual songs, when
               we use it with understanding. For it turns the deliberation away from the world. It
               also drives distraction from the mind, though it is reputed to be useful for children
               [only]. The unsteady mind profits by it at once. Spiritual allurements are more
               valuable against the affections than the force of knowledge. When thou art alone,
               guard thy heart by them if thou possessest not yet the force to be watchful in thy
               being, through contemplation which is familiar intercourse with the knowledge of
               discernment; or — if this is not [sufficient] — by the constant recollection of the
               departure from the body and by the recollection of things expected and hoped for;
               this must be accompanied by [the fulfilling of] the duties which cause delight,
               namely: the withdrawal from things which cause emotions, and the little observances
               within the cell. If, after long slavery, thou findest that thy harbour is to be
               reached with freedom, pursue it [in this way]. If thou seest that this is a foolish
               method, combine it with [the practice of] the law. For here it is easy to be
               rectified.</p>
            <p>While with these and such variations thou advancest with insight, in a ship loaded
               with the treasures of the cell — a great festival full of the
               <choice><sic>marchandise</sic><corr>merchandise</corr></choice> of the virtuous — then look with subtlety at the unequal
               children which are born to thee from apperceptive variations. Thou wilt namely see
               how every spiritual delight is preceded by the pains of the cross; <pb
                  type="external" n="217"/>how the pleasure of sin, however, is born from bodily
               comfort; [and thou wilt see] why in the harbour of chastity, spiritual love is caused
               by spiritual contemplation, which heals the mind. There is nothing secondary without
               a preceding cause, nor a third virtue without a foregoing one. Thou wilt find growing
                  <pb n="147"/>in the womb of chastity the wings with which the mind ascends unto
               divine love, in which one may venture to approach the cloud[l].</p>
            <p>This insight will give a man a considerable force, so as to mingle watchfulness with
               his affairs, and incitement unto zealous efforts.</p>
            <p>Behaviour without eyes will prove idle. For it quickly brings about dejectedness on
               account of distraction. Pray our Lord that He endow thy behaviour with eyes. Then joy
               will begin to sprout; then troubles will become sweet to thee as honey comb; then
               thou wilt think thy enclosure a festival chamber.</p>
            <p>It is not possible to vanquish the affections without apperceptive virtues, nor
               fortuitous distraction without intercourse with spiritual knowledge. Our mind is an
               agile thing; if it is not bound to an object with discernment, it will not cease to
               be distracted. And if the antecedents have not been fulfilled, there is no room for
               such a process. For there is no peace without victory over the enemies. And if peace
               does not reign, [how is it possible] to find that which lies beyond peace?</p>
            <p>Affections are the fence of hidden virtues. If they are not vanquished first by the
               manifest virtues, it is not possible to see <pb type="external" n="218"/>what lies
               within them. For it is not possible for one standing without a wall, to speak about
               what is within. It is not possible to see the sun in a cloud, nor the natural virtues
               of the soul among the trouble of perpetual affections.</p>
            <p>Pray God that He may give thee to perceive spiritual allurements. If these take hold
               of thy soul the world will depart from thee and thou from the world. But they cannot
               be perceived without solitude and emaciation and attentive intercourse with
               recitation. Without the latter thou must not pray for the former. If thou prayest for
               the former without [these virtues], they will change quickly and become of a bodily
               nature. Who is able to understand, will understand. It has pleased the wise Lord that
               we should eat this bread with sweat; not for malignity, but lest we should be
               attacked by a malady of the stomach and die.</p>
            <p>Every virtue which is the mother of a second, which is anterior to it, is a viper to
               the souls of those who find it, <choice><sic>it</sic><corr>if</corr></choice> they do not cast it from them quickly.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
