<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 81</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 81, pp. 379-384.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="81">
            <pb n="379"/>
            <head>LXXXI</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="566"/>An answer to a brother who had asked him why when our
               Lord has defined mercy as similitude to the greatness of the Father in Heaven the
               solitaries honour solitude more than it? And an apology of this point and that it is
               not becoming to neglect the distressed and sick when they are near</p>
            <p>It is well that thou hast brought forward from the Gospel a comparison and a tested
               example for the great duty of solitude, as if we were opponents to it or tried to
               reject it as something superfluous. For our Lord has defined mercy as the similitude
               to the Father by which those who perform it, can approach Him. This is true. And we,
               the solitaries, do not honour solitude without mercy, though we try to remain far
               from care and trouble, as much as possible. Not that we deny necessary things, when
               they present themselves, but we care for solitude, because in it we are constantly
               with God in lonely intercourse, by which it is more possible to be purified from
               perturbance and to approach unto quiet of mind, though such cases are rare. But when
               it is necessary, we will not neglect mercifulness, compelling ourselves perpetually
               to be inwardly full of mercy toward all kinds of rational beings, at all times.</p>
            <p>For so the doctrine of our Lord orders, and this is the distinction of our solitude,
               and it is not due to fortune. So <pb type="external" n="567"/>none of us neglects to
               show this inward virtue, — when the time corresponds with the work and the necessity
               — making known his love openly, by deeds; especially those who have not laid
               themselves wholly under the rule of solitude do so. But solitude to such ones means
               that they never meet anyone, except once a week. They have not cut themselves off, by
               the definition of their rule, from showing their fellow man deeds of mercy; only that
               one does so who is very devoted and solitary so that he avoids the sight of men. For
               we know, that without love of the fellow-man, the mind is not able to become
               illuminated by intercourse with and love unto God. Therefore, which of the says
               solitaries, who possessed food and <pb n="380"/>clothing, could see his neighbour
               hungry and naked and persevere in withholding his hand?</p>
            <p>Or which of them, when his brother according to the flesh was sick and tormented and
               destitute of visitors, has honoured the rule of his reclusion more than the life of
               his fellow, on account of love of solitude?</p>
            <p>Where, however, such circumstances, are not at hand, we keep in mind love and mercy
               unto the fellow man. Where practice is near, God demands from us plainly that we
               perform it actually.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="568"/>This is well known, that if we have acquired nothing, we
               are not allowed to expose ourselves to care and disturbance for the sake of the poor.
               But it is demanded of us [to give] from what we have.</p>
            <p>And when our dwelling place is far from the habitation of men and from intercourse
               with and sight of them, it is not necessary for us to leave our cell and our solitary
               and lonely dwelling-place and proceed erring through the world in order to visit the
               sick and to be occupied with similar practice. For it is known that he that does so
               descends from greatness to smallness.</p>
            <p>If however the recluse live in the dwelling place of many and is near to men through
               his constant dwelling with them, and he can take rest when others are fatigued — be
               he healthy or ill — it is incumbent upon him to occupy himself with practice, without
               asking largely from others. But if he see the brother according to the flesh and to
               profession, in trouble, or rather: Christ rejected and vexed, and he flee and hide
               himself, pretending a sham solitude — he that acts thus, is without mercy.</p>
            <p>Do not remind me of John of Thebais and Arsenius and the like. For who has given
               himself to such deeds and cared for the sick or the poor, and has despised solitude?
               Do not approach unto their stories. For if thou art far from all comfort and all
               meeting with men as they were, thou art allowed to despise such works of [practice].
               If however thou art far <pb type="external" n="569"/>from the state of the perfect
               and continually occupied with bodily labours and occupations, why then doest thou
               despise a commandment which suits thy measure, taking refuge with the grand behaviour
               of the saints, a behaviour to which thou art not near?</p>
            <pb n="381"/>
            <p>As to me, I will not neglect to cite the example of Macarius the Great, which was
               written, as it were, to rebuke those who despise their brethren. One day he went to
               visit some one who was sick. When he asked him whether he desired anything, he
               answered: I want some fresh bread. Those solitaries, namely, usually baked bread for
               a year; so was the custom of those places. Then that blessed man, who was ninety
               years old, went from Skete (to) the town of Alexandria, forty miles and more,
               carrying with him dry bread in his cowl. There he changed it and brought the sick
               what he desired.</p>
            <p>And an other, who was his equal, did what is still greater, a certain Agathon,
               exquisite above all the solitaries of his time, a man who loved silence and solitude
               better than all others. Once he went to a festival, in order to sell what he had made
               with his hands. There he found a stranger, lying in the street, sick. He hired a
               house and stayed with him, working with his hands and making expenses on his behalf
               and paying the hire of the house. So he served him for six months, till the sick had
               recovered. Then he said, as the story runs, I <pb type="external" n="570"/>wished
               that I could find a leper and give him my body and take his. — This is perfect love;
               let us resemble our Fathers, that we may be thought worthy of grace, as they
               were.</p>
            <p>Those who fear God, my beloved, are provided for so that they keep the commandments
               of our Lord without difficulty, even although that seems possible to them only
               through labours, and danger is thought to be incurred for its sake. Christ has
               defined and limited their totality to two commandments, which make up the sum of them
               all. I mean the love of God, and what He taught to be the like of this: love unto His
               image. The possession of the former is the aim of spiritual contemplation; that of
               the second, of contemplation and practice. Now, because God's nature is simple and
               not composite and invisible and not subject to want, the heart in its occupation
               equally does not require practice, nor bodily performance, nor material motion. Its
               performance is simple, and, on account of partial union in the [human] intellect, is
               in accordance with the simple nature of its adorable cause, which is exalted above
               the apperception of the senses and the flesh.</p>
            <p>The second commandment, love of mankind, is to be accomplished in a double way, in
               accordance with its double nature. I mean, that we accomplish it with the heart,
               invisibly, and <pb n="382"/>at the same time with the body, manifestly; but those
               things which are accomplished by practice, happen also in secret and in cooperation
               with the heart.</p>
            <p>For, as man's nature is composed of two parts, — namely body and soul — so all things
               regarding him are provided <pb type="external" n="571"/>in a double way, in
               accordance with the double character of his constitution. As everywhere practice is
               anterior to contemplation, so it is impossible for man to elevate himself unto that
               elevated part, unless he has accomplished before, by practice, that which is
               lower.</p>
            <p>Therefore, let no one venture to speak concerning the acquisition of love of his
               fellowmen, as if he possessed it already in his soul, if the part is still wanting
               which has to be accomplished by the body, according to the opportunity for practice
               granted by strength, time and place. Then by faith has to be acquired that part of
               love which is received and recognized by the heart. When, on account of these things,
               we have been made ourselves known as faithful and true, as far as possible, then
               power is given to the soul to stretch itself towards the grand part of exalted and
               divine contemplation, by means of simple emotions and without comparison.</p>
            <p>Where man has no opportunity to fulfill love of his fellow man practically by visible
               and by bodily things, it is sufficient in the eyes of God, that we keep love of our
               fellowman with our mind only, especially if we are able constantly to administer the
               service of that universal part, that is more excellent. If however we are destitute
               of the totality of that universal part, we should fill up this gap by the lower
               commandment, namely by apperceptible practice, consisting therein that, according to
               the time happening, we should provide for the comfort of our brethren, by wearying
               our body; lest our liberty <pb type="external" n="572"/>become an opportunity for the
               flesh, in that we should occupy ourselves with idle things under the pretext of
               lonely intercourse. For it is known, that it is not allowed to demand from him who is
               wholly deprived of human intercourse and who is wholly occupied with God, being dead
               to all beings because of his being deprived of them — that he should serve men.</p>
            <p>He, however, whose rule of solitude forbids intercourse except on one day every week,
               and who, after the completion of his rule, meeting and mingling and consoling himself
               with <pb n="383"/>man, neglects the trouble of his brethren and pretends to keep the
               rule of his week of prohibition, is anathema. For it is manifest that it is through a
               lack of mercy and on account of presumption and fallacious deliberations that such a
               one does not condescend to occupy himself with such things.</p>
            <p>He that neglects the sick, shall not see light. And who turns away his face from one
               in distress, may his day be dark. And who despises the cry of the vexed, may the sons
               of his house grope in darkness.</p>
            <p>Let us not dishonour the great name of solitude by our ignorance. Every duty has its
               time and place and distinction. And then its service is accepted by God who knows
               all. The service that deviates from this, is idle; for all measures have to be
               brought to completion.</p>
            <p>He that hopes that he will be consoled and visited in his misery by others, has to
               humble himself, so that he may be of use to his fellow man when the latter is
               tempted. Then during his service in solitude he may be joyful and free from
               presumption and the seduction of the demons.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="573"/>It has been said by one of the holy Fathers, Euagrius,
               one of the initiated, that there is nothing which frees the solitary from the demon
               of haughtiness and aids to the attainment of the domain of chastity when the passion
               of fornication is burning, as to visit those who are thrown on their bed and vexed by
               bodily troubles. Great is the angelic service of solitude, when it is mingled with
               such a discrimination, for humbleness is needed. For we are are plundered without our
               knowing it.</p>
            <p>We have not said these things, my brethren, that we should despise the duty of
               solitude; for we have everywhere insisted upon it. We are not now found to contradict
               our own words, and no one should pick out a single word from our argumentation and
               take this in his hand without discrimination, neglecting the rest. For I remember
               that in several places I have said with emphasis, that if a man should happen to be
               in his cell in total idleness, on account of the necessity of weakness, even then he
               should not choose to leave it completely and to perform his service outside it rather
               than to be idle, within. I have spoken of leaving the cell completely; but if a
               necessary practice presents itself, which demands some weeks, during which he may
               gain relief or the life of a fellow-man, he should not deem this idleness. If there
               is anyone who thinks <pb n="384"/>himself to be one of the perfect and exalted above
               all that is here, on account of his continually being with God, and his <pb
                  type="external" n="574"/>being far from all visible practice, he rightly withdraws
               himself even from these things. Great is the labour of discrimination, to him that is
               spoken to by God. May He in His mercy, give us to accomplish the work of Him that has
               said: Therefore all things whatsoever ye would that men should do to you, do ye even
               so to them[#n384-1]. To whom be glory and honour from the whole creation for ever and
               ever. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n384-1">Matthew 7,12</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
