<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 25</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 25, pp. 124-128.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="25">
            <pb n="124"/>
            <head>XXV</head>
            <head>The opportunities of the soul that seeks profound contemplation to immerse itself in
               it and so to escape from bodily deliberations which arise from things recollected</head>
            <p>Every<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n124-1"/> thing that is above another one is concealed from what is beneath it.
               And this is not caused by its being covered <pb type="external" n="183"/>by other
               bodies. For it possesses naturally the faculty to unveil its secrecy whenever it
               likes to do so. Thus all things which are essentially intelligible have no external
               distinctions of rank; these distinctions are confined to their emotions. This implies
               manifestly that they are more suited to receive, without any intermediary, the
               primeval light, than things of a lower<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n124-2"/> rank, not materially nor locally, but
               in relation to the high degree of purity or moderation of the minds, with reference
               to the faculty that receives hints from above.</p>
            <p>All things which are by their nature intelligible, are hidden from what is beneath
               them; not on account of natural divergences, but on account of excellence of
               impulses. This I say in respect of the members of [different] classes, viz. the
               classes of holy forces, the classes of souls, the classes of demons. The first have
               the middle place; the last the lowest in a natural and local respect and also with
               regard to their emotions.</p>
            <p>Each of the classes is hidden from the other as to their intelligible character,
               whether they see or not; from the inferior ones they are also hidden by nature.</p>
            <p>Now then, because incorporeal beings are not to be seen by other beings in the same
               way as corporeal beings, but their [power to] see one another is said to be dependent
               upon their emotions, namely the excellency and temperance of the emotions — therefore
               they see one another if they are equal <pb n="125"/>in this respect even at a
               distance and not as phantoms, but with real sight and in their true nature.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="184"/>Only — the cause of all is exalted above these
               distinctions, He, who is alone to be adored.</p>
            <p>The demons, though they are very impure, are not deprived of seeing the members of
               their own classes. But they do not see the two degrees that are above them because
               spiritual sight is serenity of emotions. These are their mirror and their eyes. And
               when the emotions have become darkened, they do not see the orders which are above
               them. [Only] one another they see, because they are more material than the order of
               spiritual things, in comparison with them. Such is the state of the demons.</p>
            <p>The souls, in accordance with their being impure and obscure, have not the faculty to
               see even the members of their own classes. Being deprived of seeing one another, they
               are also deprived of seeing themselves. But if they are purified and return unto the
               original state in which they were created, they clearly gaze at the three classes,
               viz. at those which are beneath themselves, at those which are above themselves, and
               at one another. This does not mean that they see all these classes only when they are
               transformed into material similitudes: angels, demons or the cognate soul. But they
               see them in their nature, being in their spiritual state, angels, demons and
               souls.</p>
            <p>If thou sayest, however, that it is impossible that demon or angel be seen in their
               spiritual state without being altered, then <pb type="external" n="185"/>it is not
               the soul that sees, but the body; or wherefore, then, is purification necessary?
               Demons are seen sometimes, and also angels, it is true, by those who are not pure.
               But they see them with their bodily eye when they see them, where no purification is
               needed. But the soul that has been purified sees not thus; it sees them in their
               spiritual state with its natural eye, viz. with its intellectual faculty.</p>
            <p>That the souls see one another, even when they are in the body, is not surprising. Of
               this fact there is an evident proof which thou wilt acknowledge, because its witness
               is trustworthy. The blessed Athanasius, the confessor and Catholicus, gives witness
               to it in his book on the dealings of Mar Antonius. One time when Mar Antonius prayed,
               he saw a man's soul ascending with great honour. He uttered a blessing over him that
               had been <pb n="126"/>deemed worthy of all this grace. This was the blessed Ammon,
               the recluse. And the mountain the blessed Antonius inhabited was at a distance of
               thirteen days from Nitria. — Here is a proof of the three things we have maintained,
               viz. spiritual beings see one another even at a distance, without their being impeded
               by space and the presence of objects; souls see one another when they have been
               purified; when they see they do <pb type="external" n="186"/>not see in a bodily way
               but by spiritual faculty, for it is clear that bodily sight can see what is before
               it; but as for seeing at a distance a different sight is needed.</p>
            <p>These highest classes possess an unlimited multiplicity of number. And distinctions
               and orders are noted among them. Some of them are called princes and magistrates,
               powers and lords. Perhaps those which are entrusted with magistracy and authority are
               smaller in number than those which are compelled to obey their commandment, says the
               master of teachers Diodorus Rhetor<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n126-1"/>. For they are in the possession of power
               and great if partial insight, in accordance with the highness of their orders, being
               gradated so that they ascend from degree to degree till they reach the one who is
               older and mightier and more glorious than any other and who is the head and the
               foundation of all creatures. The head, I say, not the creator of the primeval
               wonderful works of God.</p>
            <p>The angels and the archangels are very far from attaining to the wisdom of God, their
               and our creator. They are as far from it, as those of the lower degree are from them,
               but also no farther. Far, I say, as to their being higher or lower in their mutual
               relations not in a spatial sense, but in respect of power and insight. Thus we say
               that they are higher or lower in respect of natural power and insight; for in
               accordance with the measure they have reached, greater or lesser knowledge is
               inherent in them.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="187"/>All heavenly beings are named by the divine instruction
               with nine designations. It divides these three classes each into three subdivisions.
               The first comprises thrones exalted, high and holy; and Cherubs with many eyes and
               Seraphs with many wings. The [second] class [comprises] lords and powers and
               magistrates. The third: princes and archangels and angels.</p>
            <p>According to the meaning of the Hebrew, these terms are <pb n="127"/>to be
               interpreted thus: Seraphs means those who cause heat and fire. Cherubs means
               magnitude of knowledge and effusion of wisdom. Thrones means divine acceptance and
               good pleasure.</p>
            <p>This first class is called [that of] the Initiated, not because they see spiritually
               by the intermediary of the various apperceptible symbols, or because from spiritual
               writings they have acquired understanding concerning the Essence; but because they
               are full of the exalted light of the whole of immaterial knowledge and have been
               saturated with the essential contemplation of the threefold rays of the beauty that
               creates all beauties, so far as it has been permitted to them. And because they have
               been deemed worthy of communion with Jesus, not by means of images of holy formation,
               which with a certain exactness depict the divine likeness; but because they are in
               truth near to Him, stamped by Him with the mark of the primary acceptance of the
               knowledge of His divine illuminated. By the godhead they are filled with essential
               knowledge, as it is among the angels, and with primary insight into the godhead.</p>
            <p>Another and clearer [description] of the designations of the highest orders.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="188"/>Thrones are honoured [beings]. Lords are those who rule
               kingdoms. Princes the governors of the air. Magistrates are those who rule the
               peoples and human individuals. Forces are those whose sight is frightful, viz. who
               are powerful with strength. Seraphs are those who sanctify. Cherubs are bearers.
               Guards<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n127-1"/> are those who watch. Angels are messengers.</p>
            <p>On the first day eight kinds were created, seven in silence, one by voice, viz.
               light. On the second day the firmament. On the third the gathering of waters and the
               sprouting plants. On the fourth the different luminaries. On the fifth the fowls, the
               reptiles and the fishes. On the sixth the beasts and men.</p>
            <p>The form of the whole world is length and breadth. The head is the East; the end is
               the west; the right part is the North; the left part is the South.</p>
            <p>The earth is as a bed and the highest heaven as a vault the second heaven as a wheel
               adaptated to the higher one. And the borders of heaven and earth are joined one to
               the other. The Ocean surrounds them as a belt. Beyond it are high mountains ascending
               unto the sky. The sun goes its way <pb n="128"/>behind these mountains the whole
               night. The great sea is beyond them. And this encompasses four times the area of the
               dry land and one fourth is dry land.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n124-1">With the ideas of this chapter compare Frothingham, Stephen Bar
               Sudaili, p. 92: "Every intelligent nature is determined, known and comprehended by
               the essence which is above it; and determines, knows and comprehends the essence
               which is below it; but to the pure mind alone belongs the vision above and below".
               This seems to be the opening sentence of the Book of Hierotheos.</note>
            <note xml:id="n124-2">literally: later</note>
            <note xml:id="n126-1">Cf. Introduction, also for the provenience of the following
               classification of heavenly beings.</note>
            <note xml:id="n127-1">ܥܝܖ̈ܐ, also a usual term for angels in Syriac.</note>

         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
