<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 2</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 2, pp. 7-14</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="2">
            <head>II</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="11"/>Gratefulness on the part of the recipient spurs on the
               giver to bestow gifts larger than before. He who embezzles petty things is also false
               and fraudulent concerning things of importance.</p>
            <p>The sick one who is acquainted with his sickness is easily to be cured; and he who
               confesses his pain is near to health.</p>
            <p>Many are the pains of the hard heart; and when the sick one resists the physician,
               his torments will be augmented.</p>
            <p>There is no sin which cannot be pardoned except that one which lacks repentance, and
               there is no gift which is not augmented save that which remains without
               acknowledgement. For the portion of the fool is small in his eyes.</p>
            <p>Think constantly of those who are superior to thee in excellence, so thou mayest see
               thyself at all times as being less than they are. And be aware at all times of the
               heavy troubles of those whose vexations are difficult and serious, so that thou
               mayest become grateful for the small ones found with thyself and thou mayest be able
               to bear them with joy.</p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>When thou art in a state of subjection and languid and dejected, and thou art hound
               and fettered before thy foe in mournful wretchedness and laborious service of sin,
               then recall to thy mind the previous times of firmness: how thou shewest painstaking
               even concerning small things and how thou wert moved with zeal against the
               obstructors in thy course: how <pb type="external" n="12"/>thou utteredst sighs on
               account of the small things which were despised by thee as accidental and thy whole
               person was winding a wreath of victory over these things. Then, by these and similar
               recollections, thy soul will be aroused as from the depth, and be clad with the flame
               of zeal and it will rise from its immersion as if from the dead, and stretch itself
               and return to its former state, in hot strife against Satan and sin.</p>
            <p>Recollect the fall of the strong, that thou mayest remain humble under thy virtues.
               And think of the heavy sins of those who fell and repented and of the praise and
               honour they received afterwards, so that thou mayest acquire courage during thy
               repentance.</p>
            <p>Be a persecutor of thy self; then thy foe will be driven away from thee.</p>
            <p>Be on peaceful terms with thy soul; then heaven and earth will be on peaceful terms
               with thee. Be zealous to enter the treasury within thee; then thou wilt see that
               which is in heaven. For the former and the latter are one, and entering thou wilt see
               both. The ladder unto the Kingdom is hidden within thee and within thy soul. Dive
               into thyself [freed] from sin; there thou wilt find steps along which thou canst
               ascend.</p>
            <p>What the things of the world-to-be are, the scriptures do not explain. How we may
               acquire the faculty to perceive their delight even now, without change of nature or
               local transition, they teach us plainly.</p>
            <p>Though they call these things by beloved names of glorious things which are
               delightful and esteemed by us, in order to spur us on, still by saying that the eye
               has not seen, nor <pb type="external" n="13"/>the ear heard<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8-1"/> and so on, they
               show us that the things-to-be are not equal to any of the present things, by their
               being incomprehensible. They have to be reckoned by us as giving us even now
               spiritual delight, not the enjoyment of those things in themselves, such as are found
               outside the being of the <pb n="9"/>receivers and promised us for the future state.
               Otherwise "The Kingdom of God is within you"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-1"/> and "Thy Kingdom come"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-2"/>
               would teach us that we possess within us a pledge of the delight which is in those
               things. For it is necessary that there be a resemblance between these and the pledge,
               partial for the present though it be, yet to be complete in the future. Again the
               word "as through a glass"<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-3"/> shows us the comparability anyhow, even if they are
               not one in essence. If now, according to the trustworthy testimonies of the
               commentators of the scriptures, this is due to an intelligible influence of the Holy
               Ghost, and is a part of that total one, then — apart from the spiritual influence
               that by intelligible apprehension forms a communication between the Holy Ghost and
               those who are influenced — the delight of the saints in the world is not occasioned
               by any sensible mediator, be it senses or sense-organs, save only the wombs which
               contain all in defined order, which we may call the profusion of light, though not
               the intelligible profusion.</p>
            <p>A friend of excellence is not he, who zealously practices beautiful things, but who
               gladly accepts the evil things adhering to him. Patiently to bear troubles for the
               sake of excellence, is not so great as this that through the determination of the
               good will, the mind be not confused by the allurements of exciting things.</p>
            <p>For repentance which comes after the taking away of freedom, <pb type="external"
                  n="14"/>never can be a source of joy nor can it be reckoned as a redemption of
               those who rue.</p>
            <p>Protect the sinner without doing him wrong. But strengthen his courage for life; then
               the mercy of the Lord will bear thee<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-4"/>.</p>
            <p>Support with thy word the weak and the distressed in spirit whenever thou canst; then
               the hand that bears the universe will support thee. Participate with those who are
               suffering in heart, in passionate prayer and mourning of the heart; then before thy
               demand a fountain of grace will be opened.</p>
            <p>Be strenuous in prayer at all time before God, with a heart full of chaste
               deliberations mingled with passion; then He will preserve thy mind from impure
               thoughts, so that the way of God be not disordered in thee. Occupy thy gaze with
               constant <pb n="10"/>intercourse with intelligent recitation [of the scriptures],
               lest, on account of idleness, the sight of foreign things defile thy look.</p>
            <p>Do not tempt thy mind, for the sake of examination, by consideration of impure
               seductive thoughts, thinking that thou shalt not be vanquished. Even wise men have
               been perturbed in this place and deviated. Do not take fire in thy bosom, as hath
               been said<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-1"/>. Without severe bodily trouble, it is hard for the untrained youth
               to be bound under the yoke of saintliness.</p>
            <p>The sign of the beginning of darkness of mind manifests itself in the soul by
               dejection, in the first place with regard to service and prayer. For it is not
               possible that the way in thy soul towards error should be opened if thou hast not
               fallen in <pb type="external" n="15"/>this point first. Then, being bereft of God's
               help — which [else] affords a way unto Him — thou wilt easily fall into the hands of
               the foes. And further, being without care for the matters of excellence, thou wilt be
               carried towards the contrary things in every manner. Departing, from any side, is the
               beginning [of approaching] to the opposite one. Let the service of excellence be firm
               in thy soul; meditate on it and so on.</p>
            <p>Show thy weakness before God at all times, lest strangers come to examine thy
               strength while thou art separated from thy helper.</p>
            <p>The service of the cross is a double one. And this is in accordance with its twofold
               nature which is divided into two parts: patience in face of bodily troubles, which is
               accomplished through the instrumentality of the anger of the soul<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-2"/>; this is
               called<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-3"/> practice. And: the subtle intellectual service, in intercourse with
               God, constant prayer and so on, which is performed with the desiring part<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-2"/> and
               called theory. The one purifies the affectable part<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-2"/> by the strength of zeal;
               the other clears the intellectual part<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-2"/> by the influence of the love of the
               soul, which is the natural appetite.</p>
            <p>Every one, who, before being trained in the former part, passes to the latter, on
               account of the pleasures it affords, desiringly<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10-4"/> — or rather negligently —
               causes [God's] anger to <pb type="external" n="16"/>blow against him because, before
               having mortified his members <pb n="11"/>on the earth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-1"/>, i.e. before healing
               the illness of his deliberations by endurance under the labours and the shame of the
               cross, he has dared to occupy his mind with the glory of the cross. This is what has
               been said by the ancient saints: If the mind desires to ascend the cross before the
               senses have become silent on account of weakness, the anger of God will strike
               it.</p>
            <p>By the fact of the ascension of the cross causing anger he does not point to the
               first part, namely, the bearing of troubles patiently (which is the crucifying of the
               body) but to the theoretical ascension which is the second part, and which is [truly]
               subsequent to the healing of the soul. For he who hastens to meditate with his heart
               vain imaginations concerning future things, while his mind is still stained by
               reprehensible passions, will be reduced to silence on his way by punishment, because,
               before having purified his mind by means of the trials met in subduing the carnal
               desires, on account of what he has heard and read merely, he has hastened headlong to
               tread a path full of darkness, being blind — a way which exposes to danger day and
               night even those whose sight is sound and full of light, and who possess Grace as
               their guide, while their eyes are full of tears, and with prayer and weeping they
               convert night into day, on account of the danger of the course and the hard rocks
               they meet, and the phantoms of sham truth that are frequently found on the way among
               those who pretend to be true. For divine things present themselves spontaneously,
               without thy perceiving them, if the place of the heart be pure and undefiled.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="17"/>If the small pupil of thy soul has not been purified, do
               not venture to look at the globe of the sun, lest thou be bereft even of the usual
               sight, which is simple faith and humbleness and confession of the heart and light
               service in accordance with thy power<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-2"/>, and thou be cast into one of the
               intelligible places, which is the darkness without God, like him who ventured to go
               to the meal in sordid habits<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11-3"/>.</p>
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>From labour and watchfulness springs purity of deliberations. And from purity of
               deliberations inward light<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-1"/>. And from here the mind is guided by Grace towards
               that which it is not allowed to the senses either to teach or to learn.</p>
            <p>Let excellence be reckoned by thee as the body, contemplation as the soul. The two
               [form] one complete spiritual man, composed of sensible and intelligible parts. And
               as it is not possible that the soul reach existence and birth without the
               accomplished formation of the body, so it is not possible that contemplation, the
               second soul, the spirit of revelations, be formed in the womb of the intellect which
               receives the fulness of spiritual seed, without the corporeal performance of
               excellence, the dwellingplace of the knowledge which receives revelations.</p>
            <p>Contemplation is the apprehension of the divine mysteries which are hidden in the
               things spoken.</p>
            <p>When thou nearest of being far from the world, of leaving the world, of being pure
               from the world, thou art first in need <pb type="external" n="18"/>of learning and
               knowing — not after the fashion of a novice, but with the impulses of gnosis — what
               the term world means, how many different meanings the word conveys. Then thou wilt be
               able thyself to know, in how far thou art distant from or connected with the world.
               If a man know not first what the world is, he cannot understand with how many limbs
               he is bound to or far from it.</p>
            <p>There are many who think themselves wholly devoid of the world in their behaviour
               because on two or three points they refrain from it. [This is] because they have not
               understood nor perceived with discernment that they are dead to the world in one or
               two limbs, while others are living in the body of the <pb n="13"/>world. Therefore
               they even cannot perceive their affections and because they do not perceive them they
               are not anxious to be cured from them.</p>
            <p>The world is said by speculative examination to be the extension of a common name
               unto distinct affections. If we wish to call the affections by a common name we call
               them world; if we mention the affections separately, we call them by their separate
               names.</p>
            <p>The affections are parts of the usual current of the world. Where they have ceased,
               there the world's current has ceased. They are: love of riches; gathering of
               possessions; fatness of the body giving rise to the tendency towards carnal desire;
               love of honour which is the source of envy; exercising government; <pb
                  type="external" n="19"/>pride and haughtiness of magistracy; folly; glory among
               men, which is the cause of choler, bodily fear.</p>
            <p>Where their current has been dammed, there the world, after their example, has to
               some extent ceased to be maintained and to exist. In the same way as some of the
               saints, who though being alive, yet are dead; for they are alive bodily, but they do
               not live carnally. See in which of those thou art alive; then thou shalt know in how
               many parts thou art living to the world and in how many thou art dead.</p>
            <p>When thou hast learned what the world is, thou wilt be instructed in these
               distinctions and also concerning thy being bound to the world or thy being free from
               it.</p>
            <p>In short: the world is bodily behaviour and carnal thoughts. For the overcoming of
               the world is also to be recognised in these two: viz. from the change of behaviour
               and from the alteration of the impulses.</p>
            <p>From the impulses of thy mind to the things towards which its impulses go astray,
               thou canst understand the measure of thy behaviour: viz. to which things thy nature
               turns without labour; which are the constant inclinations and which are those set
               into motion fortuitously; whether the mind is the agent for the apprehension of
               incorporeal impulses only, or whether it works wholly through matter; whether this
               materiality is an affected state, or whether the impulses are but the stamps of the
               mind's service to the body, so that the mind, not of its own will, is hallucinating
               concerning those faculties by which it performs virtues and from which, in a sound
               state, it derives <pb type="external" n="20"/>its motive for fervour and
               concentration of thought, so that the mind can act corporeally, even with the
               loftiest aim, because<pb n="14"/>of its lack of experience, even though it be in no
               affected state; and whether the mind is not distressed by the unseen touch of the
               stamps of the imaginations, in view of its excessive radiance in God, which is wont
               to cut off vain recollections.</p>
            <p>The short descriptions of this chapter are sufficient for a man's illumination if he
               be quiet and intelligent; and they outweigh many books.</p>
            <p>Bodily fear is strong in man, so strong that it often withholds him from praiseworthy
               and honourable things. But when it is face to face with psychic fear it is absorbed
               by it as coldness by the force of a flame.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n8-1">1 Cor. 2,9.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9-1">Luke 17,21.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9-2">Matth. 6,10.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9-3">1 Cor. 13,12.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9-4">An idea which recurs in the work. Cf. Epicteti Diatribae Lib. 1.
               Cap. XVIII: ὅτι οὐ δεῖ χαλεπαίνειν τοῖς ἁμαρτομένοις.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-1">Proverbs 6,27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-2">Cf. The Book of the Dove, p. 524/5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-3">The text has ܡܬܩܫܝܐ. Read: ܡܬܩܪܝܐ.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10-4">We have either to cancel the waw of ܘܝܐܝܒܐܝܬ or to suppose an
               anakoluth in Isaac's construction; I have cancelled the waw.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11-1">Cf. Colossians 3,5.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11-2">Faith, confession and work are also the three elements which are
               enumerated as the constituents of Islam. Cf. Ghazālī Iḥyāʾ, 1, 109.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11-3">This sentence occurs also, with slight variations, 011 p. 50 and
               521 sq. In the last passage it shows its sententious character in an evident way. for
               here the contest is not written in the 2nd person. Its sententious character appears
               also from the fact that it occurs three times in Isaac's book. Indeed it is not
               Isaac's spiritual property, but a popular sentence in Hellenistic literature.
               Stobaeus ascribes it to Rheginus and gives it in the following redaction: καθάπερ δὲ
               τὸ τοῦ ἡλίου φῶς οὐκ ἔστι θεάσασθαι ἀσθενεῖ καὶ ἀδυνάτῳ τῇ ὄψει οὕτω καὶ ἐτὶ μᾶλλον
               τὴν ἀλήθειαν οὐκ ἔστιν ἰδεῖν ἀσθενεῖ καὶ ἀδυνάτῳ τῇ διανοίᾳ. Basilius must also have
               been acquainted with it: in the collection of sentences by Antonius and Maximus it
               occurs on his name in this form: εἰδέναι ὀφείλομεν ἃ χρῆ λαλεῖν καὶ ἃ χρῆ σιωπᾶν. οὐ
               γὰρ πάντα ῥητὰ τῆς γλώσσης τὰ τοῦ θεοῦ, ἵνα μὴ ὁ νοῦς καθάπερ ὀφθαλμὸς ὅλον τὸν ἥλιον
               θέλων ἀποβλέπειν ἀπολέσῃ ὃ ἔχει φῶς. But we can even go back to Plotinus (Enneades 1,
               6 § 9): ἐὰν δὲ ἴῃ ἐπὶ τὴν θέα</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-1">Literally: the light of the ܬܪܥܝܬܐ.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
