<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 56</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 56, pp. 265-268.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="56">
            <head>LVI</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="396"/>Beautiful considerations<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n265-1"/> concerning the life of
               man</p>
            <p>As often as man in his course approaches this world, the love of worldly things takes
               root in him, and he is constantly troubled by the thought of them, and he fights with
               man for them; and becomes bound in love to some person or other, without
               discrimination.</p>
            <p>When on the other hand the mind profits by the subtle meditation upon the world to
               be, constantly thoughts unrivalled will move in it; and expecting the things which he
               does not see, he goes to meet them, forgetting the things of this world, sometimes
               forgetting himself, because of his utter absorption in ideas, neglecting visible
               things on account of these deliberations. So deliberations as well as practice are
               despised by <pb n="266"/>him as long as he cares for these ideas. He is devoid of
               enslaving love related to single persons, but universal love which does not need
               sight is fixed in his soul. The apperception of recollection concerning human things
               gradually disappears from his mind, while the thought of hidden things increases in
               it, gains force and vanquishes bodily deliberations, till it is free from corruptible
               things, as far as nature allows this. And if it were not that the common [human]
               recollection was aroused in him, when the need of something which cannot absolutely
               be dispensed with presents itself, his mind would be directed towards future things
               the most of the time, by such thoughts as would give him profit of these things. And
               because of these he becomes a stranger<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n266-1"/> to all the wisdom of this world. So
               he becomes void of recollection and a fool as it were on account of his having
               examined human wisdom.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="397"/>Blessed is the man who has been deemed worthy of these
               things. Tears will not cease to drop from his eyes when he turns unto himself with
               the recollection of those things by which men are led into error, and why forgiveness
               is granted them, and whereby the universal end is brought about, and what labour and
               error is caused by these. It is said concerning Paul that on account of these
               emotions which prevailed over his soul, for three years he was not quit of tears,
               unable to subdue them.</p>
            <p>Such a deliberation accompanied with the emotion of tears rules man when he perceives
               the future hope and then turns his mind towards the things of this world, [thinking]
               how small psychic life is in comparison with the hope preserved for eternities, in
               the new life. By such affectability man grows dead unto all transitory things and
               thought of them; and all affections of body and soul die in him.</p>
            <p>Let us remember this, my beloved, and despise the things of this world, as much as it
               is possible for us; and let us gradually, to the same extent, approach with our
               emotions towards future things. For if a man does not compel himself, from time to
               time utterly neglecting the things which are before the eyes in order to abandon them
               gradually and to proceed onwards in this way, so that the thought and the
               contemplation of these things increase in him — he will remain <pb n="267"/>in this
               body with his behaviour. Also those who walk in the way, if they do not go forwards
               in their daily march and so diminish the distance but remain on one spot, the way
               before <pb type="external" n="398"/>them will never end and they will never arrive
               there where they hope to come.</p>
            <p>Our case resembles theirs. If we do not compel ourselves gradually, we never shall
               have the power to abandon the bodily things in order to look towards God.</p>
            <p>Because it is so difficult to free oneself from them when one has once become
               entangled in any of them, it is a matter of wisdom to struggle in order not to come
               near to them, so that one may be free even of the thought of them, and thus the mind
               be able to look towards something different. I do not mean that we should not provide
               for our wants; for these are a necessity and may bereave nature of life. But we
               should not put them in the position of the principal service by giving them the
               preference over the service of God. But attending to these needs in part, we must
               leave the care of them to God. We should confide in Him rather than in ourselves.</p>
            <p>And when a man ventures to despise these [earthly] things wholly for the sake of
               spiritual things, I do not esteem this improper, because we have all the
               encouragements of scripture that teaches us to be strong in hope; as is written: The
               Lord is at hand; be careful for nothing<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n267-1"/>. And David says: Cast thy care upon
               the Lord and He shall sustain thee<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n267-2"/>. The rich do lack and suffer hunger: but
               they that seek the Lord shall not want any good thing<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n267-3"/>. And our Lord has
               commanded us, saying: Be careful for nothing, but frequently think of the future
               things. And these earthly things which are necessary because of the needs of nature,
               will not fail thee.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="399"/>May God in His grace grant us that His love be abundant
               in us, in order that by constant meditation on Him we may forget the world and what
               belongs to it by becoming free from its bonds; and that instead of many bonds we may
               be bound with that one bond which is not loosened from those who love Him, namely the
               bond of the kingdom of the worlds above; that we also may be bound with it, and be
               deemed worthy of the prefiguration of good the fulness of which is preserved in the
               future world for those who have possessed <pb n="268"/>it here already. That we also
               may possess it and be possessed by it through the power that comes from it, for ever
               and ever, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n265-1">literally: distinctions</note>
            <note xml:id="n266-1"> literally: a fool</note>
            <note xml:id="n267-1">Philippians 4,5</note>
            <note xml:id="n267-2">Psalms 55,22</note>
            <note xml:id="n267-3">Ps. 34,10 according to the Peshito</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
