<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 29</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 29, pp. 138-140.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="29">
            <head>XXIX</head>
            <p>On the different excellent methods of wide providence in educating pupils</p>
            <p>All wisdom comes from the Lord, as hath been said<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n138-2"/>. And we exercise ourselves
               in our own things in order to become wise in the dealings of the Lord with us. The
               Father of truth <pb n="139"/>deals in different ways with his sons; He avoids
               uniformity which consists in showing always the same face, for the profit of his
               sons. On the contrary, for the sake of exercise He withdraws his love. Thus He
               displays in appearance an order such as exists not; but what is, He retains. A wise
               son recognizes in different attitudes his father's care for him and his discerning
               love.</p>
            <p>The practice of love appears in two ways when rightly understood: in joyful events,
               but also in sorrowful ones. This proves that love is constantly tending towards the
               pleasure of <pb type="external" n="206"/>its object. But sometimes it makes its
               object suffer, because of its fulness; if it makes suffer, it suffers also itself. It
               resists the motions of natural compassion because of the fear of later harm. Love
               urges us to participate; knowledge gives strength to resist [these] feelings.</p>
            <p>Parallel to the differences in its election are the varying forms of wise love
               regarding those who receive its sustenance. Let us not ask of a wise friend foolish
               love. He who kills his son by feeding him with honey, is not different from him that
               kills his son with a knife.</p>
            <p>It is namely not worthy of the wisdom of love to sustain its object in a uniform way,
               the same in health as in illness. That is to say the variations which depend upon the
               will in the choice of the emotions, not bodily changes. If we are able to choose
               those [varying] times when we love some one, with discrimination, especially when
               such a one is under our command, is it not then but right that we attribute to God
               the faculty of performing the offices of his discriminating love unto us, even if we
               do consider them in the same way as the variations we are able to show to our
               friends? This is difficult to bear, as I know myself; but it is profitable
               nevertheless. Thy nature which is liable to deviation makes thee in need of this, if
               not as a retribution for what has passed, then to excite in thee fear of what will
               certainly happen.</p>
            <p>Distressing accidents are to the inner education what wholesome medicines are to
               bodily disparity.</p>
            <p>All that is simple among creatures, is without struggle in its <pb type="external"
                  n="207"/>dealings; this is applicable to bodily as well as to non-bodily beings.
               Action is of such a nature that it is only possible in connection with disparity.
               Disparity exists only in composite beings, on account of a united duality. And though
               non-composite <pb n="140"/>and simple beings are also said to be liable to
               aberration, still this takes place wholly to the right side, and not in the way of
               action, because they have no experience of that which is on the opposite side. They
               are only affectable regarding the good. For their liability to deviation is checked
               by swift love; and where there is love, there is no struggle and no fear. Yet they
               are bound in nature; and from this being bound, their liability to aberration is said
               to originate.</p>
            <p>Good and evil are the offspring of freedom. Where the latter is lacking, to practise
               the former is superfluous with respect to remuneration. For nature knows no
               remuneration. Reward is decreed for strife. There can be no mention of victory where
               there is no struggle. When opposition is removed, freedom vanishes at the same time.
               Then nature remains without strife. A time is reserved for the annihilation of
               freedom; then a limited rationality comes into existence, among men as well as among
               the angels. Rationality, not sensible emotionality. In conception<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n140-1"/>
               rationality possesses two peculiarities, namely two forces, a rational and a
               conceiving force. The former is altogether limited. In the latter nature is complete,
               in so far as <pb type="external" n="208"/>it is conceiving. But again it is limited,
               not compulsorily, but rather delightfully, with a delightful bond. Sometimes this
               [delight] happens unto a few in this world in a symbolical way; but only in trance.
               Unto the primeval rational beings [this happened] without trance, as far as this was
               possible, though they were not perfect. What was it which happened without trance
               unto persons who were not perfect? There are mysteries that cannot be received before
               the time appointed. Those persons are imperfect therefore, who do not possess it at
               all, not those who possess what they do here possess, only in trance.</p>
            <p>Therefore constancy [is necessary], rather than trance. If trance [at all], then it
               is for those things which are most excellent. So trance for those people was an
               excellent change; with us it is annihilation, because of the sickness of the
               flesh.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n138-2">Jesus Sirach 1,1</note>
            <note xml:id="n140-1">ܝܕܘܥܬܢܘܬܐ</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
