<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 75</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 75, pp. 348-349.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="75">
            <head>LXXV</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="519"/>On hidden states and the powers and influences which are
               in them</p>
            <p>This may be taken for true by thee, that the practice of marvellous things, and the
               foreseeing of future things, and temptations, and rest from strife, and victory over
               every one of the affections, and the presence of every one of the <choice><sic>vritues</sic><corr>virtues</corr></choice>,
               and consolation, for a certain time, from grace, and purity of prayer, and warmth of
               spirit, and spiritual joy, and all the other things with which a man fatigues himself
               for a certain time, with a good intention and a mournful heart — that in <pb n="349"
               />all these God will condescend to accomplish man's will at any time. And when He
               sees his intention and longing He grants him his wish and satisfies him.</p>
            <p>As to the mysteries which belong to the spirit, namely the emotions during spiritual
               prayer, and the entering of the mind behind the curtain of the holy of holies, and
               the apperception of the indestructible inheritance — if a man does not pay their
               duty, God is not willing to grant them, even if the whole creation should beseech in
               behalf of him. Their duty is purity of the soul. When a man has reached purity from
               the affections, what no eye has seen and no ear has heard and what has not entered
               into the heart of man to ask in prayer, is revealed to him by purity, which during no
               moment ceases from mysteries and spiritual visions. And what the force of <pb
                  type="external" n="520"/>spring is wont to work unto the nature of the earth, this
               grace works unto the soul by purity. The power of spring makes even the smallest
               roots in the valleys bud, warming the earth as fire does the cauldron, so that it
               sends forth the treasures of the plants which God has laid in the earth's nature, to
               the gladness of the creation and to His glory.</p>
            <p>So grace makes manifest all the glory which God has hidden in the nature of the soul
               showing the soul this glory and making it glad because of its own beauty. So that
               when it sees the great and unspeakable treasures which God has laid in it and which
               were hidden from it by the defiled mantle of affections and ignorance, but which now
               that it has torn asunder the garment of the affections, He has shown to it — it is
               captured on account of its gladness by His love and turns its back on earthly
               things.</p>
            <p>Moreover it does not remember the body which hid its own beauties from its sight.
               Then it sees heavenly beauties in itself as the exact mirror which by its great
               purity shows the beauty of faces. Holiness suits those who are holy. All excellence
               whatever and all service by which righteousness is accomplished, may be performed and
               acquired and accomplished without solitude; but apathy and purity cannot be acquired
               without solitude.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
