<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 74</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 74, pp. 341-348.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="74">
            <pb n="341"/>
            <head>LXXIV</head>
            <pb type="external" n="507"/>
            <head>On the discrimination of virtue and the scope of the whole course and the greatness
               of the love unto mankind and the spiritual aim which it reaches in all the saints by
               creating within them a divine likeness by the rich love which he pours out upon
               mankind</head>
            <p>The scope of the whole course consists in these three: Repentance, purity and
               perfection.[p] What is repentance? To desist from former [sins] and to suffer on
               account of them. And what is the sum of purity? A heart full of mercy unto the whole
               created nature. And what is perfection? Depth of humility, namely giving up all
               visible and invisible things. Visible things: all that which is sensible. [In visible
               things](Invisible): all thinking about them. Another time the same Father was asked:
               What is repentance? He answered: A broken heart. And what is humility? He replied:
               Embracing a voluntary mortification regarding all things. And what is a merciful
               heart? He replied: The burning of the heart unto the whole creation, man, fowls and
               beasts, demons and whatever exists; so that by the recollection and the sight of them
               the eyes shed tears on account of the force of mercy which moves the heart by great
               compassion. Then the heart becomes weak<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n341-1"/> and it is not able to bear hearing
               or examining injury or any insignificant suffering of anything in the creation. And
               therefore even in behalf of the irrational beings and the enemies of truth and even
               in behalf of those who do harm to it, at all times he <pb type="external" n="508"
               />offers prayers with tears that they may be guarded and strengthened even in behalf
               of the kinds of reptiles, on account of his great compassion which is poured out in
               his heart without measure, after the example of God.</p>
            <p>And what is prayer? He replied: The mind's being free from all that is earthly and
               the heart's turning its gaze completely towards the desire of future hope. Who
               deviates from this, is as one who sews in his furrow mixed seed and as one who
               ploughs with ox and ass together.</p>
            <pb n="342"/>
            <p>How is humility acquired? He replied: By constant recollection of trespasses, by
               expectation of near death, by dressing meanly, by always choosing the lowest place
               and by always undertaking low and humble work, without compulsion, by constant
               silence, by disliking crowded meetings, by being unknown and disregarded, by choosing
               <choice><sic>distincly</sic><corr>distinctly</corr></choice> one occupation, by hating intercourse with other persons, by
               disliking profits. All his qualities are based upon these.</p>
            <p>And his mind must be exalted above vituperating and reproaching anyone and above
               zealotism. And his hand shall not be against all. Nor the hand of all with him. But
               he shall be a solitary, only occupying himself with his own things, and lonely. And
               he shall not take upon himself the care of any one in the world except himself. In
               short: abiding abroad and poverty and lonely dwelling give birth to humility and
               purify the heart. As to those who have reached perfection, their token is, that if
               ten times every day they are delivered to burning for the sake of the love of
               mankind, they are not <pb type="external" n="509"/>saturated with it. As also Moses
               said to God: If thou wilt not pardon the children of Israel, blot me out of thy book
               which thou hast written<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n342-1"/>. And as also the blessed Paul said<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n342-2"/>: I could
               desire to be removed afar from Christ<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n342-3"/>, if thereby the children of Israel
               would come near to the faith of life. And if it be thus that it is possible that
               they, for this reason, will believe in Christ and will come to life everlasting and
               will not be alienated from the living God. Then, as is written: I rejoice in my
               sufferings for you, o peoples<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n342-3"/>. Even so the other Apostles have undergone all
               kinds of death, for the sake of the love of the life of mankind. The sum of all is
               God, the Lord of all, who from love of His creatures, has delivered His son to death
               on the cross. For God so loved the world, that He gave his only begotten son for
               it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n342-4"/>. Not that He was not able to save us in another way, but in this way it
               was possible to show us His abundant love abundantly, namely by bringing us near to
               Him by the death of His son. If He had anything more dear to Him, He would have given
               it us, in order that by it our race might be His. And out of His great love He did
               not even choose to urge our freedom by compulsion, though He was able to do so. But
               His aim was, that <pb n="343"/>we should come near to Him by the love of our
               mind.</p>
            <p>And our Lord obeyed His father out of love unto us, taking upon Him scorn and
               suffering joyfully, as Scripture says: <pb type="external" n="510"/>Who for the joy
               that was set before him endured the cross, despising the shame<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n343-1"/>. Therefore
               our Lord said in the night in which He was betrayed: This is my body which is given
               for the salvation of the world unto life. And this is my blood which is shed for all
               for the remission of sins<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n343-2"/>. In behalf of them I offer myself.</p>
            <p>And so all the saints have reached this accomplishment when they became perfect, so
               that they resembled God in effusion of love and compassion for mankind. And they
               asked for themselves as a token of their resembling God, that they should be perfect
               in the love of their fellows. So did also the solitary Fathers, that they might bear
               in themselves constantly this likeness full of the life of Christ, the Lord of the
               Universe.</p>
            <p>The blessed Antonius thought that he never could do anything so useful to himself as
               that which was profitable to his neighbour, in the opinion that the profit of his
               neighbour was his excellent service. Analogous is a saying concerning the blessed
               Agathon: 'I wished that I could find a leper, and give him my body and take his'.
               Doest thou see the perfect love? Even in outward things he could not bear to
               displease his neighbour rather than himself. He possessed namely a knife, which a
               brother saw and liked it. And he did not allow him <pb type="external" n="511"/>to
               leave his cell till he had taken it. And when he possessed a thing and saw some one
               who wanted it, he did not lay any further claim to it.</p>
            <p>What do I mean by these things [which include] that many of them have given their
               bodies even to the beasts and the sword and the fire on behalf of their neighbours?
               It is not possible that a man should reach this degree of love, with the exception of
               that one who secretly perceives his faith. And it is not possible that those who love
               this world, should acquire the love of mankind. When a man has acquired love, he is
               clad with God at the same time. He that has put on God, never can be persuaded to
               acquire any other thing except Him, but he puts off his body even. And if he is clad
               with the world or with love of his life, these will not allow <pb n="344"/>him to put
               on God. For he is witness: he that does not forsake and hate all, even himself,
               cannot be my disciple<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n344-1"/>. Not only that he should leave them, but that he
               should ever hate them. And if he cannot be a disciple, how can He dwell in him?</p>
            <p>The interrogator. How is it that the service of hope is so delightful, and its
               labours so few and its work so easy to the soul?</p>
            <p>The Father. This is because it excites the natural longing in the soul and gives them
               this cup to drink and makes them drunk. And from this moment they nevermore perceive
               fatigue but become apathetic against troubles. And during the whole of their course
               it is to them as if they were moving in the <pb type="external" n="512"/>air without
               bodily motion, without seeing anything of the difficulty of the road or the streams
               and hills that are before them; but the crooked becomes to them straight and rough
               places plain<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n344-2"/>, because they always see the bosom of their Father; and all
               those things which are far and invisible it makes to them clear in themselves, so
               that they gaze at them mysteriously with the hidden eye of faith. For all the parts
               of the soul become hot as by fire, on account of the expectation of those things
               which, though far, become as near; for towards them is tended the whole direction of
               their deliberations; and they hasten to know when they will reach [their aim] and
               when they will approach unto every single virtue by practice. They do not practice
               them partly, but all of them together, at the same time. For they do not take their
               course along the king's way, as the generality of men, but choose short paths along
               which a few heroes move, who easily reach the Apartment. For hope warms them as with
               fire, and they cannot pause in their incessant course, on account of their joy. And
               to them happens as in the word of Jeremia: I said: I will not make mention of him,
               nor speak any more in his name. But his word was in mine heart as a burning fire shut
               up in my bones<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n344-3"/>. Such is the recollection of God in the heart of those who
               move in the expectation of the promise. Short <pb type="external" n="513"/>paths I
               call the concise virtues, because in them there is no winding nor the long space of
               many ways of discipline leading from here to there, nor place nor time nor
               distraction. But they stand on the way and accomplish it at once.</p>
            <pb n="345"/>
            <p>The interrogator. <choice><sic>Wat</sic><corr>What</corr></choice> is apathy?</p>
            <p>The Father answers. Apathy is not [the state] that does not perceive the affections,
               but that which does not accept them, so that on account of the many virtues
               possessed, manifest and hidden ones, the affections have become weak and cannot
               easily assail the soul. Neither does the spirit want to look at them every time,
               because at all times its emotion is filled with meditation and intercourse with
               excellent thoughts, which move with insight in the mind. And when an affection is
               beginning to move, the spirit at once hastens away from it through some insight which
               it perceives in the mind, and the affection remains idle. As also the blessed
               Euagrius says: the mind which by the grace of God performs works of excellence and
               approaches unto knowledge, perceives little of the foolish part of the soul. For its
               knowledge drags it on high and alienates it to all things in the world; this happens
               also because, on account of their purity, their mind has become subtle and light and
               swift. <choice><sic>Forther</sic><corr>Further</corr></choice> the mind is purified by asceticism, because the body is
               desiccated, and also in consequence of the fulness of solitude and the long space of
               time passed in it. Therefore it swiftly alights on several things towards which <pb
                  type="external" n="514"/>their contemplation draws them in ecstasy. Therefore they
               are rich in contemplation, and are never in want of abundant insight in their spirit,
               apart from the fact, that the Spirit ripens its fruits in them. And in the course of
               time also the eye loses sight of the recollections that come from the heart and which
               stir the affections in the soul and are a principal power of Satan. But when the soul
               does not associate with the affections by meditating upon them — because it is
               continually occupied by other care — the power of their nails cannot take hold of the
               soul's spiritual senses.</p>
            <p>The interrogator: What are the characteristics of humility?</p>
            <p>The father answers: As presumption dissipates the soul by phantastic distraction on
               account of the power inciting it to fly round the whole creation in the cloud of its
               deliberations, so humility is the power which concentrates the soul's being by the
               peace of its deliberations and the reclusion of the soul within its self. And as the
               soul is unknown and invisible to the fleshly eye, so the humble is unknown amongst
               mankind. And as the soul in the body is hidden from sight and from mingling with
               every man, so the truly humble not <pb n="346"/>only does not desire to be seen and
               known among mankind, because of his being hidden and recluded from all, but it is
               even his desire — if possible — to be shut off from his soul and to be within himself
               in total quiet and rest of his emotions and senses, as something that does not exist
               in the <pb type="external" n="515"/>creation and has not come into existence and is
               not at all, so that he does not even wish for himself to be known and perceived. And
               as long as he is hidden and shut off from the world, he is wholly with his Lord.</p>
            <p>The humble is never pleased to see crowds and gatherings of people, noise and rumour,
               nor riches and finery, nor the luxury which is a consequence of them, nor speech and
               intercourse, rumour and distraction of the senses. But above all he chooses
               concentration and reclusion with himself alone, to be quiet and shut off and lonely
               and left to himself in a solitary place void of all beings and separated from the
               whole creation. And in every respect smallness and limitation and want and poverty is
               beloved by him. And he is not occupied with many things and labours, but at all times
               he is satisfied and without care, without troublesome mingling with worldly things,
               so that his deliberations do not wander from his self, because he knows that if he
               alights upon many things it is not possible for him to remain without confused
               emotions. For many practices cause many cares. And many cares are a gathering-point
               of varied thoughts and deliberations. Then he would have to give up his being exalted
               above the care of earthly things, in peace of deliberations — except for the small
               necessary things which are inevitable — with a spirit occupied with a single care,
               the emotions being in a state of peace. And then necessary things would not allow him
               to keep silent <pb type="external" n="516"/>and so he would be injured and would
               cause injury. Thus there would be opened a gate for the affections and discriminating
               quiet would disappear, humility would flee, the gate of salvation would be shut. And
               because of all this, he continually keeps his soul away from the many things, and at
               all times thou findest him quiet and at rest and humble and peaceful.</p>
            <p>In the humble there is never violence nor terror nor confusion, nor hot nor quick
               emotions. But at all times he abides in rest. If heaven should fall on the earth, the
               humble would not be moved.</p>
            <p>Not every one who is quiet, is humble. But every one who <pb n="347"/>is humble is
               also quiet. There does not exist one who is humble without being submissive. Those
               who are submissive without being humble are found in large numbers. This is the meek
               and humble concerning whom our Lord has said: Learn of me, that I am <choice><sic>meak</sic><corr>meek</corr></choice> and
               lowly in heart; and ye shall find rest unto your souls<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n347-1"/>. The humble is
               content at all times, because there is nothing which moves his spirit. As it is not
               possible for a man to move a mountain, so the spirit of the humble is unmoved, if it
               is possible to say so. And perhaps it is not even foolish to say that even the humble
               does not belong to this world, because he is not destroyed nor moved by distresses:
               even [emotions] of joy cause ecstasy and effusion to him. But all his joy and true
               <choice><sic>excultation</sic><corr>exultation</corr></choice> is in the things of his Lord.</p>
            <p>Connected with humility are patience, a concentrated self <pb type="external" n="517"
               />— which is [real] humility — a low voice, little speech, selfcontempt, mean
               clothes, a modest gait, bashful looks, effusion of mercy, easily flowing tears, a
               lonely soul, a broken heart, the not being moved by anger, absence of distraction of
               the senses, moderate wishes, moderate wants in every respect, willingness to bear,
               patience, intrepidity, manliness of heart born from hatred of temporal life,
               endurance of temptations, few emotions which are not swift, extinguished
               deliberations, keeping of secrets, chastity, bashfulness, modesty, and above all:
               continual silence, continual having recourse to ignorance. The humble is never
               approached by necessity which makes him confused. The humble, even when he is alone,
               is shameful for his soul.</p>
            <p>I wonder whether there exists a truly humble man, who ventures to pray to God when he
               approaches unto prayer, or who is worthy of this, or of asking Him anything, or who
               knows what he shall pray. But when all his emotions are quiet and he only hopes for
               mercy, [being uncertain] which order will be given concerning himself by the adorable
               Majesty; when his face is bent towards the earth and the inner gaze of the heart
               lifted up towards the door of the holy of holies of the Highest, the cloud of whose
               dwelling-place blinds the eyes of the Seraphs, and whose splendour terrifies the
               legions of their orders, when silence lies upon all their classes and <pb n="348"
                  /><pb type="external" n="518"/>they expect the rising of mysteries from the domain
               of invisible things, in an airless womb, with emotions without voice, with unbodily
               senses, with apperception without resemblance<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n348-1"/>, without seeing the
               revelations which reach them, the vehemence of their emotions being too weak to
               endure the waves of His mysteries; then he does not venture to say anything, but:
               According to thy will, my Lord.</p>
            <p>These things so far I have endeavoured to write to thee in plain words, which the
               spirit could attain without scrutiny on account of their manifest sense; things by
               the reading of which alone the mind forgets the ways and the dealings of this world
               and its fleshly life, migrating then with the spirit unto its true and profitable
               world. [I have written this], asking thy love that, when thou comest in contact with
               these mysteries, thou shalt not leave them without profit, so that they should be
               found with thee to be dead sentences; lest it should happen to thee as it happened to
               those who were invited to the spiritual meal but excused themselves. Behold, the
               table is prepared, spiritual ideas are ranged upon it, and all delightful things are
               ready; and the bridegroom expects that we shall enter and rejoice with him. Let us,
               therefore, not excuse ourselves, lest there be said to us also the word that was said
               concerning them. What then? Verily, I say unto you, that none of those invited, shall
               eat from my meal.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n341-1"><choice><sic>litt.</sic><corr>lit.</corr></choice>: small</note>
            <note xml:id="n342-1">Cf. Exodus 32,32</note>
            <note xml:id="n342-2">The text has some words which give no sense here and are wanting
               in the Greek translation.</note>
            <note xml:id="n342-3">Cf. Col. 1,24</note>
            <note xml:id="n342-4">Cf. John 3,16.</note>
            <note xml:id="n343-1">Hebr. 12,2</note>
            <note xml:id="n343-2">Cf. Matth. 26,26,28</note>
            <note xml:id="n344-1">Cf. Luke 14,33</note>
            <note xml:id="n344-2">Isaia 40,4</note>
            <note xml:id="n344-3">Jeremia 20,9</note>
            <note xml:id="n347-1">Matthew 11, 29</note>
            <note xml:id="n348-1">The: in the text to he placed after ܕܐܘܣܝܐ</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
