<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 14</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 14, pp. 85-86.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="14">
            <pb n="85"/>
            <head>XIV</head>
            <head>As to when those who live in solitude begin to know, even to a slight extent, how far
               they have advanced in their service to the unfathomable sea of solitary life so that
               they are able to have confidence somewhat on their labours that they begin to bear
               fruit</head>
            <p>I shall tell thee a thing at which thou must not laugh; for I tell the truth. Do not
               doubt it, for those from whom I have received it, are trustworthy.</p>
            <p>If thou hangest on <choice><sic>they</sic><corr>thy</corr></choice> eyelids before God, do not think that in behaviour
               thou hast reached anything till tears come forth; for thy hidden being still
               ministers unto the world. This means, that thou art on the same stage of behaviour
               with faithful lay people. For thou workest with thy outward man in the service of God
               but the inward man is still without fruits. His fruits begin at the point which I
               have indicated. When thou hast reached the place of tears, then understand that the
               spirit has left the prison of this world and set its foot on the way towards the new
               world. Then it begins to breathe the <pb type="external" n="126"/>wonderful air which
               is there, and to spend tears. For now the throes caused by the spiritual child,
               become vehement. And grace, the common mother, hastily delivers, as it were, the
               soul, God's image, unto the light of the world to-come. And when the time of birth is
               come, then the mind will perceive a something belonging to that world, like a faint
               perfume, which the child has received in the members into which it has grown.</p>
            <p>But he who does not patiently bear what is unusual, will move his body with weeping
               mingled with joy which excels the sweetness of honey. Together with the growing of
               the child within there will be an increase of tears. The stream of tears begins when
               the spirit begins to become serene. I mean the flowing of tears belonging to the
               stage which I have described, not that partial one, which takes place from time to
               time.</p>
            <pb n="86"/>
            <p>This consolation which takes place from time to time, will come to pass to every one
               who serves God in solitude. Sometimes during spiritual contemplation. Sometimes when
               hearing or reading the words of the scriptures. Sometimes while occupied with
               beseechings.</p>
            <p>But I propose to speak of that complete one, which continues night and day without a
               break, and which comes to him who has found truth in solitude by the sincerity of his
               behaviour, when the eyes become fountains of water for a period of nearly two years.
               This happens during a transition-period; I mean symbolical transition<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n86-1"/>. At the
               end of the period of tears thou wilt reach peace of deliberations and by this peace
               of deliberations thou wilt reach the divine rest of which Paul speaks, rest in part,
               according to [our] nature.</p>
            <p>From the beginning of [this period of] rest onward, the mind <pb type="external"
                  n="127"/>will see hidden things. Then the Holy Ghost will begin to reveal unto it
               heavenly things, while God dwells in thee and promotes spiritual fruits in thee. Then
               thou wilt perceive the state which the whole nature will receive in the renewal of
               all things, dimly and mysteriously.</p>
            <p>This I have written to the profit of myself and of everyone who comes across this
               book, being that which I have attained by contemplation of the scriptures and from
               the mouth of veracious men (and to a small part by experience) that I also may gain
               profit by the prayers of those who have gained profit from these things, because I
               have toiled upon them.</p>
            <p>Listen also to another thing which I tell thee, as I have heard it from a mouth that
               does not lie: As soon as thou hast entered this place where the deliberations are set
               at peace, then the violence of weeping is again taken from thee and thou readiest the
               state of moderation.</p>
            <p>This is the exact truth in a few words; and it is true and confirmed by the whole
               church, by the excellent among her sons and by her chief protagonists.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n86-1">ܡܥܒܪܬܐ ܐܪܙܢܝܬܐ</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
