<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 23</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 23, pp. 118-120.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="23">
            <head>XXIII</head>
            <p>On the speech of true knowledge</p>
            <p>Every apperceptive thing, be it action or word, is the revelation of what is hidden
               within, if its cause be not entirely accidental, but return constantly. The latter
               element only is <pb n="119"/>considered in connection with reward; the former is
               taken into consideration to a small extent only. For the strength or the weakness of
               will is evidenced in the doing of evil or of good things, not by anything that
               happens accidentally; but the proof of its freedom is the constant repetition.</p>
            <p>To fate is given power; sometimes even so as to dominate <pb type="external" n="176"
               />freedom of will. Good or bad accidents meet man be it in order to spur him on, or
               to test, or to train, or to reward him. That which serves to spur on, is good; that
               which serves to test, is considered as being bad; that which serves to train and to
               remunerate is indifferent.</p>
            <p>There are no fortuitous accidents; for nothing fortuitous happens to man, good or
               evil. There is a governor who governs the things of this world. There is a guardian
               with each of us, whom nothing escapes and whose attention never fails. But all
               accidents are foreseen by this appointed guardian. And in these four kinds [of
               accidents] his providence is active.</p>
            <p>Passionate prayer, the companion of a course [of life] in harmony with its passionate
               nature, alters the character of those [who are subject to accidents] and brings about
               amelioration. The good are strengthened and corroborated by it; to the bad it causes
               a change to the opposite direction. Therefore, doubt not what I have said: there is
               no accident fortuitous or without a governor. If indeed prayer combined with
               <choice><sic>steadfestness</sic><corr>steadfastness</corr></choice> is able to alter or to direct, we have to believe that
               there is a governor to every accident. Blessed is he who compares every accident
               which happens to him, with his hidden [state], who scrutinizes its cause and beholds
               its governor. He that is desirous to acquire experience with God, cannot but become a
               fool to the world and a hater of human glory.</p>
            <p>Admirable is the man who conceals the greatness of his work by lowliness of soul.
               Such a one is admired by the angels.</p>
            <p>As guardians of righteousness have to be <choice><sic>reckonned</sic><corr>reckoned</corr></choice> by thee <pb
                  type="external" n="177"/>involuntary defects, which sometimes are found with those
               who are watchful.</p>
            <p>There is no prayer which is heard so soon as when a man asks to be reconciled with
               those who are angry with him. And when a man charges himself with the fault, this
               prayer is answered without delay. If thou fulfillest thy duty and art watchful in thy
               domain, yet art weak and despicable in thy <pb n="120"/>own eyes, hating human glory,
               then know that thou art surely in the way of God. But if thou perceivest that thou
               art not in this state and, when thou explorest thyself, thou seest that thoughts of
               blame cause thee pain, then know that thou art void of truth and in secret relation
               with falsehood.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
