<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 51</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 51, pp. 242-253.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="51">
            <pb n="242"/>
            <head>LI</head>
            <p><pb type="external" n="360"/>On the three degrees of knowledge and the discrimination
               between their service and impulses on the faith of the soul and the treasures of
               mysteries hidden in it and to what extent worldly knowledge in its means[#n242-1] is
               opposed to the simplicity of the faith</p>
            <p>When the soul in the course of its behaviour walks in the way of faith, this improves
               it much. When it then turns towards the means of knowledge, it becomes alienated to
               faith at once. And it is removed from that intelligible force of faith which reveals
               itself by different acts of help in the serene soul that simply, without inquiry,
               uses all that belongs to it.</p>
            <p>The soul that has once, in faith, entrusted itself unto God and, under many
               temptations, has received the taste of faith's help, no longer thinks of itself, but
               is made speechless by ecstasy and silence, nor is it allowed to return unto the means
               of its knowledge or to make use of them, lest it also be bereft, on the contrary, of
               the divine care which visits it incessantly and provides for it and clings to it
               everywhere. For the soul would consider it as a despicable thought to deem itself
               sufficient to guide itself by the power of its knowledge. For those in whose hearts
               the light of faith has dawned, do not venture to pray in their own behalf, they do
               not even venture to ask <pb type="external" n="361"/>God: Give us this, or: Take from
               us that, nor dare they think of themselves in any way. For by the initiated eyes of
               their faith they always see the paternal care which protects them on the part of that
               Father whose strong and immeasurable love surpasses the love of all fleshly fathers
               and who has power to supply us with all things above what we ask and think.</p>
            <p>For knowledge is opposed to faith and faith with all its means destroys the laws of
               knowledge. I do not mean spiritual laws. For the circumscription of the domain of
               knowledge is <pb n="243"/>this, that a man is not allowed to do anything without
               inquiry or examination; but he must investigate, so as to comply, if possible, with
               what befalls him.</p>
            <p>But as to faith, what is it? If yes and no approach unto it equally, faith does not
               consent to remain in that position. That knowledge cannot be used without methods and
               means, that it even does not exist without them, is known. And this is the token of
               its sceptical attitude regarding truth. Faith on the other hand requires a serene and
               simple mind, far from any cunning or need of means. Behold, how knowledge and faith
               are each other's opposites.</p>
            <p>The mansion of faith is a childlike mind and a pure heart. For in the purity of their
               heart people have praised God. For 'except ye be converted and become as little
               children'[#n243-1] and so on. Knowledge, however is the persecutor and opposite of
                  <pb type="external" n="362"/>these two. Knowledge adheres to the domain of nature,
               in all its ways. Faith makes its course above nature. Knowledge does not admit unto
               itself anything which is in disharmony with nature, not even for the sake of trial;
               but it lets these things dwell at a distance. Faith on the other hand orders with
               authority and says: Thou shall tread upon the serpent and the lion: the young lion
               and the dragon shalt thou trample under feet[#n243-2].</p>
            <p>Knowledge is accompanied by fear; faith by trust. As long as a man uses the means of
               knowledge, he is not free from fear, it is not even possible that he be deemed worthy
               of freedom. But as soon as he clings to faith, at once a free man and the king of his
               soul and a son of God, he will use freedom in all things, with authority. A man that
               has found the keys of faith will use all the species in nature, as God. For faith is
               allowed, even to create a new creation, just as God did. If thou willest, anything
               will stand before thee. And many times it is possible to make every thing out of
               nothing.</p>
            <p>Knowledge is not able to make anything without materials. Knowledge does not venture
               to step over unto the domain which lies outside nature. How then? That the dissolved
               nature of water does not suffer the footsteps of flesh on its back, that he who
               excites fire is burnt by it, and that it is dangerous <pb type="external" n="363"/>to
               act contrary to these [rules]. Such lore is cautiously guarded <pb n="244"/>by
               knowledge. And it is absolutely impossible to persuade it to order an advance into
               this domain.</p>
            <p>Faith on the other hand commands this with authority, saying: If thou tread on fire
               it will not burn thee; and floods will not drag thee along. And faith has done these
               things many times before the eyes of all creatures. If knowledge had been given an
               opportunity in this domain, it would not have given the permission to try such things
               at all. Through faith many have entered the mouth of the flames, and have checked the
               power of the burning fire, and have persevered in it without injury, and have walked
               on the back of the sea as if it were dry land. Verily, all these things are above
               nature and contrary to the methods of knowledge.</p>
            <p>Seest thou how faith shakes the foundations of knowledge and shows that all its means
               and laws are vain? Seest thou how knowledge guards the domain of nature? Seest thou
               also how faith walks above nature and makes there the paths for its course? For
               nearly five thousand years the means of knowledge have been governing the world and
               the world has not been able to lift its head from the earth at all nor to perceive
               the power of its creator, until faith dawned to us and freed us from the trouble of
               labouring upon earthly things and from the vain slavery of fruitless distraction. And
               now that we have <pb type="external" n="364"/>found an unexplored ocean and an
               unlimited treasure, should we desire to stay at a poor fountain? There is no
               knowledge which is not lacking, rich though it may be. As to faith, heaven and earth
               cannot contain its treasures.</p>
            <p>He whose heart is supported by the trust of faith, will never experience want of
               anything. And though he does not possess anything, he dominates all things through
               faith. As it is written: All things, whatsoever ye shall ask in prayer, believing, ye
               shall receive[#n244-1].</p>
            <p>And again: Our Lord is at hand; be careful for nothing[#n244-2]. Knowledge
               perpetually seeks means to preserve those who possess it. What does faith do?
               '<choice><sic>Exept</sic><corr>Except</corr></choice> the Lord build the house and keep the city, they labour in vain that
               build it and wake to watch'[#n244-3]. Never will he that seeks refuge with faith use
               means.</p>
            <p>Knowledge everywhere praises fear. As also the sage says: Blessed is he whose heart
               fears. What does faith do? 'He was <pb n="245"/>afraid and began to sink'[#n245-1].
               And again: For ye have not received the spirit of fear to bondage, but the spirit of
               adoption[#n245-2] to freedom in faith and trust in God. 'Fear them not
               therefore'[#n245-3], lest I crush thee before them. Fear always accompanies doubt,
               and doubt examination, and investigation means, and means knowledge. And that which
               always examines and investigates, shows doubt and fear; for knowledge does not always
               and in every thing profit, as has been shown above.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="365"/>Often hard circumstances and multifarious affairs oppose
               themselves, full of danger and of such a nature that knowledge and the means of
               wisdom are absolutely unable to give any profit; things which are so hard that they
               withstand the whole power of the domain of human knowledge.</p>
            <p>But faith is never vanquished by anything. What help can human knowledge afford in
               manifest struggles against invisible natures and incorporeal powers and many things
               of that kind?</p>
            <p>Thou seest how weak the power of knowledge and how strong the power of faith is.
               Knowledge restrains its pupils from approaching unto anything which can do harm to
               nature. But look at the power of faith; what does it command its sons? In my name
               shall they cast out devils and shall take up serpents; and if they drink any deadly
               thing, it shall not hurt them[#n245-4].</p>
            <p>Knowledge according to its laws orders all those who walk in its way, to investigate
               all things from their beginning till their end and then to begin; lest the end of the
               thing be contrary to the limits of human power, and people might undertake fruitless
               labour when their work would prove to be impossible and difficult to be realized. But
               what says faith? All things are possible to him that believeth[#n245-5].</p>
            <p>O unspeakable richness, o ocean rich in its billows and in <pb type="external"
                  n="366"/>its amazing treasures, o effusions of the power of faith! How full of
               encouragement, how delightful and full of trust is its path! And how easy are its
               loads; how delightful is its service. He[#n245-6] that has been deemed worthy of the
               taste of faith and then turns towards psychic knowledge is equal to him that has
               found a pearl of great price and changed it for a copper coin for he has left
               authoritative freedom and has <pb n="246"/>turned towards the means of poverty which
               are full of the fear of bondship.</p>
            <p>Knowledge is not to be rejected, but faith is superior to it. And if we reject, we do
               not reject knowledge, far be that from us, but the distinctions in a variety of
               classes in which it moves itself in opposition to the glory of nature, so that it
               becomes cognate with the class of the demons. This we shall discern distinctly,
               seeing in how many degrees knowledge moves, and how many distinctions there are in
               every one of them, and in which emotions it a rises within every one of the classes
               when it remains in them, and in which of these classes it comes into opposition to
               faith when it is moved in them, and leaves the domain of nature; and which are the
               distinctions of the service in them; and in which class it comes to its natural
               state, having changed its pristine direction preparing the degrees for faith by its
               beautiful behaviour; and to which point the distinctions of this class conduct it;
               and how it <pb type="external" n="367"/>proceeds from this class to a higher one; and
               what are the kinds of service in that latter class, which is the first in honour; and
               the point where knowledge is united to faith and becomes one with it and is clad by
               its influence with fiery impulses so that it blazes spiritually and acquires the
               wings of apathy and is lifted up from the service of earthly things towards the place
               of its creation, acquiring also other things.</p>
            <p>So it is meet for us to know that the degree of the service of faith is superior to
               that of knowledge. And knowledge is made perfect by faith, so that it acquires the
               power to ascend and to perceive that which is above all perceptibility and to behold
               the splendour of Him that is not attained by the mind or the knowledge of the
               creatures.</p>
            <p>Thus knowledge is the ladder on which a man ascends the height of faith, but which he
               does not use any more when he has reached faith. For now we know little out of much
               and we understand little out of much. But when perfection has come this little
               becomes useless.</p>
            <p>So faith shows us as it were before our eyes the reality of that future perfection.
               By faith we are instructed about those unattainable things, not by investigation and
               the power of knowledge. All works of righteousness: fasting, alms, vigils, holiness
               and the others which are performed with the body; and neighbourly love, humility of
               heart, forgiveness of sins,<pb n="247"/>meditation upon beautiful things,
               investigation of the mysteries <pb type="external" n="368"/>hidden in the holy
               scriptures, the occupation of the mind with the practice of good works, the keeping
               of the affections of the soul within the borders, and the other virtues which are
               accomplished with the soul: all these need knowledge as their regulating power. But
               all these are still degrees along which the soul ascends unto the elevated height of
               faith, and they are called virtues.</p>
            <p>As to the discipline of faith, its service is above excellence; it is not a service
               of labour but one of perfect rest; it is consolation and comfort and it is
               accomplished by the impulses of the soul. All the amazing distinctions of spiritual
               discipline, the service of which is apperception of spiritual forces and delight and
               exultation of the soul, and love and joy in God and all the other things which are
               granted through this discipline — all these are forthwith given by faith in fullness
               unto the soul which by grace is made worthy of this blessedness, by God who is rich
               in gifts, as they are mysteriously denoted in the holy scriptures.</p>
            <p>But perhaps some one reasons thus: If all these good things and the works of
               excellence which are mentioned above, and also the refraining from evil and the
               discrimination of subtle emotions arising in the soul, and the struggle with
               deliberation and the strife against alluring affections, and the other qualities
               without which faith cannot even show its power in its working upon the soul — if all
               these are made perfect by knowledge, how then can it be argued that knowledge is in
               opposition to faith?</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="369"/>The solution of this doubt: There are three stages in
               which knowledge ascends and descends in an intelligible way, and where it receives
               its variations according to variations of the places in which it moves, and where it
               also injures or helps. The three stages which I mean are: body, soul, spirit. And
               though knowledge is one in its nature, it becomes condensed or subtilized in
               accordance with its abiding in these intelligible places. And so also its stores are
               changed and also the working of its impulses.</p>
            <p>Hear now the [enumeration of] the stages of its service and the causes by which it
               injures or helps. Knowledge is a gift which was presented by God unto the species of
               rational beings from the beginning of their existence. It is simple in <pb n="248"
               />nature, not divided, as sunlight is, but has variations and divisions in connection
               with its service.</p>
            <p>The first stage of knowledge. When knowledge accompanies the love of the body, it
               gathers provisions as: riches, vain glory, honour, elegant things, bodily comfort,
               means to guard the body against those things which are in opposition to nature, zeal
               for rational wisdom that serves to govern this world, and to be the originator of
               inventions in crafts and learning, and the other things which crown the body in this
               visible world.</p>
            <p>To the properties of this knowledge belong those which have been enumerated above in
               opposition to faith. This knowledge is what is called simple knowledge, because it is
               bare <pb type="external" n="370"/>of every godly thought. It imparts to the mind an
               unspeakable weakness because it dominates it with a bridle and because its whole
               thought is directed upon this world. Thus this degree of knowledge never imagines
               that there is at all an intelligible force and a hidden governor regarding man, or a
               divine care which provides for him. But it thinks that all good which happens to a
               man, and his being saved from injury and guarded against severe difficult accidents
               and against the numerous adversities which inhere to our nature openly or in secret,
               all happen by its own zeal and means.</p>
            <p>This is the degree of knowledge which thinks in the way mentioned and its adherents
               say that there is no providential government in visible things. Consequently it is
               not able to desist from constant anxiety and fear regarding bodily things. Therefore
               [it is accompanied by] pusillanimity, grief, despondency, fear of demons, fear of
               men, rumours of robbers, tales about epidemies anxiety before sicknesses, fear of
               scarcity of food, fear of death, reptiles and beasts and other things of this kind.
               And at all times of the day and night knowledge is tossed about as the sea is by its
               billows, because it does not know to commit its care unto God with the trust of faith
               in Him.</p>
            <p>So knowledge in all its circumstances uses means and artifices. And when by any cause
               its means are exhausted, because it does not see hidden providence, it scolds men as
               its <pb type="external" n="371"/>hindrances and haters.</p>
            <p>By this knowledge was planted the tree of good and evil, which is the eradicator of
               love. Knowledge examines the small <pb n="249"/>stains in others and the shortcomings
               and weak points of men; and in it are the disputations of learning, and dialectics,
               and cunning artifices, and all the other means which dishonour man. In it are also
               presumption and haughtiness, because it reckons to its own credit and not to God's
               credit all things which happen, if they are wholesome.</p>
            <p>Faith on the other hand attributes its deeds to grace. Therefore it cannot be
               haughty. As it is written: I can do all things through grace which strengthened
               me[#n249-1] and again: Not I, but grace which was with me[#n249-3] and what the
               blessed Apostle says: Knowledge puffeth up[#n249-3].</p>
            <p>This he says concerning that knowledge which is not mingled with faith and trust in
               God, but not concerning true knowledge. Far be it! For true knowledge makes perfect
               by humility the souls of those who possess it, as Moses and David and Isaiah and
               Peter and Paul and the other saints who were deemed worthy of perfect knowledge, in
               accordance with the domain of nature. And because their knowledge is constantly
               enveloped by various visions and divine revelations and the supreme sight of
               spiritual things and unspeakable mysteries, their own person is in their eyes, as
               compared with these, dust and ashes.</p>
            <p>That other knowledge must needs be puffed up, because it walks in darkness and it
               examines its subjects in analogy with earthly things without knowing that there is
               something more valuable.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="372"/>But [even] those who are dominated by haughtiness
               because their behaviour is [in their own eyes] of greater importance than earthly and
               bodily things, and because they rely upon service without penetrating with their mind
               in unattainable things — when they come to meditate upon those waves of the glorious
               splendour of the godhead, and their service is on high, their mind then cannot
               deviate to think of impure things and idle deliberations. For those who walk in light
               cannot go astray. All those, therefore, who err from the light of the knowledge of
               God's son, and deviate from truth, walk in these ways.</p>
            <p>This is the first stage of knowledge accompanying the bodily love. This we reject,
               calling it oppositional not only to faith, but to all works of excellence.</p>
            <pb n="250"/>
            <p>The second degree of knowledge. When knowledge leaves this first state and turns
               towards meditation and psychic love, it performs those beautiful things which have
               been described above, through the cooperation of the psychic impulses with the bodily
               senses, by its natural light; namely: fasting, prayer, compassion, recitation of the
               holy scriptures with a view to excellence, strife against the affections, and so on.
               All beautiful deeds and excellent distinctions which are seen in the soul, and the
               amazing stages which are administered in the church of Christ, are accomplished by
               the influence of the <pb type="external" n="373"/>power of the Holy Ghost, in this
               middle stage of knowledge. The Ghost will level ways in our heart leading to faith.
               And by faith we shall gather provisions for this our true world.</p>
            <p>And till this point knowledge is still of a bodily nature and composite, though it
               occupies itself with excellence and though it is the way conducting us to faith. For
               the latter is a degree higher than knowledge; and if knowledge is as it ought to be,
               it will be able by the help of Christ, to ascend [this higher way], when it bases its
               service upon seclusion from men and recitation of the holy scriptures and prayer. And
               the other good works will be made complete by these.</p>
            <p>This is the second degree of knowledge, by which all beautiful works are performed.
               It is called knowledge of practice, because, as to its outward stage, it accomplishes
               its activity by deeds perceptible by the senses of the body.</p>
            <p>The third degree of knowledge, which is the degree of perfection. How knowledge is
               subtilized and acquires spirituality so that it resembles the discipline of those
               invisible forces the service of which is not performed by the apperceptive practice
               of works but by the thoughts of the intellect — hear this now. When knowledge
               elevates itself above earthly things and above the thought of service and begins to
               try its impulses in things hidden from eyesight, and when it partly despises the
               recollection of [worldly] things from which proceeds the perversion of the
               affections, and when it stretches itself upwards and clings to faith by thinking of
               the world to be and love of the promises and investigation <pb type="external"
                  n="374"/>concerning the hidden things — then faith swallows knowledge, gives anew
               birth to it, wholly spiritual. Then it is able to direct its flight towards
               non-bodily places and to the depths of the <choice><sic>unscrutable</sic><corr>inscrutable</corr></choice> ocean of
               wonderful and divine government <pb n="251"/>which directs intelligible and
               apperceptive beings, and to examine spiritual mysteries which are attained by the
               simple and by the subtle intellect. Then the inner senses awake to spiritual service,
               as the order of things which will be in the state of immortality and
               incorruptibility. For from here onwards they have received intelligible resurrection,
               symbolically, as a true sign of that universal renewal.</p>
            <p>These are the three degrees of knowledge, in which the whole course of man is
               contained, that of body, soul and spirit. From the time that a man begins to
               distinguish between good and evil, till he leaves the world, in these three degrees
               is contained the knowledge of himself and the accomplishment of all iniquity and
               wickedness and the summit of all righteousness; and the scrutiny of the depths of all
               spiritual mysteries is worked by one knowledge in these three degrees. Within these
               is the whole emotion of the mind that ascends or descends moving in good things or in
               evil things or between these. These three degrees are called by the Fathers the
               natural, the praeternatural and the supernatural. And these are the three directions
               in which the thoughts of the rational soul ascend and descend, as it has been said.
               Either it works righteousness in nature, or in the domain above nature, its thoughts
               wrapped <pb type="external" n="375"/>up in contemplation towards God; or it will go
               out to feed the swine in the praeternatural domain, as one that has lost the riches
               of his intellect while serving with the herd of demons.</p>
            <p>The first degree of knowledge makes the soul cold to works in the course of the good.
               The middle one excites in the soul fervour in its course in the degrees of faith. The
               third stage is the soul's desisting from service; and this is a symbol of the future,
               that the soul only finds delight in intellectual occupations, in the symbols of
               future goods. But as nature is not yet elevated above the stage of mortality and
               above the load of the flesh so as to abide totally in that spiritual state which is
               exempt from deviation, and because it is not able to administer complete perfection
               in the world of mortality and to abandon the nature of the flesh completely while it
               abides in it as yet, therefore it is in the former and in the latter stage
               alternately. Sometimes the soul in the middle degree of knowledge as a poor being is
               occupied with performing with all its power the virtues proper to nature, because of
               the nature of the body. And sometimes, as those who have received the <pb n="252"
               />spirit of adoption[#n252-1], it delights in the mysteries of freedom through the
               gift of the spirit, even as it pleases its giver. Then it turns again towards the
               poverty of its world, namely of the body, being on its guard against it, lest the
               latter should captivate it by the allurements which are found in its world through
               its troubled and easily deviating impulses. For as long as the soul is covered by the
               curtain of the flesh, it <pb type="external" n="376"/>has no trust. For there is no
               perfect liberation in a non-perfect world.</p>
            <p>The whole service of knowledge is a service of work and of exercise. The deeds of
               faith however, are not performed by labours; for they are accomplished by the
               spiritual impulses through the sole and pure efficacy of the soul [and they are
               elevated] above the senses. Faith is more subtle than knowledge, just as knowledge is
               more subtle than apperceptible deeds. For all the saints which have been deemed
               worthy of spiritual discipline which is ecstasy in God, walk through the power of
               faith, in the delight of that discipline which is above nature.</p>
            <p>I do not call this faith, that a man believes in the discrimination of the adorable
               hypostases of the Essence, or in the properties of His nature, or in the amazing
               government regarding humanity consisting in His accepting our nature. But I call this
               faith: the intelligible light which by grace dawns in the soul and, without leaving
               room for doubt, supports the heart by the testimony of the mind, namely by the
               persuasion of hope which is far from all presumptions and not by tradition from
               hearsay. This light will show the spiritual eyes of the soul the hidden mysteries
               which are in the soul, and the secret riches of divinity which are concealed from the
               eyes of fleshly men and are revealed spiritually to those who at the table of Christ
               are brought up in meditation upon His laws; as He says: If ye keep my commandments, I
               shall send you the Spirit, the Comforter, whom the world cannot receive, <pb
                  type="external" n="377"/>and He will guide you into all truth[#n252-2]. Thus He
               will also show man the holy power, which surrounds him at all times. That power is
               the Comforter. By the power of this faith all the parts of the soul are kindled as it
               were by fire so that it despises all danger on account of its trust in God.</p>
            <pb n="253"/>
            <p>And upon the wings of faith it is lifted up above the circle of the visible world
               and, as drunk, it is constantly in ecstatic thought of God. And by simple sight, and
               by insight without sight of the divine nature, it accustoms the intellect to looking
               at its secret being in meditation. For until the coming of that which is the
               perfection of the mysteries, and until we shall have been made worthy of its
               revelation eye to eye, faith administers unspeakable mysteries between God and the
               saints. May we be deemed worthy of them by the grace of Christ, here by pledge, there
               in reality in the kingdom of heaven, with all those who love Him. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n242-1">ܦܘܖ̈ܣܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n243-1">Matth. 18,3</note>
            <note xml:id="n243-2">Ps. 91,13</note>
            <note xml:id="n244-1">Matth. 21, 22</note>
            <note xml:id="n244-2">Phil. 4,4 sq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n244-3">cf. Ps. 127,1</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-1">Matth. 14,30</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-2">cf. Rom. 8,15</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-3">Matth. 10,26</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-4">Mark 16,17</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-5">Mark 9,23</note>
            <note xml:id="n245-6">Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n249-1"> Cf. Philippians 4,13</note>
            <note xml:id="n249-2"> Cf. 1 Cor. 15,10</note>
            <note xml:id="n249-3"> 1 Cor. 8,1</note>
            <note xml:id="n252-1">Romans 8,15</note>
            <note xml:id="n252-2">John 16,13</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
