<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 42</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 42, pp. 209-210.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="42">
            <head>XLII</head>
            <head>The answer he sent his natural and spiritual brother who had tried to persuade him in
               letters that he should visit him in the inhabited world because he longed to see
               him</head>
            <p>We are not strong, as thou supposest, o blessed one. Perhaps thou art acquainted with
               my weakness, but thou makest not much of my destruction. Constantly thou askest me
               this, placing nature above the thought which once burned in thee, showing thereby
               that thou doest not consider it even as a matter to be treated carefully, though to
               us it seems to be a matter of care. Do not ask from me, o my brother, what gives
               consolation to body and mind, but let me seek the salvation of my soul. Yet a short
               time and we shall have passed away from this world. It is not unknown to thee how
               many persons I should meet, if I went to thy dwelling-place; how many sorts of people
               and of places, before I should have <pb type="external" n="314"/>returned unto my
               place; and by meeting them, what cause for thought my soul would receive — my soul,
               that would be disturbed by the affections which would be awakened in it, after it has
               been left in peace by them a little. That the sight of lay people injures the
               solitary, is a fact with which thou art acquainted; not just the sight of women, but
               also of men.</p>
            <p>Behold how many varying states pass through the mind of him that has for a long time
               been alone with his soul and then suddenly comes in contact with these things,
               hearing and seeing what he is not wont to see and to hear. If meeting his fellow
               brethren injures him that is engaged in the struggle and still wrestles with his foe,
               if the brethren are not in concordance with his aim, into what pit would we fall,
               that have to be freed from the sting of our foe? Especially those [among <pb n="210"
               />us] that know these things by long experience. Therefore I am not to be persuaded
               to do this without necessity. Our heart does not err after those who say that hearing
               and seeing will not harm us and that, in the desert or in the inhabited world, within
               our cell or without it, we are alike in our deliberations on account of our being at
               rest against perturbation as long as we do not experience evil varying states and as
               long as we do not perceive the meeting with persons and things by the shock of
               affections. Those who say this, do not even know it when they receive a blow. But as
               to us, we have not yet reached this psychic health. We suffer from rotting abscesses;
               which, if they be left without bandages but for one day, so that they appeared from
               under the plasters and the bonds, would abound with worms.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
