<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 79</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 79, pp. 361-366.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="79">
            <head>LXXIX</head>
            <head>How the hidden impulses vary along with the variation of outward behavior</head>
            <p>As long as a man clings to renunciation [the thought of] departure from this life is
               continually alive in his mind. And every hour he meditates on the life after
               resurrection, contriving to prepare what is necessary for that state. And a contempt
               for all honour and comfort of the body is sown in his mind, and the thought of the
               baseness of the world moves in him at all times. And he is courageous and always
               possesses the heart of a hero in all fear and danger threatening death. For he is not
               afraid even of death, because he perpetually looks at it very near from a short
               distance and expects it. And his care is cast on God, with full, undoubting
               confidence. And when troubles oppose him, he, as a man that knows assuredly that they
               will prepare crowns for him, bears them with perfect joy, while his soul rejoices and
               exults when receiving <pb type="external" n="539"/>them. For he knows that it is God
               who sends them, because of the profits of things which remain unknown, in the hidden
               acts of providence. But when it happens that on account of some cause some transitory
               thing falls to his lot by the action of him that cunningly devises all evils, at once
               love of the body begins to stir in his soul and he thinks of a long life and
               deliberations connected with bodily comfort germinate in him every moment. But, if
               possible, he <choice><sic>witholds</sic><corr>withholds</corr></choice> his body from being hurt by anything. And he
               contrives all things which can be utilized for the comfort of the body, and becomes
               wanting in that freedom which is not subject to any deliberation of fear, and
               consequently bestows his care and deliberation on <pb n="362"/>all these things,
               namely the emotions that cause fear and the things that produce terror. For the
               courage of the heart has been taken away from him, which he possessed in his soul
               while he was exalted above the world by his renunciation. And now that he has become
               an inheritor of the world, in accordance with the quantity of his possession he also
               has received fear for the law and the provision allotted to him by God.</p>
            <p>For the side to the service of which we prepare our members, is that to which we
               become servants with a submission involving total fear, according to the word of the
               Apostle<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n362-1"/>.</p>
            <p>Anterior to all <choice><sic>affictions</sic><corr>affections</corr></choice> is self-love. Anterior to all virtues is
               that a man despise comforts. He that feeds his body with comforts, is troubled in the
               place of peace. He that indulges in luxury in his youth, will become a slave and sigh
               at the end.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="540"/>As it is impossible that he, whose head is bound within
               the dark<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n362-2"/> bosom of the water, should smell the subtle air which is poured out
               into this empty bosom, so it is not possible that he whose mind is immersed in
               earthly care, should perceive with the smell of his soul the clear air of the new
               world. As the smell of a deadly poison disturbs the constitution of the body, so does
               pernicious sight disturb the peace of the mind.</p>
            <p>As it is not possible that health and illness should be in one body without one being
               destroyed by the other, so it is not possible that money and love be in one house
               without one destroying the other. As it is not possible that glass remains whole in
               the neighbourhood of stone, so it is not possible that a saint should continually
               seek the sight of or discourse with a woman and that his purity should remain
               immaculate. As trees are eradicated by the perpetual blows<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n362-3"/> of violent
               waters, so is the love of the world [eradicated] from the heart by the violence of
               temptations assailing the body. As<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n362-4"/> solvent drugs purify the body from bad
               humours, so does the force of troubles purify the heart from affections. As it is not
               possible that a dead man should perceive the things of life, so the soul of a
               solitary, who is buried in solitude as in a grave, is exempt from the storm which
               usually blows on account of the apperception of things which pass among men. As it is
               not possible for him that spares his adversary in the field of <pb type="external"
                  n="541"/>battle to avoid blows, so it is not possible that a champion <pb n="363"
               />should spare his body and that his soul should be saved from destruction. As
               childhood, when terrified by frightful sights runs to seek refuge at the skirts of
               its parents, so the soul, when troubled by the terror of temptations, hastens towards
               God to seek shelter in perpetual beseechings. And as temptations assail, to the same
               extent it multiplies its beseechings. But when it has free-space, it expands itself
               in distraction.</p>
            <p>As those who are handed over to the judges in order to be scourged on account of
               their evils, become humble and immediately confess their faults, when they come
               suddenly before the scourges, so that their punishment is lessened and they are soon
               delivered through the agency of small troubles, but others of them are foolish and
               obstinate and their scourging is augmented and at last, after much scourging, with
               lacerated backs, they confess against their will, without gaining any profit; so when
               we are handed over from divine mercy unto justice, for the faults to which we have
               become accustomed without returning to the [good] direction, and the Judge of the
               world orders us to stretch ourselves before the rod ot temptations, lest our
               scourging in the world to be, become heavy; if, as soon as the rod of the Judge
               approaches us, we humble ourselves and recollect our forfeits and confess before the
               avenger, we shall soon be saved by small temptations; but if we become obstinate in
               troubles, and confess not that we were the cause of them ourselves and that we have
                  <pb type="external" n="542"/>deserved even more than these, and if we vituperate
               men and sometimes demons and sometimes even God's justice and assume the attitude of
               victors though we do not think and say that our works are like theirs, and if we do
               not think of the fact that God knows and recognizes us better than we do ourselves,
               and that the judgment of the Lord is over the whole earth and that no man is
               chastised without His orders, then our distresses assail us as they come, and our
               trouble becomes violent, and they hand us over the one to its fellow as in a chain,
               till we know ourselves and become humble and perceive our sins; for without
               apperception it is not possible for us even to come to [good] direction; then at last
               when we have suffered many troubles, we confess our sins in a confession without
               profit and without gathering from it any consolation. And also this that a man
               perceives his sins, is a gift which is allotted by God to the mind, when He sees that
               one <pb n="364"/>has been fatigued by various temptations, lest he depart this world
               under all these distresses and troubles, without profit; and [also this is a gift: to
               perceive] that we have not lacked insight on account of obstinacy, but on account of
               ignorance.</p>
            <p>Some depart this world under these circumstances, without confessing that they are
               guilty, but litigating and vituperating. God, however, who is compassionate, looks to
               whether they humble themselves, that He may forgive them and give them expansion. Not
               only that He will put an end to their temptation, but He will even forgive their sins
               at a faint confession of their heart.</p>
            <p>As a man who offers a large offering to the king and tries <pb type="external"
                  n="543"/>to make his face benignant, so he that sheds tears in prayer before God,
               the king of all the worlds, makes to pass away all the degrees of his sins, and is
               even granted to see His face <choice><sic>beingnant</sic><corr>benignant</corr></choice>. As the lamb that leaves the pen,
               and in its error comes before the den of the wolves, so is the solitary who separates
               himself from the communion of his fellows under the pretext of lonely dwelling, and
               constantly visits spectacles and the distraction of the town.</p>
            <p>As a man who bears on his shoulder a pearl of great price and goes on an ill-famed
               way so that he is in perpetual fear of being robbed, so is he that bears the pearl of
               chastity and walks in the world the way of the enemies. Before he enters the chamber
               of the grave, which is the place of confidence, it is not to be expected that it will
               escape robbers and <choice><sic>pluderers</sic><corr>plunderers</corr></choice>. Perhaps he that is not afraid, is able
               [to go that way]; even this man does not know either, on which spot or from where or
               at which moment he will suddenly be assailed and robbed of his hope. Some are robbed
               at the gate of their house, namely in old age.</p>
            <p>As a man who drinks wine at the time of mourning and gets drunk and forgets all the
               suffering of his sorrow, so is he that, having got drunk by the love of God in this
               world which is a place of wailing, forgets his sorrow and all his distress and,
               through his drunkenness, becomes apathetic against all the affections of sin.</p>
            <p>Whose heart is supported by hope in God, his soul is a swift beast of wings. He whose
               spirit is at all times exalted above the earth and who flies above the sky with the
               thoughts <pb type="external" n="544"/>of his deliberations, and is in continual
               prayer, is as a man <pb n="365"/>who has the wind as his driving animal, so that his
               enemy cannot reach him. Every time the latter seeks to join him, he flies away from
               him.</p>
            <p>As a man who has an advocate in the court of justice, so is he that is compassionate
               to the troubled ones.</p>
            <p>As a man who is amidst dangerous storms on the ocean and casts his utensils from the
               ship, so is he that despises the hindrances on his godly way in this world which is
               an ocean ready to suffocate him.</p>
            <p>Hindrances will not fail. What doest thou in a house which is not thine? The sight of
               a corpse ought to be for thee an instruction concerning thy departure from here. Why
               doest thou multiply bonds to thyself? Gain thy life before thy light grow dim and
               thou seek help without finding it. This life has been given thee for repentance; do
               not spend it with various things.</p>
            <p>The cross is the gate of mysteries; here takes place the entrance of the mind unto
               the knowledge of the heavenly mysteries. The knowledge of the cross is hidden within
               the sufferings of the cross. And in accordance with communion with them is the
               apperception of the cross, according to the word of the Apostle<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n365-1"/>. The greater
               place the suffering of Christ takes in us, the greater becomes our consolation in
               Christ. Consolation means contemplation, which is psychic sight. Sight gives birth to
               consolation. It is not possible that our soul produce spiritual fruits, except when
               our heart is dead to the world. For the Father quickens the soul that has died the
               death of Christ, in contemplation of all the worlds.</p>
            <p>Another observation. If thou diest not to the world, the <pb type="external" n="545"
               />spiritual <persName>Adam</persName> will not be quickened in thee. When a man, by being offered
               spiritually, dies to all dealings of this dwellingplace, and trusts his life to the
               life after the resurrection, Grace will dwell with him. And his behaviour is
               spiritually strengthened. And when he hates the world, he perceives the behaviour of
               the new man who is exalted above the filth of human habitation and is deemed worthy
               of divine revelations.</p>
            <p>It is not possible for us to be dead to the world in the world, as long as our mind
               desires comforts, and the world, by its affairs, is placed before our senses and by
               apperception <pb n="366"/>renews recollection and incites the body unto seeking what
               it wishes, by close contact with [worldly] things, by sight, hearing, touch, smell
               and taste.</p>
            <p>The soul's being dead to the world is the heart's being free from the thought of its
               recollections and the soul's being void of the deliberations concerning [worldly]
               things and the will being cut off from the love of thinking upon them.</p>
            <p>For it is not possible that our heart be in peace exalted above disturbance and in
               serenity of love lifted up above the world, when there are poured out into it
               recollections that renew through meetings with things by the senses, their
               receptacles. The mortification of the soul to the world cannot be acquired, if not
               the body be also beyond apperception and sight of things.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n362-1">Cf. Rom. 8,15</note>
            <note xml:id="n362-2"><choice><sic>litt.</sic><corr>lit.</corr></choice>: thick</note>
            <note xml:id="n362-3">ܚܘܖ̈ܦܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n362-4">Introduction</note>
            <note xml:id="n365-1">Cf. Philipp. 4, 10</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
