<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 26</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 26, pp. 128-132.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="26">
            <head>XXVI</head>
            <head><pb type="external" n="189"/>Against those who say: if God is good wherefore has he
               made these things?</head>
            <p>Sin, hell and death do not at all exist with God. For they are facts, not persons.
               Sin is the fruit of will. There was a time, when it was not. And there will be a
               time, when it will not be. Hell is the fruit of sin; at some time or other it had
               beginning; but its end is not known. Death, however, is provided by the wisdom of the
               creator. It will rule a certain time only over nature; then it will vanish
               altogether. <persName>Satan</persName> is the name of the deviation of will from the truth, but it is not
               the designation of a natural being.</p>
            <p>Although thou findest, o my brother, some of these things also in other books, still
               we may not be reckoned by thee as those who seek their own glory, because we pretend
               the work of others to be our own, but, on the contrary, as those who are humble,
               since we suck from the milk of our fore-fathers those things which we have collected
               and placed before ourselves as objects of contemplation, with the aim of enriching
               the intellect with their stores in which we may pasture and be fed.</p>
            <p>For we have not forgotten that we are not above the rank of disciples so long as we
               dwell in the flesh. The faculty of discernment is the emotionality of the natural
               ideas. When these go the natural way in their emotions, they meet with the changing
               elements and worlds. But when [they go] a subsidiary way, another use will be found
               for the former ones. For when the natural [faculties] are twofold in their
               intellectual use, they will be understood in one of these only, and that the
               non-psychic state.</p>
            <p>When thou catchest the delight of the words of the service, then the mind is eager to
               remain in it continuously. If thou desirest, however, to fulfill its wish, then
               <choice><sic>haste</sic><corr>hasten</corr></choice> towards the knowledge of its cause. If thou hast attained this
               quickly, as <pb n="129"/>one discerning and not blind, it is not difficult for thee
               to taste this [delight] constantly without impediment. And what then is the influence
               which is also called cause? By a file, which does not add anything to it, iron is
               brought to brilliancy and radiance; for these properties belong to its essence. But
               what happens? The file removes from it the rust, which has come upon it, although no
               one is responsible for that. The same theory holds true as to the nature of the mind.
               Bring it into contact with the file; then thou wilt find how it shines at the time of
               service, imitating the rays of the stars. For a thing is not able to go its way
               [without aid]; it delays, if no one cares for it. Therefore have I said that during
               the recitation of Psalms (not during the prayer of the heart and recitation) the
               heart can hardly be captivated. It is otherwise with those; with them only small care
               is needed. They are able to make [recitation of Psalms] profitable. But without them,
               care for recitation will <pb type="external" n="191"/>be found to be in vain. The
               latter will be promoted, even if there be no other increase to it, if the former be a
               stock already present<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n129-1"/>.</p>
            <p>Hunger is able to procure food; but it is not inclined to abstain from eating.</p>
            <p>Delicious for the husbandman is the bread won by his sweat. Without previous sweat,
               the bread of truth does not give saturation. The body which is the husbandman, sweats
               and feeds the rational mind. And this happens even when the mind is deprived of its
               customary, non-natural food.</p>
            <p>Spiritual excellency is the daughter of excellency of will and this it is
               necessarily. For freedom is the natural force of reason, and not slavery. But on that
               side, towards which it inclines and where it abides, it gives birth to a different
               force, which is not natural. And when this is born, freedom becomes ruled and
               governed by compulsion. I dare to say: it becomes bound, without self-government.
               Before, compulsion was voluntary; now compulsion has mastered will.</p>
            <p>And I say that this is to be seen on both sides, when a man subdues himself on the
               right side and when he gives an opportunity to the left one. But the mind that has
               learnt to see discriminately, is able to observe how compulsion on both sides
               dominates freedom, when the force which is not from nature, is born <pb n="130"/>from
               the submission of the will. I do not mean the usual force, <pb type="external"
                  n="192"/>which is very difficult; but that which is called secondary.</p>
            <p>Custom at any rate is subject to the will; though it strives to resist it. Apart from
               this we know two forces; one subdues the will; the other dominates nature. It has
               even power to alter nature. That influence dominates nature, is known to those who
               have been tested by it.</p>
            <p>The varying states of the hearts and the deviating minds which are usually born from
               them (free and bound, living and dead) are promoted to a large extent by the
               disparity<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n130-1"/> of contemplation which rises in human minds, concerning divine
               judgments. By the mediation of this disparity the world<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n130-2"/> has been preserved
               for thousands of years. This disparity is largely helpful towards changing the course
               of mortal life, and what is greatest of all, towards the contemplation of judgments
               which engender trust in God.</p>
            <p>Many hearts as soon as trust has entered them, resemble a man who has taken deadly
               poison.</p>
            <p>Even to true and veracious sons, with ten parts of love five parts of fear are mixed
               together.</p>
            <p>Nature liable to deviation is not able to receive here the perfection of divine
               truth, or to know the whole will of God regarding the class of rational beings; even
               Paul and his equals are not sufficient for this; till the liability to err has been
               taken</p>
            <!-- ec the following two paragraphs belong to footnote below -->
            <p>Going back in literature, we find the terms in the Neo-Platonists. Of importance is
               the following passage in <persName>Plotinus</persName> (Enneades III II § XVII): καὶ δὴ ὁ λόγος ὁ πᾶς εἷς·
               μεμέρισται δὲ οὐκ εἰς ἴσα· ὅθεν καὶ τοῦ παντὸς διάφοροι τόποι βελτίους καὶ χείρους
               καὶ ψυχαὶ οὐκ ἴσαι ἐναρμόττουσιν οὕτως τοῖς οὐκ ἴσοις (cf. also § XVIII and III III §
               3,5 and Proclus, Institutio Theologica, ed. Creuzer § VII).</p>
            <p>Going further back, we find that Philo was well-acquainted with the ideas of ἰσότης
               and ἀνισότης. Ed. Mangey 1 493 sqq. is very instructive. And in the fragments <persName>Mangey</persName>
               gives the following sentences from Philo (II 665):<!-- Greek? --> ὥσπερ τῶν τελειοτάτων ἀγαθῶν τὸ
               ἰσόμετρον αἴτιον, οὕτω τῶν μεγίστων κακῶν ἡ ἀμετρία, τὸν ὠφελιμώτατον λύουσα δεσμὸν
               ἰσότητος. And: τὸ ἄνισον λυπηρὸν καὶ διαστατικὸν ὥσπερ καὶ τὸ ἶσον ἄλυπον καὶ
               συνδετικὸν εἰς ὠφέλειαν. — Τὸ ἔννομον καὶ τὸ ἶσον εἰρήνης σπέρμα, καὶ σωτηρίας
               αἴτιον, καὶ τῆς εἰς ἅπαντα δαιμονῆς. Ἀνισότης δὲ καὶ πλεονεξία ὁρμητηρία πολέμου, καὶ
               λυτικὰ τῶν ὄντων. <pb n="131"/><pb type="external" n="193"/>away, so that nature no
               longer errs through being aware of this.</p>
            <p>What is parity and disparity? Disparity of contemplation — differences and variations
               in one soul — is the eternal thought of God being unattainable. Parity is truth being
               revealed.</p>
            <p>If a nature able to err should receive in this world the exact truth, it would die by
               the power of its liability to err. This is 'O, depth of the riches'<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n131-1"/> and 'How
               unsearchable are His judgments' and 'Who has known the mind of God' and the like,
               which in an astonishing way and among sighs rise in the mind from time to time, which
               by some is called the Cloud. From this, disparity of contemplation and divergence of
               insight are born concerning the unattainable inquiry into God's judgments.</p>
            <p>When, however, the perfection of nature will have come, in a world without deviation,
               nature will be no longer afraid to know divine truth, as if it would deviate to the
               left because of trust. Trust engenders contempt and profusion of spirit. Fear, on the
               other hand, is wonted to check aberration, so that it becomes bridled. This fear thou
               findest in thy soul by the contemplation of the different judgments and worlds and
               the disparity of behaviour and the non-correspondence between the retribution
               provided to men in this world and the righteousness which shows itself from time to
               time, and [God's] constant <pb type="external" n="194"/>patience, and the righteous
               and the sinners, and the contrary and incongruous meetings of repugnant persons, as
               ordered by Providence. When the intellect observes all this, emotion takes hold of
               the whole soul. And then is born in it examination of deliberations, of words and
               actions and of the outlines of the domain of divine righteousness.</p>
            <p>Now when the intellect withdraws itself from this and is exalted unto the unique
               Essence, by the contemplation of the properties of that good Nature<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n131-2"/> which
               possesses eternal knowledge, which is anterior to all existence, and of all His other
               properties, fear is expelled at once and the mind is supported by confidence.</p>
            <p>When the intellect descends again from that place and returns again to the worlds and
               their distinctions, it will fly and give way to fear, because Providence does not
               allow it to be always in the presence of this contemplation of truth. Therefore from
                  <pb n="132"/>time to time [fear] will take away from the heart the strength of
               trust which is inspired by true contemplation, and it will let the intellect be
               tortured by diverse opinions; lest [the intellect] should desist from judging
               constantly the veracity of its deliberations and actions and thus acquire
               cautiousness, for it does not know how it will meet the judgment of God. To whom be
               praise for ever and ever Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n129-1"> I am not quite certain of the meaning of the last
               sentences.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-1">Disparity (ܠܐ ܫܘܝܘܬܐ, cf. Register) is a term which, as well as
               its opposite, often occurs in cognate works, but of which it is not easy to give a
               clear definition. Dionysius the Areopagite is well acquainted with the idea (ἰσότης
               and ἀνισότης): τὴν γὰρ ἀνιστότητα εἴ τις ἐκλάβοι τὰς ἐν τῷ ὅλῳ τῶν ὅλων πρὸς ὅλα
               διαφοράς· καὶ ταύτης ἡ δικαιοσύνη Φρουρητικὴ, μὴ συγχωροῦσα συμμιγῆ τὰ ὅλα ἐν ὅλοις
               γενόμενα διαταραχθῆναι· Φυλάττουσα δὲ τὰ ὄντα πάνα κατ’ εἶδος ἕκαστον, ἐν ᾧ ἕκαστον
               εἶναι πέφυκε (De divinis nominibus, Chapter VIII). On the other hand, in the ninth
               chapter, Dionysius argues that ἰσότης is a divine property, corresponding to some
               extent with justice; it means that God is not composed and pervades and reaches the
               Universe in an equal way.</note>
            <note xml:id="n130-2"> Reading ܥܠܡܐ in stead of ܠܥܠܡܐ</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-1">Romans 11,33</note>
            <note xml:id="n131-2">ܟܝܢܐ viz. God</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
