<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 76</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 76, pp. 350-352.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="76">
            <pb n="350"/>
            <head>LXXVI</head>
            <head><pb type="external" n="521"/>Short sayings</head>
            <p>The blessed Paul teaches us saying: Put off the old man and put on the new man, which
               after God is created in righteousness and holiness<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n350-1"/>.</p>
            <p>He does not say: Put on the new man over the old man. For he knows that this is not
               possible. Look, how wisely he gives his order. He does not say: Put on the new man
               who is renewed by the knowledge of God, but he says, first put off this, and then put
               on the new. Also he says definitely in another place: Flesh and blood cannot inherit
               the kingdom of God, neither does corruption inherit incorruption<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n350-2"/>. By
               incorruption he means the knowledge of the other world. By corruption and flesh and
               blood he designates the corruptible affections of soul and body, which have the place
               of their motion in the fleshly mind. Purity he calls the new man, and by the kingdom
               of God he means the exalted and intelligible contemplation of the blessed motions of
               the essential rays into which the saintly soul only is allowed to enter when its
               incorruptible emotions are lifted up above corruption and flesh and blood.</p>
            <p>If<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n350-3"/> the apple of thy soul's eye has not been purified, do not venture to look
               at the sun, lest thou be bereaved of thy usual visual power and thou be thrown into
               one of those <pb type="external" n="522"/>intelligible places which are Tartarus and
               a type of Hell, namely darkness without God, whither those who with the impulses of
               their mind leave nature, wander by the cognitive nature which they possess. Therefore
               he that ventured to go to the banquet in sordid garments, was ordered to be thrown
               out into that outer darkness. By the banquet is designated the sight of spiritual
               knowledge. The institutions in it are the manifold divine mysteries, full of joy and
               exultation and delight of the soul. The garment of the banquet he calls the mantle of
               purity; the sordid garments the emotions of the affections in the soul which are
               defiled, the outer darkness, the state <pb n="351"/>without any delight of true
               knowledge and communion with God. He that is clad with such garments and ventures to
               think phantastically with his intellect on the heights of God and to introduce and to
               settle his soul within the spiritual contemplations of that holy banquet which is
               made to dawn in the pure only, and who, partaking only of the delight of the
               affections, wishes to mingle in the delight of that banquet — is suddenly
               overwhelmed, as it were by some hallucination, and expelled thence unto the place
               without rays, which is called Hell and destruction, which is ignorance and oblivion
               of God.</p>
            <p>For it has been said that the things of God come of their own, if there is a pure and
               undefiled place. That they come of their own, means that it naturally belongs to
               purity that heavenly light shines in it, without investigation and labour <pb
                  type="external" n="523"/>on our part. For in the pure heart, the new heaven is
               stamped; of which the sight is light and the room is spiritual. As also in another
               place it is said: As the magnet-stone has the natural faculty to attract atoms of
               iron, so has spiritual knowledge [the faculty to attract] the pure heart.</p>
            <p>Though it has been handed down rightly by the true ones that no mind is absolutely
               steadfast against the allurements of the affections in this life, yet I say with
               confidence without being afraid of the truth of experience, that he who is clad with
               the garment of mourning in his mind, is not only invincible against the allurements
               of the <choice><sic>effections</sic><corr>affections</corr></choice>, but a hero in the war against them and a victor,
               because they absolutely do not venture to show themselves with the intention of
               strife, nor do they even venture to appear from afar where there is a mourning soul
               which has made itself a wailing-place with various lamentations on account of its
               sins. As it has been said by the blessed Jacob: It makes its abode in the grave, till
               it meets the beloved Joseph. Where there is the bitterness of mourning, I do not
               believe that the above-mentioned pleasure of the affections is admitted.</p>
            <p>But I say that in watchfulness lies this service and confidence, exalted above fear.
               He that is constantly in a state of mourning because of his fear — as he does not
               know what the end of his course will be — is more excellent than he that is <pb
                  type="external" n="524"/>constantly in the way of gladness, because he perceives
               the hope of his service.</p>
            <p>O thou whose town is vanquished by inward affections, put <pb n="352"/>on the armour
               of mourning and persecute them and save thy soul from their hands. For always
               invincible is this weapon and that of confidence, and tried by the true ones.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n350-1">Cf. Ephes. 4,22,24</note>
            <note xml:id="n350-2">1 Cor. 15,50</note>
            <note xml:id="n350-3">The following passage occurs also p. 16 sq. Cf. the
               Introduction.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
