<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 57</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 57, pp. 268-272.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="57">
            <head>LVII</head>
            <p>How patience for the sake of the love of God acquires help from God</p>
            <p>In accordance with a man's despising this world and his being occupied by the fear of
               God, divine care will approach him and he will perceive its help in secret and there
               will be given to him clear emotions so as to understand it. Even though a man be not
               destitute of the goods of this world by his own will, still even as he is devoid of
               them, so mercy will follow him and divine compassion will support him. Glory to Him
               who shows us His grace in things of the right and of the left hand[#n268-1] and who
               in all of them lays a cause for the renewal of our life; and who makes the souls of
               those who, wilfully, are too weak to acquire life, ascend towards excellence, by
               involuntary distress.</p>
            <p><pb type="external" n="400"/>The poor Lazarus was not destitute of the goods of this
               world by his own will, even his body was stricken by ulcers; bitter plagues he had to
               endure, one still harder than the other: illness and poverty. Yet in the end he
               received honour in the bosom of the patriarch.</p>
            <p>God is near to the suffering heart which out of trouble cries to Him. And though the
               body sometimes refuses to bear these pains for the sake of the help, yet, as a
               physician who causes healing by the acute pains of his operations, the Lord greatly
               favours his soul in accordance with the heavy pains of his distress. Now when the
               love of Christ is not so prevalent in thee that thou art without affection in all
               troubles through thy gladness in Him, know then that the world lives in thee more
               than Christ does. When illnesses and want, or injury of the body, or fear of its
               afflictions trouble thy mind in the joy of thy hope and thy clear thought in our
               Lord, know then that the body lives in thee, not Christ. He whose <pb n="269"/>love
               is prevalent over thee, he lives in thee. If thou art able to walk in serenity on thy
               way unto Christ, fulfilling all things required without lack, without bodily
               torments, without fear of adversaries, know then that thou art sick in thy mind and
               devoid of the taste of God's glory.</p>
            <p>I do not judge why thou art so, but [I say this] in order that thou mayest know at
               least how far thou art from the <pb type="external" n="401"/>accomplishment, even
               partially, of the discipline of the saints which lived before us. Do not say: There
               is not a man to be found whose mind, shipwrecked though the body may be by every
               sorrow of temptation, is so wholly exalted above sickness that the love of Christ
               vanquished the affectability of the mind. I refrain from reminding thee of the deeds
               of the martyrs; perhaps we would be unable to remain standing firm before the deluge
               of their sufferings, in which patience through the power of love has vanquished the
               trouble and the love of the body. But because even the recollection of these things
               is difficult to human nature, in that we are troubled by the greatness of the thing
               and by its amazing aspect, we will turn towards the ungodly philosophers, and from
               them, by a comparison with their patience, we shall find instruction concerning the
               weakness of our will. But this has also to be preserved till its time when we shall
               explain it in its place[#n275-1], knowing that also this is a sign of illness. Thus
               we shall not judge this matter from ourselves, but so that we may believe how very
               low we have been cast down and how that, despite this, it is possible that the
               Highest should become wholly man. The drunkard will never believe that there are many
               men who do not even drink wine. Neither will the lascivious believe, that there are
               men who wholly abstain from sexual union. Neither will he that is troubled by a
               certain desire believe that there are men who are not troubled at all by this desire,
               even though they be incited by other things. Neither will he that is constantly ill,
               believe that there exists a body which is not ruined by illnesses. So the consolation
                  <pb type="external" n="402"/>of those who are not able to vanquish absolutely [the
               weakness of] the mind, may be in the consideration that there is no man who is
               completely elevated above this weakness. That there are people in whom the love of
               Christ has vanquished <pb n="270"/>the weakness of nature so that they wholly despise
               the body and its love, whose mind is not troubled by the gladness in Christ so that
               this should bring about the possibility of being vanquished by the power of
               oppositional forces on the part of the body, and in whom the [divine] gifts have
               overcome the incompetence of nature — this they do not believe at all.</p>
            <p>I do not say that difficulties wholly fail in the way of God, or that there is anyone
               who lives in this way without temptations. On the contrary, I say that he that lives
               in excellence, day by day will find more troubles, and the farther he proceeds
               onwards, the more he is oppressed by distresses. This is a sign of the veraciousness
               of his course, that he lives a bitter life in this world and that he departs this
               body with torments. For this world is not the world of the righteous, and they cannot
               abide in it without distresses. But the will can be strengthened by grace to despise
               all these things and keep the mind without confusion, by the gladness of the love of
               Christ.</p>
            <p>That there have been men who reached this, and that it is possible that they become
               thus even now, is due to the great help of the gift of Christ. Do not judge, o man,
               the <pb type="external" n="403"/>deeds of all men, from thy own case, and do not
               weigh their behaviour against the weight of thy own weakness. If thou seekest, begin
               with hope, then thou wilt be helped. And be not incredulous lest thou be left by Him
               that sows these things in thee, so that thou reach the measure of thine own
               smallness, whatever it be, in contrast to those who have vanquished the world and its
               confusion absolutely.</p>
            <p>If thou doest not believe the church, approach unto the philosophers. Then thou wilt
               see, how much power the will possesses to be uplifted above the body and to remain
               without confusion according to the choice of him that chooses. When thou seest how
               these, who did not know God, have displayed in the face of the world the endurance
               and vigour of a heroic will, and how they have shown how much force inner nature
               possesses to vanquish everything if it like — a man will be struck with amazement in
               reading their histories at the power which God has assembled in this nature, that, if
               we like, we can vanquish everything. But because we do not will, we preach the
               weakness of nature. And while we hide the vigour of nature by the weakness of our
               will, we say: Who should ever be able to vanquish these things?</p>
            <pb n="271"/>
            <p>One of them had mastered the will of the body to such a degree, that, in order not to
               give up and to deviate from the choice he had made, he did not even allow his mind to
               be disturbed when the sword was drawn; so fear of death could not break through the
               barrier he had made for himself. When <pb type="external" n="404"/>for many years he
               had kept silence, the king of the Greeks, wondering at his fame and desiring to put
               him to the test, ordered him to appear before him. As the philosopher remained silent
               whenever the king spoke and questioned him, giving no answer, the king grew angry and
               ordered him to be put to death, because he was not even impressed by the glory of his
               throne and crown. The philosopher was not moved by this [order], but kept his rule
               quietly. Then the king ordered the executioners to slay him if he should break his
               rule out of fear of the sword; but to bring him back living if he should be firm of
               will. When the moment had come and the executioners commanded him to bend his will or
               die, he deliberated thus: it is better once to suffer death, while keeping the rule
               of my will which I have borne all this time, than to give way out of fear of death,
               putting to shame my wisdom, and be found a coward because of that which I shall have
               to meet at any rate, whenever it be. — By this firmness of will and this heroic mind
               he was delivered even from death, being found just and true to his rule. Doest thou
               see what power will possesses? This sage stretched his neck before the sword without
               breaking his own rule.</p>
            <p>Others have trampled upon the desire of nature and have tamed it by the bridle which
               they have put into its mouth. Others have remained unmoved before disdain. Others
               have <pb type="external" n="405"/>been found consistent and without wrath, before
               blows. Some have suffered from their equals what could hardly be borne; others from
               people who were by far their inferiors. Others have remained without feelings of
               enmity or anger while their possessions were robbed. Others have shown endurance
               under horrible and severe illnesses, without being troubled, and have added even
               other ascetic practices. Some have performed voluntary labours, others have practised
               total nakedness, apart from the covering demanded by chastity, or a solitary life,
               and support of life by raw food. Thus king Alexander, when once he went to see one of
               them, did not hear anything from him except on contempt of the world.</p>
            <pb n="272"/>
            <p>All this [they practised] lest they should be withheld from meditation and the
               occupying themselves with their wisdom.</p>
            <p>If the labour of instruction and the discipline of wisdom, apart from the fear of God
               and the light of faith and the hope of a world to be, are able to perform such heroic
               deeds, who then should not be despised by his own conscience, that notwithstanding
               all the light of Christ which is poured out on the world, and the great gifts which
               are lavished abundantly in secret, and the hope on God which day by day is confirmed
               by events — still the difficulties and the pleasure of this body are master of him,
               so that he does not remain as a diamond for the sake of the love of God, despising
               everything joyfully?</p>
            <p>If it is possible to be in doubt as to how men vanquish all <pb type="external"
                  n="406"/>these things — every wise man knows that no one can do anything by his
               own power. But it is possible, because by God's help and a firm will he finds all
               things weaker than himself.</p>
            <p>By these the zeal of the solitaries has been kindled, so that they have abandoned and
               suddenly given up the world and what belongs to it, and have become strong
               withstanding all contrary things and, by endurance of will and by the help of their
               Lord, have vanquished all difficulties whatsoever. For they dwelt in the midst of
               them. Many of them were adherents of the doctrine of the philosophers, saying: If
               external sages, in spite of the fact that they were not on the way of God, have taken
               upon themselves, in return for transitory wisdom and training in the instruction of
               this temporary world, to bear these things, and have become alienated to the world
               and apart from it in their dealings, so as to reach, the desire of their will, though
               there was no just basis in their thoughts nor hope of <choice><sic>inmortality</sic><corr>immortality</corr></choice> in
               their labours, performing these things to this high degree with a view to a vain
               expectation — how much more are we bound to endure for the sake of the love of God
               and to despise all difficulties for the sake of the sublime future which has been
               promised us.</p>
            <p>So they have been confirmed by this thought and have mastered the laxity of their
               deliberations and have entered the arena and turned not their backs until they have
               gained the crown. They were an example even for later generations, and have shown the
               world how those who walk this way have to enter the arena.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n268-1">happy and unhappy</note>
            <note xml:id="n269-1"> 403 (Syriac text)</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
