<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a">Part 1, Treatise 28</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s">The Mystical Treatises of <persName>Isaac the
                  Syrian</persName></title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
               >Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editing, proofreading, data entry and revision by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus"
                  >Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#cfreeman">Cullen
                  Freeman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Mystic Treatises by Isaac of Nineveh Translated from Bedjan's Syriac Text with an
               Introduction and Registers by A. J. Wensinck, Treatise 28, pp. 136-138.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Internet Archive on 26 November 2024: <ref
                  target="https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt"
                  >
                  https://archive.org/stream/IsaacOfNinevehMysticTreatises/isaac_of_nineveh_mystical_treatises_djvu.txt
               </ref>. This Internet Archive transcription has been thoroughly edited and is made
               available under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"
                  >Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise" n="28">
            <head>XXVIII</head>
            <head>A symbolical demonstration concerning the theory of Sabbath and Sunday</head>
            <p>Sunday is the symbol of true knowledge which is not received by flesh and blood, and
               which is elevation above [mere] opinion. In this world, however, there is no eighth
               day but neither is there a true Sabbath. The fact that God rested on the seventh day
               is a symbol of the rest of our nature from the course of <pb n="137"/>this life. For
               the grave is also of a bodily nature; it belongs to this world. Six days are
               accomplished in the service of life; the seventh is accomplished in the grave; the
               eighth in departing from it. As those who are worthy receive in this world the
               mysteries of the Sunday in a symbol — they do not receive the day as long as they are
               in their bodily nature — so <pb type="external" n="203"/>those who are worthy receive
               in this world the mysteries of the Sabbath symbolically, not the true Sabbath which
               is perfect rest from wanton influences. God has given us to taste of a mysterious
               indication of all things, but He has not decreed that we should walk here in
               intercourse with the real truth. For the real, not the symbolical Sabbath, will
               happen in the grave, viz. rest which finishes the torments of the affections and the
               toil against them. The whole man gives rest there to the body together with the
               soul.</p>
            <p>In six days God established the existence of this world and created the elements
               <ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n137-1"/> and connected their existence with the administration of never resting
               motion and [ordered] that they should not rest from their course before their
               dissolution. And from the force of these, viz. the primeval elements, He has composed
               our body. He did not give those rest from their motions; neither did He grant our
               body, their offspring, rest from service. As the term of our nature He fixed rest,
               when we shall follow our first relatives, rest consisting in the dissolution of life.
               Thus He said to Adam: In the sweat of thy face thou shalt eat bread<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n137-2"/>. Till
               when? Till thou returnest unto the dust, for out of it wast thou taken. Thou shalt
               work in the ground and it shall bring forth to thee thorns and thistles. This denotes
               symbolically that this world is a world of service as long as it exists.</p>
            <p>Our Lord, since the night when He sweated, has changed this sweat caused by working
               in the earth which brings forth thorns and thistles, into the sweat which also rises
               during prayer and which man should produce in the service of <pb type="external"
                  n="204"/>righteousness. For five thousand years He left man to work in his sweat,
               for the way of the saints had not yet been revealed, as the Apostle says. He
               appeared, however, with His grace in the latter days and ordered our free will to
               replace sweat by sweat. At any rate this change does not show that He <pb n="138"
               />ordered rest. But He was merciful upon us for the sake of our long and weary work
               in the earth. If, however, we desist from sweating for this [spiritual service], we
               must necessarily reap thorns; for desisting from this, means the service of the
               material earth which brings forth thorns and thistles according to her nature. In
               reality the thorns are the affections which grow in us from bodily seed. As we bear
               the image of Adam so we necessarily bear his affections too. The earth is not free to
               desist from bearing; for it brings forth on account of its nature. The earth is our
               relative according to God's witness unto us 'the dust out of which thou wast taken'.
               The one [brings forth] thorns; the other, the rational [earth], affections.</p>
            <p>If now our Lord has been a symbolical example for us in every respect, viz. in all
               his different dealings — for till the <choice><sic>minth</sic><corr>ninth</corr></choice> hour Friday He did not take rest
               from work, not even from the toilsome work which symbolically represents our whole
               life; the Sabbath He expected in the grave only — where then are those<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n148-1"/> who
               pretend that there is a Sabbath in this world, viz. rest from affections? Concerning
               the Sunday, however, it is difficult to speak. Our Sabbath is the day of the grave.
               In reality our nature rests there. So every day it is <pb type="external" n="205"
               />necessary to eradicate thorns from this earth as long as it exists. For constant
               service brings about decrease of weeds. But even thus the earth does not wholly
               become pure. If thou relaxest but a short time in this respect, the weeds will grow
               and cover the surface of the earth and choke thy seed and thy previous work as if it
               had not existed. Therefore, it is necessary to purify, every day; for a pause in this
               work produces a multitude of weeds.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n137-1">ܐܣܛܘ̈ܟܣܐ, also the planets and zodiacal signs</note>
            <note xml:id="n137-2">Gen. 3,19</note>
            <note xml:id="n138-1">the Meṣalleyānē?</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
