<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a"> Extracts Concerning Abgar and Addaeus </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ANF, Vol. VIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Original transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Ante-Nicene_Fathers/Volume_VIII/Memoirs_of_Edessa_And_Other_Ancient_Syriac_Documents/Extracts_Concerning_Abgar_and_Addaeus"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Ante-Nicene_Fathers/Volume_VIII/Memoirs_of_Edessa_And_Other_Ancient_Syriac_Documents/Extracts_Concerning_Abgar_and_Addaeus
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription was made available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <head>Of the blessed <persName>Addaeus</persName> the apostle. From his teaching which he gave in <placeName>Edessa</placeName>
               before <persName>Abgar</persName> the King and the assembly of the city.<ptr type="noteAnchor"
                  target="#n1.1"/></head>
            <p>And, when he had entered the sepulchre, he was raised to life again, and came forth
               from the sepulchre with many. And those who were guarding the sepulchre saw not how
               He came forth from the sepulchre; but the watchers from on high—they were the
               proclaimers and announcers of His resurrection. For, had He not willed, He had not
               died, because He is Lord of death, the exit from this life; nor, had it not pleased
               Him, would He have put on a body, inasmuch as He is Himself the framer of the body.
               For that will which led Him to stoop to be born of the <persName>Virgin</persName>, likewise caused Him
               further to descend to the suffering of death.—And a little after (we read): For,
               although His appearance was that of men, yet His power, and His knowledge, and his
               authority, were those of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <head>From the teaching of <persName>Addaeus</persName> the apostle, which was spoken in the city of
                  <placeName>Edessa</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2.1"/></head>
            <p>Ye know that I said unto you, that none of the souls which go forth out of the bodies
               of men are under the power of death, but that they all live and continue to exist,
               and that there are for them mansions and an abode of rest. For the reasoning power of
               the soul does not cease, nor the knowledge, because it is the image of the immortal
               God. For it is not without perceptions, after the manner of the bodily frame, which
               has no perception of that corruption which has acquired dominion over it. Recompense,
               however, and reward it will not receive apart from its bodily form, because what it
               experiences belongs not to itself alone, but to the bodily form also in which it
               dwelt for a time. But the disobedient, who have not known God, will then repent
               without avail.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <head>From the epistle of <persName>Addaeus</persName> the apostle, which he spake in the city of <placeName>Edessa</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3.1"/></head>
            <p>Give heed to this ministry which ye hold, and with fear and trembling continue ye in
               it, and minister every day. Minister ye not in it with neglectful habits, but with
               the discreetness of faith. And let not the praises of <persName>Christ</persName> cease out of your mouth,
               and let not any sense of weariness come over you at the season of prayers. Give heed
               to the verity which ye hold, and to the teaching of the truth which ye have received,
               and to the teaching of salvation which I commit to you. Because before the tribunal
               of <persName>Christ</persName> will it be required of you, when He maketh reckoning with the pastors and
               overseers, and when He shall take His money from the traders with the usury of what
               they have taught.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3.2"/> For He is the Son of a King,
               and goeth to receive a kingdom, and He will return and come and make a resuscitation
               to life of all men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <p><persName>Addaeus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4.1"/> preached at <placeName>Edessa</placeName> and in <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName> (he
               was from <placeName>Paneus</placeName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4.2"/>) in the days of <persName>Abgar</persName> the king.
               And, when he was among the <persName>Zophenians</persName>, <persName>Severus</persName> the son of <persName>Abgar</persName> sent and slew him at
               <placeName>Agel Hasna</placeName>, as also a young man his disciple.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <p>71. and <persName>Narcissus</persName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5.1"/> For they did not suffer that
               selection of the Seventy-two to be wanting, as likewise neither that of the Twelve.
               This man was of the Seventy-two: perhaps he was a disciple of <persName>Addaeus</persName> the apostle.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <head>From the departure<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6.1"/>of Marath<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n6.2"/> <persName>Mary</persName> from the world, and the birth and childhood
               of our Lord <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>. Book the Second.</head>
            <p>In the year three hundred and forty-five, in the month of the latter Tishrin,<ptr
                  type="noteAnchor" target="#n6.3"/> <persName>Marath Mary</persName> went out from her house, and went to
               the sepulchre of <persName>Christ</persName>: because every day she used to go and weep there. But the
               <persName>Jews</persName> immediately after the death of <persName>Christ</persName> seized the sepulchre, and heaped great
               stones at the door of it. And over the sepulchre and <placeName>Golgotha</placeName> they set guards, and
               commanded them that, if any one should go and pray at the sepulchre or at <placeName>Golgotha</placeName>,
               he should immediately be put to death. And the <persName>Jews</persName> took away the cross of our Lord,
               and those two other crosses, and that spear with which our Saviour was struck, and
               those nails which they drove into His hands and into His feet, and those robes of
               mockery in which He had been clad; and they hid them: lest, as they said, any one of
               the kings or of the chief persons should come and inquire concerning the putting to
               death of <persName>Christ</persName>.</p>
            <p>And the guards went in and said to the priests: <persName>Mary</persName> cometh in the evening and in the
               morning, and prayeth there. And there was a commotion in <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> on account of
               <persName>Marath Mary</persName>. And the priests went to the judge, and said to him: My lord, send and
               command <persName>Mary</persName> that she go not to pray at the sepulchre and at <placeName>Golgotha</placeName>. And while they
               were deliberating, lo! letters came from <persName>Abgar</persName>, the king of the city of <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, to
               <placeName>Sabina</placeName> the procurator<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6.4"/> who had been appointed by
               <persName>Tiberius</persName> the emperor, and as far as the river <placeName>Euphrates</placeName> the procurator <placeName>Sabina</placeName> had
               authority. And, because <persName>Addaeus</persName> the apostle, one of the seventy-two apostles, had gone
               down and built a church at <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, and had cured the disease with which <persName>Abgar</persName> the
               king was afflicted—for <persName>Abgar</persName> the king loved <persName>Jesus Christ</persName>, and was constantly
               inquiring about Him; and, when <persName>Christ</persName> was put to death and <persName>Abgar</persName> the king heard that
               the <persName>Jews</persName> had slain Him on the cross, he was much displeased; and <persName>Abgar</persName> arose and rode
               and came as far as the river <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>, because he wished to go up against <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>
               and lay it waste; and, when <persName>Abgar</persName> came and was arrived at the river <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>, he
               deliberated in his mind: If I pass over, there will be enmity between me and <persName>Tiberius</persName>
               the emperor. And <persName>Abgar</persName> wrote letters and sent them to <placeName>Sabina</placeName> the procurator, and
               <placeName>Sabina</placeName> sent them to <persName>Tiberius</persName> the emperor. In this manner did <persName>Abgar</persName> write to <persName>Tiberius</persName>
               the emperor:—</p>
            <p>“From <persName>Abgar</persName>, the king of the city of <placeName>Edessa</placeName>. Much peace to thy Majesty, our lord
               <persName>Tiberius</persName>! In order that thy Majesty may not be offended with me, I have not passed
               over the river <placeName>Euphrates</placeName>: for I have been wishing to go up against <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> and lay
               her waste, forasmuch as she has slain <persName>Christ</persName>, a skilful healer. But do thou, as a
               great sovereign who hast authority over all the earth and over us, send and do me
               judgment on the people of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>. For be it known to thy Majesty that I desire
               that thou wilt do me judgment on the crucifiers.”</p>
            <p>And <placeName>Sabina</placeName> received the letters, and sent them to <persName>Tiberius</persName> the emperor. And, when he
               had read them, <persName>Tiberius</persName> the emperor was greatly incensed, and he desired to destroy
               and slay all the <persName>Jews</persName>. And the people of <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> heard it and were alarmed. And the
               priests went to the governor, and said to him: My lord, send and command <persName>Mary</persName> that
               she go not to pray at the sepulchre and <placeName>Golgotha</placeName>. The judge said to the priests: Go
               ye yourselves, and give her what command and what caution ye please.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <head>From the homily composed by the holy Mar <persName>Jacob</persName>, the teacher, on the fall of
                  idols.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7.1"/></head>
            <l>To <placeName>Edessa</placeName> he made his journey, and found in it a great work:</l>
            <l>For the king was become a labourer for the church, and was building it.</l>
            <l>The apostle <persName>Addaeus</persName> stood in it like a builder,</l>
            <l>And King <persName>Abgar</persName> laid aside his diadem and builded with him.</l>
            <l>When apostle and king concurred the one with the other,</l>
            <l>What idol must not fall before them?</l>
            <l>Satan fled to the land of <placeName>Babylon</placeName> from the disciples,</l>
            <l>And the tale of the crucifixion had got before him to the country of the
               <persName>Chaldeans</persName>.</l>
            <l>He said, when they were making sport of the signs of the Zodiac, that he was
               nothing.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <head>From the homily about the town of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8.1"/></head>
            <p>To <persName>Simon</persName> was allotted <placeName>Rome</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8.2"/> and to <persName>John <placeName>Ephesus</placeName></persName>;
               to <persName>Thomas <placeName>India</placeName></persName>, and to <persName>Addaeus</persName> <placeName>the country of the <persName>Assyrians</persName></placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8.3"/> 
               And, when they were sent each one of them to the district which had
               been allotted to him, they devoted themselves<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8.4"/> to
               bring the several countries to discipleship.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">Taken from Cod. Add. 14,535, fol. i.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">From Cod. Add. 12,155, fol. 53 vers.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">From Cod. Add. 17,193, fol. 36. See Teaching of Addaeus, p. 657,
               infra.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">Or <quote>of the doctrines.</quote>—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5">Extracts iv. and v. are from Cod. Add. 14,601, fol. 164, written
               apparently in the eighth century.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">i.e., Paneas.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">Extracts iv. and v. are from Cod. Add. 14,601, fol. 164, written
               apparently in the eighth century.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8">From Cod. Add. 16,484, fol. 19. It consists of an apocryphal work on
               the Virgin, of the fifth or sixth century.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9">i.e., <hi rend="singleQuote">My Lady</hi> or <hi rend="singleQuote">Madam</hi> (= <foreign xml:lang="ln">mea domina</foreign>): it is the feminine form of
               <hi rend="singleQuote">“ar.</hi>—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n10">Beginning with the new moon of October. The former Tishrin was the
               month immediately preceding.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n11">The Greek <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπίτροπος</foreign> is used.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12">From Cod. Add. 14,624, apparently written in the ninth century.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13">From Cod. Add. 14,590, of the eighth or ninth century.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14">[A note of the Middle Age. The reverse is taught in the Scriptures, but
               even Hebrew Christians slurred the name of Paul.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n15">This is probably the correct reading: the printed text means <hi rend="singleQuote">among the
               Assyrians.</hi>—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16">Lit. <hi rend="singleQuote">set their faces.</hi>—Tr.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
