<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a"> The Story Concerning the King of Edessa </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ANF, Vol. VIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Original transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Ante-Nicene_Fathers/Volume_VIII/Memoirs_of_Edessa_And_Other_Ancient_Syriac_Documents/The_Story_Concerning_the_King_of_Edessa"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Ante-Nicene_Fathers/Volume_VIII/Memoirs_of_Edessa_And_Other_Ancient_Syriac_Documents/The_Story_Concerning_the_King_of_Edessa
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription was made available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>From the History of the Church.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/></p>
         <p>The Story<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> Concerning the King of Edessa.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/></p>
         <p>Now the story relating to Thaddaeus was on this wise:—</p>
         <p>While the Godhead of our Saviour and Lord Jesus Christ was proclaimed among all men by
            reason of the astonishing mighty-works which He wrought, and myriads, even from
            countries remote from the land of Judaea, who were afflicted with sicknesses and diseases
            of every kind, were coming to Him in the hope of being healed, King Abgar<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> also, who
            was renowned among the nations on the east of the Euphrates for his valour, had his body
            wasting away with a grievous disease, such as there is no cure for among men. And when
            he heard and was informed of the name of Jesus, and about the mighty works which He
            did,—for every one alike bore witness concerning Him,—he sent a letter of request by a
            man belonging to him,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/> and besought Him to come and heal him of his disease.</p>
         <p>But our Saviour at the time that he asked Him did not comply with his request. Yet He
            deigned to give him<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> a letter in reply: for He promised him that He would send one of
            His disciples, and heal his sicknesses, and give salvation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> to him and to all who were
            connected with him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> Nor did He delay to fulfil His promise to him: but after He was
            risen from the place of the dead, and was received into heaven, Thomas<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/> the apostle,
            one of the twelve, as by an impulse from God, sent Thaddaeus,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/> who was himself also
            numbered among the seventy<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> disciples of Christ, to Edessa, to be a preacher and
            proclaimer of the teaching of Christ; and the promise of Christ was through him
            fulfilled.</p>
         <p>Thou hast in writing the evidence of these things, which is taken from the Book of
            Records<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12"/> which was at Edessa: for at that time the kingdom was still standing.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> In
            the documents, then, which were there, in which was contained whatever was done by those
            of old down to the time of Abgar, these things also are found preserved down to the
            present hour. There is, however, nothing to prevent our hearing the very letters
            themselves, which have been taken by us<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/> from the archives, and are in words to this
            effect, translated from Aramaic into Greek.</p>
         <p>Copy of the letter which was written by King<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15"/> Abgar to Jesus, and sent to Him by the
            hand of Hananias,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16"/> the Tabularius,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17"/> to Jerusalem:—</p>
         <p>“Abgar the Black,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18"/> sovereign<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19"/> of the country, to Jesus, the good Saviour, who has
            appeared in the country of Jerusalem: Peace. I have heard about Thee,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20"/> and about the
            healing which is wrought by Thy hands without drugs and roots. For, as it is reported,
            Thou makest the blind to see, and the lame to walk; and Thou cleansest the lepers, and
            Thou castest out unclean spirits and demons, and Thou healest those who are tormented
            with lingering diseases, and Thou raisest the dead. And when I heard all these things
            about Thee, I settled in my mind one of two things: either that Thou art God, who hast
            come down from heaven, and doest these things or that Thou art the Son of God, and doest
            these things. On this account, therefore, I have written to beg of Thee that Thou
            wouldest weary Thyself to come to me, and heal this disease which I have. For I have
            also heard that the Jews murmur against Thee, and wish to do Thee harm. But I have a
            city, small and beautiful, which is sufficient for two.”</p>
         <p>Copy of those things which were written<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21"/> by Jesus by the hand of Hananias, the
            Tabularius, to Abgar, sovereign of the country:—</p>
         <p>“Blessed is he that hath believed in me, not having seen me. For it is written<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22"/>
            concerning me, that those who see me will not believe in me, and that those will believe
            who have not seen me, and will be saved. But touching that which thou hast written to
            me, that I should come to thee—it is meet that I should finish here all that for the
            sake of which I have been sent and, after I have finished it, then I shall be taken up
            to Him that sent me; and, when I have been taken up, I will send to thee one of my
            disciples, that he may heal thy disease, and give salvation to thee and to those who are
            with thee.”</p>
         <p>To these letters, moreover, is appended the following also in the Aramaic tongue:—</p>
         <p>“After Jesus was ascended, Judas Thomas sent to him Thaddaeus the apostle, one of the
            Seventy. And, when he was come, he lodged with Tobias, son of Tobias. And, when the news
            about him was heard, they made it known to Abgar: “The apostle of Jesus is come hither,
            as He sent thee word.” Thaddaeus, moreover, began to heal every disease and sickness by
            the power of God, so that all men were amazed. And, when Abgar heard the great and
            marvellous cures which he wrought, he bethought himself that he was the person about
            whom Jesus had sent him word and said to him: When I have been taken up, I will send to
            thee one of my disciples, that he may heal thy disease. So he sent and called Tobias,
            with whom he was lodging, and said to him: I have heard that a mighty man has come, and
            has entered in and taken up his lodging in thy house: bring him up, therefore, to me.
            And when Tobias came to Thaddaeus he said to him: Abgar the king has sent and called me,
            and commanded me to bring thee up to him, that thou mayest heal him. And Thaddaeus said:
            I will go up, because to him have I been sent with power. Tobias therefore rose up early
            the next day, and took Thaddaeus, and came to Abgar.</p>
         <p>“Now, when they were come up, his princes happened to be standing<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23"/> there. And
            immediately, as he was entering in, a great vision appeared to Abgar on the countenance
            of Thaddaeus the apostle. And, when Abgar saw Thaddaeus, he prostrated himself before
            him.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24"/> And astonishment seized upon all who were standing there: for they had not
            themselves seen that vision, which appeared to Abgar alone. And he proceeded to ask
            Thaddaeus: Art thou in truth the disciple of Jesus the Son of God, who said to me, I will
            send to thee one of my disciples, that he may heal thee and give thee salvation? And
            Thaddaeus answered and said: Because thou hast mightily<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25"/> believed on Him that sent me,
            therefore have I been sent to thee; and again, if thou shalt believe on Him, thou shalt
            have the requests of thy heart. And Abgar said to him: In such wise have I believed on
            Him, that I have even desired to take an army and extirpate those Jews who crucified
            Him; were it not that I was restrained by reason of the dominion of the Romans.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n26"/> And
            Thaddaeus said: Our Lord has fulfilled the will of His Father; and, having fulfilled it,
            has been taken up to His Father. Abgar said to him: I too have believed in Him and in
            His Father. And<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27"/> Thaddaeus said: Therefore do I lay my hand upon thee in His name. And
            when he had done this, immediately he was healed of his sickness and of the disease
            which he had. And Abgar marvelled, because, like as he had heard concerning Jesus, so he
            saw in deeds by the hand of Thaddaeus His disciple: since without drugs and roots he
            healed him; and not him only, but also Abdu,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28"/> son of Abdu, who had the gout: for he
            too went in, and fell at his feet,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29"/> and when he prayed over him he was healed. And
            many other people of their city did he heal, and he did great works, and preached the
            word of God.</p>
         <p>“After these things Abgar said to him: Thou, Thaddaeus, doest these things by the power
            of God; we also marvel at them. But in addition to all these things I beg of thee to
            relate to me the story about the coming of Christ, and in what manner it was; and about
            His power, and by what power He wrought those things of which I have heard.</p>
         <p>“And Thaddaeus said: For the present I will be silent;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30"/> but, because I have been sent
            to preach the word of God, assemble me tomorrow all the people of thy city, and I will
            preach before them, and sow amongst them the word of life; and will tell them about the
            coming of Christ, how it took place; and about His mission,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31"/> for what purpose he was
            sent by His Father; and about His power and His deeds, and about the mysteries which He
            spake in the world, and by what power He wrought these things, and about His new
            preaching,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n32"/> and about His abasement and His humiliation, and how He humbled and
            emptied and abased Himself, and was crucified, and descended to Hades,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33"/> and broke
            through the enclosure<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34"/> which had never been broken through before, and raised up the
            dead, and descended alone, and ascended with a great multitude to His Father.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35"/></p>
         <p>“Abgar, therefore, commanded that in the morning all the people of his city should
            assemble, and hear the preaching of Thaddaeus. And afterwards he commanded gold and
            silver to be given to him; but he received it not, and said: If we have forsaken that
            which was our own, how shall we accept that of others?”</p>
         <p>These things were done in the year 340.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36"/></p>
         <p>In order, moreover, that these things may not have been translated to no purpose word
            for word from the Aramaic into Greek, they are placed in their order of time here.</p>
         <p>Here endeth the first book.</p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n">By Eusebius of Caesarea.—Tr. The ms. from which this extract from
               Eusebius is taken is numbered 14,639, fol. 15 b. It is described in Cureton’s Corpus
               Ignatianum, p. 350.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Book I. chapter the thirteenth.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Properly Urrhoi, or Orrhoi (<foreign xml:lang="">***<!-- Add Syriac/Arabic/etc. --></foreign>). It seems probable that the word is
               connected with Osrhoene, the name of the province in which Edessa held an important
               place, the correct form of which is supposed to be Orrhoene. The name Edessa (<foreign xml:lang="">***<!-- Add Syriac/Arabic/etc. --></foreign>)
               occurs only once in these Documents, viz., in the “Acts of Sharbil,” sub
               init.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">“By this title all the toparchs of Edessa were called, just as the
               Roman emperors were called Caesars, the kings of Egypt Pharaohs or Ptolemies, the
               kings of Syria Antiochi.” Assem., Bibl. Or., vol. i. p. 261. Assemani adds: “Abgar in
               Syriac means lame.” Moses of Chorene, however, with more probability, derives it from
               the Armenian Avag-aïr, “grand homme, à cause de sa grande mansuétude et de sa
               sagesse, et de plus, à cause de sa taille.” See below the extract from his History of
               Armenia, book ii. ch. 26.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Eusebius has δι᾽ ἐπιστοληφόρου. See note on ταχυδρόμου , on next
               page.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Lit. “deemed him worthy of.”—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Gr. σωτηρίαν: and so the Syriac word, meaning “life,” is generally to
               be translated in this collection.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Syr. “near to him;” Gr. τῶν προσηκόντων.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">His real name was Judas Thomas: see p. 8.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">The name is taken from Eusebius, but in the original Syriac treatises,
               which follow, he is called Addaeus.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">In The Teaching of the Apostles he is said to have been one of the
               “seventy two apostles.” His name, like that of Thomas, seems to have been the very
               common one, Judas.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">These were kept in the archives of the kingdom, which were transferred
               by Abgar from Nisibis to Edessa when he made it the capital of his dominions. See
               Moses Chor. B. ii. ch. 27, infra. The archives appear to have been still kept at
               Edessa in a.d. 550. [Compare this fact with Tertullian’s statement, vol. iii. p.
               164.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n">The kingdom of Edessa was brought to an end and entirely subjected to
               the Romans in a.d. 217 or 218.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">The extract from the archives was probably made by Sextus Julius
               Africanus, and copied by Eusebius from his Chronographia.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Gr. τόπαρχος.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Called Hanan in the original Syriac document; and so in Moses Chor.;
               Eusebius has ᾽Ανανίας, which is copied here.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Gr. ταχυδρόμου. But the post held by Hananias must have been one of
               more dignity than that of a courier. He was probably a Secretary of State. In The
               Acts of Addaeus (infra) he is called, in connection with the name Tabularius, a
               sharir, or confidential servant. It would seem that Tabularius has been confounded
               with Tabellarius, a letter-carrier.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Or “Abgar Uchomo.” The epithet was peculiar to this King Abgar. He was
               the fourteenth king: the eleventh was called Abgar Sumoco, or “the Red.” The occasion
               of the name “Black” is doubtful: it can hardly have arisen from the fact that Abgar
               was suffering, as Cedrenus asserts, from the black leprosy.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">“Head,” or “chief.”—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Comp. Matt. iv. 24; “And His fame went throughout all Syria,” etc. See
               also Moses Chor. B. ii. c. 30.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Gr. ἀντιγραφέντα, “written in reply.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n">[John ix. 39, and xx. 29, 31; Hab. i. 5; with Isa. lii. 15, liii.
               1.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Cureton, “were assembled and standing;” nearly as Euseb.: παρόντων καὶ
               ἑστώτων. But in 2 Sam. xx. 1, the only reference given by Castel for the word <foreign xml:lang="">***<!-- Add Syriac/Arabic/etc. --></foreign> is
               used for the Heb. ארקנ, “he chanced.”—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n"><foreign xml:lang="">***<!-- Add Syriac/Arabic/etc. --></foreign>, like the 
               προσεκύνησε of Eusebius, may be rendered “worshipped.”—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n"><foreign xml:lang="">***<!-- Add Syriac/Arabic/etc. --></foreign>; Gr. μεγάλως, 
               lit. “greatly;” C. “nobly.” But nothing more than intensity is
               necessarily denoted by either word. Compare, for the Syriac, Ps. cxix. 107, 167; Dan.
               ii. 12.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Compare the letters of Abgar and Tiberius, infra.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">In another piece, The Teaching of Addaeus, i.e., Thaddaeus, we have a
               portion of the original Syriac from which Eusebius’ translation was made. The only
               portions that correspond are: in the present piece, from this place to “—accept that
               of others,” near the end; and, in the following one, from the beginning to “—that
               which is not ours.” Some of the variations are worthy of notice.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">See note 9, p. 657, infra.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">This answers sufficiently well to the Greek: ὁς καὶ αὐτὸς προσελθὼν ὑπὸ
               τοὺς πόδας αὐτοῦ ἔπεσεν; but, as the original Syriac, p. 12, reads “he too brought
               his feet to him, and he laid his hands upon them and healed him,” the Greek
               translation must have been at fault. For brought read presented.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">The original Syriac has “I will not hold my peace from declaring
               this.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n">So Euseb. The orig. Syr. has “His sender.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n">The orig. Syr. has “the certitude of His preaching.” The error seems to
               have arisen from the Greek translator confounding <foreign xml:lang="">***<!-- Add Syriac/Arabic/etc. --></foreign> 
               with <foreign xml:lang="">***<!-- Add Syriac/Arabic/etc. --></foreign>. More probably with
               <foreign xml:lang="">***<!-- Add Syriac/Arabic/etc. --></foreign>, “newness (of his preaching),” which was freely translated by him (περὶ) τῆς
               καινῆς αὐτοῦ κηρύξεως; and this, again, was by the Syrian re-translator rendered
               literally, as in the text. The word certitude (above) may be rendered unerring truth.
               —Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Or “Sheol,” as in Hebrew. The orig. Syr. gives “the place of the
               dead.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Eph. ii. 14.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Comp. Matt. xxvii. 52.</note>
            <note xml:id="n">Valesius says that the Edessenes commenced their era with the 117th
               Olympiad, the first year of the reign of Seleucus. The year 340 corresponds,
               therefore, with the fifteenth year of Tiberius. It should be the beginning of the
               117th Olympiad.—Tr.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
