<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a"> The Teaching of the Apostles </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ANF, Vol. VIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Original transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Ante-Nicene_Fathers/Volume_VIII/Memoirs_of_Edessa_And_Other_Ancient_Syriac_Documents/The_Teaching_of_the_Apostles"
                  >
                  https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Ante-Nicene_Fathers/Volume_VIII/Memoirs_of_Edessa_And_Other_Ancient_Syriac_Documents/The_Teaching_of_the_Apostles
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription was made available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>The Teaching of the Apostles.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/></p>
         <p>At that time <persName>Christ</persName> was taken up to His Father; and how the apostles received the gift
            of the Spirit; and the Ordinances and Laws of the Church; and whither each one of the
            apostles went; and from whence the countries in the territory of the Romans received the
            ordination to the priesthood.</p>
         <p>In the year three hundred and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n2"/> thirty-nine of the kingdom of the Greeks, in the month
            Heziran,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n3"/> on the fourth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4"/> day of the same, which is the first day of the week, and
            the end of Pentecost<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5"/>—on the selfsame day came <persName>the disciples from <placeName>Nazareth</placeName> of <placeName>Galilee</placeName></persName>,
            where the conception of our Lord was announced, to the mount which is called that of <placeName>the
            Place of Olives</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n6"/> our Lord being with them, but not being visible to them. And at the
            time of early dawn our Lord lifted up His hands, and laid them upon the heads of the
            eleven disciples, and gave to them the gift of the priesthood. And suddenly a bright
            cloud received Him. And they saw Him as He was going up to heaven. And He sat down on
            the right hand of His Father. And they praised God because they saw His ascension
            according as He had told them; and they rejoiced because they had received the Right
            Hand conferring on them the priesthood of the house of <persName>Moses</persName> and <persName>Aaron</persName>.</p>
         <p>And from thence they went up to the city, and<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7"/> proceeded to an upper room—that in
            which our Lord had observed the passover with them, and the place where the inquiries
            had been made: Who it was that should betray our Lord to the crucifiers? There also were
            made the inquiries:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n8"/> How they should preach His Gospel in the world? And, as within
            the upper room the mystery of the body and of the blood of our Lord began to prevail in
            the world, so also from thence did the teaching of His preaching begin to have authority
            in the world.</p>
         <p>And, when the disciples were cast into this perplexity, how they should preach His
            Gospel to men of strange tongues<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9"/> which were unknown to them, and were speaking thus
            to one another: Although we are confident that <persName>Christ</persName> will perform by our hands mighty
            works and miracles in the presence of strange peoples whose tongues we know not, and who
            themselves also are unversed in our tongue, yet who shall teach them and make them
            understand that it is by the name of <persName>Christ</persName> who was crucified that these mighty works
            and miracles are done?—while, I say, the disciples were occupied with these thoughts,
            <persName>Simon Cephas</persName> rose up, and said to them: My brethren, this matter, how we shall preach
            His Gospel, pertaineth not to us, but to our Lord; for He knoweth how it is possible for
            us to preach His Gospel in the world; and we rely on His care for us, which He promised
            us, saying: “When I am ascended to my Father I will send you the Spirit, the Paraclete,
            that He may teach you everything which it is meet for you to know, and to make
            known.”</p>
         <p>And, whilst <persName>Simon Cephas</persName> was saying these things to his fellow-apostles, and putting
            them in remembrance, a mysterious voice was heard by them, and a sweet odour, which was
            strange to the world, breathed upon them;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n10"/> and tongues of fire, between the voice and
            the odour, came down from heaven<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n11"/> towards them, and alighted and sat on every one of
            them; and, according to the tongue which every one of them had severally received, so
            did he prepare himself to go to the country in which that tongue was spoken and
            heard.</p>
         <p>And, by the same gift of the Spirit which was given to them on that day, they appointed
            Ordinances and Laws—such as were in accordance with the Gospel of their preaching, and
            with the true and faithful doctrine of their teaching:—</p>
         <p>1. The apostles therefore appointed: Pray ye towards the east:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12"/> because, “as the
            lightning which lighteneth from the east and is seen even to the west, so shall the
            coming of the Son of man be:”<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13"/> that by this we might know and understand that He will
            appear from the east suddenly.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n14"/></p>
         <p>2. The apostles further appointed: On the first day of the week let there be service,
            and the reading of the Holy Scriptures, and the oblation:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n15"/> because on the first day
            of the week our Lord rose from the place of the dead and on the first day of the week He
            arose upon the world, and on the first day of the week He ascended up to heaven, and on
            the first day of the week He will appear at last with the angels of heaven.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n16"/></p>
         <p>3. The apostles further appointed: On the fourth<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n17"/> day of the week let there be
            service: because on that day our Lord made the disclosure to them about His trial,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n18"/>
            and His suffering, and His crucifixion, and His death, and His resurrection; and the
            disciples were on account of this in sorrow.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n19"/></p>
         <p>4. The apostles further appointed: On the eve of the Sabbath,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n20"/> at the ninth hour, let
            there be service: because that which had been spoken on the fourth day of the week about
            the suffering of the Saviour was brought to pass on the same eve; the worlds and
            creatures trembling, and the luminaries in the heavens being darkened.</p>
         <p>5. The apostles further appointed: Let there be elders and deacons, like the
            <persName>Levites</persName>;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n21"/> and subdeacons,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n22"/> like those who carried the vessels of the court of the
            sanctuary of the Lord; and an overseer,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n23"/> who shall likewise be the Guide of all the
            people,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n24"/> like <persName>Aaron</persName>, the head and chief of all the priests and <persName>Levites</persName> of the whole
            city.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n25"/></p>
         <p>6. The apostles further appointed: Celebrate the day of the Epiphany<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n26"/> of our Saviour,
            which is the chief of the festivals of the Church, on the sixth day of the latter
            Canun,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n27"/> in the long number of the Greeks.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n28"/></p>
         <p>7. The apostles further appointed: Forty<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n29"/> days before the day of the passion of our
            Saviour fast ye, and then celebrate the day of the passion, and the day of the
            resurrection: because our Lord Himself also, the Lord of the festival, fasted forty
            days; and <persName>Moses</persName> and <persName>Elijah</persName>, who were endued with this mystery, likewise each fasted
            forty days, and then were glorified.</p>
         <p>8. <persName>The apostles</persName> further appointed: At the conclusion of all the Scriptures other let the
            Gospel be read, as being the seal<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n30"/> of all the Scriptures; and let the people listen
            to it standing upon their feet: because it is the Gospel of the redemption of all
            men.</p>
         <p>9. The apostles further appointed: At the completion of fifty<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n31"/> days after His
            resurrection make ye a commemoration of His ascension to His glorious Father.</p>
         <p>10. The apostles appointed: That, beside the Old Testament, and <persName>the Prophets</persName>, and the
            Gospel, and the Acts (of their exploits), nothing should be read on the pulpit in the
            church.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n32"/></p>
         <p>11. The apostles further appointed: Whosoever is unacquainted with the faith of the
            Church and the ordinances and laws which are appointed in it, let him not be a guide and
            ruler; and whosoever is acquainted with them and departs from them, let him not minister
            again: because, not being true in his ministry, he has lied.</p>
         <p>12. The apostles further appointed: Whosoever sweareth, or<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n33"/> lieth, or beareth false
            witness, or hath recourse to magicians and soothsayers and Chaldeans, and putteth
            confidence in fates and nativities, which they hold fast who know not God,—let him also,
            as a man that knoweth not God, be dismissed from the ministry, and not minister
            again.</p>
         <p>13. The apostles further appointed: If there be any man that is divided in mind touching
            the ministry, and who follows it not with a steadfast will<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n34"/>, let not this man
            minister again: because the Lord of the ministry is not served by him with a stedfast
            will; and he deceiveth man only, and not God, “before whom crafty devices avail
            not.”<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n35"/></p>
         <p>14. The apostles further appointed: Whosoever lendeth and receiveth usury,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n36"/> and is
            occupied in merchandise and covetousness, let not this man minister again, nor continue
            in the ministry.</p>
         <p>15. The apostles further appointed: That whosoever loveth the Jews,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n37"/> like <persName>Iscariot</persName>,
            who was their friend, or the pagans, who worship creatures instead of the
            Creator,—should not enter in amongst them and minister; and moreover, that if he be
            already amongst them, they should not suffer him to remain, but that he should be
            separated from amongst them, and not minister with them again.</p>
         <p>16. The apostles further appointed: That, if any one from the Jews or from the pagans
            come and join himself with them, and if after he has joined himself with them he turn
            and go back again to the side on which he stood before, and if he again return and come
            to them a second time,—he should not be received again; but that, according to the side
            on which he was before, so those who know him should look upon him.</p>
         <p>17. The apostles further appointed: That it should not be permitted to the Guide to
            transact the matters which pertain to the Church apart from those who minister with him;
            but that he should issue commands with the counsel of them all, and that that only
            should be done which all of them should concur in and not disapprove.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n38"/></p>
         <p>18. The apostles further appointed: Whenever any shall depart out of this world with a
            good testimony to the faith of <persName>Christ</persName>, and with affliction borne for His name’s sake,
            make ye a commemoration of them on the day on which they were put to death.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n39"/></p>
         <p>19. The apostles further appointed: In the service of the Church repeat ye the praises
            of <persName>David</persName> day by day: because of this saying: “I will bless the Lord at all times, and at
            all times His praises shall be in my mouth;”<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n40"/> and this: “By day and by night will I
            meditate and speak, and cause my voice to be heard before Thee.”</p>
         <p>20. The apostles further appointed: If any divest themselves of mammon and run not after
            the gain of money, let these men be chosen and admitted to the ministry of the
            altar.</p>
         <p>21. The apostles further appointed: Let any priest who accidentally puts another in
            bonds<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n41"/> contrary to justice receive the punishment that is right; and let him that has
            been bound receive the bonds as if he had been equitably bound.</p>
         <p>22. The apostles further appointed: If it be seen that those who are accustomed to hear
            causes show partiality, and pronounce the innocent guilty and the guilty innocent, let
            them never again hear another cause: thus receiving the rebuke of their partiality, as
            it is fit.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n42"/></p>
         <p>23. The apostles further ordained: Let not those that are high-minded and lifted up with
            the arrogance of boasting be admitted to the ministry: because of this text: “That which
            is exalted among men is abominable before God;” and because concerning them it is said:
            “I will return a recompense upon those that vaunt themselves.”</p>
         <p>24. The apostles further appointed: Let there be a Ruler over the elders who are in the
            villages, and let him be recognised as head of them all, at whose hand all of them shall
            be required: for <persName>Samuel</persName> also thus made visits from place to place and ruled.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n43"/></p>
         <p>25. The apostles further appointed: That those kings who shall hereafter believe in
            <persName>Christ</persName> should be permitted to go up and stand before the altar along with the Guides of
            the Church: because <persName>David</persName> also, and those who were like him, went up and stood before
            the altar.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n44"/></p>
         <p>26. The apostles further appointed: Let no man dare to do anything by the authority of
            the priesthood which is not in accordance with justice and equity, but in accordance
            with justice, and free from the blame of partiality, let all things be done.</p>
         <p>27. The apostles further appointed: Let the bread of the Oblation be placed upon the
            altar on the day on which it is baked, and not some days after—a thing which is not
            permitted.</p>
         <p>All these things did the apostles appoint, not for themselves, but for those who should
            come after them—for they were apprehensive that in time to come wolves would put on
            sheep’s clothing: since for themselves the Spirit, the Paraclete, which was in them, was
            sufficient: that, even as He had appointed these laws by their hands, so He would guide
            them lawfully. For they, who had received from our Lord power and authority, had no need
            that laws should be appointed for them by others. For <persName>Paul</persName> also, and <persName>Timothy</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n45"/> while
            they were going from place to place in the country of <placeName>Syria</placeName> and <placeName>Cilicia</placeName>, committed these
            same Commands and Laws of the apostles and elders to those who were under the hand of
            the apostles, for the churches of the countries in which they were preaching and
            publishing the Gospel.</p>
         <p>The disciples, moreover, after they had appointed these Ordinances and Laws, ceased not
            from the preaching of the Gospel, or from the wonderful mighty-works which our Lord did
            by their hands. For much people was gathered about them every day, who believed in
            <persName>Christ</persName>; and they came to them from other cities, and heard their words and received
            them. <persName>Nicodemus</persName> also, and <persName>Gamaliel</persName>, chiefs of the synagogue of the Jews, used to come to
            the apostles in secret, agreeing with their teaching. <persName>Judas</persName>, moreover, and <persName>Levi</persName>, and
            <persName>Peri</persName>, and <persName>Joseph</persName>, and <persName>Justus</persName>, sons of <persName>Hananias</persName>, and <persName>Caiaphas</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n46"/> and <persName>Alexander</persName> the
            priests—they too used to come to the apostles by night, confessing <persName>Christ</persName> that He is the
            Son of God; but they were afraid of the people of their own nation, so that they did not
            disclose their mind toward the disciples.</p>
         <p>And the apostles received them affectionately, saying to them: Do not, by reason of the
            shame and fear of men, forfeit your salvation before God, nor have the blood of <persName>Christ</persName>
            required of you; even as your fathers, who took it upon them: for it is not acceptable
            before God, that, while ye are, in secret, with His worshippers, ye should go and
            associate with the murderers of His adorable Son. How do ye expect that your faith
            should be accepted with those that are true, whilst ye are with those that are false?
            But it becomes you, as men who believe in <persName>Christ</persName>, to confess openly this faith which we
            preach.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n47"/></p>
         <p>And, when they heard these things from the Disciples, those sons of the priests, all of
            them alike, cried out before the whole company of the apostles: We confess and believe
            in <persName>Christ</persName> who was crucified, and we confess that He is from everlasting the Son of God;
            and those who dared to crucify Him do we renounce. For even the priests of the people in
            secret confess <persName>Christ</persName>; but, for the sake of the headship among the people which they
            love, they are not willing to confess openly; and they have forgotten that which is
            written:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n48"/> <quote>Of knowledge is He the Lord, and before Him avail not crafty devices.</quote></p>
         <p>And, when their fathers heard these things from their sons, they became exceedingly
            hostile to them: not indeed because they had believed in <persName>Christ</persName>, but because they had
            declared and spoken openly of the mind of their fathers before the sons of their
            people.</p>
         <p>But those who believed clove to the disciples, and departed not from them, because they
            saw that, whatsoever they taught the multitude, they themselves carried into practice
            before all men; and, when affliction and persecution arose against the disciples, they
            rejoiced to be afflicted with them, and received with gladness stripes and imprisonment
            for the confession of their faith in <persName>Christ</persName>; and all the days of their life they
            preached <persName>Christ</persName> before the Jews and <persName>the Samaritans</persName>.</p>
         <p>And after the death of the apostles there were Guides and Rulers<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n49"/> in the churches;
            and, whatsoever the apostles had committed to them and they had received from them, they
            continued to teach to the multitude through the whole space of their lives. They too,
            again, at their deaths committed and delivered to their disciples after them whatsoever
            they had received from the apostles; also what <persName>James</persName> had written from <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, and
            <persName>Simon from <placeName>the city of Rome</placeName></persName>, and <persName>John</persName> from <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, and <persName>Mark from <placeName>Alexandria</placeName></persName> the Great,
            and <persName>Andrew from <placeName>Phrygia</placeName></persName>, and <persName>Luke from <placeName>Macedonia</placeName></persName>, and <persName>Judas Thomas from <placeName>India</placeName></persName>:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n50"/> that
            the epistles of an apostle<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n51"/> might be received and read in the churches that were in
            every place, just as the achievements of their Acts, which <persName>Luke</persName> wrote, are read; that
            hereby the apostles might be known, and the prophets, and the Old Testament and the
            New;<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n52"/> that so might be seen one truth was proclaimed in them all: that one Spirit
            spoke in them all, from one God whom they had all worshipped and had all preached. And
            the divers countries received their teaching. Everything, therefore, which had been
            spoken by our Lord by means of the apostles, and which the apostles had delivered to
            their disciples, was believed and received in every country, by the operation<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n53"/> of our
            Lord, who said to them: “I am with you, even until the world shall end;” the Guides
            disputing with the Jews from the books of the prophets, and contending also against the
            deluded pagans with the terrible mighty-works which they did in the name of <persName>Christ</persName>. For
            all the peoples, even those that dwell in other countries, quietly and silently
            received<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n54"/> the Gospel of <persName>Christ</persName>; and those who became confessors cried out under their
            persecution: This our persecution to-day shall plead<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n55"/> on our behalf, lest we be
            punished, for having been formerly persecutors ourselves. For there were some of them
            against whom death by the sword was ordered; and there were some of them from whom they
            took away whatsoever they possessed, and let them go.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n56"/> And the more affliction arose
            against them, the richer and larger did their congregations become; and with gladness in
            their hearts did they receive death of every kind. And by ordination to the priesthood,
            which the apostles themselves had received from our Lord, did their Gospel wing its way
            rapidly into the four quarters of the world. And by mutual visitation they ministered to
            one another.</p>
         <p>1. <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName> received the ordination to the priesthood, as did all the country of
            <placeName>Palestine</placeName>, and the parts occupied by <persName>the Samaritans</persName>, and the parts occupied by <persName>the
            Philistines</persName>, and <placeName>the country of <persName>the Arabians</persName></placeName>, and of <placeName>Phœnicia</placeName>, and <persName>the people of
            <placeName>Caesarea</placeName></persName>, from <persName>James</persName>, who was ruler and guide in the church of the apostles which was
            built in <placeName>Zion</placeName>.</p>
         <p>2. <persName>Alexandria the Great</persName>, and <placeName>Thebais</placeName>, and <placeName>the whole of Inner Egypt</placeName>, and all the country
            of <placeName>Pelusium</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n57"/> and extending as far as the borders of the <persName>Indians</persName>, received the
            apostles’ ordination to the priesthood from <placeName>Mark the evangelist</placeName>, who was ruler and guide
            there in the church which he had built, in which, he also ministered.</p>
         <p>3. <placeName>India</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n58"/> and all the countries belonging to it and round about it, even to the
            farthest sea, received the apostles’ ordination to the priesthood from <persName>Judas Thomas</persName>, who
            was guide and ruler in the church which he had built there, in which he also ministered
            there.</p>
         <p>4. <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, and <placeName>Syria</placeName>, and <placeName>Cilicia</placeName>, and <placeName>Galatia</placeName>, even to <persName>Pontus</persName>, received the apostles’
            ordination to the priesthood from <persName>Simon Cephas</persName>, who himself laid the foundation of the
            church there,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n59"/> and was priest and ministered there up to the time when he went up
            from thence to Rome on account of <persName>Simon</persName> the sorcerer, who was deluding the people of
            Rome with his sorceries.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n60"/></p>
         <p>5. <placeName>The city of Rome</placeName>, and all <placeName>Italy</placeName>, and <placeName>Spain</placeName>, and <placeName>Britain</placeName>, and <placeName>Gaul</placeName>, together with all
            the rest of the countries round about them, received the apostles’ ordination to the
            priesthood from <persName>Simon Cephas</persName>, who went up from <placeName>Antioch</placeName>; and he was ruler and guide
            there, in the church which he had built there, and in the places round about it.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n61"/></p>
         <p>6. <placeName>Ephesus</placeName>, and <placeName>Thessalonica</placeName>, and all <placeName>Asia</placeName>, and all <placeName>the country of the <persName>Corinthians</persName></placeName>, and
            of all <placeName>Achaia</placeName> and the parts round about it, received the apostles’ ordination to the
            priesthood from <persName>John the evangelist</persName>, who had leaned upon the bosom of our Lord; who
            himself built a church there, and ministered in his office of Guide which he held
            there.</p>
         <p>7. <placeName>Nicaea</placeName>, and <placeName>Nicomedia</placeName>, and all the country of <placeName>Bithynia</placeName>, and of <placeName>Inner Galatia</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n62"/> and
            of the regions round about it, received the apostles’ ordination to the priesthood from
            <persName>Andrew</persName>, the brother of <persName>Simon Cephas</persName>, who was himself Guide and Ruler in the church which
            he had built there, and was priest and ministered there.</p>
         <p>8. <placeName>Byzantium</placeName>, and all the country of <placeName>Thrace</placeName>, and of the parts about it as far as the
            great river,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n63"/> the boundary which separates from the barbarians, received the
            apostles’ ordination to the priesthood from <persName>Luke the apostle</persName>, who himself built a church
            there, and ministered there in his office of Ruler and Guide which he held there.</p>
         <p>9. <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, and all the countries round about it which were on all sides of it, and
            <placeName>Zoba</placeName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n64"/> and <placeName>Arabia</placeName>, and all the north, and the regions round about it, and the south,
            and all the regions on the borders of <placeName>Mesopotamia</placeName>, received the apostles’ ordination to
            <persName>the priesthood from <placeName>Addaeus</placeName></persName> the apostle, one of the seventy-two apostles,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n65"/> who himself
            made disciples there, and built a church there, and was priest and ministered there in
            his office of Guide which he held there.</p>
         <p>10. The whole of <placeName>Persia</placeName>, of <persName>the Assyrians</persName>, and of <persName>the Armenians</persName>, and of <persName>the Medians</persName>, and
            of the countries round about <placeName>Babylon</placeName>, <persName>the Huzites</persName> and <persName>the Gelae</persName>, as far as the borders of
            <persName>the Indians</persName>, and as far as the land<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n66"/> of <persName>Gog</persName> and <persName>Magog</persName>, and moreover all the countries
            on all sides, received the apostles’ ordination to <persName>the priesthood from <placeName>Aggaeus</placeName></persName>, a maker
            of silks,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n67"/> the disciple of Addaeus the apostle.</p>
         <p>The other remaining companions of the apostles, moreover went to the distant countries
            of the barbarians; and they made disciples from place to place and passed on; and there
            they ministered by their preaching; and there occurred their departure out of this
            world, their disciples after them going on with the work down to the present day, nor
            was any change or addition made by them in their preaching.</p>
         <p><persName>Luke</persName>, moreover, the evangelist had such diligence that he wrote the exploits of the Acts
            of the Apostles, and the ordinances and laws of the ministry of their priesthood, and
            whither each one of them went. By his diligence, I say, did <persName>Luke</persName> write these things, and
            more than these; and he placed them in the hand of <persName>Priscus</persName><ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n68"/> and <persName>Aquilus</persName>, his
            disciples; and they accompanied him up to the day of his death, just as <persName>Timothy</persName> and
            <persName>Erastus of <placeName>Lystra</placeName></persName>, and <persName>Menaus</persName>,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n69"/> the first disciples of the apostles, accompanied <persName>Paul</persName>
            until he was taken up to the city of Rome because he had withstood <persName>Tertullus</persName> the
            orator.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n70"/></p>
         <p>And <persName>Nero Caesar</persName> despatched with the sword <persName>Simon Cephas</persName> in <placeName>the city of Rome</placeName>.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n71"/></p>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">This work is taken, and printed verbatim, from the same ms. as the
               preceding, Cod. Add. 14,644, fol. 10. That ms., however, has been carefully compared
               with another in the Brit. Mus. in which it is found, Cod. Add. 14,531, fol. 109; and
               with a third, in which the piece is quoted as Canons of the Apostles, Cod. Add.
               14,173, fol. 37. In using the second, a comparison has also been made of De Lagarde’s
               edition of it (Vienna, 1856). This treatise had also been published before in
               <title><foreign xml:lang="ln">Ebediesu Metropolitae Sobae et Armeniae collectio canonum Synodicorum by Cardinal Mai</foreign></title>.
               It is also cited by Bar Hebraeus in his Nomocanon, printed by Mai in the same volume.
               These three texts are referred to in the notes, as A. B. C. respectively. [It seems
               to me that this and the Bryennios fragment are alike relics of some original older
               than both. To that of vol. vii. (p. 377) and the Apostolic Constitutions, so called,
               this is a natural preface.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">A. omits <hi rend="singleQuote">three hundred and.</hi> They are supplied from B. The reading of
               C. is 342.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3">This month answers to Sivan, which began with the new moon of
               June.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4">C. reads <quote>fourteenth.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n5">The day of Pentecost seems to be put for that of the Ascension.</note>
            <note xml:id="n6">Syr. “<foreign>Baith Zaithe</foreign>.” Comp. Luke xxiv. 50 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n7">Comp. Acts i. 12 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n8">[It is evident that the apostles had no such ideas until after the
               vision of St. Peter, Acts x. 9–35.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n9">[It is evident that the apostles had no such ideas until after the
               vision of St. Peter, Acts x. 9–35.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n10">The reading of B. and C.: A. reads <quote>answered them.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n11">B. reads <hi rend="singleQuote">suddenly.</hi> [The translator interpolates upon him.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n12">On praying toward the east, comp. <title>Apost. Constitutions</title>, ii. 57, vii.
               44; and Tertullian, Apol., 16. A. C., ii. 57, contains an interesting account of the
               conduct of public worship. It may be consulted in connection with Ordinances 2, 8,
               and 10, also.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13">Matt. xxiv. 27.</note>
            <note xml:id="n14">B. and C. read <quote>at the last.</quote> Ebediesu has <quote>from heaven.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n15">i.e., the Eucharist.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n16">C. reads <quote>His holy angels.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n17">For Ords. 3 and 4, see Ap. Const., v. 13–15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n18">B. reads <quote>His manifestation.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n19">The reading of C.</note>
            <note xml:id="n20">Lit. <hi rend="singleQuote">“ the evening,”</hi> but used in particular of the evening of the sixth
               day of the week, the eve of the seventh: the evening being regarded, as in Gen. i. 5,
               as the first part of the day. Similarly, <foreign xml:lang="gr">παρασκευή</foreign> , which the Peshito translates by
               our word, is used in the Gospels for the sixth day, with a prospective reference to
               the seventh.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n21">See Ap. Const., ii. 25.</note>
            <note xml:id="n22"><title>Comp. Eccl. Canons</title>, No. 43. The Gr. <foreign xml:lang="gr">ὑποδιάκονοι</foreign> is here used, though
               for <hi rend="singleQuote">deacon</hi> the usual Syriac word is employed, meaning <hi rend="singleQuote">minister</hi> or <hi rend="singleQuote">servant.</hi> From
               Riddle, <title>Christian Antiqq</title>., p. 301, with whom Neander agrees, it would seem that
               subdeacons were first appointed at the end of the third century or the beginning of
               the fourth.—Tr. [See vol. v. p. 417.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n23"><foreign xml:lang="">***<!-- Add Syriac/Arabic/etc. --></foreign>, equivalent, 
               not to ἐπίσκοπος, but to σκοπός = watchman, as in Ezek. xxxiii.
               7.</note>
            <note xml:id="n24">For this B. reads <quote>world.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n25">B. has <quote>camp.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n26">See <title>Ap. Const</title>., v. 13. Christmas, of which no mention is made in these
               Ordinances, is called “the first of all,” the Epiphany being ranked next to it in the
               Constitutions.—Tr. [See vol. vii. p. 492.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n27">January: the Jewish Tebeth. “The former Canun” is December, i.e.,
               Chisleu.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n28">The era of the Seleucidae, 311 a.c., appears to be referred to. In this
               new names were given to certain months, and Canun was one of them. See p. 666,
               supra.</note>
            <note xml:id="n29">Eccl. Can., No. 69.—Tr. See Ap. Const., v. 13–15.</note>
            <note xml:id="n30">Properly <hi rend="singleQuote">the sealer:</hi> for, although the word is not found in the
               lexicons, its formation shows that it denotes an agent. The meaning seems to be, that
               the Gospel gives completeness and validity to the Scriptures.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n31">C. reads <quote>forty.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n32">See Ap. Const., ii. 57; <title>Teaching of Simon Cephas</title>, ad fin.; <title>Eccl. Can.</title>,
               Nos. 60, 85.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n33">B. and C., as well as <persName>Ebediesu</persName>, read <hi rend="singleQuote">“and.”</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n34">Lit. <hi rend="singleQuote">it is not certain (or firm) to him.</hi>—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n35">The exact words of the Peshito of 1 Sam. ii. 3. The E.V. following the
               K’ri <foreign>ולו</foreign>, instead of the <foreign>אלו</foreign> of the text, renders <hi rend="singleQuote">and by Him actions are weighed.</hi>
               The Peshito translator may have confounded the Heb. verb <foreign>ןכתּ</foreign>, which appears not to
               exist in Aramaean, with its own verb <foreign>ןקתּ</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="">***<!-- Add Syriac/Arabic/etc. --></foreign>), through the similarity in sound of
               the gutturals כּ and ק<foreign>׃</foreign></note>
            <note xml:id="n36">See Eccl. Canons, No. 44.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n37">Comp. Eccl. Canons, Nos. 65, 70, 71.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n38">See Eccl. Canons, No. 35.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n39">See the letter of the Church of Smyrna on the martyrdom of Polycarp,
               and Euseb., Hist. Eccl., iv. 15; [also p. 664, note 4, supra].</note>
            <note xml:id="n40">Ps. xxxiv. 1.</note>
            <note xml:id="n41">The particip. <foreign xml:lang="">***<!-- Add Syriac/Arabic/etc. --></foreign>, 
               though usually pass., may, like some other participles Peil, be taken actively, 
               as appears from a passage quoted by Dr. R. Payne Smith,
               Thes. Syr., s.v. This would seem to be the only possible way of taking it
               here.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n42">Comp. Ap. Const., ii. 45 sqq.</note>
            <note xml:id="n43">[Note the Institutions of Samuel, vol. vii. p. 531, and observe the
               prominence here assigned to that prophet. Comp. Acts iii. 24.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n44">[But note the case of Ambrose and Theodosius; Sozomen, Eccl. Hist.,
               book vii. cap. 25.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n45">Acts xvi. 4; comp. ch. xv.</note>
            <note xml:id="n46">The belief was common among the Jacobites that Caiaphas, whose full
               name was Joseph Caïaphas, was the same person as the historian Josephus, and that he
               was converted to Christianity. See Assem., Bibl. Orient., vol. ii. p. 165.</note>
            <note xml:id="n47">[The visible Church and sacraments are necessary, on this principle, to
               the conversion of the world.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n48">[Perhaps a metaphrase of Job v. 12, 13.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n49">This would seem to have been written anterior to the time when the
               title of Bishop, as specially appropriated to those who succeeded to the apostolic
               office, had generally obtained in the East. [Previously named as in the Greek of 2
               Cor. viii. 23.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n50">For writings ascribed to Andrew and Thomas, see Apocryphal Scriptures,
               this volume, infra. Comp. Eccl. Canons, No. 85.—Tr. There is no mention here of the
               Epistles of Paul. They may not at this early period have been collected and become
               generally known in the East. The Epistle of Jude is also omitted here, but it was
               never received into the Syriac canon: see De Wette, Einl., 6th ed. p. 342.</note>
            <note xml:id="n51">So the printed text. But <hi rend="singleQuote">the apostles</hi> seems to be meant.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n52">See note 10 on p. 668.—Tr. It is plain from this that the Epistles were
               not at that time considered part of what was called the New Testament, nor the
               prophets of the Old.</note>
            <note xml:id="n53">Lit. <hi rend="singleQuote">nod,</hi> or <hi rend="singleQuote">bidding,</hi> or <hi rend="singleQuote">impulse.</hi>—Tr. [See Tertull., vol. iii. p.
               252.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n54">Lit. <hi rend="singleQuote">were quiet and silent at.</hi>—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n55">Lit. <hi rend="singleQuote">be an advocate.</hi>—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n56">[Heb. x. 33, 34.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n57">C. reads <hi rend="singleQuote">Pentapolis.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n58">A. has <hi rend="singleQuote">the Indians;</hi> C. <hi rend="singleQuote">the Ethiopians.</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="n59">C. adds, <quote>and built a church at Antioch.</quote></note>
            <note xml:id="n60">See note 3, p. 673, infra.</note>
            <note xml:id="n61">[The omission of reference to St. Paul is a token of a corrupt and
               mediaeval text here.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n62">The reading of C. The ms. A. gives what Cureton transcribes as Gothia,
               which is almost the same as the word rendered <hi rend="singleQuote">Inner.</hi> Possibly this explains the
               origin of the reading of A. <hi rend="singleQuote">Galatia</hi> was perhaps accidentally omitted.—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n63">C. has “the Danube.”</note>
            <note xml:id="n64">Or <hi rend="singleQuote">Soba,</hi> the same as Nisïbis.</note>
            <note xml:id="n65">The number seventy-two may have arisen from the supposition, mentioned
               in the Recognitions and in the Apostolical Constitutions, that our Lord chose them in
               imitation of the seventy-two elders appointed by Moses.</note>
            <note xml:id="n66">Or <hi rend="singleQuote">place.</hi>—Tr.</note>
            <note xml:id="n67">See note 6 on p. 661.</note>
            <note xml:id="n68">B. reads <quote>Priscilla,</quote> C. <quote>Pricillas.</quote> Prisca and Priscilla are the
               forms in which the name occurs in the New Testament.</note>
            <note xml:id="n69">Probably the same as Manaen, mentioned in Acts xiii. 1, as associated
               with Paul at Antioch.</note>
            <note xml:id="n70">[The failure to praise the work of him who “laboured more abundantly
               than all” others, is noteworthy, and can only be accounted for by Middle-Age
               corruptions of the text.]</note>
            <note xml:id="n71">C. adds, <quote>crucifying him on a cross.</quote> C. also adds, <quote>Here endeth the
               treatise of Addaeus the apostle.</quote></note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
