<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en"><persName>Plutarch</persName>'s Moralia</title>
            <editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data architecture and encoding by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz"
                  >Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR cleaning and initial markup of persons and places by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#echrisanthus">Evangelos Chrisanthus</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <title>A Tract of Plutarch on the Advantages to be Derived from One's Enemies</title>,
               translated by Eberhard Nestle, London: C. J. Clay and Sons, 1894.
            </p>
            <p>Published in 1894, this translation is in the public domain.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="work">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head type="title">A Tract of <persName>Plutarch</persName> on the Advantage to be Derived by a Man from
               his Enemy</head>
            <p>Because I see, <persName>Cornelius</persName>, that thou hast chosen for thyself to walk in meekness, so
               that, whilst thou art helping the common affairs, thou in thy own person shewest
               hardness to no man; and again because, as the writers say, there is not to be found
               in the land of <placeName>Crete</placeName> any wild beast, but no community of men is to be found, even
               in modern times, free from envy and jealousy and strife, which are the springs of
               enmity: yet how often friendship is wont to produce on the other side enmity, as also
               <persName>Chilon</persName> the wise pointed out! For when he was told that a certain man had no enemy,
               he answered and said <quote>and therefore no friend</quote>. For he was persuaded that it was
               right for a man to know how the affairs of enemies stand; and it was not in vain that
               <persName>Xenophon</persName> said that <quote>it is the mark of a wise man that he knows how to profit by his
                  enemies</quote>.</p>
            <p>For lo! to them of old time it was enough if only they were not hurt by wild beasts,
               and this single consideration was the end in view in their fight against them: but
               those who came after and learned their use, took advantage of their bodies for food,
               and of their hair for clothing; and for healing, too, they took matter from them;
               they armed themselves with their claws, and covered themselves with their hides; so
               that in consequence of this <pb n="2"/>it is to be feared that when the beasts have
               disappeared from our life, our own life may become as that of the beasts, in which
               resources will not be found, though wildness may be.</p>
            <p>Now since for most men it suffices that their enemies do them no damage, but
               <persName>Xenophon</persName>, on the other hand, said that they are very profitable to the wise man
               (and on this point one must not doubt); we will examine how this advantage is to be
               found. For the examination of it is needful for us, who cannot live without enemies.
               For the gardener cannot change every tree for the better, nor again is it easy for
               the hunter to tame all beasts; yet they understand how by certain means to derive
               profit from wild things: and we may see the planter deriving advantage from fruitless
               trees, and the hunter from wild beasts. The waters of the sea are salt and very
               bitter, but they grow fish at all parts of their depths and conduct merchants on
               their waves. Fire, again, burns him who comes near to it, but it shews light and
               diffuses warmth, and is the means for all handicrafts that know how to use it. See if
               the enemy be not like to these in that while in one direction a man approaches him
               warily, in others he fulfils our need and is profitable. And we may see many things
               which, while they are antagonistic to us and hurt us, are in other respects useful to
               us. How many have fallen into bodily sickness, and their sickness has humbled them
               and restrained them from evil! How many have fallen on toil, and the toil has given
               strength and hardness to their members; others have been deprived of their country
               and their fortunes, and they have made use of both losses as food for the journey,
               and they became to them the means of rest and of useful occupation, as in the case of
               <persName>Diogenes</persName> and <persName>Crates</persName>. <persName>Zeno</persName>, when he heard that the ship, which had been sent by
               him to sea, had been wrecked, answered <pb n="3"/>and said: <quote>It is well for me, so
                  that I may turn to philosophy.</quote> For as those animals whose stomachs are sound, if
               they eat snails or scorpions, digest them; and as others feed on pebbles and clay,
               and through the warmth of their stomachs, digest them; but those, whose stomach is
               weak, become ill even if they get sustenance of bread and wine; in the same way the
               fools are wont even by friendship to get damage, while the wise profit by enmity,
               making good use of it.</p>
            <p>For lo! that which is considered the most difficult, is for the discriminating the
               most profitable; it is this; he (the enemy) searches out thy ways of living and does
               not sleep from examining thy steps and trying to find a cause against thee, while he
               turns hither and thither; therefore watchfulness does not hurt thee, but recalls thee
               to useful behaviour. For the enemy does not make his inquisition carelessly; for his
               gaze enters, as it were, through the walls of thy house, and his spy pierces the
               stones of thy dwelling, yea! he plunders the very mind of thy friends, and through
               thy neighbours he spies out thy works and gets thy secrets from the midst of thy
               beloved by gifts which he offers them. For people are very often, through
               carelessness, in the habit of not noticing even the death of their friends: but
               enemies enquire even about the things that they see in their dreams. And if illness
               come upon a man, or if he takes a loan or has a quarrel with his wife, his enemies
               perceive it before his friends. But especially their glance keeps to the failings of
               their foes, and from all quarters they search them out. And as the vultures by scent
               are gathered on carcases, while they do not at all perceive sound bodies; so also
               enemies come down and gather on evil ways and dead deeds, and draw near to them and
               tear them. And this is profitable; yea! beloved, it is great profit, that we become
               watchful over our ways and examine <pb n="4"/>our persons and do nothing carelessly
               and say nothing thoughtlessly, but that we be blameless in all our steps, for herein
               the danger lies. By chastising our passions and warning our thoughts he increases in
               us the study to live soberly and without reproof. For as towns against which war is
               raised by their neighbours and against which armies advance, are constantly weaned
               from their evil customs and are governed according to law instead of being in
               revolution, thus also many are reproved by reason of enmity: they become awake and
               watchful and are not ready to do anything lightly, and by and by they learn not to
               fail again and they adorn themselves with virtue and are alarmed even at blame. For
               every thing, in which the enemies rejoice, if it comes to their heart, holds them
               back from them and their deeds.<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n4-1"/> We see also those who play on the lyre, that
               when one of them plays by himself in the theatre, he often employs his art
               carelessly: but when he goes down to the contest against the other players, his
               fellows, then he not only recalls his mind from wandering, but he awakens and
               strengthens also the strings of his lyre and puts them in good order for the contest.
               Thus also must he who is conscious that he is going down into the battle with his
               enemies in order to conquer them by his prowess or that they may conquer him, watch
               especially over himself and like that player on the lyre see to himself and his
               deeds.</p>
            <p>For this also is a mark of evil that a man is more ashamed when he sins before his
               enemies than before his friends: as also a wise man signifies; for when it was said
               to him that the affairs of the Romans must be in safety, since they had subdued and
               conquered their enemies, he answered and said: Now there is great danger since <pb
                  n="5"/>there is not left them any before whom they might be ashamed. But
               understand, dear friend, the word which <persName>Diogenes</persName> said, which is very wise and
               helpful. For when he was asked by someone how to avenge himself on his enemies, he
               answered and said to him: Thus canst thou avenge thyself, by becoming good and
               honest. For if they feel grieved when they see the horses of those against whom they
               have hatred to be praised, or his dogs or his garden, what will they do when the man
               himself is praised and when everybody declares his righteousness and sobriety and
               wisdom and the care over his ways, in that he gathers fruit from the deep furrows of
               his mind whence spring all the thoughts that are full of righteousness? And another
               wise man has said that the enemies are brought to silence, not merely as such, nor
               all of them, but according as they see that their enemies are sober and good and
               merciful towards them. For these virtues are a bridle to their tongues, and shut
               their mouths and direct them to quietness. And thou, therefore, if thou wishest to do
               harm to thy enemy, do not call him voluptuous or a liar or an impertinent fellow, but
               shew thyself in thy own person the contrary of it, and be cautious and true and
               merciful and righteous towards every man. But if thou art also provoked to blame him,
               be thyself far from the blame which thou layest upon him: enter into thy mind, and
               examine thy deeds,<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n5-1"/> lest thou hear from these that thou art a physician whilst
               thou art full of sores. If also thou callest him a fool, do thou thyself add and win
               wisdom; if a coward, multiply thou courage; and if thou callest him voluptuous,
               buffet thou the lusts that are in thy own mind. For there is nothing which is more
               hateful and distressing, than a reproach which falls back on him that sent it; and as
                  <pb n="6"/>weak eyes are hurt by light, that falls on a place and is reflected
               upon them, so also a blame, when it reflects from without a truth on him that has
               uttered it, he who sent it forth is vexed thereby. And <persName>Plato</persName>, when he saw men that
               were vile, was wont to say as he turned away from them: <quote>Lest I myself were to become
               so</quote>. He, therefore, who reproaches his neighbour, when he turns to him and sees
               himself, as in an example, is himself also helped by the reproach which he cast,
               though it is [otherwise] very damaging. But most men laugh when they see a man who,
               while he is bald or hump-backed, reproaches others with those faults. But many fools
               reproach others with what turns back on themselves. <persName>Leo</persName>, however, when he was
               called blind by one who had a hump, answered and said to him: Thou reproachest me
               with a bodily defect, but thou bearest thy defects upon thy shoulders. Therefore do
               not call thy neighbour an adulterer, while thou thyself art sensual; nor licentious,
               while thou art impertinent. <persName>Domitius</persName> wished to reproach <persName>Crassus</persName>, who, when an
               animal died that he had kept in a cage, had wept about it; but <persName>Crassus</persName> said to him:
               <quote>That I might not be like thyself; thou hast buried three wives that thou hast had,
               and hast not wept for one of them</quote>. But this is not required, that a man be ready for
               slandering and daring and raising his voice, but that, while he reproaches, he does
               not give opportunity that the reproach be sent back to himself For this also God
               demands from any who wishes to reproach his neighbour, that he first examine himself,
               lest while he says what pleases him, he should hear what does not rejoice him, and
               lest his ears should unwillingly perceive what his mouth has sent forth
               willingly.</p>
            <p>This, therefore, is the advantage of the man that reproaches his enemies: but there
               is also another advantage <pb n="7"/>to be found, in that a man be reproached by his
               enemies. Therefore rightly <persName>Antisthenes</persName> said: He whose object is that he be famous
               in his conduct, has need either of true friends or of mighty enemies, inasmuch as
               they, by chastising him when he has sinned and by reproaching him, turn him away from
               that which is foul. But because the voice of love is feeble<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n7-1"/> and cannot
               reprehend with a full mouth, but is ready for sweet words: it is necessary therefore
               that we should hear the truth from our enemies. For like as <persName>Telephus</persName>, who had no
               physician, brought the sore of his complaint under the lance of his enemy, so must he
               who has no friend to reprehend him, tolerate the reprehension of his enemies, when
               they reprehend and unveil his vices, looking on the healing that he gets, and not on
               the mind that is working him ill. For like the man whom from hatred some one wished
               to kill, and struck him with the sword on a tumour, and thus, through this stroke, as
               through an incision, the tumour was opened and he saved from death; so often from
               anger or from enmity a reproach is uttered, and a pain, that is hidden or covered in
               the soul, is made whole. But most people, when they are reproached, do not look
               whether the reproach be true or not, but they look for some other word by which he
               who reproaches them may be reproached: after the fashion of athletes, who go down to
               fight, who do not at all wipe away what is thrown upon them, but turn and throw
               again; thus also do these defile each other with reproaches in their fight with one
               another. But we ought, when we are reproached by our enemies, if it is a true word,
               to keep our soul from it and not leave the sore that was shewn to us: but, if it be
               not true, we must seek the cause from which this reproach was taken: but we must <pb
                  n="8"/>fear and be cautious, in case we have transgressed or done something like
               or similar to what was said: a thing which happened also to that king of <placeName>Argos</placeName>; for
               the hair of the locks of his head, and a lazy manner of walking, brought upon him a
               foul suspicion. Again there came upon <persName>Pompeius</persName> from a certain cause a similar
               reproach, though he was far from lasciviousness. Moreover <persName>Crassus</persName> was reproached on
               account of a virgin. For, because he wished to buy from her a parcel of ground, he
               was obliged to write to her and to honour her. And for <persName>Postumia</persName> inordinate laughter
               and freedom of speech gained the reproach of licentiousness, so that she was accused
               of adultery: but she was found innocent. The judge, however, warned her and told her
               not to use words at all that are foreign to modesty. <persName>Themistocles</persName>, too, though he
               was pure, and no traitor of the town, fell into a suspicion of treachery because he
               constantly received letters from his friend <persName>Pausanias</persName>. When therefore a word is
               spoken that is not true, we must not, because it is a false rumour, despise and
               [contemn](condemn) it, but we must search and see, whether in our speech or in our
               deeds, or in those who are attached to us, there be found anything that is like the
               rumour. We must avoid and flee from it.</p>
            <p>For if to most people the losses that befell them increased their knowledge, as also
               <persName>Merope</persName> said: <quote>misfortunes have taken from me my friends and have taught me
               caution</quote>: what hinders us from setting up for ourselves constantly a teacher, free of
               charge, and learning from him what is hidden in our own mind? For the enemy perceives
               many things, of which the friend is not conscious. For, as <persName>Plato</persName> said, he who loves
               is blind as regards seeing the faults of his friends. But hatred, while his glance is
               keen, has also his mouth open. <persName>Hieron</persName> when he quarrelled with his enemy was
               reproached by him for the foulness <pb n="9"/>of the smell of his mouth. Then, when
               he came to his house, he answered and said to his wife: <quote>neither hast thou told me
               the defect that is upon me</quote>. But she, because she had not had intercourse with
               another man, and was innocent, answered and said to him: <quote>as for me, I believed that
               such was the smell of the mouth of all men</quote>. Thus it is easy to learn known faults
               and secret faults first from enemies, before we learn them from friends and
               lovers.</p>
            <p>And without this it is not possible for us to restrain our tongue and gain, without
               much exercise, that great part of the righteousness which a man must have in order to
               subdue his passions which love noise and talkativeness which are the cause of
               quarrelsomeness and enmity. For if it happens that our tongue trespasses with a word:
               it flies like a bird from our nests; and from the mouth of a man who is not practised
               in subduing his anger there often fly words<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n9-1"/> and from his weakness and
               carelessness and impertinence he stumbles. But <persName>Plato</persName> said that of the lightest word
               people must pay damages both to God and man. But silence not only, as the physicians
               say, keeps from thirst, but also from reprehensions and rebukes. There is nothing
               more honourable than that a man when he is reproached by his enemy should keep
               silence. For if thou art silent towards him, it is much more easy for thee to endure
               thy wife, if she speaks ill of thee: and the brother, too, and the friend, thou canst
               tolerate when they reproach thee. And, further, thou dost endure without anger thy
               father and thy mother, even when they beat thee. For <persName>Isocrates</persName> (sic!) took a hard
               and passionate wife in order that it might be easy for him to bear with strangers,
               having been exercised by her in patience. It is, however, much <pb n="10"/>better
               that a man should be exercised by his enemies, and practised by their reproaches and
               their railing, and that he restrain his anger and do not suffer it to arise when
               reviling provokes it.</p>
            <p>Meekness, therefore, and patience, we must thus shew towards enemies, but [also we
               must shew] simplicity and sweetness and goodness, even more than towards friends. For
               it is not so much a great thing, if we do good to our friend, as it is a shameful
               thing, if we do it not. But as regards one's enemy, if a man forbears vengeance, when
               it was easy for him to avenge, this is a mark of goodness: but if he weeps over his
               fall and stretches out his hand towards his need and shews kindly care with goodwill
               towards his children or towards his relatives, when he sees them in need: who would
               not love such an one and praise his peacefulness and his goodness, whose heart he
               sees to be made as of iron and diamond! When <persName>Caesar</persName> ordered to re-erect the statues
               of <persName>Pompeius</persName> his enemy, that had been thrown down, a wise man answered and said:
               Those statues thou hast re-erected, but thine own thou hast fastened. Therefore we
               must neither spare praise nor honour, if it is due to any one who is our enemy. For
               he is more praised who praises his enemy, and through this there is room that his
               reproof be believed, when he reproves, as of one who does not hate the man, but
               repudiates his deeds. And what is the best of all, is that it is observed concerning
               him that he is very far from envying the valor of his friends, because he often
               praised his enemies. For through this he shews, that still less is he becoming
               envious, because his friends succeed. And lo! what study can be better than this,
               that a man should gain the mind that eradicates envy and jealousy from his soul? For
               like as those who are accustomed to war are possessed by the passion of <pb n="11"
               />anger, and it is, therefore, not easy for them to repress it during peace, though
               it is damaging, because it is rooted in them with other passions, that are fit for
               war, but not useful in peace, so is it with enmity, which brings in with the hatred
               envy and jealousy and causes a man to rejoice in evil and to keep wrath, while he is
               cunning and full of tricks and ready to do hurt. For all this, when it is used
               against enemies, does not appear very hard: but it is treasured in the soul and from
               custom a man is led to use it also against his friends, and he does wrong to his
               beloved, if he is not careful towards his enemies. Therefore one of the philosophers,
               that he might accustom himself to be friendly towards men, shewed mercifulness
               towards animals.</p>
            <p>For it is very honourable, if we have enmity against a man, that we also in the time
               of our anger walk righteously toward him and do not deceive our enemy, and be not
               cunning in evil, so that it may be possible for us to be free from falsity in our
               love to our friends. <persName>Scaurus</persName> was an enemy of <persName>Domitius</persName>. There came a slave of
               <persName>Domitius</persName> privately to open the secrets of his master to his enemy <persName>Scaurus</persName>. But
               <persName>Scaurus</persName> did not allow him to open his mouth, but took him and sent him to his
               master. Now this not only brings praise, but is also very advantageous. For if we
               accustom ourselves to be righteous towards our enemies, we shall be in no wise wicked
               towards our friends. Now because there comes on us envy and strife, it is proper that
               when we suffer from them, we should go to the doors of the wise, as to the doors of
               the physicians, and through useful words extinguish the flame. But when a man has to
               bear great evils from his enemies, the word will come to his heart, which the wise
               <persName>Demos</persName> has spoken. For this man was very fond of his friends, and he was noble in
               his words: when now a revolution took place <pb n="12"/>in his town, and his party
               was victorious, he began to counsel and to say: And, my comrades, we will not destroy
               all our enemies, but leave a residue of them, lest if these disappeared from us, we
               should begin to do harm to ourselves. So ought we to do: if there are in us evil
               passions, we will exhaust them in endurance against our enemies, that we may not in
               the least do harm to our friends. For it must not be, that things should be, as
               <persName>Hesiod</persName> speaks of; for he says the potter envies the potter, and the neighbour the
               neighbour, and again the sons of brothers envy each other. But if it is not easy for
               a man to be free from envy, I counsel that he subdue it<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-1"/> towards his enemies,
               and not<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-2"/> envy them<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n12-3"/> when they succeed, that he may be able to be
               without envy towards his friends. For like as the rose-gardeners believe, that the
               rose or the lily become more beautiful, when they plant beside them onions and
               garlic; for they suck up all foulness and sharpness; so also the enemy sucks up all
               our bitterness and makes us to be pleasant to our friends. Therefore we must become
               like them in their ability and emulate them in their virtue, and not grudge them
               their successes, and understand from what causes they excel, and be zealous to
               surpass them through carefulness, keeping an eye on our own selves and walking
               cautiously: as also <persName>Themistocles</persName> said: that the victory which <persName>Miltiades</persName> gained
               does not allow him to sleep. For he who envies the successes of his enemies and <pb
                  n="13"/>at once plunges himself in grief uses his envy as an idle thing. But he
               whose eyes are not blind, profits by him whom he envies, by seeing that most of his
               results are gained by zeal and carefulness, so that in lifting his glance upon them,
               he is benefited by imitating them, and he casts from him his sleep and his idleness.
               But if he sees in them disquiet and subtilty, or that they judge without
               righteousness, or gain fortune by shameful means, he is not at all angry at this; but
               perhaps his mind rejoices, that through comparison with them his candour will be
               recognised. As <persName>Plato</persName> said: All the gold that is found on the earth and in the midst
               of the earth, does not weigh against the gloriousness of conduct, according to what
               <persName>Solon</persName> said: We in no wise exchange virtuous behaviour for riches, nor for the
               praises of drunken spectators, nor to obtain honour with eunuchs and concubines and
               satraps of kings. For there is nothing that is enviable and virtuous that sprang from
               a shameful cause. But because the faults<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n13-1"/> of our friends are not seen by us,
               but the vices of our enemies we quickly perceive, we must not rejoice, even if we are
               inclined to, when they fall, nor be distressed when they succeed, nor stay
               unprofitably in either the one or the other: but from their vices we must guard
               ourselves, and their virtues we must imitate, so that by watchfulness against the
               evil we may surpass and conquer our enemies, and in the imitation of their virtues we
               may not fail nor fall behind.</p>
            <p>Endeth the tract of <persName>Plutarch</persName> on the advantage to be derived by a man from his
               enemy.</p>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n4-1">The Syriac is not clear.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5-1">Did he read <foreign xml:lang="gr">περισκόπει τὰ σὰ ἔργα</foreign>
               instead of <foreign xml:lang="grc">τὰ σαθρὰ</foreign>?</note>
            <note xml:id="n7-1">Lit. extinguished.</note>
            <note xml:id="n9-1">Remark the idiomatic expression <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡ̈ܠܝܢ
                  ܡ̈ܠܝܢ</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-1">So the MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-2">So again MS.</note>
            <note xml:id="n12-3">It is strange that, as stated by Wyttenbach: <quote><foreign
                  xml:lang="la">Stephanus dedit <foreign xml:lang="grc">δάκνεσθαι μὴ τῶν
                     ἐχθρῶν</foreign>: perperam <foreign xml:lang="grc">μὴ</foreign> arripiens ex
                  Pol. et Jannot. Abest recte ab Ald. Bas. Xyl. A. B. E. Mosc. 1. 2.</foreign></quote> The
               Greek text of Wyttenbach is <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀλλ’ εἰ μηδεὶς τρόπος ἐστὶν <foreign xml:lang="la">[sic]</foreign> ἄλλος ἀππαλαγῆς ἐρίδων
               καὶ φθόνων καὶ φιλονεικῶν, ἔθιζε σαυτὸν δάκνεσθαι τῶν ἐχθρῶν εὐημερούντων, καὶ
               παρόξυνε καὶ χάραττε τὸ φιλόνεικον ἐν ἐκείνοις θηγόμενον</foreign>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n13-1">According to the Greek <foreign xml:lang="grc">τυφλοῦται τὸ φιλοῦν
                  περὶ τὸ φιλούμενον</foreign> we expect instead of <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                  >ܕܡܘܡ̈ܐ</foreign> something like <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܖ̈ܚܘܡܐ</foreign>.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
