<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8798">Nisibis 65</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LXV"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LXV
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 65</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Man: O Death, despise thou it not, that image of <persName>Adam</persName>: which like a seed is committed
               to earth, till the Resurrection.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Response: To thee be glory Who didst descend and plunge, after <persName>Adam</persName>: and draw him out from
               the depths of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>, and bring him into Eden!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Death: I marvel at this seed, and at your words: for lo! after five thousand years,
               it springs not yet.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Man Its present state passes away, as winter does: and as a handful of corn it comes
               in the resurrection, to the garner of life.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Death: That there is vintage-time, lo! I know, but I have not seen: the dead at any time
               sown, or yet reaped.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Man There is coming a reaping, O Death, that will leave thee bare: and the Watchers
               shall go forth as reapers, and make thee desolate.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>Death: When did I become husbandman, instead of vine-dresser? who has turned <placeName>Sheol</placeName> the
               wine-press, into a tilled field?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Man Does not the seed then teach thee, which decays and dies: and is cut off from
               hope, yet from the rain, recovers hope?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>Death: A dream have ye seen ye feeble ones, of life from the dead: for in waking time
               the resurrection, ye do not see.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>Man Thy drowsiness hinders thee, that thou seest not: the multitudes of mysteries
               which cry aloud, of the resurrection.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Death: I know that seeds come to life, but I have not seen: bones that grew in <placeName>Sheol</placeName>,
               and sprang and came up.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>Man All thy discourse is like thyself, for lo! Ezekiel: has taught thee how in the
               valley, the dead come to life.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Death: Trees have I seen how in summer, they put on their garments: but bones in their
               nakedness, are cast into <placeName>Sheol</placeName>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Man <persName>Moses</persName> broke by his splendour, thy heart, O Death: the son of <persName>Adam</persName> has regained
               and put on, the glory of <persName>Adam</persName>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>Death: Our law in <placeName>Sheol</placeName> is this, to keep silence: for you are words and for me deeds, O
               feeble ones.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>Man How are the aged passed over if thou be vinedresser? He Who hindered thee from
               taking their lives, the same quickens all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>The babe in the womb confutes thee, which is as buried there: to me it proclaims life
               from the dead, but to thee despoiling.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>The despised flower despises thee, for it is shut up and passed over: yet though lost
               it is not lost, but blossoms again.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>The chick cries out from the egg, wherein it is buried: and the graves are rent by a
               Voice, and the body arises.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>For a body too is the chick, that is in the egg: lo! its body to our body proclaims,
               the life from the dead.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>With the locust thy plea is overthrown, and ended, O Death: for in coming forth from
               the dust it teaches, the life from the dead.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>Death: I had been content if already, the resurrection had been: for the day of
               resurrection had disturbed me less, than your judgments.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>Merciful is the Son of the Highest, yea good and just: and will not harshly avenge on
               me, the death of <persName>Adam</persName>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>Have ye then no understanding, to perceive this: that your father laid on you, this
               retribution?</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
