<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8740">Nisibis 3</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_III"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_III
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 3</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Fix thou our hearing, that it be not loosed and wander! For it is a-wandering if one
               enquire, who He is and what He is like. For how can we avail, to paint in us the
               likeness, of that Being which is like to the mind? Naught is there in it that is
               limited, in all of it He sees and hears; all of it as it were speaks; all of it is in
               all senses.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Praise to the One Being, that is to us unsearchable!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>His aspect cannot be discerned, that it should be portrayed by our understanding: He
               hears without ears; He speaks without mouth; He works without hands, and He sees
               without eyes. Because our soul ceases not nor desists, in presence of Him Who is
               such; in His graciousness He put on the fashion of humankind and gathered us into His
               likeness.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Let us learn in what way that Being is spiritual and appeared as corporeal; and how
               it also is tranquil and appears as wrathful. These things were for our profit; that
               Being in our likeness was made like to us that we may be made like Him. One there is
               that is like Him, the Son Who proceeded from Him, Who is stamped with His
               likeness.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>O Nisibis, hear these things, for, for thy sake these things were written and
               spoken. Both to thyself and to others, thou hast been in the world a cause of strife
               and of disputations. Mouths over thee, O thou that wast shut up, even over thee
               mouths sang; when thou didst triumph and wast enlarged, in thee mouths were opened,
               for lamentation and for thanksgiving.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>The prayer of thy inhabitants, sufficed for thy deliverance; it was not that they
               were righteous, but that they were penitent: according as they were disgraced, so did
               they haste to submit to the rod. In transgressions and in triumphs they had like
               part. They whose crimes were great, so be their fruit great; they who triumphed in
               their sackcloth, have triumphed also in their crowns.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>The day of thy deliverance, is king of all days. The Sabbath overthrew thy walls, it
               overthrew the ungrateful; the day of the Resurrection of the Son, raised again thy
               ruins; the day of Resurrection raised thee according to its name, it glorified its
               title. The Sabbath relaxed its watch; for the making of the breaches, it took blame
               to itself.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>In Samaria hunger prevailed, but in thee fulness prevailed. In Samaria there broke
               in and came on her, abundance of a sudden; but in thee there roared and came in on
               thee a sea of a sudden. In her was eaten a child, and it saved her alive; in thee was
               eaten the body, living and all life-giving; of a sudden He delivered them, the Eaten
               delivered the eaters.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>We know that the Blessed wills not the afflictions, that have been in all ages;
               though He has wrought them, it is our offences that are the cause of our troubles. No
               man can complain against our Creator; it is for Him to complain against us, who have
               sinned and constrained Him, to be wrathful though He wills it not, and to smite
               though He desires it not.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>The Earth, the vine, and the olive, are in need of chastisement. When the olive is
               bruised, then its fruit smells sweet; when the vine is pruned, then its grapes are
               goodly; when the soil is ploughed its yield is goodly. When water is confined in
               channels, desert places drink of it; brass, silver and gold, when they are burnished
               shine.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>If then it be that man, by chastening makes all things goodly; and if he who
               despises and rejects chastening, is hated and all rebels against him; then by that
               which he chastens, let him learn Him that chastens him; since whoso chastens does so
               that he may profit thereby. For whoso chastens his servants, does so that he may
               possess them; the good God chastens His servants that they may possess
               themselves.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Let thy afflictions be, books to admonish thee, for the thrice-besieged, suffice to
               become for thee, books to meditate therein, every hour on their histories. Because
               thou despisedst the two Testaments, wherein thou mightest read thy life, therefore He
               wrote for thee, three hard books wherein thou shouldst read thy chastisements.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>Let us avert by that which has been, the thing that is yet to be; let us be taught
               by that which has come, to escape that which is coming; let us remember that which is
               past, to avoid that which is future. Because we had forgotten the first stroke, the
               second fell on us; because we forgot the second, the third bore heavy on us. Who will
               yet again forget!</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
