<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8795">Nisibis 62</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LXII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LXII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 62</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Lo! Death, the King of silence, complains, my brethren: that we have filled his abode
               with the wailing, of Hope cut off.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Response: To Him be great praise Who comest down, to us here below: and suffered and rose
               again and in His Body, raises our bodies!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>While we weep like madmen, at the gates of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>: hearken what Death says,
               reproaching us.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>It shames me, says Death, that ye, have overcome me: the half of <placeName>Sheol</placeName> suffices not,
               to contain your slain.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>For alien corpses together, lie heaped in <placeName>Sheol</placeName>: there are two divisions there, the
               dead, the slain.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Whereas I should complain that ye have wronged me, lo! ye are weeping: ye have burst
               the gate of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>, and done me hurt.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>For ye are like unto an infant, which while yet weeping: laughs again as ye also,
               over your dead.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>For there is no discretion in your mourning, and no understanding: in your
               laughter—for to me ye seem like, to a weaned babe.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>One hour weeping and wailing, and after a little: both jesting and wantonness, as of
               children.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>For ye are unable to become, perfect men: that weep not yea and laugh not, as the
               discreet.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Touching your books we are grieved, that they have toiled over them: who should read
               them unto you, even the divine Scriptures.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>The readers are crying aloud, for ye are deaf: this their crying proves concerning
               you, that ye are as stocks.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>For since the reader and the interpreter, are crying aloud: your ears therefore are
               heavy, or else your hearts.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>For if there were with you an ear, open to persuasion: it were meet to hear little,
               and to do much.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>But because its hearing is closed, whoso knocks at it: the voice returns back to him,
               who sent it forth.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>There is no crying with me of mine, I am not deaf: none that reads or interprets for
               me, I am not dull.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>The breath that is from Him commands me, sons the God of truth: and with the command
               there follows, also the fulfilment.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>With me is no holding back, no turnings aside: I wot no arrow even, could outstrip
               me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>But your voices are scorned by me, when ye are weeping: over the graves of your
               departed, in the cutting off of hope.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>Were it possible or permitted, when ye are weeping: I would go forth and tell you, to
               your faces.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab><quote>I am endeavouring to give, an account of the death: and your voices disturb me, that
               I err in my count.</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>Ye nations, let not your understanding, become childish: like that nation whose
               intelligence, was never great.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>In which prudence bestows not itself, as in a fool: for its thoughts are darkness,
               without discernment.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>For your infants and your sons, in the resurrection: they shall be foremost to come
               forth, as the first fruits</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>Then after them shall come the just, as victorious: last shall come forth the sinner,
               as put to shame.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>For although in the twinkling of an eye, they be quickened: yet is it in order that
               their ranks, come forth from <placeName>Sheol</placeName>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>Prophets come forth and Apostles, and holy Fathers: following them in due array,
               according to command.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <ab>Lo! that which now is sown, in random mixture: is yielded back in great order, as
               garden-herbs.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="29">
            <ab>For though one in the sowing, should mix all seeds: that which is earlier than its
               fellow, prevents its fellow,</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="30">
            <ab>And not as their going down was confused, so disordered shall be: their coming up
               from the earth, for its order is fixed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="31">
            <ab>Lo! I have been against myself, in what I have said: for secret things which ye
               comprehended not, from me ye have learned.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="32">
            <ab>Instead of the tears that profit not, which are at the tomb: pour them forth in your
               prayer, in the midst of the Church.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="33">
            <ab>For to the dead there is profit in these, and likewise to the living: weep not with a
               weeping that afflicts, both dead and living!</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
