<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8743">Nisibis 6</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_VI"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_VI
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 6</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>I will run in my affections, to Him who heals freely. He who healed my sorrows, the
               first and the second, He who cured the third, He will heal the fourth. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Heal me, Thou Son the First Born!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>My sons, O my Lord, drank and were drunken, of the tidings which wrath had mixed;
               and they rushed on my adornments, and spoiled and cast away my ornaments; they rent
               and spared not, my garments and my crowns.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>They uncovered me and I was made bare. Because I was shamed a little, by means of
               that stripping, the first and the second, because I was shamed a third time, lo! they
               have stripped me a fourth time.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>For they have seized and taken away my garments, my ornaments and my gardens. On the
               sackcloth that girds my altar, look Thou, O my Lord, and have pity on me! Let the
               sackcloth be to me, O my Lord, the breastplate of salvation!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Lo! it is not by the hand of the chaste, that Thou hast chastised me, O my Master!
               For lo! his shame is before him, and behind him his disgrace; for as to his marriage,
               adultery is better than it.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Lo! his daughter is his wife, and his sister his consort; and his mother whence he
               came forth, he turns again and takes her to wife! The heavens are astonished that
               thus, he provokes Thee, and lo! he prospers.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>And though, O my Lord, my crimes are many, are my offences so heavy, that Thou
               shouldst make over a chaste woman, mother of chaste daughters, to foul Assyria,
               mother of defiled daughters?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Restrain him that he come not, and wag at me his head, and stamp on me his heel, and
               rejoice that the voice of his fame, thus troubles the world; and be uplifted yet a
               little!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>My sons, O my Lord, have seen my nakedness, yea have uncovered me and wept. Uncover
               Thou me before my children, who are pained by my pain, and let not those mock at me,
               the accursed that have no pity!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>My lands had brought forth fruits and pleasant things; good things in the vineyard,
               abundance in the fields. But as I rested secure, of a sudden wrath overtook me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>The husbandmen were plundered, the spoilers heaped the grain; what thou had borrowed
               and sown these destroyed. With one’s debt his hunger, haply will also remain
               unsatisfied, for his bread is snatched from him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>The husbandman, O my Lord, is plundered, for he lent to the earth; she has received
               the deposit, and given it to a stranger; she has borrowed it of the husbandman; and
               paid it to the spoiler.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Be jealous over me who am Thine, and to Thee, O my Lord: am I betrothed! The Apostle
               who betrothed me to Thee, told me that Thou art jealous. For as a wall to chaste
               wives is the jealousy of their husbands.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Samson stirred up seas, because he was mightily jealous over his wife, though she
               was greatly defiled, and was divided against him. Keep Thy Church, for no other, has
               she beside Thee!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>Whoso is not jealous, over his spouse despises her. Jealousy it is that can make
               known, the love that is within. Thou art called jealous, that thou mayest show me Thy
               love.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>The nature of woman is this; it is weak and rash: it is jealousy keeps it, under
               fear every hour. Thou hast been named among the jealous, that Thou mightest make
               known Thy solicitude.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>Every man has been master, of something that was not his own; every man has gone
               forth gathering, something that he scattered not. The day of confusion, I have
               prepared for myself by my crimes.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>How shall they bear the suffering, the labourers and tillers? In the face of the
               vinedresser, they have cut down the vines and driven away the flocks of the
               husbandman; his sowing they have reaped and carried off.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>They had yoked cattle sown and harrowed, they had ploughed, planted, nurtured. They
               stood afar and wept; and they went away bereft of all. The labour was for the
               toilers, the increase for the spoilers.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>The rulers, O my Lord, maintained not, order in the midst of Thy wrath. If they had
               willed it they might have kept order, but our iniquity suffered it not. Though wrath
               had greatly abated, wrath compelled them to spoil.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>To whom on any side, shall I look for comfort, for my plantations that are laid low,
               and my possessions that are laid waste? Let the message of the voice of peace, drive
               away my sadness from me!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>Give me not over; lest it be thought that Thou, hast given me a writing of divorce,
               and sent me away and driven me out! Let them not call me, O my Lord, the forsaken and
               the disgraced!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>I have not anything, to call to mind before Thine eyes, for I am wholly despised.
               Call Thou to mind for me, O my God, this only that none other, have I set before me
               beside Thee!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>Who would not weep for me, with voice and wailing? for before the days of full moon
               I was chaste and crowned; and after the days of full moon, I was uncovered and made
               bare.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>My chaste daughters of the chambers, wander in the fields; for the wrath that makes
               all drunken, has caused my honourable women to be despised. Let Thy mercy which gives
               peace to all, restore these beloved ones to honour!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>My elder daughters and my younger, lo! they cry before Thee; the damsels with their
               voices, they that are aged with their tears; my virgins with their fasts, my chaste
               ones with their sackcloth!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>Mine eyes to all the streets, I lift up and lo! they are deserted. There are left of
               a hundred ten, and a thousand of ten thousand. Give Thou peace and fill my streets,
               with the tumult of my dwellers!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <ab>Bring back them that are without, and make them glad that are within! Mighty is Thy
               grace, that Thou extendest it within and without. Let the wings of Thy grace gather
               my chickens together!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="29">
            <ab>Let the prayer of my just men, save my fugitives! The unbelievers have plundered me,
               and the believers have sustained me. In them that believe put Thou to shame them that
               believe not!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="30">
            <ab>There came together on one day, two festivals as one: the Feast of Thine Ascension,
               and the Feast of Thy Champions; the feast that wove Thy Crown, and the memorial of
               the crowning of Thy servants.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="31">
            <ab>Have thou mercy because there were doubled for us, these feasts on one day; and
               there were doubled for us instead of them, even the two feasts in one, suffering from
               the voice of ill tidings, and mourning from desolation!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="32">
            <ab>Give peace to my festivals! for both my feasts have ceased; and instead of
               rejoicing, of my remnants in festivals, tremblings and desolations meet me in every
               place.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="33">
            <ab>Bring home mine that are far off, make glad mine that are nigh; and in the midst of
               our land shall be preached, good tidings of joy; and I shall render in return for
               peace, praise from every mouth!</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
