<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8801">Nisibis 68</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LXVIII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LXVIII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 68</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Man: O, Death, be not thou boastful, over the just: the sons of thy Lord who at His
               command, come to dwell with thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Response: To thee be glory that by Thy command, Death has reigned: and by Thy Resurrection
               has been humbled to low estate!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Death., Herein am I exceeding great, according to thy saying: that though I be
               bond-man I trample on them that are free.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Man: Adam was chosen and ruler, and under his yoke: thou, Death, and the Evil One, thy
               fellow, became bondmen.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Death: This is our pride that lo! the slaves have become lords: Death, and Satan, his
               fellow, have trampled on Adam.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Man: Lo! the humbling of thee and thy fellow, accurst servants! how Enoch trampled on
               you both, and rose aloft and reigned.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>Death: If so be Enoch made me grieve, yet have I comfort for on Noah’s dust in Sheol,
               lo! I trample.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Man: Tremble, O Death, before man, for though a servant, the yoke of his dominion
               reigns on all creatures.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>Death: I rejoice then that they are no mean foes that I have overcome: for according to
               the greatness of the vanquished, he is great that overcomes.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>Man: Well does thy voice sing triumph, O Death, over the just: for Enoch and Elijah
               have broken thy pair of wings.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Death: I know how to weigh my sorrows with my comforts: in place of two, lo! many are
               come and coming.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>Man: All that are come and coming to thee dwell as sojourners, and depart from thy
               abode as Lazarus.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Death: This thy saying hurts me not, rather it heals me: for Lazarus who rebelled
               against me, I again subdued.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Man: Make answer, O Death, and argue what constrained him, to be raised unless it were
               a mystery, showing forth his resurrection.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>Death: Ye are famous in arguing as idle ones, while I labour in my task to discern and
               perform</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>Man: Thou wast well prepared for argument, what has checked thee? The truth of our
               resurrection has constrained thee by its reputations.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>Death: Ye have made me hated by you, though I be not hateful: I am he that gives rest to
               your aged, and your afflicted.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>Ye have made me as one that troubles, O ye mortals: Adam brought death upon you, and
               I bear the blame.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>Gently will I expose you, for I am a slave, and ye are they that by your sins have
               made me king.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>The will of Adam roused me for I was at rest: I was dead and ye quickened me, that ye
               might die by me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>I accuse the lying ones, who slew and denied it: for Adam slew himself and charges
               me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>The beginning of strife was the accursed serpent which has rightly been crippled:
               which crept, entered, and set enmity between me and you.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>Satan is passed by and it is against me that ye are roused: go, strive with the Evil
               One who made you transgress.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>He is my comrade and I deny it not, but though he be much hated, what need that I be
               blamed for him. I deny him henceforth.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>Hearken to my words, O mortals, and I will console you: I have afflicted you and I
               confess the life from the dead.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>For there begins to steal into my ears a voice of preparation: of the trumpet that
               holds itself ready to sound.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>Hear my words and put much oil into your lamps: for hindrance from my part there is
               none for you.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <ab>Yet, Know ye that even although I have said these things, dear is the sound of your
               voice in the solitude of Sheol.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="29">
            <ab>For man has been weighed by me, and great is his peace: for snakes and fishes and
               birds come to meet him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="30">
            <ab>But it is a marvel that to the Watchers, too, his converse is dear: yea, the Evil One
               in Gehenna, desires his presence.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="31">
            <ab>Ye shall have life from the dead, O ye mortals, and I who am bereft shall be bereft
               in the midst of Sheol.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="32">
            <ab>Let praise ascend from all to Thee Who quickenest all, and from every quarter
               gatherest the dust of Adam!</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
