<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8753">Nisibis 17</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XVII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XVII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head><placeName>Nisibis</placeName> 17</head>
         <head type="sub">Concerning Abraham, Bishop of Nisibis.</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Suffer, O Lord, that even my lowliness, should cast into Thy treasury its farthing,
               even as the merchant of our flock, who made increase of his talent of Thy doctrine,
               and has departed and entered Thy haven. I will speak of the shepherd, under him who
               has become head of the flock; who was disciple of the Three, and has become our
               fourth master. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has made him our comfort!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>In one love will I cause them to shine, and as a crown will I weave them, the
               splendid blossoms, and the fragrant flowers of the teacher and of his disciple, who
               remained after him as <persName>Elisha</persName>; for the horn of his election and he was consecrated and
               became head, and he was exalted and became master. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who made him chief!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>And they in heaven rejoiced for the flock, that by the pastor whom they fed, they
               feed it; the abode of the shepherds under him rejoiced, because they saw the
               succession of their degrees. He took and set him as a mind in the midst of the great
               body of the church, and his members came round him to buy of him life, doctrine, new
               bread. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who made him their treasury!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>He chose him from the multitude of shepherds, because he had given trial of his
               stedfastness; the time tested him in the midst of the flock, and length of days
               proved him as a crucible; for that he gave proof in his person, He made him a wall
               for many. Let thy fasting be armour to our country, thy prayer a shield to our city,
               let thy censer purchase reconcilement. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has hallowed thy sacrifices!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>The Pastor who has been parted from his flock, fed them on spiritual pastures, and
               by his exalted staff, he defended them from secret wolves. Fill thou up the room of
               thy master, which thirsts for the sound of his melody; set up thyself as a pillar, in
               the city of the trembling people; support her with thy prayers. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has made thee our pillar!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>He has committed the Hand to his disciple, the Throne to one that is worthy of it,
               the Key to one that is proved faithful, the Flock to one that has excelled. To thy
               hand belongs the laying-on, to thy offering propitiation, and to thy tongue
               consolation. May peace adorn thy Dominion; be the watchmen within and the
               congregations without. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has chosen thee for rejoicings!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>May thy doctrine abound, in deeds more than words! In saying few words, till Thou
               our land with labour, that by much tillage the scanty seed may become rich, the
               increase of the old seed, may come among us thirtyfold, and thy new seed sixtyfold.
            </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who multiplies an hundredfold!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>The wrath that was against thee ceases, because peace flows over thee altogether;
               the jealousy against thee is quenched, for thy love hourly flames forth: thou hast
               broken the string of envy, that it should smite none in secret; slander that
               confounds, to it thy ear turns not, for open truth is pleasing to thee. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who adorned thy members!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>Thou shalt give counsel in the midst of thy people, like <persName>Jethro</persName> among the Hebrews;
               thou shalt altogether go with him, who for thy profit counsels thee, thou shalt
               altogether flee from him, who otherwise counsels thee: <persName>Rehoboam</persName> shall be a sign to
               thee; thou shalt choose counsels of profit, thou shalt refuse counsels of envy. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has counselled comfort!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>The gift that has been given thee, from on high it flew and came down: thou shalt
               call it by a name of man, thou shalt not bear it in another power, lest haply to its
               place there should come, Satan in his guile, supposing, that the sons of men have
               given it to thee, so that this freeborn gift should serve in bondage to man. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has handed down his gift!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Thy master is painted in thy person; lo! his likeness is on thee altogether; parted
               from us one with us is he. In thee we shall see those three, the excellent ones who
               are parted from us. Thou shalt be unto us a wall as <persName>Jacob</persName>, and full of tenderness as
               <persName>Babu</persName>, and a treasury of speech as <persName>Valgesh</persName>. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who in one has painted them!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>I, too, the offscouring of the flock, have not withholden aught that was meet: I
               have painted the similitude of these two, in the colours of these two; that the sheep
               may see their adornment, and the flock their beauties. And I who have become a lamb
               endowed with speech, unto Thee, O God of <persName>Abraham</persName>, in the posture of <persName>Abram</persName> will give
               Thee praise. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed be He Who has made me His harp!</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
