<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8774">Nisibis 41</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XLI"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XLI
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head><placeName>Nisibis</placeName> 41</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>The Evil One said, “I fear Him, even <persName>Jesus</persName>, lest He destroy my arts. For lo! I am
               thousands of years old, and never have I had repose. I have seen nothing established,
               that I have turned from and left. There has come One making the unchaste pure: there
               is sorrow since He has destroyed all that I had built. Many have been my labours and
               my teachings, that I might cover all creation with all evils. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who came and laid bare the wiles of the Crafty One!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>I matched my speed with the swift, and I outstripped them: I waged war; the tumult
               of multitudes was armour to me. In the tumult of the people I rejoiced, because it
               gave me ready room, for grievous is the onslaught of multitudes. By the strength of
               multitudes I raised a great mountain, a tower I stretched unto heaven. If they waged
               war with the Height, how much more shall they conquer Him whose warfare is on
               earth?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>As time serves and as help offers, I wage war, but cautiously. The people used to
               hear that God is one; they made for themselves a multitude of gods. And when they saw
               the Son of God, they made haste to the One God, that as though confessing God they
               might deny Him, and as though in zeal might flee from Him; so that they in all times
               perverse shall be found to be without God.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Lo! I am ancient of many years, and no infant have I ever rejected. The burden of
               children have I ofttimes borne, so that from the beginning I might make them acquire
               habits that are not goodly, that their faults might grow up with them. But there are
               foolish fathers, who do not crush the seed that I have sown in their sons; and there
               are some who like good husbandmen, root up faults from the mind of their
               children.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>As with a chain I have bound men with sloth, and they sat in idleness. I have drawn
               away their senses from all good things; their eyes from reading, their mouths from
               singing praise, their understanding from doctrine. For hurtful and vain fables how
               eager are they; for empty talk how ready! If the word of life fell among them, they
               either thrust it from them, or rose and went forth from its presence.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>How many <persName>Satans</persName> are there among men! and me even me alone every man curses. For lo!
               the anger of men—it is a devil that grinds him every day. Demons are like wayfarers,
               who depart if they are compelled: but against anger though all righteous men adjure,
               it is not rooted out from its place. Instead of pernicious envy, every one hates a
               weak and wretched demon.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>The enchanter is put to shame with the wizard, who every day tames serpents. The
               viper that is within him is out of his power; for the lust that is within him he
               tames not. Secret sin like an asp, when it breathes on him he is scorched. Even when
               he takes the viper through his cunning, delusion smites him secretly. He lulls the
               snake by his incantations: he wakens against himself mighty wrath by his
               incantations.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>I set my stings and I sat and waited: who is long-enduring as I with all? Beside the
               patient-spirited I sat, and step by step I bewitched him, so that he came unto
               despair. Him who was ashamed of his transgressions, habits subdued him: little by
               little I mastered him, till he became under the yoke, till he came in to it and was
               used to it and did not even wish to go forth.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>I perceived and saw that the long-enduring is he that can subdue all. At the time
               when I conquered <persName>Adam</persName>, he was but one. I left him till he had begotten children, and
               I sought for myself another task, for idleness is not to my taste. I counted the
               sands of the sea, that thereby I might make my spirit patient, and might prove my
               memory whether it would suffice, for the sons of men when they were multiplied.
               Before they were multiplied, I proved them in many things.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>The servants of the Evil One disputed with him, and they refuted his words with
               their rejoinder. <quote>But lo! <persName>Elisha</persName> brought the dead to life, and conquered death in the
               upper chamber, and brought to life the widow’s son. Lo! now is he in bondage in
               Sheol.</quote> But because the reasoning of the Evil One was very powerful, with their own
               words he refuted their words. <quote>How has <persName>Elisha</persName> been overcome? Lo! in <placeName>Sheol</placeName> he brought
               the dead to life by his bones.</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab><quote>If Elisha, who was of small power, was great in might in the midst of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>, and if
               so be he brought one dead to life therein, how many dead then will be raised therein,
               by the death of <persName>Jesus</persName> the mighty! Hence even from this consider ye, how much greater
               therefore is <persName>Jesus</persName>, than we my comrades. For lo! by His craftiness He deceived you,
               and ye sufficed not to determine His greatness when ye compared Him to the
               prophets</quote><!-- the quote has a beginning but no end -->.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab><quote>Your consolations are of small power,</quote> said the Evil One to them of his company.
               <quote>For He Who brought <persName>Lazarus</persName> to life though dead, how can Death suffice against Him?
               And if Death conquers Him, it is that He wills to be subdued unto him; and if so be
               He wills to be subdued, fear ye greatly, for He dies not in vain. He has wrought in
               us great terror, lest when dying He may enter in to raise <persName>Adam</persName> to life.</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Death looked forth from within his den, and marvelled when he saw our Lord
               crucified, and he said <quote>O raiser of the dead to life where art thou! Thou shalt be to
               me for meat, instead of the sweet Lazarus, whose savour lo! it is still in my mouth.
               <persName>Jairus</persName>’ daughter shall come and see this Thy cross. The widow’s son gazes on Thee. A
               tree caught <persName>Adam</persName> for me: blessed be the Cross which has caught for me the Son of
               <persName>David</persName>!</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Death opened his mouth and said, <quote>Hast Thou not heard, O Son of <persName>Mary</persName>, how <persName>Moses</persName> was
               great and excellent above all? became a God and wrought the works of God? slew the
               first-born and saved the first-born? turned aside the pestilence from the living? To
               the mount I went up with <persName>Moses</persName>, and He Whose glory be blessed gave him to me from
               hand to hand. For however great the son of <persName>Adam</persName> becomes, dust he is and to his dust
               returns, because he is of the ground.</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab><persName>Satan</persName> came with his servants, that he might see our Lord cast into <placeName>Sheol</placeName>, and might
               rejoice with Death his Counsellor; and he saw Him sorrowful and mourning, because of
               the dead who at the voice of the Firstborn, lived and came forth thence even from
               <placeName>Sheol</placeName>. The Evil One arose to console Death his kinsman. <quote>Thou hast not destroyed as
               much as thou wast able. Even as <persName>Jesus</persName> is in thy midst, to thy hand shall come they
               that have lived and that live.</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab><quote>Open for us to see Him, yea and mock Him: let us answer and say, <quote>‘Where is Thy
               power? For lo! three days have passed for Him, and let us say to Him, O Thou of three
               days, Who didst raise <persName>Lazarus</persName>, when he had lain four days, raise Thine own self.’</quote></quote>”
            Death opened the gates of Sheol, and there shone from it the splendour of the face of
               our Lord; and like the men of <placeName>Sodom</placeName> they were smitten; they groped and sought the
               gate of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>, which they had lost.</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
