<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8741">Nisibis 4</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_IV"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_IV
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 4</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>My God, without ceasing, I will tread the threshold of Thy house; I who have
               rejected all grace, I will ask with boldness, that I may receive with confidence.
            </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Our hope, be thou our Wall!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>For if, O Lord, the earth, enriches manifold, a single grain of wheat, how then
               shall my prayers, be enriched by Thy grace!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Because of the voices of my children, their sighs and their groans, open to me the
               door of Thy mercy! Make glad for their voices, the mourning of their sackcloth!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>O firstborn that wast a weaned child, and wast familiar with the children, the
               accurst sons of <placeName>Nazareth</placeName>, hearken to my lambs that have seen the wolves, for lo! they
               cry.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>For a flock, O my Lord, in the field, if so be it has seen the wolves, flees to the
               shepherd, and takes refuge under his staff, and he drives away them that would devour
               it.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Thy flock has seen the wolves, and lo! it cries loudly. Behold how terrified it is!
               Let thy Cross be a staff, to drive out them that would swallow it up!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>Accept the cry of my little ones, that are altogether pure. It was He, the Infant of
               days, that could appease, O Lord, the Ancient of days.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>The day when the Babe came down, in the midst of the stall, the Watchers descended
               and proclaimed, peace—may that peace be, in all my streets for all my offspring.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>Seventy and two old men, the elders of that people, sufficed not for its breaches.
               The Babe it was, the Son of <persName>Mary</persName>, that gave peace on every side.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>Have mercy, O Lord, on my children! in my children call to mind Thy childhood, Thou
               Who wast a child! Let them that are like Thy childhood, be saved by Thy grace!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Mingled in the midst of the flock, are the cry of the innocents, and the voice of
               the sheep, that call on the Shepherd of all, to deliver them from all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="lacuna">
            <ab>* * * * * * *</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>There is a joy that is affliction, misery is hidden in it; there is a misery that is
               profit, it is a fountain of joys, in that new world.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>The happiness that my persecutor has gained, woes are hidden in it; therefore I
               rejoice. The wretchedness that I have gained from him, happiness is concealed for me
               in it.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>Who will not give praise, to Him that has begotten us, and can beget again, from the
               midst of evil rumours the voices of glad tidings!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>Thou Healer of all, hast visited me in my sicknesses! Payment for Thy medicines, I
               cannot give Thee, for they are priceless.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>Thy mercies in richness, surpass Thy medicines: they cannot be bought, they are
               given freely, it is for tears they are bartered.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>How, O my Master, can a desolate city, whose king is far off, and her enemy nigh,
               stand firm without aid of mercy?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>A harbour and refuge, art Thou at all times. When the seas covered me, Thy mercy
               descended and drew me out. Again let Thy help lay hold on me!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>Apply to my afflictions, the medicine of Thy salvation, and the passion of Thy help!
               Thy sign can become, a medicine to heal all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>I am greatly oppressed, and I hasten to complain, against him that troubles me. Let
               Thy mercy, my Lord, take the bitterness from the cup, that my sins have mixed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>I look on all sides, and weep that I am desolate. Very many though be my chiefs and
               my deliverers, one is He that has delivered me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>My young men have fled, O Lord, and gone forth, and are like chickens, which an
               eagle pursues; lo! they hide in a secret place: may Thy peace bring them back!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>The sound of my grape-gatherers, lo! my ears miss it, for their voices fail. Let it
               resound with the glad tidings, O Blessed One of Thy salvation!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>A voice of terror, I have heard on my towers; as my defenders cry, while they guard
               my walls. Still Thou it with the voice of peace!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>The noise of my husbandmen, shall speak peace without my walls: the shouting of my
               dwellers shall speak peace within my walls, that I may give peace without and
               within.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>Make an end, O Lord, of the mourning, of this Thy pure altar, and of Thy chaste
               priest, who stands clothed in mourning, covered over with sackcloth!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <ab>The Church and her ministers shall give praise for Thy salvation; the city and its
               dwellers. Be the voice of peace, O Lord, the reward of their voices!</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
