<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8786">Nisibis 53</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LIII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LIII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 53</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Come, let us hear how they contend for victory: the guilty ones who never have
               conquered, nor will conquer.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Death said unto the Evil One: In the end the victory is mine: for Death is master of
               the close, as a conqueror.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Satan: This were to be Death indeed, wert thou able: to bring to death a living man,
               by means of lusts.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Death: Lo! I who behold the dead, both good and bad: the righteous who despise thee, O
               Evil One, me they despise not.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Satan: This dying of the body, is sleep for a time: think not, O Death, that thou art
               Death, who art as a shadow.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Death: Thee, O Evil One, the just have conquered, yea will conquer: but these that have
               conquered thee, lo! I conquer.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>Satan: Even this that thou bringest to death the just, is not of thyself: because of
               Adam whom I conquered, they drink this cup.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Death: Lo! Sheol is full of the men of Sodom, and the Assyrians: and the giants who were
               in the flood, who is like me?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>Satan: These, O Death, all of them, by me were slain: I am he that caused them to sin so
               that they perished.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>Death: Joseph who conquered thee I conquered, O Satan: in the chamber he conquered thee
               but I conquered, and cast him into the tomb.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Satan: Moses who conquered thee, O Death, by sprinkling of blood: he conquered thee in
               Egypt, but at the rock, who conquered him?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>Death: Elijah who feared thee not, O Satan: fled before Jezebel’s face, because he
               feared me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Satan: Aaron who withstood thee, O Death, with smoke of incense: to him I gave earrings
               of gold: and he fashioned a calf.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Death: Thou wentest down to contend with Job, and he conquered thee and came up: but I,
               after he had conquered thee, then conquered him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>Satan: David who by his sackcloth stayed that pestilence: him on the house-top I
               conquered, who had conquered Goliath.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>Death: Jehu who destroyed the house of Baal, the temple of the Evil One: was unable to
               destroy Sheol, the stronghold of my realm.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>Satan: Solomon who snatched from thy mouth, a child by his judgment: him in his old age
               I made a builder of idol-altars.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>Death: Samuel who in respect of gold scorned thee, O Satan: him I conquered, the
               conqueror, who conquered bribes.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>Satan: Samson who in respect of the lion’s whelp, scorned thee, O Death: through
               Delilah, frail vessel, I yoked him to the mill.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>Death: Josiah from his childhood despised thee, Evil One: but me not even in his old
               age, could he withstand.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>Satan: Hezekiah withstood thee, Death, when he overcame the bound of life: I misled him
               and he neglected the miracle, and showed his treasures.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>Death: John who conquered thee, Evil One, and absolved and baptized: I extinguished that
               torch, which had disclosed thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>Satan: Simon overcame thee, when he brought to life that blessed woman: in a woman he
               overcame thee and by a woman I overcame him and made him deny.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>Satan: Apostles and prophets with one voice, curse thee, O Death: “Where is the victory
               of Death, and the sting of Sheol?”</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>Thy Lord in Sheol thou hast shut up, O cursed servant: God hates thee and also man,
               hold then thy peace.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>Satan: It was the will of Him who gives life to all, that shut him in Sheol: it was thou
               that called Him to this, when thou madest Adam sin.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>O comrade of Nabal who in the wilderness reproached his lord: abhorred be thy mouth
               which said to Him, “Fall down and worship me!”</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
