<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8791">Nisibis 58</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LVIII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LVIII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 58</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Lo! Death was prompt beforehand, to mock Satan: him who was doomed to become a
               mockery at the last.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Response: Glory to Thee Who by Thy crucifixion, didst conquer the Evil One: and by Thy
               resurrection gain victory, likewise over Death!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>And for our Lord’s sake Death spake curses on him: who was the cause of His shame,
               and crucifixion.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Death: The fiery pit be thy grave, O Satan: who blasphemedst the Voice from the grave,
               that rent the graves</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>My Lord I know, and the Son of my Lord, O thou Satan! thou hast denied thy Lord, and
               crucified the Son of thy Lord.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>This is the name that fits thee, “Slayer of thy Lord”: when He appears Whom thou
               slewest, He shall slay thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>At thee shall every one shake the head, for by thee the chiefs: shook their heads at
               Him, the Lord of life.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>A bruised reed under the feet, of the just shalt thou be: for through thee they put a
               reed in His hand, Who upholds all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>With a crown of thorns was He crowned, to signify: that He took the diadem of the
               kingdom, of the house of David.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>With a crown of thorns was He crowned, the King of kings: but He took the diadem of
               the king, of those that shamed him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>In the robes of mockery that they gave him, in those He mocked them: for He took the
               raiment of glory, of priests and kings.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>To vinegar is thy memory akin, O thou Satan: who didst offer vinegar for the thirst,
               of the Fount of Life.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>The hand shall every man lift against thee who strengthenedst the hand that smote Him
               by Whose hand, all creatures stand.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>He was smitten by the hand and He cut off the hand, of Caiaphas: the hand of the
               priesthood is cut off, in the cutting off of the unction.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>On the pillar again they stretched Him, as for scourging: Him Whose pillar went
               before, to guide their tribes.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>The pillar on the pillar, He was scourged: He removed Himself from out of Zion, and
               its fall came.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>When they put two beams together, to form the Cross: He broke them, even the two
               staves, the guardians of them.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>Ezekiel put together the sticks, the two in one: in the two beams of the Cross, their
               staves have ceased.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>The two sticks, as it were wings, bore the people: lo! his two staves were broken,
               even as his wings.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>The bosom and wings of the Cross, He opened in mercy: its pinions bowed and bore the
               nations, to go to Eden.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>It is akin to the Tree of Life, and unto the son of its stock: it leads its beloved
               that on its boughs, they may feed on its fruits.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>Go howl and weep, Evil One, for me and for you: for not one of us shall enter the
               “Garden of Life.”</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>Death: Now that thou hast confessed O Death, come let me tell thee: that all this
               discourse of thine, to me is idle talk.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>I will go and watch the snares, which I have set: thou too, Death, fly and look
               after, all that are sick.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>Our Lord has brought both to nought, on either hand: the Evil One shall be brought to
               nought here, and Death hereafter there.</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
