<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8749">Nisibis 13</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XIII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XIII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 13</head>
         <head type="sub">Concerning Mar Jacob and his Companions.</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Three illustrious priests, after the manner of the two great lights,—have carried on
               and handed down one to another, the See and the Hand and the Flock.—To us whose
               mounting was great for the two, this last is wholly a consolation. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Glory to Thee Who didst choose them!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>He Who created two great lights, chose for Himself these three Lights,—and set them
               in the three dark seasons of siege that have been.—When that pair of Lights was
               quenched, the other shone wholly forth.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>These three priests were treasures, who held in their faithfulness,—the key of the
               Trinity; three doors they opened for us;—each one of them with his key, unlocked and
               opened his door.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>In the first was opened the door, for the chastisement that befel us;—in the next
               was opened the door, for the King’s power that came down on us,—in the last was
               opened the door, for the good tidings that came up for us.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>In the first was opened the door, for battle between two hosts;—in the next were
               opened doors, for the kings from either wind;—in the last was opened the door, for
               ambassadors from either side.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>In the first was opened the door, for battle because of misdeeds;—in the next was
               opened the door,—for the kings because of strife;—in the last was opened the door,
               for ambassadors because of mercies.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>Lo! in these three successions, as in a mystery and a figure,—wrath is likened to
               the sun; it began under the first;—it waxed strong under the next; it sank and was
               quenched under the last.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Three figures the Sun also, shows forth in the three quarters:—its rising is keen
               and bright; its meridian strong and overpowering;—and like a torch that is burnt out,
               its setting is mild and pleasant.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>Small yet bright is its rising, when it comes to waken sleepers;—hot and
               overpowering its meridian, when it comes to ripen the fruits;—tender and pleasant its
               setting, when it reaches its consummation.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>Who is this daughter born of vows, enviable above all women,—whose successions thus
               proceed, and her ranks are thus manifold,—and her degrees thus ascend, and her
               teachers thus excel.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Do these similitudes belong, only to the daughter of Abraham,—or to thee too, O
               daughter, born of vows, whose adorning is according as thy beauty?—for as thine
               occasion, so was thy help, and as thy help so was its minister.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>According to the measure of her need, there came to her the supply of her need.—Her
               fathers were as was her birth; her teachers were as was her understanding;—her
               training as was her growth; her raiment as was her stature.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Grace weighed out to her and gave all these things as in the scales;—she laid them
               in her balance, that therefrom there might be profit;—she drew them into succession,
               that therefrom might be perfection.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>In the days of him that was first, peace abounded and peace vanished;—in the days of
               him that was next, kings came down and kings went back;—but in the days of the last,
               hosts assailed and hosts retreated.—</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>By the first order came in, it came in with him and went out with him;—by the next
               the diadem that gladdened our churches, came nigh and withdrew far away;—but by the
               last there dawned on us, grace that was not thankfully received.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>Against the wrath that was first, the labour of the first contended;—against the
               heat that was at noon, the shade of the second stood up;—against peace that was
               thankless, the last multiplied warnings.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>For the first invader of the land was the first and illustrious priest;—for the
               second invader of the land, was the second and merciful priest:—but the prayers of
               him that was last, repaired our breaches secretly.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>Nisibis is set<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> upon waters, waters secret and
               open:—living streams are within her; a noble river without her. The river without
               deceived her; the fountain within has saved her.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>The first priest was her vinedresser; he made her branches to grow even unto
               heaven.—Lo! being dead and buried within her, he has become fruit in the midst of her
               bosom:—when therefore the pruners came, the fruit that was in her midst preserved
               her.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>The time of her pruning came; it entered and took from her her vinedresser,—that
               there should not be one to pray for her. She made haste in her subtlety;—He laid in
               her bosom her vinedresser, that she should be delivered through her vinedresser.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>Be ye wise like Nisibis, O ye daughters of Nisibis,—for that she laid the body
               within her, and it became a wall without her.—Place ye within you the living body,
               that it be a wall for your lives!</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1">The verb is nʾsab,—a play on the name of the city.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
