<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8796">Nisibis 63</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LXIII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LXIII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 63</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Who shall weigh the recompense of <persName>Abraham</persName>? whom I marvelled at when he bound, his
               only son.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Response: To thee be glory, Voice that bringest to life the dead in Sheol: and they have
               come up as preachers, of His Son Who quickens all!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>At that time I came forth in haste, to see the marvel: how that his knife was drawn
               out, against his beloved.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>I gathered my manifold memories, from all quarters: and I collected my spirit to
               marvel, at that illustrious one.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>How therefore can ye read, that great story? ye have despised the reading of it, in
               your very ears.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>The sword of <persName>Jephthah</persName> rebukes, him that laments: his daughter was to him a mirror of
               life from the dead.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>She gave herself for her father, so commend ye: your life to the Father of all, in
               the hope of your end.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>In the womb then did ye not make trial, of a mystery of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>? yet in <placeName>Sheol</placeName> ye had
               more rest, than in the womb.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>It is stubborn in you to stand up against, my mighty will: for lo! to succour them I
               take away, your departed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>By the king of <placeName>Moab</placeName> who slew, his son with his hands: he is put to shame who laments,
               for the departed one.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>He was a profane man, lo! according, to what you read: but ye are doctors and
               teachers, as ye suppose.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>He endured, but ye are furious, in your mourning: against the will of the Lord of
               all, while ye are weeping.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>I fear however to let pass, the story of <persName>Job</persName>: through this feeble mouth of mine, for
               I am unworthy.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>So in like manner I turn aside, from mention of their bones: though I praise Him who
               granted, that they should come to me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>Dishonour not your members, by your sins: for in <placeName>Sheol</placeName> the bones are despised, of
               evildoers.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>Whenever I see the body of one of the evil: I trample on it and curse, even his
               memory.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>But wherever I see a bone, of one of the just; I set it apart and honour it, and do
               it worship.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>Ye feeble ones understand not, all my ordinances: with you orders are confused, for
               ye are blind.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>It is <persName>Moses</persName> alone that I know, to have honoured like me: the bones of that <persName>Joseph</persName>
               whom I magnify.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>But <persName>Moses</persName> did such honour, to one pure body: but I to the body and the bones, of all
               the righteous.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>Brightly shine the bones of Prophets, and of Apostles: a lamp to me in darkness, are
               all the righteous.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>I worship Him Who lightens for me, the darkness of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>: the splendour of <persName>Moses</persName> who
               was so great, was as the sun to me.</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
