<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8792">Nisibis 59</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LIX"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LIX
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 59</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Lo! Death for us on Satan, inflicts vengeance: come let us hear his shame and
               rejoice, for he rejoiced in our shame.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Response: To Thee be glory from Thy flock, from Thee: are subdued both Death and Satan,
               under Thy Feet!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Death: Evil ones shall be hung upright, but thou, head downward: for, reversely, thou
               crucifiedst, Simon on the tree.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Satan: Touching all else I am silent, Death, for my time wanes: Simon himself conjured
               me, “Crucify me thus.”</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Were it the just that cursed me, I had not grieved: the curse of Death unto me, is
               worse than hell.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Death: The shame of our Lord I have not spoken of, it is too great for my mouth: that I
               should weigh and compare His Passion, with Thy torment.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>Twelve judgment thrones shall He set, for His Twelve: for by the twelve tribes thou,
               even thou, shall be condemned.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>A halter unbought shalt thou hang thee, O thou Satan: as that Thy disciple hung him,
               a halter for a price.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>Haply yon hell in mercy, shall be emptied: and thou shalt dwell there alone, with Thy
               ministers.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>Manifold are Thy curses, and how shall I count them? Lo! the sum of all thy curses,
               is on thy members.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>The evil in the fire shall stab thee, who madest them evil: they shall upbraid thee
               “wherefore, broughtest thou us hither?”</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>Sinners shall rail against thee, and haply their threats: shall be worse to thee than
               the torment, of yonder hell.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>These shall be unto thee there, all of them Satans: as thou hast been to them here,
               the one Satan.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>The Watchers shall seize and hurl thee down, calling to mind: how through thee men
               hurled their Lord, from the height to the depth.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>All men will run to stone thee, not forgetting that through thee the maddened people
               ran, to stone their Maker.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>On thee, Evil One, from all mouths shall be, the spitting of wrath: for through thee
               they spat on Him Whose spittle, gave sight to the blind.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>On thee, Evil One, from all tongues, shall be all curses: for through thee men
               blasphemed Him, Who opened dumb mouths.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>Blessed is He Who avenged our wrong, though in silence: and stirred up Death against
               the Evil One, to fall upon him!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>Sound we Hosannas, my brethren, as did Gideon:<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#n1"/> who when he sounded, the
               oppressors, fell on one another!</ab>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note xml:id="n1"></note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
