<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8771">Nisibis 38</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XXXVIII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XXXVIII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head><placeName>Nisibis</placeName> 38</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>My throne was set for me in <placeName>Sheol</placeName>: and one arose that was dead, and hurled me from
               it. Every man feared me alone, and I feared no man. Terror and trouble were among the
               living, rest and peace among the dead. In a man that was slain lo! there has entered
               into <placeName>Sheol</placeName> He that takes her captive. I used to take all men captive: the Son of
               Captivity Whom I took captive has taken me captive. He Whom I took captive has led
               her away and is gone to Paradise. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who has quickened the dead of <placeName>Sheol</placeName> by His Cross!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>All men complain much against me; and I against one only have complained. Who is
               there among men so just as I? Has corruption touched my integrity? I held all men in
               affection, and whoso hates me knows it; I know not all my days what a bribe is. The
               person of a king have I not accepted. By me is preached equality, for bondman and his
               lord in <placeName>Sheol</placeName> I make equal.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Before God it is that I minister, with Whom is no acceptance of persons. What other
               is there that endures as I do, I that am cursed when I do good? Perversely are
               requited to me the benefits I have rendered. Though my deeds are goodly, my name is
               not goodly. Yet my mind rests in its integrity: in God it is that I comfort myself;
               for though He is good He is denied every day and endures it.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>The old I remove from all sufferings, likewise the young from all sins. Secret
               contention I quell in <placeName>Sheol</placeName>; in our land there is no iniquity: it is <placeName>Sheol</placeName> and Heaven
               alone, that are removed from all sins; this earth that lies between, in her iniquity
               dwells. He therefore that is prudent will either go up into Heaven, or, if that be
               too hard, will go down to Sheol which is easy.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>To one man because of one that is dead, every man hastes to comfort him. But for me
               though many of my dead have come to life, there is none that comes in and comforts
               me. <persName>Satan</persName> came in, against Whom, had been proclaimed seven woes even against him;
               though mightily the Son of <persName>Mary</persName> had trodden on him, yet uplifted is his spirit; for
               he is the serpent that strives though bruised. Better is it for me to fall and
               worship, before this <persName>Jesus</persName> Who has conquered me by His Cross.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>When He enters at the gate of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>, in place of <persName>John</persName> who preached before His
               coming, then will I cry “Lo! He that quickens the dead is come; Thy servant am I from
               henceforth, <persName>Jesu</persName>! Because of The Body I reviled Thee, for it covered Thy Godhead. Be
               not angry, O Son of the King, against Thy treasury; at Thy command I have opened and
               closed. Though my wings be very swift it is at thy nod I haste to every quarter.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>All that have been raised were not first born; for our Lord is the First-born of
               <placeName>Sheol</placeName>. How can any that is dead go before Him, that power whereby he was raised?
               There are last that are first, and younger that have become first-born. For though
               <persName>Manasseh</persName> was first-born, how could it be that <persName>Ephraim</persName> should take the birthright? And
               if the second born was set before him, how much rather shall the Lord and Creator
               prevent all in His Resurrection!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Lo! <persName>John</persName> as a herald declares that he is later, though he was elder-born; for he
               said, “Behold a man cometh after me, and yet He was before me.” For how could he be
               before Him, that Power in Whom he preached? For everything that comes to pass because
               of another thing, is after that other even though it seem to be before. For the cause
               which called it into being, is elder than it and before it in all things.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>The cause of <persName>Adam</persName> was elder than all creatures, which were made for him, for to him
               even to <persName>Adam</persName> He had respect continually, the Creator even while he was creating. Thus
               though <persName>Adam</persName> as yet was not, he was elder than all creatures. How much more then, my
               Lord, must this Thy manhood be elder, which in Thy Godhead is, from eternity with Him
               that begat Thee! To Thee be praise and through Thee to Thy Father from us all!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>To Thee be praise for Thou art the first, in Thy Godhead and in Thy manhood! For
               even though <persName>Elijah</persName> was first to go up, he was not able to prevent Him, for whose sake
               he was taken up. For his type depended on Thy verity: and even though the types
               apparently are before Thy fulfilment, it is before them secretly. Creatures were
               before Adam; he was before them because for his sake they were made.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>O my Lord, work for me this resurrection, not of Thy compulsion but of Thy love. For
               Thy compulsion gives life to sinners also: <persName>Iscariot</persName> would rather again choose for
               himself the death of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>, than the life of <persName>Gehenna</persName>. Work for me then the
               resurrection that is of Thy mercy; and even though Thy justice permits not, let there
               be occasion for Thy grace. This only let it remember for me, that in it I have sought
               refuge.</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
