<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8788">Nisibis 55</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LV"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LV
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 55</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Lo! the Evil One reproached Death, and was in turn reproached: from each and to each
               and against each, were their taunts.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Response: To Thee be glory, Son of the Lord of All, Who diedst for all: for He was raised
               to give life to all, in the day of His Coming!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Satan: Jonah who conquered thee, and returned back from Sheol, became my advocate in
               asking, why sinners were spared?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Death: Slander not, O Evil One, the son of Amittai: he showed a face of anger, that they
               might praise thee more.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Satan: Quite powerless is all thy persuasion, O tyrant Death: for there pleases me
               nothing, of all thou hast said.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Death: For when was the word of truth pleasing to thee? A gulf is between thee and
               truthfulness, O lying one.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>I am righteous all my days, with nought to repent: I am he that rescues from thee the
               sons of men.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Satan: Proclaim thy repentance, Death, thou art well come: lo! Saul also among the
               prophets, great cause of scorn.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>If thou, Death, be justified, then for myself: I cut not off hope, likewise, of
               repentance.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>Death: No idol with my Lord have I made, O hater of thy Lord! lo! thou by dead idols,
               slayest the living.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Satan: That thou, Death, art half of me, I know, and I half of thee: if half of me
               repents, it repents, but I marvel.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>Death: Thy partner am I in share, but not in sin: mine are the slain and thine the
               slayers, whom thou madest sin.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Satan: My craftiness weeps for itself, when I dispute with thee: my wiles mourn over me,
               when I meet thee.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Death: Workers of witchcraft and soothsayers, with all their offences: the fire that
               thou kindledst in the world, in Sheol I have quenched.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>Satan: Thou penitent who strainest out gnats, and swallowest the just: the chaste shall
               rend thee, who cry, from within thy belly.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>Death: It is the treasure-house where I keep all the righteous: their resurrection
               threatens ill to thee, who didst persecute them.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>Satan: The greedy one who carries all creatures, in his bowels: lo! he casts up to me
               that I am robbed, of my possessions.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>Death: Before the stroke lament not, for it has not yet reached thee: the day will come
               when thou shalt cry out, and I shall hear and rejoice.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>The fire will come that shall strip off thee thy very skin: as by the potsherd thou
               didst strip the skin of Job.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>Death: The savour of sloth begins, as if to hover on me; it is then a dream that I
               ceased, for a short space.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>It was not that words failed me, and therefore I was silent: it is for the time I
               grieve, that has passed idly.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>The hurt done by thy speech is very great: would I had not heard it! For my whole
               mind is intent upon my work.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>This humankind that is lost, was undone by wandering thought: slothfulness, with
               negligence, brought it under yoke.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>The madness of desire bid for wealth, and bought it: contention with boastfulness,
               were the sureties.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>With persistence for strength, I wage my war: and if I neglect but a little, my sway
               is naught.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>By continual dropping, I clean the rocks: for continual dropping can dissolve even a
               mountain.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>Habit even over nature, becomes master: it trains and leads even lions, as beasts of
               burden.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <ab>Habit, repose, and increase, with persistence; by these is freedom conquered, though
               stubborn above all.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="29">
            <ab>If its will be firmly set, it breaks the fetters; but if lax, a fragile net, can
               capture it.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="30">
            <ab>If so be that Freedom shouts, we are scattered: but if she be silent we gather
               together, to mock at her.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="31">
            <ab>Let us cease from much speaking, lest it lead to much sloth: with one mind let us
               assail the wall, and lo! it is broken down.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="32">
            <ab>Satan: Go thou and see to diseases, and I to snares: for to me sins and to thee
               pestilences, are great solace.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="33">
            <ab>And even though I have paused, I have not paused from my cares: for my will at no
               time rests, but is ready.</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
