<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8794">Nisibis 61</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LXI"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LXI
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 61</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>In wisdom let us hearken to Death, O my beloved: how he accuses us for our weeping,
               and for our mourning.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Response: To thee be praise Who cameth down, to follow Adam: and foundest Adam and also in
               the children of Adam.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>And rightly perhaps he says, <quote>Ye slay: without mercy and lo! ye weep, as though
               merciful.</quote></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Ye have made me as a cruel one, O ye murderers: for ye slay one another, without my
               help!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>While Death was but desiring to come, the sword came before him: let us see then
               against whom cries out, the blood of the slain.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Against you cry out the strangled, who were suffocated: for it shames me of the rope,
               of their strangulations.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>They take away from me even my rest, for without me: how could the strangled and the
               slain, enter Sheol?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Lo! your infants are cast out, as those in Egypt: your sons have ye sacrificed to
               demons, O demoniacs!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>While Death was but desiring to taste, of your corpses: Cain refreshed me beforehand,
               with blood of man.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>While I was but desiring to wait patiently, till Adam should die: before I had power
               ye gave me power, over your bodies.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Cain with his sword overthrew, the gate of Sheol: for it was closed and before the
               time, he first opened it.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>He by treading made the way of Sheol, without my help: for in the way ye have trodden
               out for me, lo! I walk therein.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Nine hundred years I sat and waited, for Adam to die: but Cain not even a day,
               endured his brother.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Robbers upon the highways, are worse than I: I am slumbering while they, are watching
               to slay.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>Lo! your slaughtered in the graves, and your murdered in your ways; and your
               strangled upon your stakes!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab><quote>If I rebelled against my lord, yea and slew him: who was he that slew these here,</quote>
               said Jehu.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>And if I Death have taken, your departed: the strangled, the slain, and the
               slaughtered, who was it slew them?</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>Ye are Satan to each other, and the Evil One is abhorred: ye are pestilence to each
               other, and Death is blamed!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>Your own will to you is Satan, yea and a murderer: but of Death and of Satan, all men
               complain.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>Poison of Death ye give also to drink, each to other: lo! how many Deaths have ye,
               beside me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>Wiles, stratagems, yea and snares, sword and poison: how many Deaths from you and in
               you, lo! are there born.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>The judge in the judgment-hall, is a second Death: he slays for secret reward, but I
               for naught.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>I have seen bribery and marvelled at it, that ran and outran me: how many slain does
               bribery, slay, and none perceives!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>I am ashamed that so unskilfully, I conduct myself: if I take even one corpse, all
               men perceive it.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>In the houses weeping and in the streets, also wailing: and even unto the gates of
               Sheol, they groan over me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>Groan over yourselves that ye are thus hateful, and ye hate me: Sheol henceforth
               shall groan over you, O murderers!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>With torture, scourging and fire, yea with stoning: ye put to death the sons of men,
               and ye are proud!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <ab>I am more modest than you and merciful, also reverent: for with reverence I bear
               away, your departed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="29">
            <ab>On the bed I deal gently, with him that is sick: and quietly I lay him to sleep, for
               but a while.</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
