<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8772">Nisibis 39</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XXXIX"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XXXIX
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head><placeName>Nisibis</placeName> 39</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>There have come to me ransomers from among the saints, but none has plundered me
               like the Son of <persName>Mary</persName>. For lo! <persName>Elijah</persName> brought a dead man to life; and even though he
               himself escaped from my hands, yet had I consolation after him, for the dead man whom
               he quickened, I carried off from him. By <persName>Elisha</persName> son of <persName>Shaphat</persName>, I was beaten as with
               rods, for he brought two dead men to life. By one staff I in turn bore away both the
               prophet and the dead whom he had raised. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is He Who cleft the tombs of <placeName>Sheol</placeName> by His voice!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>I feared him even <persName>Gehazi</persName> when I saw, him lay the staff upon the youth. The thief
               took the staff away and returned; <persName>Elisha</persName> came and bowed himself; laid himself low as
               the child and raised himself up, and walked hither and thither. I marvelled at the
               new mysteries which I saw there, which restored but one youth to life. It was well
               with me then when those were but mysteries, and not now when the dead have rebelled
               and conquered me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Moses when I saw the mighty splendour upon his face, I feared him: yet not according
               to what I feared befel it me. <persName>Nisan</persName> in <placeName>Sheol</placeName> he caused to spring for me; for a
               pasture, a pasture of corpses, of six hundred thousand fell.—This lowly and despised
               whom I contemned, has healed the sick and the diseased: to others He has multiplied
               bread, but our bread even ours from our mouths He snatches.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>A mighty feast there was in Sheol, when I swallowed up <persName>Korah</persName> and his company. A
               great delight <persName>Satan</persName> made for me, when he made strife among the Levites. A fount of
               milk and honey, made he flow for me in a dry place, when the congregation of
               transgressors went down to <placeName>Sheol</placeName>.—Lo! the righteous have lived and come forth: <persName>Moses</persName>
               sent down the living thither, but <persName>Jesus</persName> has revived and brought up the dead.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>It was well with me then, in the day of the zealous, those in whose swords I had
               delight. <persName>Phinehas</persName> the zealous pierced and gave me, on the head of his spear for my
               delight, <persName>Zimri</persName> and <persName>Cozbi</persName> both together; on the head of his lance he presented them to
               me. To whom then were there ever two fatted oxen, offered on the head of a spear?—But
               instead of <persName>Cozbi</persName>, daughter of princes, the daughter of <persName>Jairus</persName> has <persName>Jesus</persName> rescued from
               my hands.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>The censer of <persName>Aaron</persName> caused me to fear, for he stood between the dead and the living
               and conquered me. The Cross causes me to fear more exceedingly, which has rent open
               the graves of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>. The Crucified Whom on it I slew, now by Him am I slain. Not very
               great is his reproach, who is overcome by a warrior in arms. Worse to me is my
               reproach than my torment, in that by a crucified man my strength has been
               overcome.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>The lance of <persName>Phinehas</persName> again has caused me to fear, for by the slaughter he wrought
               with it he hindered the pestilence. The lance guarded the tree of life, it made me
               glad and made me sad; it hindered <persName>Adam</persName> from life, and it hindered death from the
               people. But the lance that pierced <persName>Jesus</persName>, by it I have suffered; He is pierced and I
               groan. There came out from Him water and blood; <persName>Adam</persName> washed and lived and returned to
               Paradise.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>The Sadducees were as a mouth for me, and disputed with Him after my mind, that
               there is no rising of the dead at all. <persName>Jesus</persName> answered them in a saying, which I alone
               understood; He spake aloud the hateful word and saddened me, “I am the God of him
               even of <persName>Abraham</persName>, and God is not the God of the dead.” It was well with me then these
               were but words, and He had not yet showed me the life of the dead indeed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab><persName>Jesus</persName> son of Nun, slew thirty kings, and filled the graves and pits for me; he laid
               waste <placeName>Jericho</placeName> and filled <placeName>Sheol</placeName>. But this <persName>Jesus</persName> who is come, has wasted the graves of
               their dead, and has filled the cities of the upper world. Wherefore thus when lo!
               they are like in their names, are they unlike in their doings? That gave me the body
               of <persName>Achor</persName>, but this snatched from me the body of <persName>Lazarus</persName>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab><persName>Moses</persName> trod down that Egyptian, with his meekness he mingled justice. Whence has this
               new law sprung for me, <quote>If one smite thee on thy cheek, turn to him thy other cheek,
               and see that thou hate him not?</quote> Instead of the strong man of zeal who trod down and
               slew, a new man of mercy has risen for us. <persName>Samuel</persName> hewed <persName>Agag</persName> in pieces, but <persName>Jesus</persName>
               healed the paralytic.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Tender mercy which had as it were waxed less, lo! in this time has waxed great. And
               moreover it was then detested, lest through it one should transgress the commandment;
               for without mercy <persName>Saul</persName> and <persName>Ahab</persName>, were slain because they desired, to have mercy on
               the evil ones, and they were not slain who were deserving of punishment. In my time
               <persName>Jesus</persName> has changed this, by giving life to all men and having compassion on His
               slayers.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>I remember <persName>Samson</persName> that lion’s whelp, who brake and gave me the pillars of <placeName>Philistia</placeName>;
               also that mighty man of valor <persName>Abner</persName> son of <persName>Ner</persName>, took for me that fleet wild roe,
               <persName>Asahel</persName> son of <persName>Zeruiah</persName>, and smote him and cast him on the ground. <persName>Benaiah</persName> in the holy
               temple slew <persName>Jacob</persName>, justly as it is written.—Because justice has restrained her sword,
               henceforth penitents shall rejoice in grace.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab><persName>David</persName> measured the Edomites, by line and line and destroyed them. How merciful then
               art Thou, O Son of <persName>David</persName>! <persName>David</persName>’s justice was twofold, when he put to death two
               lines, and saved one full line alive.—Lo! the Son of <persName>David</persName> teaches us, <quote>Forgive thy
               brother even unto seventy times seven.</quote> There justice was measured; but here clemency
               is without measure.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Of zeal and strength <persName>David</persName> was possessed; the lion and the bear he slew together. He
               left that mighty lion and hasted, to meet the strong giant. With a stone he quenched
               his light, and his soul left him and he perished. But <persName>Jesus</persName> cried to the young man
               that was dead <quote>Young man!</quote> Even the dead to Him are sleepers. That young man He
               brought to life and rescued from me. The despised swine He drowned for me in the
               sea.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>The Levites slew because of the calf, their fathers and their brethren. <persName>Jephthah</persName> by
               his own hands was ready to slay his daughter. The King of <placeName>Moab</placeName> on the wall, was
               sacrificing his first-born son: In presence of his sword I rejoice.—By <persName>Jesus</persName> the
               sword was blunted; yea the fever was rebuked, the sister of <placeName>Sheol</placeName>: the mother-in-law
               of <persName>Simeon</persName> was healed, but the fame of her healing smote <placeName>Sheol</placeName> with pain.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>This <persName>Jesus</persName> though he be the Son of the Just One, all that He preaches is grace. But
               to me this His grace is torment. Envy is the cause of pleasure to us, for Envy at the
               beginning mixed for me the first shedding of blood. Why is it guilty in the sight of
               the Son of <persName>Mary</persName> Who is come commanding, <quote>Thou shalt not be angry against thy
               brother?</quote> He has taken away the sword from between brethren; while in the sword of
               <persName>Cain</persName> I had pleasure from the beginning.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>An honeycomb in the midst of the skeleton, <persName>Samson</persName> found—was it then a mystery? This
               <persName>Jesus</persName> has multiplied for us mysteries. Amid billows of mysteries have I fallen, which
               show me in parable the life of the dead, in all mysteries and in all types. <quote>Out of
               the eater came forth meat</quote> was <persName>Samson</persName>’s parable. But to me it has befallen
               contrariwise; for the eater has come forth to me out of the meat, for out of <persName>Adam</persName> lo!
               has come the Son of <persName>Adam</persName> Who has destroyed me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>Just men likewise have robbed me manifold, when by them was preached the rising of
               the dead: but they mingled with my sorrows great consolation. By the prayer of <persName>Asa</persName>
               and <persName>Hezekiah</persName>, I was fed upon the dead, yea I feasted upon corpses. <persName>Elijah</persName> slew the
               prophets of <persName>Baal</persName> and gave them to me, who on the bread of <persName>Jezebel</persName> had waxed fat. The
               righteous has constrained me to devour, but <persName>Jesus</persName> has compelled me to disgorge all
               that I had eaten.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>I was afraid because of the sprinkled blood, which <persName>Moses</persName> sprinkled on every door;
               for though the blood of the slain, it was that which saved the living. Blood from of
               old I feared not, save that blood that was on the doors, and this moreover that was
               on the Tree. The blood of the slain is a delight, and is as sweet perfume: but the
               blood of <persName>Jesus</persName> is to me a terror; for whenever I come and smell His blood, the savour
               of life that lurks therein terrifies me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>Priests and pontiffs, anointed men and kings, who foreshow types of the rising of
               the dead, have never triumphed through their crosses. Crowns and diadems were set on
               them; and when I engaged in struggles with them, I was smitten sometimes and
               sometimes also I smote. But this carpenter’s son with his crown of thorns, has
               humbled and cast down my pride, in His shame and His dying: <placeName>Sheol</placeName> has seen Him, yea,
               and fled from before Him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>When the sea saw <persName>Moses</persName> and fled, it feared because of his rod, and likewise because
               of his glory. His splendour and his rod and his power, the rock also saw which was
               cleft. But <placeName>Sheol</placeName> when her graves were rent, what saw she in Him even in
               <persName>Jesus</persName>?—Instead of splendour He put on the paleness of the dead and made her tremble.
               And if His paleness when slain slew her, how shall she be able to endure, when He
               comes to raise the dead, in His Glory!</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
