<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8775">Nisibis 42</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XLII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_XLII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head><placeName>Nisibis</placeName> 42</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>The Evil One wailed <quote>“Where now, is there a place for me to flee to from the
               righteous? I stirred up Death to slay the Apostles, that I might be safe from their
               blows. By their deaths now more exceedingly am I cruelly beaten. The Apostle whom I
               slew in India is before me in <placeName>Edessa</placeName>: he is here wholly and also there. I went there,
               there was he: here and there I have found him and been grieved.”</quote> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: Blessed is the might that dwells in the hallowed bones!<ptr type="noteAnchor" target="#1"/></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>The bones that merchantmen carried, or was it then that they carried him? For lo!
               they made gain each of the other. But for me what did they profit me? yea they
               profited each by each, while to me from both of them there was damage. O that one
               would show me that bag of <persName>Iscariot</persName>, for by it I acquired strength! The bag of <persName>Thomas</persName>
               has slain me, for the secret strength that dwells in it tortures me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab><persName>Moses</persName> the chosen carried the bones, in faith as for gain. And if he a great prophet
               believed, that there is benefit in bones, the merchant did well to believe, and did
               well to call himself merchant. That merchant made gain, and waxed great and reigned.
               His storehouse has made me very poor: his storehouse has been opened in <placeName>Edessa</placeName>, and
               has enriched the great city with benefit.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>At this storehouse of treasure I was amazed, for small was its treasure at first;
               and though no man took from it, poor was the spring of its wealth. But when
               multitudes have come round it, and plundered it and carried off its riches, according
               as it is plundered, so much the more does its wealth increase. For a pent-up spring,
               if one seeks it out, when deeply pierced it flows forth mightily and abounds.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>It is evident that <persName>Elisha</persName> was a fountain in a thirsting people: and because they
               that thirsted sought him not out, his outflow was not great. But when <persName>Naaman</persName> sought
               him out, he abounded and poured forth healing. The fountain into the midst of a
               fountain, he took him and plunged him; for in the river he cleansed the leper. <persName>Jesus</persName>
               the Sea of benefits, into <!-- Is Siloam a place? -->Siloam sent the blind man whose eyes were opened.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab><persName>Gehazi</persName>, with the staff that brought to life the dead, was unable to raise the child.
               And how could the famous prophet have been brought up by the sorceress? We were they
               that mocked <persName>Saul</persName>, for instead of one demon whom he questioned, two demons came up and
               mocked him. From the bones of <persName>Elisha</persName> learn also of the bones of <persName>Samuel</persName>; for though
               <persName>Elisha</persName>’s bones brought to life the dead, the sorcerers could not bring up the dead,
               the living and sacred bones.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>And though I asked this petition, He who gives all gave it not to me. For though the
               demons were troubled, by the bones of some priest, or magician or wizard, of <placeName>Chaldean</placeName>
               or soothsayer, yet I was aware that this was but mockery. In two ways I cause men to
               err: either I make the Apostles to lie, or I make my Apostles like the Apostles.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>The party of the demons lo! it is spoiled; the party of the devils endures stripes:
               though there be none that lifts the rod openly, the demons cry out with pain; though
               there be none that fetters and binds, the spirits hang bound. This silent judgment,
               which is calm and still, and works not even by questioning, the one power that is all
               sufficing, lo! it dwells in the bones of this second <persName>Elisha</persName>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>He gave judgment unto His Twelve, that they might judge the twelve Tribes. And if so
               be that they are to judge the sons of the great <persName>Abraham</persName>, this is then no great
               matter, that they shall judge demons now. And unless they make the crucifiers fulfil
               the judgment that is to be, by our judgment shall they be proved. For worse than we
               did they cry out, in presence of the Apostles the judges of the tribes.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>For a wolf was <persName>Saul</persName> the Apostle, and on the blood of the sheep I reared him; and he
               waxed strong and became a singular wolf. But nigh to <placeName>Damascus</placeName> suddenly, the wolf was
               changed into a sheep. He said that the Apostles, are to judge Angels; for by the
               Angels he signified the priest as it is written. If so be then they are thus
               powerful, woe to the demons from the strokes of their bones!</ab>
         </div> <note xml:id="n1">[The bones of St. Thomas were reputed to have been brought to Edessa by a merchant from India.]</note> 
     </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
