<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8744">Nisibis 7</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_VII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_VII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 7</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Wrath came to rebuke, the greedy who in the midst of peace, bargained, defrauded and
               plundered. In calamity the greedy have waxed rich: lo! what was theirs they have
               scattered, what was not theirs they have gathered. </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="response">
            <ab>Response: Give peace, O Son, to our land!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab>Twenty years my troubles, have been like branches, O my Saviour! which are kept back
               throughout winter, but when it is time to shoot forth, my troubles shoot forth: with
               our fruit our heart ripens.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Nisan is the time of buds: in it the ill tidings budded. When our delights crowded
               on us, then crowded on us our ills. At the time of winnowing of wheat, came the
               winnowing of cities,</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>For the three brethren in Babylon fled not from the fire that men kindled, because
               they were steadfast: from lust they fled, because they were perfect.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>The fire of them that have triumphed, is able to turn the black kids into white: the
               fire of vain men is able to make the lambs into spotted leopards.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>How great will be my cries, to be cried at any alarm! How great my indignation to
               ripen at every ill tidings! How great my harvests, to perish every mouth!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>For the crimes of my sons He has chastened me, in their struggling for my
               deliverance. The people who deliver me, bring chastisement upon me. Restrain ye your
               sins, and lo! my chastisements are restrained!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>In ill tidings they are afflicted; in time of wrath they are tortured; in time of
               peace they are distressed; for when every man breathes freely, and all are unthankful
               for grace, they render thanks on behalf of every man.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>Their sackcloth is humble for my sake; their ashes are sprinkled in my affliction;
               their prayer is for my victory; their fast for my deliverance: Lo! the debt is on my
               ascetics, the guilt with my nobles.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>Great is in every age, the folly of the wise; the scribes and elders envied and
               killed the teacher, who taught all people the Law of Moses.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Wisdom in this age is a possession that brings loss: he who has a little folly, very
               small is his guilt; but he who has a little prudence, his iniquity passes
               measure.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>They build with their words, and overthrow in their deeds; for the teachers were
               many and foolish, but the mouth of the judge is both of these things, the judge and
               the accuser.</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
