<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="a" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8790">Nisibis 57</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" level="s" ref="http://syriaca.org/work/8737"> Hymns on Nisibis -
                  <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܰܢܩܺܝܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܕܪ̈ܳܫܶܐ ܕܰܢܨܺܝܒܺܝܢ ܕܣܺܝܡܺܝܢ ܠܛܽܘܒܳܢܳܐ ܡܳܪܝ̱
                  ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>
            </title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem the Syrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>NPNF: Series II, Vol. XIII -- Translation in the public domain.</p>
            <p>Transcription of the text downloaded from Wikisource on 9/15/2024: <ref
                  target="https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LVII"
                  >
                  https://en.m.wikisource.org/wiki/Nicene_and_Post-Nicene_Fathers:_Series_II/Volume_XIII/Ephraim_the_Syrian_and_Aphrahat/Nisibene_Hymns/Hymn_LVII
               </ref>. This Wikisource transcription is available under a <ref
                  target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons
                  Attribution-ShareAlike License</ref></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Nisibis 57</head>
         <div type="section" n="1">
            <ab>Listen, my brethren, to Death, mocking the Evil One: that caused the head of our
               race to sin, and its mother.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="2">
            <ab/>
         </div>
         <div type="resopnse">
            <ab>Response: To Thee be glory that by Thy humiliation, Satan is subdued: and that Thy
               abasement has exalted Adam, who was abased.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="3">
            <ab>Death: Thy great nakedness shall be seen, by the sons of Adam; as thou mockedst his
               nakedness, when thou madest him sin.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="4">
            <ab>Eve will cease from that serpent, and rail at thee: for thou, O Dragon, wast he that
               beguiled her simpleness.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="5">
            <ab>Abel will see him, even, Cain, who has come to thee: the disciple of his wrath will
               blame his cursed master.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="6">
            <ab>Satan: Noah who conquered the flood, as it were death: by the mouth of Ham I laughed
               at, when wine overcame him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="7">
            <ab>Death: Noah was not harmed, but thy garment, wherewith thou clothedst him: even
               cursings, he put on, and became a slave.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="8">
            <ab>Satan: Lot who overcame anger which is, thy likeness, Death: to his daughters I gave
               such counsels, as were pleasing to me.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="9">
            <ab>Death: And Lot’s wife who was thy vessel hearkened, to thy counsel: may half of thee be
               dried up, as thy whole vessel was dried up!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="10">
            <ab>Gehenna be overturned, upon thy head: as thy malice overturned Sodom, its
               dwellers!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="11">
            <ab>Floods of fire be stirred against thee, in the resurrection: who against Moses and
               Elijah, didst stir the people!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="12">
            <ab>Let the just mock thee at the last, and Joseph rejoice! whose brethren mocked him,
               set on by thee!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="13">
            <ab>Let vapour of smoke come in, and choke thy senses: as the waters of the sea choked,
               the senses of the wicked! </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="14">
            <ab>Let chaste women also mock thee, by whose counsel: the daughters of Midian mocked,
               the foolish people!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="15">
            <ab>Flame be kindled on thy head, for Samson’s sake: for by a woman thou shavedst his
               locks, that lion of strength!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="16">
            <ab>Satan: Saul whom I conquered by envy, by witchcraft conquered thee: for he asked for
               and brought up Samuel, out of his grave.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="17">
            <ab>Death: Slander not the living dead, for he came not up: thou wast he that came up in
               the phantom for thou wast worthy.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="18">
            <ab>Let the commandment hang thee over the flame, thou Evil One! for by thee they hanged
               Absalom, upon a tree.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="19">
            <ab>In the fire mayst thou see thyself humbled, among vile women! for Solomon by thee
               was degraded, among profane women.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="20">
            <ab>Justice be measured to thee, as thou didst inflame her! even Jezebel who devoured
               the prophets, thou kindledst her.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="21">
            <ab>In fire mayst thou justly burn, who madest them drunken! the two whom Elijah burnt
               up, when they went up and assailed him.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="22">
            <ab>On thee also be coals heaped! may he see and rejoice: that Naboth in whom thou
               heapedst, a pile of stones!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="23">
            <ab>Be thou clad in scorn in the day of judgment, before all beholders! who clothedst
               Gehasi in a leprosy, by means of thy theft.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="24">
            <ab>With lightning for a dart be thou pierced, O Satan! who in the heart of Josiah,
               didst fix thy darts.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="25">
            <ab>Sink thou in the dregs of Gehenna, O Satan! who didst sink Jeremiah in the mire of
               the pit.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="26">
            <ab>Daniel escaped from the pit, whither thou didst cast him: may he have comfort in
               seeing thee, in the furnace for ever!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="27">
            <ab>Be thy wickedness returned on thy head, Hater of man: as his wickedness was returned
               on the head, of Haman thy fellow! </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="28">
            <ab>May the King’s Bride mock thee, as did Esther: when thou beseechest her in the
               judgment-day, to plead for thee!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="29">
            <ab>Fire released the righteous ones, whom thou hadst bound: a mighty bond be to thee,
               the flame of fire!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="30">
            <ab>Be thou torn in sunder, and may the seven brothers, see thy defeat: the sons of
               Shemuni who by thy wolves, were torn in sunder!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="31">
            <ab>May fire triumph over thy pate, as thou didst mock: the two heads of Nazarites, sons
               of the barren!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="32">
            <ab>May fire make mock of thy head, for mother and daughter: triumphed over John’s head,
               when thou didst madden them!</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="33">
            <ab>Flame triumphed over thy head, O Evil One: for on the charges thou didst triumph,
               over John’s head!</ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
